<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 16:06:55 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 16:06:55 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Something She Said by Béla Fleck</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/M-fdyC388-s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soundslice-notation-and-tablature&quot;&gt;Soundslice Notation and Tablature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living sheet music brought to you by &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Wanna know more? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;our interview with Soundslice co-creator, Adrian Holovaty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/71461/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bela_Fleck&quot;&gt;Béla Fleck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s album &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outbound_(B%C3%A9la_Fleck_and_the_Flecktones_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outbound&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was released in 2000 with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9la_Fleck_and_the_Flecktones&quot;&gt;Flecktones &amp;lt;i class=”non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square” aria-hidden=”true”&lt;/a&gt;. I was 18 when it came out and pre-ordered a double-CD release from Barnes &amp;amp; Noble or Best Buy. &lt;em&gt;Something She Said&lt;/em&gt; was one of the songs that really stood out to me because of its odd chord changes and textural elements with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on electric guitar, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawn_Colvin&quot;&gt;Shawn Colvin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on vocals, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_McCandless&quot;&gt;Paul McCandless &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_horn&quot;&gt;English horn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 17 years and here we are! I’ve finally gotten around to figuring out the intro to this song. One reason it took me so long was because trivial efforts to learn it were met with unexpected difficulty. Honestly, I had no idea how hard this piece of music was until this week when I started seriously practicing. My fingertips hurt typing this paragraph just from all the left-hand fortitude required to play it. It seriously tore my callouses apart. Sheesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway every single measure of this piece is difficult. Bela originally played it on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resonator_guitar&quot;&gt;resonator guitar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (I’ve always wanted a resonator guitar). Every measure had some weird trick to left- or right-hand acrobatics to make the piece particularly tricky. If you’ve followed my work for a while, you’ll know I don’t usually pick simple pieces of music to learn, but let me say that this was seriously challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of that, there are speed bumps everywhere you look in this piece. I couldn’t decide on a definitive fingering, so it’s up to you how you want to play it. Watch the video and see if it helps you. If you decide to try learning it, please reach out and let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/something-she-said</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/something-she-said</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Erudite Eyes by Robert Fripp (Cover)</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-old-music&quot;&gt;New Old Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I covered Robert Fripp’s &lt;em&gt;Erudite Eyes&lt;/em&gt; in 2011, posted it to YouTube, and forgot about it. Six years later, I stumbled upon it again and found that I really liked what I did. So, in a fit of creativity and motivation, I recorded this video to go along with the song. I hope you enjoy it as much as I enjoyed making it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, my cover is quite a bit darker/moodier than the original. I spent time “updating” it to something more aligned with what Robert might write and release today. There is quite a bit more dissonance and it’s much less cheerful. The song originally came out in 1968 on the pre-&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Cheerful_Insanity_of_Giles,_Giles_and_Fripp&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cheerful Insanity of Giles, Giles, and Fripp&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an album I grew up listening to and still enjoy decades later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard the original, I highly encourage you to check it out. It’s very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NeWE8Su3sVc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/erudite-eyes/erudite-eyes.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/erudite-eyes/erudite-eyes.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/erudite-eyes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/erudite-eyes</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evil Genius</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Evil Genius is an experimental jazz trio out of Los Angeles featuring &lt;a href=&quot;http://maxkutner.com&quot;&gt;Max Kutner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on guitar, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bonepocket.com&quot;&gt;Mike “Bonepocket” Lockwood &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on drums, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stefankac.com/&quot;&gt;Stefan Kac &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on tuba. They kicked off their 2017 tour in Phoenix and I had the privilege of catching the show and hosting the band at my house. I met Max at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bluemouthpromo.com&quot;&gt;Blue Mouth Promotions &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; dinner at NAMM in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max is the guitarist for several bands, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/GRANDMOTHERSOFINVENTION/&quot;&gt;Grandmothers of Invention &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/TheMagicBand/&quot;&gt;The Magic Band &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (see also &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/captain-beefheart&quot;&gt;Captain Beefheart&lt;/a&gt;). He’s also good friends and a collaborator with &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;. You could say we hit it off pretty quickly when we met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evilevilgeniusgenius.com&quot;&gt;Check out Evil Genius’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UrwtFrJ0Y1g?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/evil-genius/evil-genius.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/evil-genius/evil-genius.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and we’ve got the band Evil Genius here from Los Angeles. You guys wanna introduce yourselves and what you play and how you got to know each other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Sure. My name is Mike Lockwood. I play drums and am from Reno, Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: I’m Max Kutner and I play guitar. I’m from Las Vegas, Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I’m Stefan Kac. I play tuba and I’m from Minneapolis, Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you’re all based in LA now? What brought you to LA?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Institute_of_the_Arts&quot;&gt;Cal Arts &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh? Is that where you all met?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: I met Mike in Reno, actually. We went to the same bachelor’s school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Same bachelor party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Or several…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us a little about your music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Awkward silence.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: This band was sort of started by Max Kutner, so I’ll let him take that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: I really wanted to put together a group with these people. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It happened to be tuba, guitar, and drums. It could have easily been something else.&lt;/span&gt; But, yeah, that’s really all I was thinking about when I wanted to do it. I wanted to play with Mike forever. Finally found an excuse and I wanted to play with Stefan. And here it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eo8Ce2dxEII?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m so glad I got to see you guys play last night. Seriously, that was one of the best concerts I’ve ever seen. It could have just been the atmosphere and I know you guys were exhausted, but just being in that small place and seeing you play up close and personal. And the music… What stunned me was just total creative freedom. It wasn’t like, “free jazz” or something like that, it was just people expressing creative fun and art. Can you tell me about your composition approach and how you guys put these crazy songs together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Like Max said, he got us together because he wanted to work with us as musicians and as people, not so much because of the instrumentation. So, for that reason, we all bring a lot of different backgrounds. Our three backgrounds are pretty different, although there’s enough overlap, obviously, that we can work together. It gives you a situation where that freedom aspect is very constructive for us because there actually are lots of possibilities for things that could happen because of all the different things we all do and have done in other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Compositionally, I’ll be honest, it took me a whole cycle of a tour and a record and some other things before I really knew what I wanted to write for this group. I had to do a lot of sketching, a lot of drafts, a lot of revision, and I don’t even want to say I thought about it a lot, but I had to let it settle and percolate, ruminate, whatever you wanna call it, before this next batch of tunes that we drew on a lot at the show last night presented themselves. And those were much more designed for these guys specifically whereas things that I had before for us were things I’d already had done and we made them work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now we have more of a custom repertoire for the band that actually comes out of the band, comes out of things that we’ve done. As we were talking earlier, the titles of the tunes come out of band events, events in band history, etc. etc., which I think everyone in a band knows how that works. That’s not anything novel, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s good to have arrived at that point where there’s actually a body of work that we ourselves can draw on and be ours.&lt;/span&gt; Whereas we didn’t necessarily know exactly what we were right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that part of it is always going to stay undecided and I’m totally cool with that.&lt;/span&gt; There’s something that can’t really be defined about all the abstract things that are happening, a working relationship like this, whether it’s happening live, compositionally… That’s stuff that I feel works best when it’s not completely defined. It’s always developing. It’s not to say that we’re throwing our hands back and saying, “It’s whatever.” It’s always evolving and changing. It’s a real living thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re reading a lot of sheet music throughout the night. All three of you. Are the songs more like jazz pieces where there’s very compositional stuff, then there’s “okay, we’re gonna go break for a little while, then we’re going to come back to it…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: There’s all sorts of charts. Some of them are lead sheet-ish. Very few of them, but… You go that direction and then some things are completely orchestrated, notated exactly. At least for these two guys, most of the charts don’t have any drum information so my role has been to–while they dig through reading, I dig through also reading and trying to make sense of what I feel like should happen with their parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I told you this last night. Until last night, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_King_(drummer)&quot;&gt;Dave King &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Bad_Plus&quot;&gt;The Bad Plus &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was the most exciting drummer I’d ever seen live. And then I saw what you were doing and I was like, “I can’t even believe how this guy thinks.” Who are some of your big influences? I hear a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Cow&quot;&gt;Henry Cow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the band, I don’t know if that’s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/T0Auumv5leI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Sure. Sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I have no… That’s not…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, for you on the drums, who are your inspirations? It was so stunning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Well, Dave King… I’ve listened to a fuck-ton of Dave King and I have tons of respect for him. That’s one. Early on, lots of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Stewart_(musician)&quot;&gt;Bill Stewart &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ari_Hoenig&quot;&gt;Ari Hoenig &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I listen to a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah there was a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyrhythm&quot;&gt;polyrhythmic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff going on. You were playing lots of different rhythms and changing the feel. It was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: The influences have been wider than I would feel comfortable talking about to some fellow jazz musicians. That’s not true, I would talk about it, but it’s all over the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you used a lot of percussion and percussive…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Trash?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Not instruments, but, yeah, trash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Found instrument things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, we don’t have the baguette bag on this tour, unfortunately. We played for this radio station in Santa Cruz called &lt;a href=&quot;http://kpig.com&quot;&gt;KPIG &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we usually travel without a drum kit and we just played this tiny space and we were kind of like, “Okay, what are we going to give Mike to use?” He said, “I have this stuff. Let’s make this happen.” Things like “cymbal on ground,” baguette bag, toys…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I proposed that we rename the band at that point to Bang on the Baguette, but the proposal was not taken by the other guys in the band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: But, yeah, that’s part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How long have you been together as Evil Genius?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: What is it? 3?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: 3 years at this point, although we didn’t play a lot the first year or so. Mike was living in a couple different places for a while until very recently. So, we’ve had the band for a lot longer than our amount of actual playing out might dictate, but now we’re all gathered in Los Angeles. We’re looking forward to being more functional on an ongoing basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/789-VrBsO4c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Speaking of “basis”–bad joke here–hearing you play the tuba in the band, it’s clear there are very normal bass lines going on, but then there’s a lot of bebop parts going on too. I don’t know what the dynamic of a jazz band would be with a tuba playing a bass. I don’t know if that’s a standard arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I think it’s nice that you say it that way, that you wouldn’t assume. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Most people would assume that he’s just playing bass in the band, but Stefan definitely does that, but so much more.&lt;/span&gt; Max was playing bass a little bit last night, too. Passing the roles is something that enables us to be more free, like you were saying earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So tell me about the dynamic of having you playing tuba in this band and how you approach the instrument in this experimental music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When I write I approach guitar and tuba as two horn parts&lt;/span&gt; knowing that if I got any grander ambitions I have more guitar stuff that can happen because of multiple notes. At the writing stage, I look at it just as sort of two &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counterpoint&quot;&gt;contrapuntal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; lines and don’t really worry so much about function unless the style dictates doing something. If there’s a clear bass harmonic, clear soul function, something like that. That can still happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Writing-wise, I think of counterpoint. Playing-wise, I got way into bebop playing in high school and college and didn’t give a lot of thought to even functioning as a bass instrument. I would only do it when I was sort of forced to, which looking back on it is sort of weird, but that’s just the way it worked out. It wasn’t until I got out of school and out doing stuff, going to a jam session…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Once, I walked in and could immediately see the bass player was sweating and panting and unhappy, probably been there all night playing 25-minute long versions of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stella_by_Starlight&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stella by Starlight&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and sees me come in and take the tuba out. After the tune, puts the bass down and says, “Oh, thank God, there’s another bass player here. Can you…” and I was like, “Hey, I don’t really do that. I’m a horn player. I don’t do the bass stuff.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And he looks at me and is like, “You’re a &lt;strong&gt;tuba player&lt;/strong&gt;.” And I’m standing there in front of this guy I’ve never met and I’m like, “Damn, I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; a tuba player. That’s kind of messed up that I don’t know how to do this.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that was one thing that happened. And then, once I got into it, I realized it’s fun to be the bass instrument. You have more responsibility. You’re a part of the rhythm section “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vulcan_(Star_Trek)#Mind_melds&quot;&gt;Vulcan mind meld &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” thing. When I learned that and started doing it, I got hooked on that. So, I do play as the bass instrument in a lot of different jazz settings and other “rock-ish” weird gigs that come along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I played in a polka band for a couple years and we would play rock tunes because there’s rock tunes those bands play and it’s like you’re a rock band with an accordion and tuba instead of guitar and bass. That kind of thing can totally work. But the final sort of synthesis stage of all this was when I got hooked up with people who were really into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Frisell&quot;&gt;Bill Frisell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Lovano&quot;&gt;Joe Lovano &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Motian&quot;&gt;Paul Motian &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; trio and, I hate to say “similar groups” because there’s no other group like that, but that type of group, that era of “jazz music” where not only were roles not as clearly defined, but the group interplay and the strength of the individual voices was such that the roles couldn’t really contain those people and the instruments they were playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JaCCxBIoEZc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I started working with peers who were really into that way of playing, then the external pressure was, “No, I want you to be able to do &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt;” and if you’re both or neither, you go back and forth. I was like, “Wow, I can’t do that. That’s really hard.” It took a long time to get comfortable. I’m still not super comfortable. It’s very compartmentalized because of the way I went through this process, which I think was a good way to learn. I got to focus on one and then the other, but putting them together is not a simple thing, necessarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This group has been great for me in that way and it’s giving me a lot of new ideas and it’s gotten me out of that box a lot more. I do come from those two functions and trying to put them together, I just go with stuff as it comes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s so much baton passing between the three of you. It’s almost like each person kinda takes a turn at leading the band and I don’t know if that’s a compositional thing, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s clear you’re &lt;strong&gt;listening and communicating.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Rhythmically, Mike might start doing something, and then Max will start doing something different rhythmically, and the whole band starts to gravitate around that. Is that something that evolved through your communication style on the instruments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I would say that it’s a byproduct of just being improvisers at our core. That’s probably what probably drives each of us to our playing music like this. Like you said, there’s tons of sheet music, there’s lots of notes, and lots of things to focus on other than the improvising, but that is sort of the root. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The communication thing takes–it’s hard to do this, but it needs to float above all the other material.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah. I would say that’s the thing. It’s very fluid. When I said forming a group with these particular people, I kind of expected that would happen and it wouldn’t stop happening. It’s keep developing. Human beings change and evolve and get into things and stuff happens and that’s going to change the playing too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The communication only gets deeper and deeper and deeper because of that listening and knowing how to listen.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like you’re almost expecting a kind of response from a thing. It’s very interesting to me, but I think it kinda worked out how I figured it would work out. In some cases, it’s going way deeper than I thought was possible in the writing and everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You have this most recent album. Can you tell us about it and what you’re working on now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, the most recent album came out at the end of 2015 called &lt;em&gt;Bitter Human&lt;/em&gt;. It was released on a three-year-old Los Angeles-based record label called &lt;a href=&quot;http://orendarecords.com&quot;&gt;Orenda Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which fosters this type of thing. Los Angeles artists, a lot of jazz fusiony stuff, a lot of experimental stuff, and all mostly friends of our. Well, all friends of ours. Not most. [Laughter.] Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Yeah, so we put it out on that. That stuff is kind of a compendium of tunes that we’ve written leading up in the band. Not necessarily written specifically for the band. Like Stefan said, there’s three pieces he wrote on that. I think I wrote seven pieces on that. And they’re from different stretches, from different periods in my compositional thing. But, we just recorded another album last year at the end of another tour and we’re working on mixing all that now. That stuff is all specifically written for this band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KTGrM231N48?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: We played a lot of it last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay. Yeah, I recognized a few tunes from your bandcamp page, but most of it was new to me. I was so thrilled. When is that album coming out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Hopefully summer. It depends on a few things falling into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Yeah, just trying to line up the mixing and mastering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, trying to figure out what to do with it. Lots of ideas. Not to get into the larger discussion of CDs, vinyl, streaming, all that. Trying to figure out ways we can do that. It’s a different batch from the first album, for sure. It’s a bit more through-composed whereas the first album was kind of molten and feels kind of primordial and looser and more free playing. But, yeah, that’s our recorded thing for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And how long are you on tour now? This is your first? second date? You played in LA last night?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: No, Arizona is our number one. Ichi ban.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, we played Phoenix last night and we’re playing Santa Fe tonight. We’ll be out for ten or eleven days. Something like that. Going up to Minneapolis, then back through Chicago, and all the way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool! Great! One thing I did want to ask about… And this is my total ignorance on the tuba. I noticed while you were soloing last night, you were primarily just using two fingers and getting so many notes. I know with a horn, there’s a lot with your embouchure. Can you clarify how it is you were able to do so much with just two fingers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KpjkpSdt9k4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I may be able to clarify, I may make it less clear. I’ll do my best. As you overblow through an overtone series, the notes get closer together and what that means is that there’s a new open note, a new open note, and those open notes get closer and closer so that by the time you get into what normally acculturated human ears are going to detect as a regular “middle of the piano” range of sound on the tuba, you’re already way up in the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;French horn is like this also. It’s pitched much closer to the tuba than you’d thing looking at it. They play much higher in the series than trombones do. So, once you’re up there, you’ve got a lot of open notes just stacked up against each other and getting closer together. What the valves do is they add length, so they lower the note a little bit and a little bit and a little bit. And because the open notes are close together by that time, you don’t need anything but the first couple positions on the valves to get yourself down to the next open note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, because playing the guitar, I was thinking it would be like only using three frets on the different strings, but the range you got and the note selection just between supposedly-three notes…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: The other part of that is there’s a lot of “wiggle and blow” in some of those intense tuba solos… [Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: You weren’t intentionally playing every single note?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I was BS’ing some of the notes because when you’re so high up on the tuba, the notes are so close together, you can BS it and you can use your embouchure and your chops and get the notes you’re after. So, I don’t know if that makes it more or less clear. It’s a physics thing. You watch trombone players, you’ll see the same thing. When they’re up in the bebop-trombone-land, they’re up there and the slide hardly ever comes very far out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, the frets get smaller, basically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Mike, do you play any other instruments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Not proficiently enough to do in front of other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’d never guess because the compositions of yours from last night…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Just one. I’ve only written one for this band and it came after, like Stefan said he felt comfortable after a year and a tour, I felt comfortable after two years and two tours. And also being out of town, blah blah blah…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That was not a simple or easy song. Not that I would expect it to be, but the stuff you wrote for the guitar and tuba were very complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BPnzjkIAvD8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I’ve been writing music since I started playing. On the computer a lot, but I compose primarily on the piano and going up through a master’s program in music, hopefully I’ve learned some sort of theory that I can actually work my way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: By the way, that tuba part is a good example of something where you look at it and technically it goes against what they’ll teach you in those orchestration classes. It’s not “idiomatic” or “playable,” but when you think artistically and conceptually and think, “Well if the tuba’s not good for this, we should toss it off the bridge and find something else.” It works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: And you’re an amazing tuba player so if you can’t play it, then yeah we should throw it off a bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I practice his parts a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Mike writes some really guitar-y guitar parts. From chugging chords to effect-laden feedback drone-y stuff. That’s in the chart. That’s not super common amongst the prior music or charts, so that’s pretty refreshing, especially chunking chordal stuff. Albeit, kinda funky chords. I had to re-tune for that tune. I don’t have to do that in any other tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I was thinking in his piece in particular, “I wonder if Mike plays guitar or tuba in particular” because some of what you were doing seemed very idiomatic. I knew you had re-tuned, but I wasn’t paying close attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: It wasn’t a super-out tuning. It was just drop-D. But it’s drop-D, not to get the D. It’s drop-D to get a voicing that would be impossible otherwise and it sounds really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Someone who taught at Cal Arts while we were there would always say that the way to learn about this was just to be around them and eventually start to intuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/udfZORFCq9Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: And having an ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Study-Orchestration-Fourth-Samuel-Adler/dp/0393920658&quot;&gt;the Adler orchestration book &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at my fingertips at all times, but that’s like 5% of it. I struggle with strings and guitars specifically. Orchestra strings also because it’s just such a foreign way of thinking about things. I know how to write clusters on the guitar that you can mathematically calculate what’s possible and what’s not, but as far as coming up with something that’s got that “guitar-ness,” that’s a longer-term process. I don’t know if there’s a book I can read that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: &lt;a href=&quot;http://guitarplayer.com&quot;&gt;Guitar Player Magazine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: There are books I could read, but I’m not going to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: They’re called monthly issues. Anyway, the show was awesome. I saw Mike not reading in a lot of songs, but he was definitely reading in other songs, and you guys were reading almost the whole night. I had assumed he was making up his own parts for a lot the songs that you had written, but it’s awesome to see the way you guys communicate, you write for each other, and you write music that challenges each other. Mike, you’d even said, “Let’s do something hard,” which was so ironic because every song sounds impossible to play. Thanks so much for spending some time and sharing what you do. It really was one of the best concerts I’ve ever seen. It was really stunning. I can’t wait to see what happens in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Band: Right on. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/evil-genius/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/evil-genius/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aye-Aye Monster by Mike Keneally and Andy West</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mike-keneally-house-concert&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally House Concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2016, Mike kindly played a house concert in my dining room, which was great fun. It took me several months to finally get around to editing some of the footage and this song was one of the highlights of the evening. Mike and Andy did several songs together and Mike did several other songs on his own. More of this concert will be released throughout 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, enjoy this first release from the concert titled “Aye-Aye Monster” from the 1995 release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/the-mistakes/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Mistakes&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://store.keneally.com/products/ex-2303d&quot;&gt;buy a digital copy from keneally.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FvNgs3dWkas?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should check out Mike’s newest album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.keneally.com/products/copy-of-mike-keneally-you-must-be-this-tall-download-only&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/aye-aye-monster</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/aye-aye-monster</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weasel Shake by Robbie Seahag Mangano</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;weasel-shake&quot;&gt;Weasel Shake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, I went to New York on a business trip and bumped into Robbie Seahag (more on that in a later video), whose name you may recall from our rooftop recording of &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/33-in-buffalo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;33 in Buffalo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; off his sold-out album, &lt;em&gt;Full Moon Fever&lt;/em&gt;. As I accidentally stumbled upon his residence, he quickly taught me another song from &lt;em&gt;Full Moon Fever&lt;/em&gt; and we recorded this fun video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5z2d9EdBF_4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should check out Robbie’s new album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bumbleweenie.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and buy one of his donation packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-stuff&quot;&gt;Video Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robbie graciously offered to do some wonderful animation to make this video stand out from the rest. I’m proud to feature this song on the site and to have participated in this recording. Thank you, Robbie!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for some really fun, funny, and ridiculous content from my day with Robbie. Gonna make your cheeks hurt. I had a headache from laughing so hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bumbleweenie&quot;&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a commercial for Robbie’s amazing new album, &lt;em&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v6kjkAk0jKc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/weasel-shake</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/weasel-shake</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Another Groan by Nick Prol</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9PSlHJzPyzw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Be sure to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/proletariansmusic/&quot;&gt;follow Nick &amp;amp; the Proletarians on Facebook &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nick-prol--the-proletarians&quot;&gt;Nick Prol &amp;amp; The Proletarians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Prol is an artist and musician based in Tucson, Arizona. He’s a super cool dude and has amassed an incredible roster. He is working on a new album with his band, Nick Prol &amp;amp; The Proletarians. Here’s some information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fproletariansmusic%2Fvideos%2F1256978847712376%2F&amp;amp;show_text=0&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The album is being produced by the one and only &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ianbeabout&quot;&gt;Ian Beabout &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and features artists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R._Stevie_Moore&quot;&gt;R. Stevie Moore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rob_Crow&quot;&gt;Rob Crow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinback&quot;&gt;Pinback &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thymme_Jones&quot;&gt;Thymme Jones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheer-Accident&quot;&gt;Cheer-Accident &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), and members of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sleepytime_Gorilla_Museum&quot;&gt;Sleepytime Gorilla Museum &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knifeworld&quot;&gt;Knifeworld &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_Chiefs_3&quot;&gt;Secret Chiefs 3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking_Plague&quot;&gt;Thinking Plague &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bent_Knee&quot;&gt;Bent Knee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a veritable “who’s who” of weird music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shamelessly begged Nick to let me participate in some way and he offered a guitar solo opportunity. He asked for something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discipline_(King_Crimson_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discipline&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; era. I threw in a little &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Frith&quot;&gt;Fred Frith &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for good measure and captured the solo you see and hear above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I’d like to note: I’ve never let myself “go” like I did with this solo. It’s the first time you’ll ever see me &lt;em&gt;move&lt;/em&gt; while playing the guitar. My wife once called me “an impenetrable monolith,” which I’d say also describes my guitar playing. It was a lot of fun recording this and I was highly surprised to see the video afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/nick-prol/another-groan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/nick-prol/another-groan</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture, Ep. 4</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-4-overzealous-precision&quot;&gt;Episode 4: Overzealous Precision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After learning about the technique Robert Fripp uses to play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;FraKctured&lt;/em&gt;, I became somewhat obsessed with following the technique religiously. Then I realized that the technique is a starting point and not a mandate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fracture/id978457922?i=978458012&quot;&gt;Purchase King Crimson’s &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.nexternal.com/dgm/starless-and-bible-black-c228.aspx&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Robert Fripp’s website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the video to accompany this episode of &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1enMm81dexg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-failure-to-fracture&quot;&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a video series I’ve put together about all the things that have stood in the way of my successfully playing the song &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; despite years and years of study, practice, writing, and making videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-list&quot;&gt;Episode List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Episode 0: Introduction&lt;/a&gt; (includes notation/tablature)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/stress&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Tension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/picks&quot;&gt;Episode 2: Picking Picks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/inefficient-picking&quot;&gt;Episode 3: Inefficient Picking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/overzealous-precision&quot;&gt;Episode 4: Overzealous Precision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;too-precise&quot;&gt;Too Precise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After hours and hours of practicing the technique learned at my Guitar Circle introductory course in February 2015, I became a bit too zealous in following the “rules” of right-hand picking and “release and return.” Particularly during the “death picking” section of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;’s moto perpetuo section. That’s the part with all the string skipping. Well, the part where the string-skipping spans multiple strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have tried playing the piece, you’ll know what I’m talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, to pick a note, you should move the pick to it via the elbow and move the pick through the string via the wrist. So, to play a note on the 5th string, then the 3rd string, then the 2nd string, then the 3rd string, and over and over again, it requires 4 movements of the elbow to bring the pick to each string before striking the pick through the string. All this during a barrage of 16th notes at 130 beats per minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not gonna happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I changed my approach to think of the space between the strings and where the pick could be moved through the string via pickstrokes from the wrist. Again, these motions have their origins &lt;em&gt;between&lt;/em&gt; strings. So, to play…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;|-----------------------------------------|
|-----6---6-------6---6-------6-------6---|
|---6---6---6---6---6---6---6---6---6---6-|
|-------------3-----------5-------6-------|
|-4---------------------------------------|
|-----------------------------------------|
  X Y         X Y         X Y     X Y

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By following the presumed “rules” (i.e. rules I’d made up using my own assumptions, not specifically taught in the introductory course), I would move my elbow to bring the pick to every string, which really wasn’t realistic. By forgetting the rules and sticking the the spirit of the technique, as I understood it after dozens of hours of practice, I would only move my elbow for the notes marked with X or Y in the tablature above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the duration of Y, I would keep my hand positioned so that the pick would remain between the 2nd and 3rd strings in an idle origin state. This gave me an opportunity to focus on just a few motions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving from position X to Y&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving my wrist to hit the notes while in position Y&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving from position Y to position X&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the notes for position X are always downstrokes, a simple repetitive pattern is easily established. The hardest part is moving to the right strings in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the video in case this isn’t clear from the writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are some gifs of the master playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/0FP5kyPiyKE?t=10m29s&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Moving Force&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is basically a piece built around the death picking section from the moto, but in Fripp’s New Standard Tuning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/fracture/fripp-death-pick-1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;gif of Fripp death picking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/fracture/fripp-death-pick-2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;gif of Fripp death picking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/overzealous-precision</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/overzealous-precision</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Patrick Grant</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Patrick Grant is a composer based in New York City. He founded the musical group, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiltedaxes.com&quot;&gt;Tilted Axes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and has worked with with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cage&quot;&gt;John Cage &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Robert Fripp and the Orchestra of Crafty Guitarists, Billy Joel, and Quincy Jones. I met Patrick in Mexico while I attended the Guitar Circle introductory course. He was attending the Ochestra of Crafty Guitarists preparation course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this interview and Patrick offers so much wisdom and insight. Lots of great stuff in here, so make sure you read/listen/watch the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; for pushing me in Patrick’s direction!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickgrant.com&quot;&gt;Check out Patrick’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0VBDV0YxGUg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/patrick-grant/patrick-grant.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/patrick-grant/patrick-grant.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and we have a special guest with us from New York City. His name’s Patrick Grant and he’s a composer. Thank you for joining us, Patrick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Thank you for having me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, no problem. It’s my privilege to have you on here and I really appreciate you taking the time this early morning to chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: We’ll see how you feel about that a little later…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs] So, I know you’ve been working in music for 30 years now and you’ve got a lot going on now. A lot of momentum in your career. Can you talk about some of the projects you’ve got going on right now and some of the highlights that you care to share with us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Sure! I was born in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit&quot;&gt;Detroit &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was making music there. No child prodigy by any means. I was always interested in visual art, but I made this shift to music when I was around 11 years old because it just seemed to be another way of creating universes within which to dwell, which is probably a good way for a first-born child to go when you have no other playmates. You just create these universes. But anyway, I’ll be jumping ahead many years here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I moved to New York in 1985 to continue schooling at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juilliard_School&quot;&gt;Juilliard School &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to finish there as well as to play in bands because I was also interested in rock and pop music, which is a real Detroit thing to have a foot in both worlds. I continued to have a foot in both worlds ever since. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If I had three feet, I’d be sticking that in a third world, too.&lt;/span&gt; It seems that every five years or so, I take my work into a different direction, but it’s all part of the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the things that really got me going here in New York City was the opportunity to work with theater companies. They always need composers. Avant garde theater companies were creating original work as well as having an opportunity to put on concerts and perform in art galleries because that always attracted me as an idea. I still produce a lot of shows myself, so I’ve always had that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Our_Gang&quot;&gt;Little Rascals &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “Hey guys, let’s put on a show” kind of feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I like the fact that a lot of the composers I admired–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cage&quot;&gt;John Cage &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Glass&quot;&gt;Philip Glass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–at the time in the 1980s, they drew a lot of inspiration and resource from the art world here in New York City. So, that was a way for me to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Along the way, I found myself creating music for theater and dance, working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamelan&quot;&gt;gamelan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, writing a lot of electronic music. For a while, I was known mostly as being a keyboardist, but when I decided to try out with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Circle &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and get back into my guitar playing, I created this project, Tilted Axes: Music for Mobile Electric Guitars that has most people now thinking of me as a guitarist or working with electric guitars more than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sQ78iTKSFkA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Generally, I feel that when people feel a little too comfortable in terms of what I am, it’s time to shake things up. Maybe that’s what lies ahead for me in 2017. Time to shake things up again.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s great. That’s how you and I met–we were at the Guitar Circle course in Mexico. You were in the Orchestra of Crafty Guitarists Preparation course and I was in the Introduction course. That’s how I found out about you, just playing guitar. Obviously, you’ve done much more than guitar. I absolutely love on the Tilted Axes CD how much you blend a lot of the Guitar Circle-oriented material, or just some of the kind of thematic concepts from that style of music, into a kind of a rock-oriented context or groove-oriented. I really appreciate that about your album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah, well, I would say that one of the things that drew me to the Guitar Circle was I was working with large–I had just started re-examining large ensembles a year or two prior to joining the Guitar Circle or even really knowing about the Guitar Circle and created the Tilted Axes project. What drew me so much to the group was its similarity to my work with the Indonesian gamelan and creating music in circles and how working within a circle inspires music that’s created by geometric and visual patterns, which I’d done a lot of before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_0-_3pcwC-Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Yeah, I definitely have absorbed some of the techniques from the Circle, but I also say at the same time, I’ve also admired how the Circle has absorbed other techniques from the gamelan itself, which doesn’t seem surprising because when I look at a lot of their work–or, I’m happy to say “our work” in the Circle over those number of years–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s just a lot of parallels there in terms of how music can be made in circulations, in terms of breaking up music made in a circle into different patterns of 2s, 3s, 4s, 5s, 6s, even 9s and have it all work out equally well in terms of 360-degree music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I definitely have incorporated or synthesized a lot of stuff. That’s probably something I got from working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Living_Theatre&quot;&gt;The Living Theatre &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The Living Theatre is–if one doesn’t know, they should definitely look it up because one of the things that attracted me to working with them is they have a long history, but they’re also the venue upon which composers like John Cage and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lou_Harrison&quot;&gt;Lou Harrison &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were able to peruse their first concerts in the 1950s and 1960s and they would always give a lot of trust to their composers to really create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Being a composer for them also meant that I had a space to work within. So, there was a parallel there in terms of working with and synthesizing a lot of different elements. In fact, Living Theatre is probably most known for and have been credited with being synthesists in that whatever’s going on in their environment, not just as individuals, but in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitgeist&quot;&gt;zeitgeist &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, finding a way of pulling everything together under a larger umbrella and showing the bigger picture. The Tilted Axes picture was definitely a part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a lot of different kinds of music I was working with that appeared on that album as well as a lot of guitar stuff that, as you said, yeah I did. In terms of becoming “groovified” in terms of the greater good come together in what I hope is a cohesive album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s a fantastic record. &lt;em&gt;The Kneadle Variations&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Coda&lt;/em&gt;… I laughed for minutes, not because there was anything comical but just because I love what you did. It brought such joy to my heart hearing those pieces reinterpreted in that style. It was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah, those were two themes. One’s a very famous Guitar Craft theme, &lt;em&gt;Eye of the Needle&lt;/em&gt;, by Robert Fripp. This other one was just a riff, a way of breaking up rhythm that had a lot of resonance with what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Béla_Bartók&quot;&gt;Bartok &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; does in terms of what he gets from folk music that I just put a blues scale into. Then with &lt;em&gt;Eye of the Needle&lt;/em&gt;, I was playing that–at least its core riff being the same fingering, but played in standard tuning as opposed to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_standard_tuning&quot;&gt;New Standard Tuning &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–which, in one position, it’s all whole tones. In another position it’s all pentatonic. And then writing melodies that pulled it all together. Robert was very generous in saying, “Go for it,” because I think he knew it wasn’t a goof but it was really a sincere experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right! It’s great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Thanks! I was definitely very happy to have his support of that with a bit of a wink and a nudge, but I think he’s glad how it turned out as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. Can you tell us about some of your other musical releases that might be available for purchase or listening online or outside of a theater?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Sure. I have been self-releasing and they’re available–four other albums. One shows a period of time about, jeez, in the late 1990s when I was doing a lot of work combining my love of gamelan with chamber ensembles, so I was playing a lot of keyboards that might have been tuned according to the gamelan. Or, I’d be using pure just intonation tunings mixed in with violas and guitars and–I think there’s one piece on there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/m7Vua_1xhSU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of music for film. I did music for a horror film that, for a while, was the essence of what was called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m7Vua_1xhSU&quot;&gt;Patrick Grant Group &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was 13 musicians and that in itself was a mini-orchestra using three keyboardists as its foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That I got from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P._D._Q._Bach&quot;&gt;PDQ Bach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when I was a kid. He wrote this opera, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schickele.com/composition/monksaria.htm&quot;&gt;Hansel and Gretel and Ted and Alice: An Opera in One Unnatural Act &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was impressed because they had a piano, they had a harpsichord, and they had a calliope and the sound of those three keyboards was a perfect mini-orchestra. So, I’ve always used three keyboards in my ensemble augmented with violin, cello, trombone, electric guitar, flute, clarinet, and two percussion. So, a lot of work in that time period. &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/7351293&quot;&gt;You’ll find that work out there &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then the work for gamelan proper, some of the scores that I’ve written for theatrical visionary, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Wilson_(director)&quot;&gt;Robert Wilson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, most famous for his creation &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Einstein_on_the_Beach&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Einstein on the Beach&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Philip Glass. For me, that was a huge influence in terms of what could be done on the stage and in terms of how music could be used and the creation of non-narrative narrative, which was fantastic. Bob Wilson said to me, “Patrick, everybody always asks me: &lt;em&gt;*What is Einstein on the Beach&lt;/em&gt; about?” I’d just tell him, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variation_(music)&quot;&gt;Themes and variations &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Themes and variations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dKEXZ0YCNkI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;As a musician, that’s all I needed to hear.&lt;/span&gt; I thought, “That’s the story.” And that’s how we can create a lot of narratives. Themes and variations. So, I decided to try something different this year and I put together the Tilted Axes: Music for Mobile Electric Guitars album and it did better than I expected. I was happy that the public and the press really responded to it. There’s all kinds of music blogs out there I never knew existed who wrote some nice things about it, but also larger organizations like the Boston Globe, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/tilted-axes-music-for-mobile-electric-guitars-by-patrick-grant-and-rushing-past-willow-by-nick-zoulek-reviews-1476827463&quot;&gt;Wall Street Journal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://teamrock.com/review/2016-10-29/review-roundup-this-months-best-new-progressive-music-releases&quot;&gt;Prog &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the UK, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/chris-kompanek/on-the-culture-front-musi_b_13807228.html?&quot;&gt;the Huffington Post &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… They really were able to see what I was doing, I felt, in terms of “it’s not a rock album, it’s not a classical album.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you look beyond the veneer of, “Hey, electric guitars,” there’s actually composition elements happening there that I’m happy people were listening to. So, now the trick is, how do I follow that up? The good news is: there is a plan and that plan is that I have a number of tracks that I’m finishing now and a number of tracks that have just been sitting around for the last year waiting for a reason that showcase the other kinds of music that I do that I’m working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I would say, compositionally, whether you like it or not, it sounds like me or it sounds like what I was influenced by or working with that week. I’d say it’s mostly, for a lack of a better word, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chamber_music&quot;&gt;chamber music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.” A lot of music for ensembles. There will be some electric guitar, percussion, and bass, but also violins, and cellos, and wind instruments, and some singing. One of the “hits” is this one piece that uses this very, very old public domain recording of one of those &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smithsonian_Folkways&quot;&gt;Smithsonian Folkways recordings &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that were made down in Louisiana that I added elements to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/j1PxYB0wqSE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I figured that, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;while I have people’s ears, let’s put out some other stuff to balance that&lt;/span&gt; out because on its heels, the album after that is the next Tilted Axes music, which is gonna be a little bit more thorny and convoluted than the first album. The first album dealt with themes and variations of different kinds of genres that one would associate with electric guitar. The punk ones, the blues ones, bass ones, even some that border on jazz to some level or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I would say that I’m trying to showcase what I can do in a contemporary classical way with the next album, and the Tilted album that we’re already working on, is going to be a sort of mix of the two in that the composition forms might be a little bit–I wouldn’t say “longer,” but I’d say “broader” or “more convoluted” because one of the reasons why the Tilted Axes album was so long was there was a big body of material, but I wanted to put it out on one album, so it’s 75 minutes long, but it’s almost a one-act theater piece in itself from beginning to end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Still, the pieces are more or less, with a few exceptions, sort of based in 4/4 and the reason of that is because, since this began as procession music, when Tilted Axes began 5 years ago for an event called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makemusicny.org/winter/&quot;&gt;Make Music Winter &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as a public parade–I like to call them “processions” because, as it’s written in the album note, “What is the difference between a parade and a procession? Intention.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s amazing how just putting it that way into the minds of the players, everyone all of a sudden shapes up a little bit, stands up a little bit straighter, and projects a different kind of vibe.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of that music had to be in 4/4 because that is the tradition of being a biped and playing music that is mobile, going back to all kinds of marching bands, processions, going back a lot further than that… I have found out that, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;while it’s possible to play in 7/4 or 13/4 when we’re moving around, it is more challenging.&lt;/span&gt; This album’s not going to be concentrating on that as much as I want to create music that might not be as mobile, but can be used in a fashion–I like to say I’m concentrating on music for planetariums because for me, that’s sort of the dream gig because most museums have planetariums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We have had a number of Tilted Axes events where we were mobile inside of a museum. There’s plenty of room to move, you can be inspired by the art, and for me, as a producer, I don’t have to worry about the weather. That was always a huge concern because, when you go through all this effort and it’s a one-day or two-day event and if you have the weather go bad on you–but I never have to worry about this inside of big museums. And most big museums do have planetariums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zAmv0-eeoYI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I have written a number of theater works and chamber works that are based upon elements from science&lt;/span&gt;, whether it’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickgrant.com/genome.htm&quot;&gt;the human genome &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdbaby.com/cd/patrickgrant22&quot;&gt;CD Baby &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)–I actually had a piece called &lt;a href=&quot;http://patrickgrant.com/BigBang.htm&quot;&gt;Big Bang &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Big_Bang_Theory&quot;&gt;the hugely popular CBS sitcom &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came on the air and pretty much killed that title for anybody else. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That was actually created, like a lot of this work, in collaboration with scientists. That’s very important for me, too.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Whether it seems that these pieces are whimsical, because I’m doing my poetic interpretation of these scientific things, still as it’s presented, the science has to be correct and accurate. That’s very important to me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can bust me on a whole number of things: “Why did you use that chord?” “Why did you decide to use that rhythm?” But you can’t bust me on the science.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I’ve found a lot of inspiration in my gamelan works and other pieces in structural models found in science. That was another phase I went through. I was finding structures and forms in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaos_theory&quot;&gt;chaos theory &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Music that is self-similar and self-described, where it may be finding one measure of the music, in a way, becomes the DNA for a larger piece. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s just a matter of scaling it to different discrete levels, moving at different speeds. But that kind of stuff really interests me and is the stuff that gets me motivated.&lt;/span&gt; But, first and foremost, if you’re just a casual listener or a deep listener, it’d be nice that there’s a level or layer there that you could find worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’ve mentioned gamelan music quite a bit and, for people that are unfamiliar, I thought it might be helpful for you to define what that is. Part of our mission is to educate people and to expand their horizons with music, but also you’ve mentioned in other interviews that music is such a social event and in this day and age where you’ve got people like me who sit in a bedroom recording interviews and guitar things on my own…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Am I in your bedroom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Not MY bedroom, but a bedroom in my house. [Laughs] It’s just interesting to me that I grew up just playing an instrument not thinking of it as such a social thing, but music to you is clearly very social and almost all of your work is for a group, mostly large groups it sounds like. At least, large compared to normal band sizes of 3-5 pieces. So could you talk about gamelan and your concept of music as a social event?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-6YWAZwI9Sk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: First of all, I’ve been talking about gamelan. “Gamelan” is the Indonesian word for “orchestra.” If you’re saying “gamelan,” you might as well be saying “the Indonesian ensemble.” Their indigenous ensemble, whether it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java&quot;&gt;Java &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bali&quot;&gt;Bali &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is made up of a series of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallophone&quot;&gt;metallophones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or as I tell people, “Like xylophones, except all the keys are made of bronze.” It has a really nice metallic ring and shimmer to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These are all arranged from tiny little ones that play in very high octaves of 5-note scales. There are some with 7, but that’s getting a little too “inside baseball.” Pretty much one octave per instrument. So as you go down in octaves, the instruments get progressively bigger and bigger until you get to the very lowest octaves and you have, maybe, huge slabs of bronze that are playing these low notes and then the foundation that holds it all together are huge, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gong#Nipple_gong&quot;&gt;button-faced gongs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that–not to be confused with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gong#Chau_gong_.28Tam-tam.29&quot;&gt;Chinese tam tam &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that you see at the beginning of old movies. These are gongs that are tuned to specific pitches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of the music centers around some kind of a tonal center. So they have all these instruments. Sometimes 30-40 players playing these and they’re held together by two drummers playing something that I guess would look like congas held across the lap on the side. What makes this ensemble sound musically interesting to me is that all the instruments are played in pairs. The reason for that is that if they have two little ones, then two next size, two of those… the players playing in pairs are able to produce very blindingly fast passages by–I guess the western word is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hocket&quot;&gt;hocketing &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where they each divide up a melody, so if they want to play something that’s 16th notes, one player might be [playing one pattern and the other filling in the gaps].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rp2yRpC2AR4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When you put the two together, it becomes a great thing to listen to having two ears because you hear this melody broken up. To complicate matters even more is that these two guys also have another two guys playing their same parts. They are tuned a couple of cents, depending on the village. Some villages like a large number of cents apart. Some a smaller number of cents. But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when you have those two bars that hit at the same time, the same pitch, and they’re off a number of cents, there will be a vibrato that happens between the two.&lt;/span&gt; So instead of just having a dull ringing tone, they’ll actually produce a shimmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of gamelan aficianados feel that–well, some villages feel like, “Oh, we’re more rock and roll than you because we like a wider vibrato, so we tune ours 15 cents apart.” Other people say, “Oh no, that’s too brutal.” There’s all kinds of different styles, like any other kind of music. There’s many different uses for it, but one of the things that I found attractive and lent my ear to listen to it was it was one of the–along with West African drumming, which similarly concentrates on patterns that fit together in a hocketing kind of fashion–that attracted composer &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Reich&quot;&gt;Steve Reich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He was attracted to Indonesian gamelan, too, because a lot of the rhythms can only be described as very bebop sounding when you go to the island of Bali, which is interesting in that they’ve had this long tradition of creating the music in Java. But then in the 1920s when the Dutch–and a lot of Dutch artists have taken advantage of it being a colony and hanging out there for inspiration–but a lot of the Balinese gamelan music was really a 20th century creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;They actually, in the way that people used to chop old cars and turn them into hot rods, they pretty much melted down the Javanese gamelan and rebuilt it for speed. At the same time that some people were having a problem in the western world that classical musical instruments were being bastardized by being used to play jazz in the 1920s, and those rhythms were “barbaric” and “not for lofty purposes…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The exact same thing was happening in Indonesian in terms of the beautiful court instruments of the Javanese gamelan were being melted down and were now being played by those “barbaric” Balinese as a kind of “moron music.” That’s what jazz was being derided as in the 1920s. But to pull that whole thing together and to put an umbrella over it all is that this music doesn’t exist in an abstract fashion in these societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HfrOSJRCsfM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Whether it’s the courts of Java or the more ceremonial use in Bali, they’re always for a specific purpose and they’re still not, like a lot of West African music, they’re still not divided from the dance. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s not “the dance,” there’s not “the music.” They’re one and the same thing.&lt;/span&gt; That division has not been made yet. If it was the afternoon ceremony doing an offering for the gods, there’s a specific song and dance for that. If there’s a special ceremony for the full moon–which full moon? Well, we’ve got a ceremony and a dance for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And there’s more social ceremonies that would always have their village gamelan and their dancers dance for weddings and feasts and all these other things that every society has used to mark their calendar. So, that’s the one thing that interests me very music was that the music had a purpose in every society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I first went to Bali–I’ve been there three times to study the work–was that as you pass through the different villages, you can hear each village having its own gamelan perform its evening music or taking part in some kind of ceremony. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s for real and that’s why I liked it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And they have their own tuning system, which I found very interesting, too. They’re using 5-note scales, but they’re not at all tuned like the 5 black keys on our piano. They may be technically pentatonic scales, because they use five notes, but they break up the octave very differently. So when you do hear it, all of a sudden, there’s no such thing as “harmony.” A lot of it is “horizontal” movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyways, this obviously was hugely impactful upon what I wanted to do. When I studied those rhythms and studied how those things were put together, I did join &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamelan_Son_of_Lion&quot;&gt;Gamelan Son of Lion &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a new music gamelan that’s been around since the 1970s here in New York City and it gave a chance for young composers to write for these ensembles and experiment, but I was also interested in using those kinds of rhythms and non-standard tunings with my electronic keyboard ensemble because I felt like I owned that more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I didn’t want to be grabbing someone’s music, but I was happy to learn about how the rhythms could interact and apply that to a lot of the other music I’d been using. A lot of that still carries forth when needed in everything I do today. A lot of that can be heard on this last Tilted Axes album. Here and there, it’s there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZXJWO2FQ16c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: As Steve Reich’s Music for 18 Musicians is one of my favorite albums of all time, you’ve also mentioned it in a couple of places…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;a friend gave that to me when I was 14 and that’s maybe too young.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But, I would imagine these kinds of ensembles that have had such an impact on you have greatly informed your composition style. In going to Juilliard, did you study orchestration or something or write pieces for larger ensembles or is that just something that you felt personally inclined to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: I always say, “I went to Juilliard,” but I never claimed to have finished Juilliard. So anyone who says I’m a Juilliard graduate is putting out a fiction that I never put out. But, I did go to Juilliard for two years but I never finished because I had to work here and I did that by working for a classical music publisher, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edition_Peters&quot;&gt;C F Peters &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who also published John Cage’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that’s how I was able to meet with the people who were working with John Cage and work within that circle, but I was taking private composition lessons when I was 15 because that’s all I was doing. I was just trying to–even if I didn’t know what I was doing, I still had a facility for writing music and I thought I was drawing pictures sometimes. The patterns were there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vFYdNMXJOsE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, how orchestration really came about for me–not having an orchestra–was having electronic keyboards and synthesizers. It seems that the way our ears work and the way physics works that you can find any possible sound-making device and you can pigeonhole it into, “Well, is it string-like? Is it percussion? Is it brass? Or is it a woodwind sound?” That pretty much covers the spectrum of how sound is made. But, working a lot with orchestral scores and working a lot with composer composers contributed a lot to just understanding orchestration and how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;One of the things that was useful was moving to New York City and just knowing a lot of people really doing it.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like, “Read this book because everybody here read it and that’s how we’re doing it.” That becomes a whole little culture in itself, but a lot of that… I did grow up playing violin and viola and playing in an orchestra, so I had a pretty good idea for how these instruments work and I was writing for these instruments since I was a kid, so–it didn’t happen overnight, but that was definitely part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But getting back to what you’re saying, I’ve always liked the idea of music for ceremony. Working with The Living Theatre who was influenced by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theatre_of_Cruelty&quot;&gt;Artaud Theater &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as ritual, John Cage himself would say that every performance is a form of theater. I take it as seriously as that. So, I’ve been able to apply that and of course my love of Indonesian music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not just a gig for me. It is a kind of a ceremony.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nBFnK82yyOI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Even the smallest performance should be taken that way. I think that whether it’s expressed to the public or not that this is the reason behind the performance, it comes through. Even &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Byrne&quot;&gt;David Byrne &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talking_Heads&quot;&gt;Talking Heads &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; wrote a book called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_Music_Works&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Music Works&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it’s got some good sections. The one section that I think he writes near the beginning reinforces what I’m saying is that he’s coming out of playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CBGB&quot;&gt;CBGB &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s in the late 1970s, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;any music that ever seems to work has to come out of some kind of a scene. If there’s no scene, the music doesn’t go very far.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So maybe his work has come out of a scene, but I think that’s a form of a ceremony. You look at something like CBGB’s in the 1970s, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was like a church in a way. It was a ritual. People knew how to dress for it. People knew how to act for it. There was a whole code that went along with those serious performances.&lt;/span&gt; That had its code as well as performances in Indonesia as well as at a rave in Amsterdam has its code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, whether you want to call it ceremonies or scenes, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s important and that’s one of the things I like about producing the shows is: you are creating a scene.&lt;/span&gt; If you’re going to do that, it’s good to know what all your forbears did before you. Not just in terms of their successes, but a lot of times in terms of their failures, too, because you don’t want to fail when you don’t have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But if you don’t try, you’ll never know. You can’t be afraid to fail&lt;/span&gt; because I can’t say that everything I’ve done has worked, but you can dust yourself off and learn something from that and move on. I’m happy to say it seems like there’s been enough things that we’ve done that when we synthesize and pull things together, it’s been having a decent impact on a large number of people. So, despite 2016 being such a year of extremes, there has been good parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely. And to wrap things up, can you tell us where to find your music and where to find more information about you and your projects?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/njifOZB74A8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah. I’ll take this as an opportunity to tell you that as a result of my interest in chaos theory and such, the name of my production company has been Strange Music. So, you’ve got the “weird music,” I’ve got the “strange music.” I used to put on concerts and say, “Strange Music Presents.” When I was with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadcast_Music,_Inc.&quot;&gt;BMI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Strange Music was the name of my publishing company. Now it’s Peppergreen Media with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Society_of_Composers,_Authors_and_Publishers&quot;&gt;ASCAP &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But still, my larger company, the one I file with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncle_Sam&quot;&gt;Uncle Sam &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; every year, that’s Strange Music, Inc. The reason why is because I was finding–a number of reasons! First of all, the word “strange” contains my last name, “Grant.” Also, I was thinking of the strange attractors that were found in chaos theory in terms of patterns that are created out of seemingly random events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also influenced very much by a Samuel Butler quote that John Cage was particularly influenced by, and that is, “The only things that we truly hate are the unfamiliar things.” Especially when you apply that towards music, a lot of people–they want to be pacified. They don’t want to be challenged, you know? I remember that even albums like Steve Reich’s 18 Musicians…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I mean, I was 14 years old and I can’t say that I &lt;em&gt;liked&lt;/em&gt; it the first time I heard it, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;like most things I really end up liking, I get challenged, I don’t like it at first, but you keep on coming back like, “Oh, let me listen to it again to be sure that it really sucks.” As it turns out, it grows on you because it ends up changing your mind. It’s that laziness that a lot of people are battling with when they’re challenged.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kIAtNak16KU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, anyways, that’s the name of my company. All websites lead to Rome. Or, at least, all websites lead to the same place, so if you go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://strangemusic.com&quot;&gt;strangemusic.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that’s the same as &lt;a href=&quot;http://patrickgrant.com&quot;&gt;patrickgrant.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is the same as &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiltedaxes.com&quot;&gt;tiltedaxes.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So, that’s one way of centralizing things because I find that after a 30-year career, people stumble upon my work or are looking to get from my work different things. So, there’s different ways of putting it out there. So, that’s pretty much information central for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you go there, you’ll see that we have our own podcast called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stringsandthingsshow.com&quot;&gt;Strings and Things podcast &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that we have Facebook fan pages and all the usual stuff you’d expect to find. But, it needs a revamping, but all the information is current. And I have to say, speaking of such, you really do a fantastic job at Make Weird Music. Your stuff looks great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, thanks a lot! I appreciate that. It’s really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: I notice those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you, Patrick. There is so much more I want to talk to you about, so if you wouldn’t mind, I’d like to have a follow-up conversation with you in a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Sure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Plenty to think about from this and plenty of places to diverge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Oh, absolutely. But, thanks for letting me spout off. I hope I was helpful. One thing I did have to say, being thorough, but not too thorough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, it’s perfect. Thank you so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/patrick-grant/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/patrick-grant/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Steve Vai's EVO &amp; Mad Hatter Terminator Kit</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LETPKHwA7AY&quot;&gt;Here’s a video &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about the installation of the Mad Hatter SVST-HSH Terminator Kit in EVO:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LETPKHwA7AY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/terminator-single-volume-kits/products/copy-of-single-volume-single-tone-complete-kit-with-a-5-way-selector-switch-for-humbucker-single-humbucker-svst-hsh&quot;&gt;You should buy yourself a Mad Hatter Guitar Products Terminator SVST-HSH Kit &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the same as what we put into EVO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;podcast-audio&quot;&gt;Podcast Audio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/evo/EVO-mad-hatter.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/evo/EVO-mad-hatter.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Russell Muller for joining me on some of this escapade and engineering the A/V stuff for the installation video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preface&quot;&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda promised myself I wouldn’t make this a sentimental/nostalgic post, but the content means so much to me that I’d feel inauthentic doing otherwise. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt;’s guitar, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evo_(guitar)&quot;&gt;EVO &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, can be heard on on some of my favorite music of all time. I was &lt;em&gt;obsessed&lt;/em&gt; with the guitar as a teenager when I found out about the guitar in 1995. Seriously, I carried &lt;a href=&quot;http://ibanezrules.com/catalogs/us/1995/index.htm&quot;&gt;the 1995 Ibanez Guitars catalog &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; everywhere I went in junior high and drew pictures of EVO in all my art classes (and other classes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EVO was all I would talk about with my friends and family at that time. In 1997, my grandmother, parents, and I pooled our money together and bought my Ibanez Jem7vwh, new in box. I’ve had that guitar ever since. That was 20 years ago now!! Sheesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, you may remember &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/mad-hatter&quot;&gt;my interview with “Electric Ed” Heisler&lt;/a&gt;, owner of &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Guitar Products &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I told Steve about Ed’s patent-pending potentiometer designs and what a difference it made in my Jem. Steve immediately said, “Would you install it in EVO?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, um… We did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a little nerve-wracking leaving the venue with one of the most valuable guitars on the planet. I joked with Ed that I would rather Steve handed us a bag with 1 million dollars cash because cash is replaceable. I think Ed double-checked his homeowner’s insurance after he brought EVO home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installation&quot;&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[You really should just watch the video to see what we did.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Ed installed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/terminator-single-volume-kits/products/copy-of-single-volume-single-tone-complete-kit-with-a-5-way-selector-switch-for-humbucker-single-humbucker-svst-hsh&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Terminator SVST-HSH System &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he took note of the existing wiring configuration. Steve was using a push-pull volume pot configuration with a 331K (.0033 microfarad) ceramic capacitor modification that rolled off some of the low end frequencies when engaged. Also, his tone pot had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guitarelectronics.com/product/TCO033/Orange-Drop-022-Microfarad-Tone-Capacitors-for-Guitar-Bass.html&quot;&gt;Vishay orange drop .022 microfarad tone capacitor &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed customized a &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/pages/yin-yang-push-pull-pot-mods&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Yin Yang 500K push pull volume pot &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by placing the ceramic capacitor in parallel with the pot. He installed the Vishay capacitor on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/products/mad-hatter-universal-cts-dual-value-potentiometer-with-stss-tone-lead&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Killer Tone dual-value pot &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and wired it to 500K. He replaced Steve’s output jack with a new Mad Hatter Switchcraft output jack and replaced the existing 5-way CRL selector switch with the Mad Hatter Terminator 5-way CRL selector switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Terminator system design is solderless, so Ed connected everything to the appropriate terminals using the Mad Hatter Little Ass Screwdriver and gently tugged on all the wires once installed in the terminals to ensure secure attachment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before restringing the guitar, he used the Little Ass Screwdriver to ensure the pickups and switch configuration were working as expected. Once it passed inspection, we restrung the guitar and demo’d the new hardware. It sounded great to our ears, but only one set of ears truly mattered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed and I brought the guitar to Steve’s studio about a week later and he loved the upgrade. He said, “It’s like EVO has a bigger set of lungs,” and specifically commented on an increase of clarity in the mid-range frequencies. Thomas Nordegg, Steve’s guitar tech, was also very happy with the tone. Ed and I were both smiling for hours afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this was a huge deal for me because Steve’s music, instruments, and friendship have played a significant part in my life. To play a small part in the history of this incredible instrument is an indescribable honor. And it was awesome to get to hang out so much with Ed, learn even more about his awesome products, and get to know him better on a road trip to LA. He exposed me to some cool weird music I’ll be sharing at some point, too!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/evo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/evo</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mike Keneally Talks To Andy West</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conversation took place in my dining room on Sunday, November 13, 2016. It was the day after Mike and Andy performed a concert in that same dining room. I just thought it’d be cool if the two of them sat down and talked to each other on film since they’re old friends who hadn’t played together in years. It was a cool conversation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Check out our interview with Mike Keneally!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;And our interview with Andy West!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/omJhldQT-JQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west/mike-keneally-andy-west.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west/mike-keneally-andy-west.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks so much to Julie Cord, co-founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bluemouthpromotions.com&quot;&gt;Blue Mouth Promotions &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. BMP is hosting the &lt;a href=&quot;/link/x-jamm-2017&quot;&gt;2017 NAMM X-JAMM&lt;/a&gt;, featuring a slew of great artists performing for 6 hours the Saturday of NAMM in Anaheim. Julie works with Mike in all sorts of ways and BMP is a great company worth supporting. Check them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Andy West: So Mike, I was listening to the radio on the way over here, and um, it was kind of a, uh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally: They played a bunch of my stuff, didn’t they? [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Yeah, exactly! It was fascinating, but there was a lot of this doom and gloom scenario about science and this kind of stuff, but you know, overlaid with this sense of hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right, in terms of how technology can actually help us instead of hurt us. So, my question is: as someone who’s been a lifelong musician and in the business for so long, how do you… not a business question, but how do you see music evolving? Because it’s really struck me recently as I kind of continue to sort of look backwards and forwards at the same time, particularly with YouTube, you know, you can go see the videos of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thelonius_Monk&quot;&gt;Monk &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all the classic guys that are just extreme, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Right. [Chuckles]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And then, here we are now. So, do you ever think about or do you have any sense of kind of an evolutionary sort of thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I don’t have a shape or a pattern in my head. I do think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s fascinating to think about. But, I don’t know. I mean, you framed that by starting by talking about technology, and I recognize definite luddite tendencies in myself, you know, when I compare things that are happening now compared to… I mean, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I tend to idealize the early seventies as a period where musicianship was really fresh&lt;/span&gt;. The influences were still new enough so that the way they were being processed and recontextualized was really fresh feeling, and audio technology was just at a point in history in the early seventies that it produced a sound that seems amazingly good to me and a lot of other people. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think there’s a reason why a lot of people intrinsically are so affectionate for the music of that era, and obviously a lot of it has a lot to do with what people were playing, but a lot of it also has to do with the way it sounded.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Just this really full and warm–and it’s very clichéd to use the word ‘warm’ when describing analog sound and analog technology, but most clichés have more than a grain of truth to them. I think that as digital recording technology started to take hold in the eighties, that it caused some kind of mass hypnosis, and many musicians with great ears that have been proven to have great ears got seduced and hypnotized a little bit by the clarity of digital. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you listen to that stuff now and it’s almost unconscionable what was done to music&lt;/span&gt;. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And that was accompanied by people starting to ratchet up compression in order to make things louder. So obviously everybody recognizes that the earliest digital recordings, especially in pop music in the eighties, a lot of it sounded really strange. So I think a lot has been done to compensate for that since then. And newer digital recordings are warmer, but they do arguably feel less human than the stuff that we were in love with and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that that humanity is lost now&lt;/span&gt;. I say all that being super grateful for the flexibility of digital recording and the availability of the tools. All that is fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But, as with so many things, it’s hard not to mourn what’s been lost, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well I wonder if people are looking for that through various forms of live performance and things where people actually can attend. There’s kind of a renaissance of certain sort of jazz styles that are not like a rebirth of an old thing, but kind of an approach I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I don’t know if you’ve heard somebody like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vijay_Iyer&quot;&gt;Vijay Iyer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something like that where it’s just kind of piano jazz but not really a standard jazz form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK. Sure. Oh yeah, sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: So let’s hope that that’s kind of mediating that other kind of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, yeah. I mean, definitely it’s out there. As with anything, there’s going to be an equal and opposite reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Which is why you’re going to see a huge rise in progressive activism over the next few years. But I love that format that you’re describing. My friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Mitchell_(pianist)&quot;&gt;Matt Mitchell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s a keyboardist and composes for small jazz groups, sounds nominally like jazz but it heads in directions that are unpredictable, and you can feel the acquired knowledge and the exposure to all kinds of culture and music over the last many decades. It gets soaked into it. People will hear the word ‘jazz,’ and they think it’s going to sound like &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But it’s all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: “It must swing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: You know, I’m hearing a lot of things with more straight time and interesting rhythmic kind of things with these sort of harmonic overlays or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I love that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I mean, that’s fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, that’s kind of cool. The other thing I’ve noticed, and maybe you can comment on this is…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I don’t mean to make you ask all the questions, but I’m enjoying this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Ok cool. We’ve all…you know, people who have…I don’t want to say ‘studied music’, but sort of watched the evolution of players and musicianship over time. So in that time period when you were talking about, to actually discover a great musician was something that happened almost by serendipity or through some kind of filtered process of editorializing. I remember the first time I ever heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahivishnu_Orchestra&quot;&gt;Mahavishnu Orchestra &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for example, was in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creem&quot;&gt;Creem Magazine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s amazing that that’s where you went, because that’s…when you said that I precisely went to the first time I saw Mahavishnu Orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, but now it’s YouTube, right? As a bass player, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve sort of had to come to grips with the fact that I could go on YouTube and find a hundred people that are just monstrous players that have technique and abilities that you just couldn’t find thirty years ago. It just didn’t exist.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Uh-huh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And now it does. So there’s some some cause for that effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m wondering if it’s kind of like there’s a lot of noise out there, and there’s this very high level of musicianship along with the noise.&lt;/span&gt; So it requires a filtering mechanism of say, “This is something that I can actually connect with, or not.” And the only way that I’ve found to do it is through my own trial and error, literally just going through and listening to stuff. And maybe that’s part of the evolutionary process that needs to develop here or something, which is some way to sort of… I don’t know if ‘editorialize’ is the right word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, you can only rely on your instincts, and you’ve only got a limited amount of time in a day. It’s so much stuff to process and filter, that you kind of have to. Everyone does it. You go by first instincts when you get a link that someone has forwarded to you, and it’s one of 30 links that you’ve been momentarily intrigued by that day. And you don’t have time to watch them all. You have to, and that’s informed by all kinds of prejudices and things that you have to decide. “Am I going to listen to this thing that probably sounds like something I’ve heard before, or am I going to go this direction that might be more challenging?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And knowing you, I’m sure you probably tend to go for the more challenging things if you have a limited amount of time. But, if you have the time, you might say, “I just want a cross-section of what’s going on.” Or there’s a million reasons why you might be tempted to click on a link and see what’s going on. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And there’s so much that I don’t see. I made peace with that many many years ago.&lt;/span&gt; And if someone hands me a disc on the road or something, I accept it graciously always and with gratitude. “Thank you for sharing this work with me.” And, you know, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s probably a little part of me that’s like apologizing in advance saying, “There’s a good chance I won’t hear this.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You know, I don’t say that out loud ‘cause I don’t want to, I don’t want to corrupt the moment, or…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And you may!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Or negatively influence anything. I might very well listen to it. But I know that at the end of every tour I end up with a stack of stuff and not the time to listen to all of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: OK, so actually, this leads to a story that Anthony can edit out if he wants. But it’s how I met him. Did I tell you this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK. Um? Tell me again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: OK. So Anthony and I worked at the same company down here in the Phoenix area. And he came to my office one day kind of cold and said, “Excuse me, but are you Andy West the bass player?” Which happens maybe eight or ten times in my entire thirty year computer career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. [Laughs] Not very often, but you know, interestingly more in the last ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That makes sense to me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It takes time for this stuff to soak through the water supply.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: But the point is he came in, and he said, “Oh, well, that’s great. You know I’m a musician, blah blah blah.” And he gave me a CD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And he said, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ahab.garone.net&quot;&gt;“This is a CD I made with my dad.” &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And I said something to the effect of, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Ah that’s great. Yeah, I’ll definitely listen to it. By the way, I hate almost everything.”&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs] You know, or something to this effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs] That’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: “You know, don’t take it personal, but I’ll definitely listen to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And I listened to this album, and it was…I had probably a year earlier reread &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moby_Dick&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moby Dick&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; again. It’s kind of like one of these books that I go back to every now and again. And it turns out that this album was conceptualizing the story of &lt;em&gt;Moby Dick&lt;/em&gt;. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Mmm hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Written by his dad, and Anthony played all the parts, and produced it, and all this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Too cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And this was like one of the… I’m looking for an adjective here. I can’t find an adjective to describe how I felt about this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: It was really interesting. Of course I love the story. And the lyrics and the melodies were very unusual, and it turns out his dad was you know, proudly unschooled. [Laughs] Like he would say, “Don’t ever try and teach me how to read music” or something, you know, “because I’m afraid it will corrupt me.” You know, kind of a weird attitude but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He had a voice, and he wanted to preserve it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah! So it was like he was in the Amazon living in the forest and did not want to come out. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: He liked it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: So it was just a very interesting story because this album, it’s not like something I would coldly recommend to anybody because it’s very eclectic and weird. So I was like, “God, what do I do with this? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love this, but I’m not going to tell everyone like ‘go listen to this album’ because they’ll think I’m nuts.&lt;/span&gt;” [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I’ve run into that and I’ve become involved in projects specifically because I thought that the music was was so amazing and how could the world not love this, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Mmm hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Sometimes I get a little clouded about that just because I think something is so amazing. I don’t know if I ever feel frightened that people will question my own sanity by recommending something. [Laughs] But then I know, yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you don’t just tell anybody that they should go check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trout_Mask_Replica&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trout Mask Replica&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You gotta read the room. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, well Trout Mask… Ok, so just to jump haphazardly to another topic, you know when we first met, and you mentioned this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crazy_Backwards_Alphabet&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crazy Backwards Alphabet&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right. That I did with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Kaiser&quot;&gt;Henry Kaiser &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s a really good album. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That album was a real complete statement. And I like that record a lot.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. It’s a pretty neat thing. Now, because of course &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;on the internet, you’ll see all kinds of people say things, just really horrible things, about this stuff.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Like, “What were they thinking?” You know, this kind of thing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But we were thinking all kinds of things and just sort of playing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs] That’s a good answer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] But it was fascinating to me because of course &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/captain-beefheart&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beefheart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was not part of my past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I was sort of into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allman_Brothers&quot;&gt;Allman Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cream_(band)&quot;&gt;Cream &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you know, that whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Right on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mothers_of_Invention&quot;&gt;The Mothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; too, for sure. But not, like, beyond The Mothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It didn’t go far… yeah, yeah. Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. So Henry had me playing all these Captain Beefheart songs that I had never heard. And also the approach to the songs was so different because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was not grounded in the kind of musical education that I had, which was very precise and harmonically, cohesive, and all this kind of stuff. So, it was very eye opening to me…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s ’cause they’re tone paintings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: In a different kind of way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. So that was pretty cool, and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, what I enjoyed hearing you play that kind of stuff, not just the Beefheart stuff, but the sort of Beefheart-influenced, uh, “Henry stuff” and whatnot, is how perfectly matched your approach and tone was for that kind of music. Like, I listened to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rockette_Morton&quot;&gt;Rockette Morton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, his bass playing on Trout Mask, and I see a taste of lineage…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: A parallel universe! [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, well just that. I see a link between your style and his style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well that’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And it’s something to do with the attack on the strings and the musicality of it and the solidity of the sound and all this stuff. When I heard you in the seventies with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dixie_Dregs&quot;&gt;The Dregs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it was all about precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And The Magic Band, the Beefheart stuff, is about discipline, because they had to practice those songs a million times to get all these disparate events to line up in any kind of way. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But it’s not about precision in the accepted sense.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But in a way it is ‘cause you gotta drill that stuff endlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well ok, so in line with the original evolutionary sort of commentary, do you hear anything that is, I mean… What could you comment on besides yourself–which we can go to another topic on; I want to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/scambot1/&quot;&gt;Scambot &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before you leave. But, do you hear any trends? Or is it just kind of like isolated, “Wow, this is a really interesting approach that these folks are doing or this guy is doing?” I mean, do you hear any kind of overall trending?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I’m so out of touch. I mean, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I regret the fact that I don’t make the time to listen to everything that crosses my path.&lt;/span&gt; I would find it im…I clearly do find it impossible to do so, but there’s so much that passes me by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But I wouldn’t presume to indicate my awareness of a trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well, ok, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But I hear good things a lot. Something will come out, and it might be years after it’s current, but I hear relatively new music. Like, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Thunes&quot;&gt;Scott Thunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gave me a recording of the band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Field_Music&quot;&gt;Field Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; like eight years ago or something. And I really enjoyed it. And then I sort of didn’t think about them anymore. And then &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Minnemann&quot;&gt;Marco Minnemann &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; became obsessed with the band Field Music, and then started playing it on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Satriani&quot;&gt;Satriani &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I realized I was aware of them. I had even heard their music years ago, and I went, “Yeah, that’s really good.” But then when I heard it a couple years ago again, I was reminded it’s actually really brilliant. It’s exciting. It’s beautifully constructed pop music, that, you know, in its field, it definitely deserves to stand alongside &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XTC&quot;&gt;XTC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the best of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd_Rundgren&quot;&gt;Rundgren &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and all that stuff. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love super well-constructed, non-predictable pop music very much.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love a chord progression that is just beautiful. You don’t see where it’s going, but when it arrives, you realize, “Oh, that was the perfect solution nailed.”&lt;/span&gt; That stuff is so much fun for me. And Field Music has that in spades. So that’s reasonably new music that’s brilliant, and always my response when I hear something great unexpectedly is to be, you know, a little shocked. [Laughs] And then to be super super grateful to be reminded that I can be a curmudgeon as much as I want. But I can never really have the whole picture of everything that’s happening, and there’s always great stuff going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well maybe it’s part of this evolutionary thing I keep harping on. The fact that there is a lot, but you have to discover it. Maybe it becomes more of a–it’s like a localized thing, you know? If you go back to the reason music is important to people, or why people love music, there’s an emotional thing there. There’s a human connection kind of thing that’s going on, or there should be. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Ideally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I guess there are people that have never experienced a profound feeling from listening to music, but that would be very sad to me. You know?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh, it would be. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s only occasionally that something hits me that makes me need to go on the old social network platforms and share it.&lt;/span&gt; But when I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kendrick_Lamar&quot;&gt;Kendrick Lamar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the Grammys earlier this year… Did you see that performance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Maybe the single greatest musical performance I’ve ever seen on television.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Oh my God, ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And so I saw this and had to spread the word. It’s like, if you think nothing’s going on, wait ‘til you hear this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s amazing. Not just the content of the words, which is powerful and huge, but also the actual content of the performance, and the band playing which was… They’re just like deadly great. And the musical conception, which is really evolved, and it’s endemic of now, what’s happening in the the sort of intersection between hip hop and DJ culture and jazz and spoken word and activism and all the stuff that’s coming together in an insanely powerful way. And which, you know, will continue to do so. That’s just like, I…I…Kendrick Lamar at the Grammys. That’s all I can say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. I’m going to have to go look at that. That’s awesome. Here in Phoenix there’s a–I mean, I’ve looked, and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s kind of a dearth of opportunity for people to hear live music.&lt;/span&gt; You know, it’s really spare. There’s a local club here that is set up as a non-profit called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thenash.org&quot;&gt;The Nash &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is about jazz. But it’s purely jazz. Do you know what I mean? They’re not going to be doing other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Which I think is kind of unfortunate ‘cause I think that there’s room for other stuff. And kind of like a pure music venue where people don’t need to go to buy drinks or, you know, the stupid thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s why Anthony’s going to open the MWM Club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah! Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: He’s not in the room. OK, we can, we can divulge all of his clients now. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Yeah right. It’s uh, it’s going to be right here in the living room. Of course his wife has got something to say about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: No, it’s cool though. But you know, I think in New York or Boston there seems to be more of–maybe it’s just the concentration of cities. LA, you know, has the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Baked_Potato&quot;&gt;Baked Potato &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I guess the other side of that is really that now you go to the issue of musicians and artists creating and how do they support themselves? And then that opportunities become–well, you have to be very creative about this, and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if live performance is the only thing that’s gonna really do it, that’s an issue. But yet, we still do.&lt;/span&gt; I mean, people still create stuff no matter what. They’re driven to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Maybe that’s really the filter. You know, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the filter is, “What are your motivations? What are your reasons?” And if they’re strong enough in the pursuit of expression, it’ll happen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You find a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yep. If that was a question, you just answered it. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] I guess so. I’m just sort of musing on it, you know, because…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, it’s good to think about, and it’s definitely good to check yourself every once in a while. Does your drive remain strong? Check your motives. And just keep putting one foot in front of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And you know, people who…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s why I keep asking us that. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] I have to put in a plug here for pragmatism too because I know a lot of musicians, and myself included, who have sort of taken a path of providing for themselves and their family through other means, having a day job, whatever. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And back in the day, that used to be a real sort of sign of failure or something.&lt;/span&gt; You know, not necessarily a sign of failure, but it was not a sign of success. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And now I feel like it’s great if people can figure out how to make it work. There’s a lot of ways to do this, but again it kind of goes back to your motivation. And then sometimes they can kind of merge into a commercial successful thing, and sometimes not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, it’s your motivation and also your specific intent. And, if your desire is simply to make music and not necessarily be out on the road for months at a time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: …then all of a sudden it becomes very practical and real smart to find a way to fund those activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You know I definitely have. I got involved with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/School_of_Rock&quot;&gt;School of Rock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2007 and that was my attempt for a year at doing precisely that, holding down a day job. And it just became un-unworkable because by the end of that year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dethklok&quot;&gt;Dethklok &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was touring, and then suddenly there was an impasse that couldn’t be breached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: There’s certainly no stigma attached to it now, and I think it’s obviously laudable and quite necessary in a lot of cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well you know, it’s, it’s another means, although um, you know, people who have a family and a job, and want to do music…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: …it’s really, you know, it can be a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well it is. I absolutely admire anyone who has the psychic space to encompass all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. So, what else is on your mind? [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh man. I’m just grappling with my schedule all the time, which is challenging, so I’m a little self-centered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Right now. So as soon as you said that all, I saw was stuff I have to do. You know, and that’s not at the expense… I don’t want this to be a political conversation so, obviously the, the election is on my mind, as it is on everyone’s. And, just going to have to see what happens there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But, I’m feeling good. I just did a lot of live playing. I was out touring with &lt;em&gt;Beer for Dolphins&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryan_Beller&quot;&gt;Bryan Beller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.killuglyradio.com/wiki/Joe_Travers&quot;&gt;Joe Travers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and then we wound up on election night at The Baked Potato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: With &lt;a href=&quot;http://rickmusallam.com&quot;&gt;Rick Musallum &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; joining us.  We were a trio up until that last show, and then we were a quartet which I saw as sort of crossing the threshold in Beer for Dolphins activity next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Oh really? Awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I want it to be a quartet with Rick whenever it’s possible. But then, it goes into finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Touring just now on the east coast and in the South and in the Midwest was so much more feasible with three players than it would have been with four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Even in terms of van space and just all kinds of logistics. And I’m looking at the really scant amount of money that I maybe made on the tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Oh man. I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But then I had–I say that only because it’s fresh and on my mind. It’s an answer to your question. So, in December I’m out on the road with Satriani, for the month in South America. And that covers my expenditure that I just put out on my tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: So that’s the balance of my career anyway. You know, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m lucky enough to have these mainstream touring gigs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: With people that you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: With people that I like, and actually really enjoy playing with. And it’s like, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;playing Satriani music is so different from playing my own. I gain so much from it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s the way he approaches these concise song forms and how he, with very small gestures melodically, just paints this complete picture that everyone responds to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah! Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And that’s really thought-provoking for me because I’m always searching for that thing way out there, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Joe finds something right here next to you, and when you hear it, you realize, “Well that’s the perfect thing for that moment.”&lt;/span&gt; And then you watch people’s response to it in the audience, and it’s fascinating to me. What would be endless recombinations of musical information and what you can do. It’s so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] I know. When I listen–so of course I have all of the Satriani stuff, and I’ve seen you guys play with him many times. Well several times at least, and I also have a similar reaction in the sense that I’m in the audience so I’m kind of experiencing the music, but I’m also experiencing the audience and kind of fascinated by the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Mmm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well, it’s like: what is it that these people are really responding to? They’re responding to something that’s not something that I would normally conceive of, nor would I normally expect them to respond to what I’m hearing in the way that they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Mmm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: So it’s, it’s really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah. Well, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the basic themes are generally quite simple so people grasp that immediately take it in. The treatment is endlessly varied.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s like there are subtleties of articulation when he approaches the same melody in different parts of the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: He’s really attuned to the emotional arc of a piece of music which a lot of anti-guitar hero people might be surprised to even consider because they think it’s just about fireworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And of course the fireworks are a huge part of it, and that’s one of the things that keeps the audience kind of catalyzed and into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s just these sounds and occasionally flagrant displays of technique because it’s exciting. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;People respond viscerally to somebody who’s really good doing something really well.&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] If they happen to show up, they will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, exactly. Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And, and that’s the other thing about Joe. Because of the way he conceives things melodically, he puts out music that people embrace. And so, he still has a major label deal after all these years, and still is able to do touring at a nice level of comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And believe me, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;as a musician who is very reliant on well-paying jobs in order to feed my addiction of making my own music, I’m so grateful.&lt;/span&gt; You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: …That that there is something like the Satriani gig where we get to tour nicely and play for a lot of people playing instrumental music that’s not the most immediately conventional thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And that he gives me, and Beller, and Marco a place to be ourselves within this framework. It’s not a completely orchestrated thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah I definitely notice that. And you feel that. And I think that’s super smart and appropriate. And you guys have something to add. [Laughs] Obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And Joe enjoys it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Joe enjoys the fact that we’re adding that and the audience enjoys the fact that Joe is enjoying it, and that we’re doing whatever we’re doing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: The chemistry in the Satriani band right now is really cool, and kudos to Joe for wanting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And accepting it so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I agree. Oh, You want to wrap it? [Laughs] Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You got any requested topics, Mr. G?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony Garone: No, I think this is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Can we talk about the first three &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_(band)&quot;&gt;Chicago &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; albums? Were you into them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] You know, I think I was, but I think I was &lt;strong&gt;then&lt;/strong&gt;. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK, when’s the last time you heard that stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah? Check it out. Actually, I really like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_V&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chicago V&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The first five…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: They’re playing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Some version of Chicago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, some version of them is playing here. I mean, I’m sure they’re playing those songs and probably better than they did then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I don’t know. I’m a real &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terry_Kath&quot;&gt;Terry Kath &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; enthusiast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Oh, ok. All right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And I’m also a real &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny_Seraphine&quot;&gt;Danny Seraphine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; enthusiast, the drummer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: So there was, there’s a chemistry on the way those players sounded together on, for me, the first five records especially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I saw them play at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlanta_International_Pop_Festival_(1970)&quot;&gt;The Atlanta Pop Festival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh, well that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And they were great. And you know, horns seem to be making a comeback. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, I was just thinking about popular music that stretches the conventions and they popped into my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. Nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Those records–just to wax nostalgic for second about a time when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia_Records&quot;&gt;Columbia Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would fund the first three Chicago albums, which were double albums with all sorts of weird musical experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: With, you know, a million different genres and then just doing whatever they wanted. The fourth album was a live album that was four disks. [Laughs] You know, the four record set…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: …with about eighteen pounds of posters in it. You know, they could do whatever wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the marketplace was supporting that.&lt;/span&gt; And, I don’t know, I wouldn’t argue with anybody who doesn’t dig Chicago, but I have a real–obviously sentimental, but also I think somewhat logical–affection for them and that early Chicago stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Cool. Well, it’s at least added to my YouTube list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: There ya go! Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I’ll check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs] Well, ok. We good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Thank you. Make weird music! [Everyone laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: All right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: See ya.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
