<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>A resource for musicians to discover new artists, learn weird music techniques, listen to interviews, and share their weird music.
</description>
    <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 19:56:29 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 19:56:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jan Zehrfeld Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the first of a multi-part interview with Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett, the world’s best and only jazz-metal band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Panzerballett is? Check out our Discover post about them!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the time difference between Arizona and Germany, we conducted this interview early in the morning for Jan and in the middle of the night for myself. I was probably more tired than he was, but it’s hard to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Jan’s camera could only record ~40 minutes at a time, so our interview ended abruptly. I also hadn’t figured out how to record our conversation correctly, so I’m missing the audio and video from my end. And it was so hot in the Arizona summer that I had to run the air conditioner so my computer wouldn’t melt. This made the quality of my audio suck eggs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing this is just a personal hobby project or I’d feel like I really failed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-1&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-mwm-20151022.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-mwm-20151022.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kkNfXg1RRuY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first videoconference interview I’ve done with the site. There are some issues that I’m figuring out. This was a great learning experience for me, which probably makes it a less enjoyable viewing and listening experience. Anyone who complains will be justified, but will also be called a “freeloader.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I am here with Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett. Jan, could you introduce yourself? The purpose of the site is to introduce people (particularly musicians) to new music and to expand their horizons. So, go ahead and tell us what you do and how you got into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jan: Hello! I’m Jan Zehrfeld from Munich, Germany. I started a band called Panzerballett, or “Panzer Ballet” as Americans say it, back in 2004 and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;this is kind of extreme music&lt;/span&gt;. It mixes and blends together styles which are basically far away from each other, like &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there is a lot of heavy metal in there as well as jazz&lt;/span&gt;. So, you could call it “jazz metal” or “metal jazz” or whatever, also mixed with some other styles like funk and maybe some grooving styles, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think mainly it’s about extremeness and complexity&lt;/span&gt; and about complex rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m a big fan of extremely sophisticated music. Back in 2004, I was just finishing my studies as a jazz guitar player. My influences were, at that time, or my heroes were &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Henderson&quot;&gt;Scott Henderson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tribal_Tech&quot;&gt;Tribal Tech &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planet_X_(band)&quot;&gt;Planet X &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virgil_Donati&quot;&gt;Virgil Donati &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_MacAlpine&quot;&gt;Tony MacAlpine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mats/Morgan_Band&quot;&gt;Mats/Morgan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which are friends of Meshuggah, also from Sweden. They do kind of similar rhythmic stuff like Meshuggah, but not that heavy. It’s more funky or &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Zappa&lt;/a&gt;-esque, maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eQR2nzu3vkc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Well, I’m not a big fan of Frank Zappa, actually, but I dig his music a lot. I mean, I respect it a lot and I can see there are many people drawing parallels between the music I compose and Frank Zappa’s music, which I totally agree to because the basic statement of the music is kind of the same. Panzerballett’s music came many years after and the musical statements are related. I think there is a lot of music that were my main influences that were influenced by Frank Zappa’s music. So, there are big parallels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t actually listen a lot to Frank Zappa&lt;/span&gt; because it’s not my cup of tea. He has lots of criticism about politics happening back then in America, which I don’t know and I’m not inside the whole thing so I don’t understand it that well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And there is a lot of lyrics and I don’t do lyrics &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. I cannot write lyrics, actually. Everything that I’ve tried is nothing that I’d like people to hear. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t think it’s anything that I consider as “worth spreading.”&lt;/span&gt; I think only about the music itself, not about lyrics. I would say, now that I got kind of into a dead end, or blind alley… I was about to explain the music of Panzerballett…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So tell me about when you finished your studies in 2004, how did Panzerballett come about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I had this vision of what I wanted to do and, having written a thesis about Meshuggah and Meshuggah’s music and development, I got deep into the stuff and transcribed and played and covered some of Meshuggah’s stuff in my final exam… I started composing my own songs during my jazz guitar studies and I thought, “Well, I want to actually form a band that’s playing only my own compositions.” That’s when I started looking for musicians because the band that I had back then for my final exam–it was fun playing with them, but they didn’t have time for a steady band. So, I had to actually look for musicians who had enough time to form a band and to really rehearse a lot and get into things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then I found three guys, Max Bucher, Flo Schmidt, and Gregor Bürger. I knew all of them from the local scene as jazz musicians and Gregor had his own funk big band, which is still happening. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.earforce-bigband.de&quot;&gt;Ear Force &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I played in his big band. The first thing was I was looking for was a keyboard player, but I couldn’t find any. There weren’t that many keyboard players who were much into jazz music or, on the other hand, the jazz pianists playing keyboards with sounds usually didn’t do that. So, there were maybe two or three guys and they were already professionals that didn’t want to or have enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was racking my brain how to solve this problem. Then there was, in a different context, a rehearsal with a band that was rehearsing just for fun and they were already good musicians who didn’t want to join Panzerballett, but they invited me to come into the rehearsal room and they said, “Well, bring your own songs. We can jam on them.” These were a drummer, bass player, and a saxophone player. I thought, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Well, I could compose something for this session without it being a band, but I want to do something cool.”&lt;/span&gt; So, I started composing something for guitar, saxophone, drums, and bass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These were actually the first songs that later I used for Panzerballett. Because it turned out that it’s actually working with heavy guitar and saxophone, these were fusion compositions and it was a lot of fun trying out things with this lineup and this instrumentation. I didn’t think that the saxophone could be something that could play a role like a keyboard, but on the other hand, I found out I could play some of the role the keyboard would, so I found a way for this lineup and instrumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was kind of the starting point for writing my own compositions and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; I found those compositions in Munich for having this steady band and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; we met once a week and rehearsed for half a year and it turned out that it worked and we played our first gig. I think it was half a year later. We formed in January and the first gig was around June or something in a small club. It turned out it was fun and it worked. We decided, “Well, let’s make a record.” I wrote some more songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At first, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it takes a lot of work until you have enough material for a concert and then a CD&lt;/span&gt;. In the concert, there were some songs that were not in 100% in the Panzerballett concept because we played some standards and some blues stuff as well. It wasn’t the thing that I actually wanted to do with Panzerballett. In the end, maybe a couple months later, we had enough material and we went into the studio in March 2005. This was the debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;During the recording of this album, we were a quartet. I found that in the studio, songs were missing a guitar or something. Sometimes the saxophone was standing there a little bit “alone” and I thought, “I could actually do overdubs.” In every song, I found some parts that I could double some guitars or some saxophones and play comping and guitar solos. After we recorded this debut, I thought, “It would be great if we could do this live as well.” So I asked a friend, a second guitar player, who played all these parts live. It was Andreas Dombert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This was the beginning of 2006 when we started to play live as a quintet. From that time on, it’s stayed as a quintet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It turned out that in this Panzerballett sound, you have two main parts: one is the wrecking ball heavy metal part which is the riff part which is bass and rhythm guitar (what I basically do) and then there’s the melody part, which is the saxophone and to support this, the lead guitar doubles the saxophone, which is a nice blend. You can arrange a second voice, which sounds very nice, and the melody part gets stronger and gets equal to the riff part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jM4W3qaNfng?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And of course the drums play a very big role. Or it’s the counterpart? We have two main parts: the drums and the rest of the band because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the drums hold it all together&lt;/span&gt;. All the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyrhythm&quot;&gt;polyrhythmic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff that happens in the composition has to be underlined in the drums. Both parts, which are rhythmically working against each other are brought together in the drums. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It has to happen in the drummer’s brain.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It took some time to realize or to implement and assemble. Sebastian came to the band since our first drummer, Max, came from more of a jazzy funky groovy world and not so much from a metal world. He was not a metal head at all. Sometimes I felt the music needed something like a metal impact from the drummer. He played great, but at some time, when I met Sebastian, I immediately knew that this is the guy that I needed for the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: A perfect fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: A perfect fit! Right! And then we had some other lineup changes, but basically from the time on that Sebastian joined the band, it was sounding already a lot like it sounds now. The first record with Sebastian was &lt;em&gt;Starke Stucke&lt;/em&gt; and then there was this record label, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.actmusic.com/en&quot;&gt;ACT &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was from–actually it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siegfried_Loch&quot;&gt;Siggi Loch &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who founded this label and he used to be the head of Warner at one time, then he founded his own label. This is a very important jazz label. He came to one of our release shows from the debut and he signed us after that after that. He told me, “If we want to work together you have to cover music as well.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He wanted 50% cover material. It was his concept.&lt;/span&gt; At first, I thought I wanted to only write my own stuff, but then I thought about it and tried to cover and my first cover was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Pink_Panther_Theme&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it was a bit fun and it turns out that it worked. I tried to translate &lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt; into the same style that I composed the other songs. It worked out well and it was fun doing it because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s another way of working because you already have a musical pool you can draw from&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/c27XfStLp1o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This was more than just covering; it was a bigger invasion into the musical material&lt;/span&gt;. I call it “verkrassung,” or the “crassification” of it. That’s kind of my word for it. It’s really an invasion in taking out the elements and putting them together in a completely different way. This was the fun part about it. This is where I think the humor comes from. This is where people recognize some humorous stuff in the arrangements because they recognize what actually happens to the musical material when they know it and they know the original and how I treat the music. They can hear it and recognize it and that’s the fun part about Panzerballett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: After &lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt;, I thought, “Let’s take some more songs that everybody knows from both the jazz world and the metal world.” So, I took &lt;em&gt;Paranoid&lt;/em&gt; and made a jazz ballad out of it. I took &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smoke_on_the_Water&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smoke on the Water&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and translated it. It all worked well and it was kind of the starting point that’s gone until now. The latest record, we have &lt;strong&gt;again&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt;. This is an arrangement of an arrangement. We have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mah_Nà_Mah_Nà&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mahna Mahna&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on this record. I’m sure you know it. Everybody knows it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yes. I did an arrangement of it myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Oh really?! I want to hear it! Through all the years, it’s always been my aim and my intention to do research and exploit the old boundaries of what’s possible and to &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;go to the limit of what’s possible for the single player and for the whole band&lt;/span&gt;. If you can play your own part, it doesn’t mean the whole band can play it as well. It was really a lot of work for every single musician separately as well as for the whole band. It’s like building some complex sculpture and you first you have to build the single elements and then you have to put them together. It’s like twice the amount of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It takes a lot of time, especially when we started this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuplet&quot;&gt;quintuplet &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing, it took a lot of work. The first quntuplet arrangement was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Brecker_Bros.&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The whole song is based on quintuplets and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it took us half a year to get through the head of the song&lt;/span&gt;. And then we had to find a way of improvising on it, which took another half a year until we got through it. In the following years, we started to really play it more and more relaxed and now we actually, after writing some more quintuplet arrangements, we got used to it. In the first phases, it was really hard to “get” it. Now it’s starting from zero again because we started from septuplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BFoZoTwGfJk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: When I first heard &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;, I thought, “Are they actually doing this all in quintuplets?” And then I thought, “No, that’s really stupid. Why would anyone do that?” I thought I was totally wrong. Then after about four months of really listening to it, I thought, “No, they really are subdividing quintuplets.” It just blows me away that you did something like that. It’s so detailed and complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes, when thinking about it, it blows me away too. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This was the exciting thing about it: to do something that nobody else does.&lt;/span&gt; That way to divide the groove and divide the beat into 5 parts. I didn’t hear it before. Of course in Zappa’s music, you have lots of quintuplets, but not a whole song in quintuplets. Or you have some solo players playing some fast drums in quintuplets, but it’s a totally different effect to arrange something for a whole band based on this quintuplet quantization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I thought I was interpreting it incorrectly because it was so far out of the norm that I must be misinterpreting what was being done. So when I said, “That would be stupid,” I was thinking &lt;em&gt;for me&lt;/em&gt;, “Why would you think that’s what they did? That’s nonsensical.” But that’s what it was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Totally! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It is total nonsense to do it. And that’s the fun part about it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, you mentioned you’re really into complexity and you’re using these genres that don’t typically go together–jazz and metal. Can you talk about what got you into the complexity and why that is so attractive to you that you wanted to form a whole–not just a band about it, but a completely unique band that blends these interesting genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Well, probably because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I cannot do anything else than that because anything else would not make sense to me&lt;/span&gt;. It’s a reflection of my own inner way of thinking. From the time that I played guitar or maybe one year after I took up playing guitar, I got into jazz music and I always liked to play jazz music. I decided to study jazz music as well, so this was something that had a big part of my musicianship. It played a very important role to have freedom of improvising and also there’s sophistication and the elaborateness of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The complexity of jazz was always attractive, the harmonies, etc. On the other hand, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the reason I play music is to channel aggression&lt;/span&gt;. The reason why I took up playing guitar when I was 16, it was the time of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guns_N%27_Roses&quot;&gt;Guns n’ Roses &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica&quot;&gt;Metallica &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… The metal boom. The power that came from metal or heavy rock…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AC/DC&quot;&gt;AC/DC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was my first love of rock music. AC/DC had maybe the heaviest impact on my musical taste up to then. The first riffs I learned were AC/DC riffs. I still dig their music a lot. I was recently at a concert on their last tour. It was one of the greatest shows I’ve ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I always needed the wrecking ball in the music and this is something that was always missing in jazz&lt;/span&gt;: the loudness and the distortion. It never got aggressive enough for me. I wanted to blend this. Jazz musicians were kind of denying this or they were basically refusing to play distorted loud music. This element of wrecking ball in heavy metal… they never wanted to do this. So, that was the hard part of finding musicians who are actually willing to play this. A saxophone that wants to play in a band that is loud and playing metal riffs 50% of the time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve always wanted to bring these elements together. I wanted to be able to both do improvisation and play complex stuff and also being kind of the wrecking ball. The music has to have all these free elements. So, that’s what turned out of it. Meshuggah was a big impact because they blended metal with Indian rhythms. This polyrhythmic thing has as great a sophistication as jazz has in a harmonic context. Rhythmic maybe as well. But, Meshuggah, the rhythm is so much more important and is so much more sophisticated. This is something that I really grasped onto. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh yeah. You could say, “I latched onto it,” or, “I grasped it…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Who&amp;#39;s been listening to the new Panzerballett album, &amp;quot;Breaking Brain?&amp;quot; I love it! What do you think? &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/8vDJXoL22G&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/8vDJXoL22G&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/664232776204464128&quot;&gt;November 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: So complexity from jazz harmony, complexity from Indian rhythms or polyrhythms… This always felt great for me to, on the one hand, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;punch the audience in the face by playing really energetic and loud music&lt;/span&gt; and, on the other hand, to make it sophisticated in a way that they actually don’t get it in the first place, or they have to first think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You have two elements: this raw–like in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quentin_Tarantino&quot;&gt;Quentin Tarantino &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; movie–you have this &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;raw power combined with those really sophisticated conversations&lt;/span&gt;. You have both elements and that’s also something for me. Humor comes from music, you have both of these elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Usually you get punched in the face at a metal concert and, of course, meanwhile there are tech metal bands that have lots of sophistication, but then there’s this really jazzy part about it with improvisation. The whole band gets down to almost zero and we start building a groove or we start playing improvisation from zero to 100. In each night you have a different solo, each night something new happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This element was always important to me, to keep it fresh for myself, to keep it fresh for the musicians, not only playing every night the same stuff like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIDI#Standard_MIDI_files&quot;&gt;MIDI file &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; playing every night. You really have something and you build something new. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You have an element of the music that’s open.&lt;/span&gt; This seems appealing to me to have both of these elements. There aren’t that many bands that have both of these elements. For instance, in Tribal Tech it was like that, especially in the era where they played not so much jamming, like the last era where they do lots of jamming. That’s not appealing that much to me. But, in the era where the compositions were extremely elaborate and they also had this amazing improvisation and this was my favorite era of Tribal Tech as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Where did you come across these technical artists? How did you first discover them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Tribal Tech was through a friend of mine. It was the same guy that I played my demo to later on and inspired me to name the band Panzerballett because he said, “It sounds like tanks that are kind of dancing ballet.” It was the same guy who took me–years before that–he was very into technical music, he’s a guitar player who got into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Gilbert&quot;&gt;Paul Gilbert &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; [NOTE: Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;our Steve Vai interview&lt;/a&gt;!] and all those guitar heroes very early, and he always showed me those guys and he was buying all these guitar magazines, which I did not do at the time, but he got me to this technical music. He also took me to a Tribal Tech concert in Munich. My first experience was not a CD or recording, but a live concert and it was a punch in the face, and to the brain as well. And it was so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-1&quot;&gt;End of Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Jan’s camera ran out of disk space. We will soon be doing Part 2!! Stay tuned!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lyla by Avishai Cohen</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-we-learning&quot;&gt;What are we learning?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post explores a solo guitar arrangement I did of a beautiful song called &lt;em&gt;Lyla&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/avishai-cohen&quot;&gt;Avishai Cohen&lt;/a&gt;. The original recording features &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhodes_piano&quot;&gt;Fender Rhodes keyboard &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, drums, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_bass&quot;&gt;upright bass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, flute, and trumpet. I’m a sucker for moody songs played on the Rhodes (see also &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt;’s incredibly beautiful song, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/the-power-and-the-glory/id731975200&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aspirations&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) and this song certainly fits that description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was immediately attracted to this song when I first heard it a few years ago and it’s never quite left my short-term musical memory banks. At some point, I realized the sheet music for the song was available in Avishai’s online store, so I bought it and saw that it could probably be arranged into a nice solo guitar piece. It took over a year of sporadic effort to turn it into what we’ll cover in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/avishai-cohen&quot;&gt;Check out our Discover post about Avishai Cohen!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instructional-video&quot;&gt;Instructional Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put together an instructional video that illustrates everything in the charts below. Watch that if, like me, you don’t like reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VIDEO COMING SOON&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheet-music&quot;&gt;Sheet Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an incredible web app that offers HTML5 sheet music without the need for Adobe Flash or any other plugins. It’s super-duper awesome. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the score for performing &lt;em&gt;Lyla&lt;/em&gt; on guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/36180/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re interested, here are the &lt;a href=&quot;http://musescore.org&quot;&gt;MuseScore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and MusicXML files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/lyla/lyla.mscz&quot;&gt;MuseScore (.mscz) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/lyla/lyla.xml&quot;&gt;MusicXML (.xml) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;structure&quot;&gt;Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main parts to this arrangement (the original recording has 3 or 4 parts). There’s the opening section that’s fairly straightforward consisting of chord triads. I’ll call that ‘Part A’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part, ‘Part B,’ is the part with the beautiful harmonic minor melody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;harmonic-minor&quot;&gt;Harmonic Minor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re unfamiliar with the harmonic minor scale, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minor_scale#Harmonic_minor_scale&quot;&gt;Wikipedia has a nice entry about it &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s the scale that’s most often used to play Middle Eastern-sounding music. It’s a natural minor scale with a raised 7th note. Avishai plays with the scale in the Part B melody, but if you think of it as staying within B harmonic minor, you’ll be all right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a C major scale: C D E F G A B C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a C natural minor scale: C D &lt;strong&gt;Eb&lt;/strong&gt; F G &lt;strong&gt;Ab&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Bb&lt;/strong&gt; C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a C harmonic minor scale: C D Eb F G Ab &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the 3rd, 6th, and 7th change between major and natural minor. Then notice that the 7th changes between the natural minor and the harmonic minor. Alternatively, the 3rd and 6th are the only notes that differ between a major and harmonic minor scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrelevant conceptual question: Can you guess what a C harmonic major scale looks like based on the above information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performing-and-hands&quot;&gt;Performing and Hands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that left-hand fingerings are quite a stretch at times. Maintaining consistently solid notes is a huge challenge, as is playing the piece with continuity between measures. Part B relies on a series of minor 2nd intervals since it’s based in harmonic minor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part A has its own challenges, though. That stretch in measure 17 is a doozy to play smooth. Same with measure 18 and 19. Further beware of transitioning out of those little fills around the open high E string and effortlessly landing on that Bb major triad. Tough stuff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace_note&quot;&gt;grace notes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the score. Those are the little notes with lines through them. They’re basically “notes of no rhythmic value.” In other words, play them as fast as you can before playing the following note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll also note some notes with “4:3” within brackets. This is a particular &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuplet&quot;&gt;tuplet &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; called a quadruplet. That means that 4 beats will replace 3 beats. In the case of this song, two quadruplet quarter notes are equal duration to a non-quadruplet dotted quarter note. Clear as mud, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this piece can be played with a pick, I recommend playing with fingers instead. It’s a little more sensible and this is a sensitive piece of music that can use the finesse and softness of fingers. I’m a self-avowed picking nerd and I can’t imagine wanting to play this piece with a pick. But, to each his/her own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the melody in Part B beginning on the 3rd beat of each measure, you’ll want to lead with the fingers that play the melody. I’ve indicated left hand fingerings with the little numbers near the note heads in the upper stave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-signature&quot;&gt;Time Signature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song is in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triple_metre&quot;&gt;the 3/4 time signature &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is normally pretty straightforward. What makes this song difficult from a time perspective is where the accents live in Part B. The melody begins on the 3 and the rhythm support is on 1 and 2. Traditional 3/4 songs usually have the melody begin on beat 1, but this song’s melody lives almost entirely within beat 3. Pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/lyla/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/lyla/</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kerry Minnear Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-friendly-disclaimer&quot;&gt;A Friendly Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following interview content with &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerry_Minnear&quot;&gt;Kerry Minnear &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of Gentle Giant is in a pretty different format than you might expect because of the nature of how Kerry and I met and conducted an informal interview over the weekend of October 3, 2015. It was not filmed, no audio was captured, and it was completely impromptu. This may seem less like an interview than any other interview you’ve ever read; however, I’ve never claimed to be a journalist, nor even a storyteller. I can assure you I will do my best here to describe the experience I had talking at great length with Kerry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Kerry did review his answers via email and helped with some corrections and misrememberances. (Is that a word?) He has given his “thumbs up” for this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a long-form article because it is such a personal story and I’m writing this as I’m coming off a bit of a high from the events that have taken place just hours ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never heard of Gentle Giant? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;our Discover post about Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt; is a band very, very close to my heart. Their music was food for my soul when I was growing up. From contrapuntal multi-part vocal pieces like &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/knots/id693527786?i=693527910&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knots&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/on-reflection/id731948334?i=731948404&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Reflection&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to atonal power rock like &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/proclamation/id731975200?i=731975215&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proclamation&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/the-advent-of-panurge/id693527786?i=693527787&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Advent of Panurge&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to beautiful ballads like &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/think-of-me-with-kindness/id693527786?i=693527913&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Think of Me With Kindness&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/a-reunion/id731938339?i=731938362&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Reunion&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, there is seemingly no end to the breadth and depth of their music. There is a sweet mix of nostalgia, awe, and mystery for me when I think of these (and other) GG songs and the musicians behind them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of their music was written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blazemonger.com/GG/Ray_Shulman&quot;&gt;Ray Shulman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blazemonger.com/GG/Derek_Shulman&quot;&gt;Derek Shulman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blazemonger.com/GG/Kerry_Minnear&quot;&gt;Kerry Minnear &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which made these guys heroes to me. As a guitarist, I have paid particular attention to how &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blazemonger.com/GG/Gary_Green&quot;&gt;Gary Green &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; contributed electric guitar parts to this music, even when it seemed juxtaposed or anachronistic amidst medieval and baroque moments sprinkled throughout GG’s diverse musical portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my musical influences have also listed Gentle Giant as a significant influence. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt; called them out specifically in &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;our interview with him&lt;/a&gt; as he spent an entire summer learning every GG guitar (and probably keyboard) part he could. Many friends and family musicians have spent hours talking about GG’s music with me and the influence the group has had on them. All this to say: GG is a non-trivial part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gorgg&quot;&gt;GORGG&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that GG is a non-trivial part of many other people’s lives as well! This summer, I received an email from an Israeli guitarist named Yehuda about our mutual efforts in fighting our way through playing the &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; piece, &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. After a few months of back-and-forth communication, he asked me if I listened to Gentle Giant, to which I emphatically replied, “Yes!” Then he informed me that he’s an organizer of an event called GORGG [Global On-Reflection Giant Gathering], which is an annual gathering of the GG mailing list members, including original GG members Kerry Minnear, Gary Green, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blazemonger.com/GG/Malcolm_Mortimore&quot;&gt;Malcolm Mortimore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He said, “Consider yourself invited,” and I immediately booked my travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/interview/kerry-minnear/mwm-boxen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Make Weird Music gift boxes for Kerry Minnear and Gary Green&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made some custom gift boxes as a token of appreciation for Gary and Kerry. The boxes contained a handwritten card, an Amazon gift card, and a USB flash drive containing videos of the &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-youtube-play&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Steve Vai interview&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-youtube-play&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Mike Keneally interview&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/share/harnch&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-youtube-play&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Harnch&lt;/em&gt; for 4 guitars&lt;/a&gt;, and several GG-inspired songs I’d released (namely &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/pune-feat.-jake-ineck/id561140550?i=561140751&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pune&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/god-rest-ye-merry-gentle-giant/id584043305&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;God Rest Ye Merry, Gentle Giant&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-have-i-gotten-myself-into&quot;&gt;What Have I Gotten Myself Into?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insanity of doing all this didn’t hit me until a couple days before I had to fly to Montreal for GORGG. “I’m going to spend money I don’t want to spend to fly to a place I’ve never been to meet a bunch of people I don’t know based on an email invitation from another guy I’ve never met who lives on the other side of the planet.” The idea of traveling to new places is exciting to many people, but not me. I’m what you might call a “homebody.” I don’t speak French, I don’t like flying, and I’m uncomfortable traveling without a business purpose or without my wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only guarantee I had of a good time was a ticket to see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blazemonger.com/GG/Three_Friends_(band)&quot;&gt;Three Friends &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a GG tribute band consisting of Gary Green, Malcolm Mortimore, and several other talented musicians who’ve formed to perform music by Gentle Giant. My flight landed at 5PM on Saturday, October 3, and I had to check in to my hotel and get to the venue by 7PM–or was it 8PM? The concert ticket email (written in French) had both times listed. It was a hectic evening made a little more stressful by an unexpected traffic jam on the freeway as the bus was heading from the airport to downtown Montreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;three-friends-concert&quot;&gt;Three Friends Concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert venue doors opened at 7PM and I waited an hour amongst people (primarily speaking French) all of whom seemed to have a buddy to hang with. I hadn’t felt so lonely in quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening act, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moulettes.co.uk/&quot;&gt;The Moulettes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, blew me away (more on that in another post coming soon) and Three Friends performed. Three Friends were great, too! I’d never seen/heard Gentle Giant music performed live, so it was a real treat to get ~2 hours of it amongst ~1,200 enthusiastic fans. At some point during the show, I saw Kerry Minnear sitting about 10 seats to my right and my stomach clenched in nervous excitement. “He’s here! He’s really here!” I had no idea at this time how this would be the very tip of the iceberg in terms of my interaction with him over the course of the next two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;In Montreal for the Three Friends concert to hear live &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GGIANTMUSIC&quot;&gt;@GGIANTMUSIC&lt;/a&gt; music!! &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/QAvTWorr7d&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/QAvTWorr7d&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/650455932627869697&quot;&gt;October 3, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the show, I saw a guy with a GORGG shirt and introduced myself. He said to meet in the “hospitality room” at the hotel after the show. I didn’t know where that really was and I was pretty exhausted from traveling all day, so I just went back to my hotel and got some much-needed rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meeting-gary-green&quot;&gt;Meeting Gary Green&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the morning, I found the hospitality room. No one was there. I waited in the lobby until I saw a guy wearing a Gentle Giant shirt. He was a college-grad filmmaker named &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCSN3kZ1j5jG1G9_1yeP-rHg&quot;&gt;Morgan Miller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who made a great music video based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_Hand&quot;&gt;Free Hand &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vUu3A5HOxLY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, I met a few other super-friendly people (namely Phil Nomore) and then Gary Green and his wife. I nervously pulled the gift box from my jacket pocket, thanking him as he opened it up. He was touched and gave me a big hug, thanking me for the gift. It was so welcoming! Then someone suggested we get a picture together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Met Gary Green of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GGIANTMUSIC&quot;&gt;@GGIANTMUSIC&lt;/a&gt; this morning. Very kind person. &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/tyvooEj9sY&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/tyvooEj9sY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/650690466019733504&quot;&gt;October 4, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a nice conversation and then went our separate ways for a morning activity and lunch. I went with Phil, “twosheds”, and his wife, to a pub to watch a soccer game on TV. Then we went to a small coffee shop to see The Moulettes play again, where Malcolm kindly introduced himself and Kerry ended up sitting down at the same table as me. Feeling slightly overwhelmed, I gave Kerry the gift box and he put it in his pocket, thanking me quietly. About 15 other GORGG attendees filed in over time. The place was packed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meeting-kerry-minnear&quot;&gt;Meeting Kerry Minnear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After The Moulettes slayed us all with a wonderful acoustic set, approximately 20 GORGG people left to find a pub. Drinking is a frequent activity at GORGG. On the way to the pub, I saw Kerry looking around calling my name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Antony? Antony?” (This is how British people say my name.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes?” I replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you so, so much for the gift. I am deeply moved and would love to do an interview.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wow, thank you, Kerry!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Here’s the thing, I don’t like being filmed and broadcast on YouTube, so can we do it informally? And what do you want to talk about? I’m a pretty boring interview.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hah, I doubt that!” I said. “I’m asking people questions about creativity, motivation, finding their own unique voice, composition, and those kinds of things. It’s a way for me to learn myself as I do these interviews.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh, wonderful. I should be able to answer those questions. But, can we just do the interview now, instead? While we’re walking? I’m probably only good for about 20 or 30 minutes of conversation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sure!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He then introduced me to his wife, who also thanked me for the gift. I was astounded at their humility and down-to-earth nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Meeting Kerry Minnear of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GGIANTMUSIC&quot;&gt;@GGIANTMUSIC&lt;/a&gt;. Incredible. Never thought this would happen. &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/M9hMN75zlz&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/M9hMN75zlz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/650791133728100352&quot;&gt;October 4, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerry and I ended up talking for ~90 minutes about a variety of subjects. I’ll try to recount them here as best I can. I did not expect to do an ad-hoc interview and had brought a suitcase full of video, audio, and lighting equipment just in case either Gary or Kerry found the time to do an interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-summary&quot;&gt;Interview Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this interview was not recorded and is not a direct transcript in any way. What I’ve written below is a best-attempt at capturing Kerry’s words by memory on my flight back home from Montreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d consider it a synthesized recounting of events and conversation, at best. He is a man of Christian faith and is humble beyond description. He specifically doesn’t want to be “quoted” or committed to a misspoken statement. So, I will do my best to summarize what we talked about and try to recall what he said as he said it in a way that synthesizes a lot of our casual conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-happened-after-gentle-giant&quot;&gt;What Happened After Gentle Giant?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After Gentle Giant disbanded in 1980, everyone went their separate ways. Ray [Shulman] went on to make techno music and did well with that. He used the pseudonym of “Head Doctor” and was part of a larger crowd of floating musicians doing these sort of techno releases for discos and clubs. After doing music for TV adverts he went on to do video and DVD work, like building interactive menus and assembling DVD content for Marillion, Queen, and some Hollywood stuff. He’s done all the artwork and video stuff for our recent releases, too, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.burningshed.com/store/gentlegiant/product/522/5784/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Power and the Glory&lt;/em&gt; remix DVD &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.burningshed.com/store/gentlegiant/product/522/6951/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Octopus&lt;/em&gt; remix DVD &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He and I experimented with working together but our ideas were so different and distractions plentiful it meant we couldn’t make it work at that time. That was a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Derek went on to work in the music business. He was always the business person behind Gentle Giant, which was great for us and difficult in some ways. He managed our salaries, helped to use record company advances effectively. The record company would give us a sizable advance and Derek would split it up. The priority was of course the studio time, and the left over money covered our living costs.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Another great thing about Derek managing the financial affairs was that when he wanted a raise, he would make sure we all got raises, so none of us would have to ask for more money. Derek still retains a lot of the creative control over the band. Ray is the whizz kid of dvd authoring and illustrations. My wife does all the bookkeeping and paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As for me, I wanted to use my musical capabilities for something different than the rock band performance context. Between 1980 and 1985, I was part of a Christian evangelistic team, working throughout the United Kingdom. Their musical director had stayed with me for a time when the team came to Dorset and eventually the family and I moved to Cornwall where the team were based. We went to churches all over England across various denominations, although I don’t think we entered any Catholic churches, which is a real shame because the Catholics had been responsible for the last major revival throughout England some time ago. I mostly lived off of royalties and “love gifts” from other believers who contributed to the cause.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In 1985, we couldn’t afford to live that way anymore. We had young children to think about, so we moved to the Midlands and I began teaching music to children, while also producing music for children’s educational TV.  I never really told anyone about my work with Giant, although a couple of students did find out and we had fun talking about that. But, I didn’t use my experience with Giant to get ahead except for one job where it was relevant to have experience with percussion arrangements and band-leading. Teaching children was just wonderful - except when I had students that did not practice or put the time in that was required.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We’ve been living in a typical English leafy suburban town near Birmingham for some time now, although we both miss the countryside.  My wife’s mother is close by as are our grown-up kids, so I don’t imagine we will be moving too far away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-you-up-to-lately&quot;&gt;What Are You Up To Lately?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I retired a couple years ago and my wife also retired, so we have been spending a lot of time at home, helping our children out with their lives and taking care my mother-in-law. It’s an ordinary life, really. We have a couple of grandchildren and we get to see them often.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As far as music, I play very regularly at church. I play more guitar now, and some bass.  Our church is about 100 people with 4 drummers (not at the same time like King Crimson), so I don’t play drum.  For the most part, I volunteer and participate where I am needed. I fill the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Speaking of King Crimson, they were the first rock band I ever really heard. They had amps and electric instruments and made all sorts of raucous noise! It was wonderful!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I don’t like leading the church band or choosing the music because I’m too picky musically. If I get music from someone else, I just play it to the best of my ability and try to create an environment where people can experience and meet God. There can be a fine line when playing some of the pad patches because it can almost feel manipulative playing certain chords and picking bass notes that have real resonance and impact on people. But, I do what I can and serve honestly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-you-writing-any-new-music&quot;&gt;Are You Writing Any New Music?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In terms of composing, I’ve been in a bit of a dry spell and I’m working through that. It has been the cause of some anxiety because I know what I used to do with Giant and that work set a personal expectation of a standard for my music. Perhaps I am a different person now or I’ve evolved. I am still looking for that person inside of me. Nowadays, I start to compose and I don’t seem to have any ideas that really pull me in and show real cause for mental investment. If it isn’t worth the investment, I don’t find much reason to do anything but put it to one side.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am usually composing on the piano when I do try to compose. Sometimes I’ll just play some chord progressions and let a finger or two wander and do what they wish, but nothing in the past couple of years has really been fruitful. It’s been a challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;One of my daughters was involved in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_Dance_(musical)&quot;&gt;Lord of the Dance &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Flatley&quot;&gt;Michael Flatley &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing, and just recently has sung with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Bainbridge&quot;&gt;Dave Bainbridge &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.burningshed.com/store/progressive/product/536/6238/&quot;&gt;Celestial Fire &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  And my other daughter is singing in another band. I thought it would be nice to be able to write some nice contrapuntal songs that the four of us (my son is a drummer but has joined us on vocals occasionally) could perform together, so I promised myself and them that I would write some stuff in my retirement, but it just hasn’t gone anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a studio upstairs in the loft at home and a way of recording the piano downstairs. Most ideas start at the piano and if there’s anything worth investing in, I’ll take that idea to the computer upstairs where the rest of the instruments are. It’s not a very convenient workflow. Perhaps that has affected my lack of productivity as well.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I still have my old white cello, though the bow is broken and the instrument is quite beat up after someone borrowed it. I’ve got my Tokai Stratocaster copy, which I got very cheap for 80 quid somewhere, and I would love to upgrade, but I really dislike the instrument shopping experience. I’ll try a strat or a tele in the store and bring my Tokai to compare with the new guitar and say, “No, this isn’t as nice as my Tokai.” Those guitars are looked upon favorably in the market, it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Most of my gear is pretty low end and most of my friends have nicer equipment than I do, which is something I probably need to change. I’m looking at getting some new gear, like a better Strat, maybe a Tele, and an Avid Eleven Rack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-listen-to-for-inspiration&quot;&gt;What do you listen to for inspiration?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I love a lot of the early church music, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Byrd&quot;&gt;William Byrd&lt;/a&gt;. I am a big fan of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&quot;&gt;Bach&lt;/a&gt;.  I like a lot of choral music and classical music. A friend here at GORGG just gave me a CD of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel_Faur%C3%A9&quot;&gt;Gabriel Faure&lt;/a&gt;’s piano quintets, which should be nice as I’m already familiar with several of Faure’s works. I don’t care much for modern pop music or much of the church music nowadays. The choruses and the songs are often difficult to sing and uninspiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interesting-tidbits&quot;&gt;Interesting Tidbits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerry also shared several interesting facts about his life that I thought would be worth noting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He owned a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lotus_Seven&quot;&gt;Lotus Super Seven Series 4 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (I have always wanted a Super 7 and even owned a kit for a replica!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knots&lt;/em&gt; was not written on paper. They recorded it one layer at a time in the studio under Kerry’s guidance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He once went to play &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/experience/id731938339?i=731938359&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Experience&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wurlitzer&quot;&gt;Mighty Wurlitzer organ &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; wearing a black cape and got stuck in the organ pit when he couldn’t find the ‘up’ button&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While driving the tour bus through Arizona, he slammed on the brakes upon seeing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roadrunner&quot;&gt;roadrunner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; crossing the road, which woke up the entire band and he was so excited to tell them what he’d seen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vibraphone&quot;&gt;vibraphone &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was bought from his percussion teacher at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Academy_of_Music&quot;&gt;Royal Academy of Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I forget whether he said he still had them, but I’m pretty sure he doesn’t.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He doesn’t feel that Gentle Giant fit within the ‘prog rock’ genre. It’s too constrained a category to define what GG was going for.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Despite living an hour from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and being in the touring circuit at the same time as King Crimson, Kerry and Robert have never met.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kerry is a big &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Gabriel&quot;&gt;Peter Gabriel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; fan, but the two have never met. They were recently in the same room at the 2015 Prog Awards where Gentle Giant won a lifetime achievement award, but Kerry and Peter didn’t cross paths.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant being presented with &amp;#39;Lifetime Achievement Award&amp;#39; at Prog Music Awards at Globe,London, Sept 3, 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/DAGkBKgFns&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/DAGkBKgFns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Derek Shulman (@dvsmusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dvsmusic/status/639723761990811648&quot;&gt;September 4, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wrap-up&quot;&gt;Wrap-Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerry and I spent many hours getting to know each other personally that weekend. I could not believe what a kindred spirit I’d found in him and I feel that we have developed a new friendship that I hope will endure for years to come. I am so grateful for the experience I had at GORGG and the open arms with which everyone welcomed me. What a great community! Next year’s GORGG can’t come soon enough…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Had such a great time at the GORGG Gentle Giant gathering in Montreal. Thank you to all my new friends! &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/lUNqM5v9bY&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/lUNqM5v9bY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/651421086408667137&quot;&gt;October 6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/kerry-minnear/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/kerry-minnear/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Steve Vai Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a 1-hour interview with Steve Vai conducted on September 12, 2015 at 12PM. It was filmed/engineered by &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/carl-king&quot;&gt;Carl King&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Steve Vai is? Check out our Discover post about Steve!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/steve-vai/vai-interview-mwm-20150912.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/steve-vai/vai-interview-mwm-20150912.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vwTBhKy2A98?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may notice some issues with color and editing; that’s totally my fault. Carl did the filming and audio editing (the good stuff). I did the rest (the amateur stuff).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whoa&quot;&gt;Whoa!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Never thought our &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stevevai&quot;&gt;@stevevai&lt;/a&gt; interview would get written about on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GuitarPlayerNow&quot;&gt;@GuitarPlayerNow&lt;/a&gt;! Thanks!! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/dXUDmsnTtx&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/dXUDmsnTtx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/661374897805856769&quot;&gt;November 3, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview has been featured &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guitarplayer.com/artists/1013/steve-vai-six-inspiring-concepts-from-his-make-weird-music-interview--video/54836&quot;&gt;on Guitar Player Magazine’s website&lt;/a&gt; on the front page! And the feedback for the interview has been fantastic!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Awesome interview. Gives me a new look into how I will direct myself musically.” - Timothy R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This is the best interview Steve has ever done. Well done Guys!! This is gold.” - La Plata Clases de Guitarra&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I have pretty much seen anything and everything Steve has ever done- I have to say- I watched the whole interview last night- WOW- impressive- probably the best overall interview i’ve ever seen him do- it wasn’t campy and stupid like ‘what strings do you use’ or ‘blah blah blah wah pedal’ or ‘tell me about david lee roth’ it was really deep- on both ends- and great- i was extremely impressed.” - Jeries A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you to the hundreds of people who have shared this interview&lt;/strong&gt; and to the &lt;strong&gt;tens of thousands&lt;/strong&gt; that’ve viewed it!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sponsors&quot;&gt;Sponsors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting started, I want to take a moment to thank the sponsors of this interview, without whom I wouldn’t have been able to afford to conduct the interview and have the hardware to do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://softwareplusplus.com&quot;&gt;Cory Berg at Software++ &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;Ed Heisler at Mad Hatter Guitar Products &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://carlkingdom.com&quot;&gt;Carl King Creative &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cory is a software development and management expert who’s written a fantastic book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Software-Must-Have-Skills-Engineers-ebook/dp/B00U4ZRQC6&quot;&gt;Software++: Must-Have Skills for Engineers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There are a lot of software people I’ve met via Make Weird Music and Guitar Circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed is an electrical engineer and business management consultant. He runs Mad Hatter Guitar Products and has developed a great &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com/pages/mad-hatter-solderless-tone-shaping-system-kits&quot;&gt;solderless electronics kit for guitars &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I purchased one and installed it in my white Ibanez Jem. It’s never sounded better. I’m not a tone connoisseur, but even I can tell that the guitar sounds &lt;em&gt;so much better&lt;/em&gt; than the standard, low-end stock components that came with the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl is an expert filmmaker, author, and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/carl-king&quot;&gt;former musician&lt;/a&gt;. His book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Youre-Creative-Genius-Now-What/dp/1932907920&quot;&gt;So, You’re a Creative Genius… Now What? &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, has been a huge inspiration for me and many others. He filmed this interview and provided lots of great equipment and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Check out this awesome contributed artwork of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stevevai&quot;&gt;@stevevai&lt;/a&gt; by Nick Prol. More of his work: &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/iNy6DjxoDd&quot;&gt;http://t.co/iNy6DjxoDd&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/VvJUMKpBOv&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/VvJUMKpBOv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/655421741846495232&quot;&gt;October 17, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from Make Weird..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Steve proceeds to give me a noogie and then rearrange/fix my hair.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Steve: Get outta here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And that’s how we start it! Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with Steve Vai. Steve, the purpose of Make Weird Music is to be a resource to musicians who may or may not have explored a lot of new kinds of music. So, could you give a brief intro to yourself and what you do musically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, on one level, my name is Steve Vai and I am a musician and a guitar player and I love traveling around making music and playing it live. And I play the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’m highlighting you on Make Weird Music and the context of the word “weird” is not necessarily “unlistenable” or “unapproachable” or anything like that. People who do things different, who don’t write pop music targeted to the radio for mass sales and that kind of thing. I want to get behind the motivation of your creativity, what your approach is to composition and how you ended up getting into instrumental guitar music and that kind of thing. When you say, “I play music” and “I play the guitar,” what makes you different from, say, a guitar player who plays in a blues band?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, the same thing that makes them different from people that play in other kinds of bands. There’s a wide selection of music that I enjoy. I like listening to various genres, but when I was growing up, I was a teenager in the 70s, and so I was into all that progressive rock stuff, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yes_(band)&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_(band)&quot;&gt;Queen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and all that stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As I was growing up, I was really into these kinds of progressive guitar players. I listened to blues. I went through jazz phases. Classical phases. It was so interesting to hear such great players all the time. One of the things I realized is “I’ll never be that good.” It was stimulating, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I never felt like I’d be very good at doing &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; and why, when somebody else was doing it so well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I would learn the riffs just for fun, but the thing that always turned me on the most, and the one thing that I’ve always had with me through my whole career, was always the “home base”–the enthusiasm I feel for coming up with something new. For me, at least… New for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You’re always expanding on your own self.&lt;/span&gt; You’re never the same one moment after the next, so the most exciting thing for me is when I do something or I come up with an idea that I haven’t had before. That’s my fuel, that’s my source of inspiration. What I realized I was doing as I never thought I was “good enough” is I would come up with things on my own and say, “Well, that’s interesting. That’s fun. I haven’t heard that.” And then I’d challenge myself to reach different plateaus of technical proficiency and see where that could take me on a creative level and then rise above it. Constantly this rising and it’s exciting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s how I developed my own style. It’s like an accident.&lt;/span&gt; It was almost kind of a conscious turning away from “the norm.” When I say, “the norm,” I mean “genre-specific type of playing,” which is beautiful, I love it, but I can’t do it. It seemed like a waste of time to try to play what sounds like something else that’s already better than what I could do. I just sort of organically started finding things that I liked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;One of the things that made it work is I had no expectations.&lt;/span&gt; I wouldn’t sit down and say, “Okay, I need to write something that everybody will like.” I didn’t think anybody would &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; hear anything I did anywhere. It was my little secret, which created an opening because if nobody’s going to hear what you’re doing, then you can just do whatever you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was really excited when I would come across something that sounded unique to me. Like I said, I had no expectations… So this is sort of a challenge that I to people sometimes when I’m giving a lecture or something, I say, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Go to write a song, but write a song as if no one’s ever going to hear it.”&lt;/span&gt; If I was to tell you that the next song you write is not going to get on the radio, nobody’s going to hear it, nobody’s going to buy it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Some people respond to that with, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Well, then why would I do it?” My answer is, “You shouldn’t because you don’t really want to.”&lt;/span&gt; Some people see the opening in that. What that opening is is the message that “now you have no expectations, you can do whatever you want, you can be completely free of the fear of being criticized, the fear of failing.” You’ve put it away, you’ve already “failed” so to speak with worldly success of it. So, it can create this opening of freedom, like real fearlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Fear is the thing that holds people back from their own unique potentiality.&lt;/span&gt; The interesting thing is, that piece of fearless creative enjoyable enthusiastic non-critical work that you then do is usually the thing you’re going to be the most successful at. You’re usually creating a style and your real true self is flowing into it. Then, the appropriate audience will be responding to it as opposed to trying to second-guess an audience, which is just stress, and you’re competing with people who write music in a field that’s very natural to them. So, that’s what I’ve become more aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Were those fears and anxieties ever a part of your development of your voice and your identity as a musician?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: On one level, yes, because once I started to tour, like when I started with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt;, or even when I’d have to play live, I enjoyed it, but there was always this nervousness. What that nervousness is (that we feel) really is just our ego. It’s fear. It boils down to fear of not being accepted. You know what I mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: When you start to recognize that for what it is, then you can work on it. That’s really your true work because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you can’t really be uniquely expressive if you’re afraid.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How did you feel when you released your debut album, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flex-Able&quot;&gt;Flex-Able &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;? Were you feeling that “I’m just gonna do this and nobody’s gonna listen to it and that’s cool.” Was that where you were coming from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah. When I made &lt;em&gt;Flex-Able&lt;/em&gt;, I had no intentions of being a–at least in my head–a touring, famous… Matter of fact, the idea of being famous was terrifying to me. I don’t know why. I think when I was young, you know you hear things? I think somebody said, “People who are famous go insane.” So I always felt like I was teetering on the edge anyway, so I thought “fame is gonna make me crazy.” It did take its toll in various ways. I’m not so famous, which is kind of nice. I can live a normal life. Um… What was the question?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Hah, when you were making &lt;em&gt;Flex-Able&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Okay. So, still I loved that feeling of recording and editing and making music, coming up with an idea and working on it. So I would record tons and tons and tons of stuff because just recording was fascinating to me and it was all this really crazy stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was living in Sylmar with 8 people in the house, all friends. It was like a wayward home for musician refugees. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I was making music to entertain me and my friends.&lt;/span&gt; I didn’t even plan on releasing it, you know? So there was no expectation. There was just this free flow, no concern if it was going to make me money or not, no concern if I’m going to be accepted with it or not. Pfft, the &lt;em&gt;furthest&lt;/em&gt; thing! Because it was so weird!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The music was kind of left of center. It was very Zappa-influenced because Frank was one of my biggest influences so you can hear that phase of my life. I was working with him, I was seeing how he made music, and it was very… I was very impressionable. I loved his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So then when it was all finished–and that was my biggest learning curve, I recorded that record twice because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I used to work really fast and sloppy. “Okay it’s done!” and I would listen to it and go, “Why does this sound like crap?”&lt;/span&gt; So after hanging out with Frank and seeing how everything is “like this,” I maybe went even too much into that really rigid precision, but it was good for me because it created an integrity. At the time, sometimes it was too much. And even now, sometimes I get carried away with the forensic nature of editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you feel that through your career as a musician, you’ve evolved your voice? Do you feel like you were still discovering it and you’re still in the process of discovering it? Like, that was your voice for that time? How do you feel about the evolution of your self?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Everybody is constantly evolving. You cannot stand still. It’s absolutely impossible. On some levels, it looks that way, but no. Even at this moment, when I was talking a minute ago, I’m different. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When you make a record or you do a piece of art or anything creative, it’s like a little snapshot as to where you were at the time&lt;/span&gt; and you continue to evolve and so many things have an effect on your creative outlook, your creative perspective, how you’re finding yourself… Things that even seem almost inconsequential: people you meet, things you might eat, places you go, the little voice in your head that remembers things from your past or projects into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;All of these things are continually undergoing metamorphosis. Your perspective on even the same thoughts that you’ve had is changing constantly. So, that would only naturally have an effect on your creative integrity. So, yeah, I look back at that music and the guy that was making it and I see a lot of innocence, a lot of almost bombastic freedom. It’s that youthful freedom when you’re 21/22 years old. It was an explosion of freedom. And then when I released &lt;em&gt;Flex-Able&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I was even apprehensive to try because I thought, “Oh, this music is weird.” But I thought, “Well, I like it.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It sort of captured this this weird innocence and corniness side to me that was just pretty prevalent at one point. I thought, “Well maybe somebody will like it.” And then I released it and, yeah, it attracted a particular type of audience. I think what they’re responding to in it is just the honestness, the sincerity of it. I know that when I make music that isn’t very honest, when I’m actually trying to hit a particular group, I always miss the mark. Even if it’s a hit, or even if it’s something that some people might like, I always feel that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;unless there’s something in it that moves me a particular way, I’ve missed out on my potential.&lt;/span&gt; And those songs have no real pull to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Interesting! Composition, what is composition like for you? How has that evolved over time for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, composition is like anything else. It’s a creative expression and it’s the one that I do that I like doing the most. There’s other ways that I love being creative, but composition is like anything else in that there’s a period of time that you go through where you have to hone your tools, you have to sharpen your knives, you have to prepare your vessel, and there’ a lot of focus and a lot of thinking (so to speak) and it’s a lot of repeating and repeating and repeating, it’s a lot of focusing how to change your style a little bit, or researching other music…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Whatever it is, there’s a period of time where, if you’re an athlete, you’re honing your craft, you’re learning the hoops. If you ever played golf, it’s this extraordinary sport because my father used to take me and he used to try to teach me. I’m so golf spastic. Actually, I was pretty good until my back… But, there’s so much to think about, you keep your eye on the ball, keep your knees this way, swing and follow all the way through, keep your head down, and it’s like, “How can you remember all this stuff?” Because you do it over and over and over and over and over and over again until it becomes natural. And then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;once something becomes natural, once the technique becomes honed, then you have to go deeper than the technique.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You have to access that part of you that’s deeper than the mind portion, that’s deeper than just the technique, or else you’ll sound great, but you’ll just sound like technique that knows what it’s doing. It needs that level of depth and then the technique becomes your tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So in composing, you go through the period, and it’s not hard… There’s some rules you gotta know because you’re dealing with time-based reality and people’s abilities and the limitations of an instrument, but there’s so many creative tools when you’re composing, it’s just amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s so much more, for me, in many ways, it’s so much more open and creative than just with a band or even just sitting and playing guitar because now you have a whole large group of people that have to play &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what you write and there’s tools where you can manipulate notes, there’s dynamics, there’s articulations, there’s all sorts of things you can do to one little note to make it sound a certain way. And then you can combine them with all these instruments. It’s this incredible palette of colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For me, the composition process makes every day like Christmas because you just hear things in your head. You don’t want to have to think about how to put it out. You hear it and then you know. So, the composition process is very similar in many ways to other creative processes, although the results are completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: When you are composing, whether it’s for an orchestra or a rock band arrangement, do you ever feel that you’re in a rut or “I keep doing this same thing and this is not who I am.” Maybe your influences have had too much influence and you’re not expressing yourself. If so, how do you break out of that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, yes and there’s various ways you can circumnavigate around those ruts. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The first thing is: Don’t worry about it.&lt;/span&gt; That’s &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt; though, because a lot of people &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; worry. They think, “Oh my God, I’ve lost my mojo. I have no more vision. I have no more creativity. What am I gonna do? I keep repeating myself!” Well, that’s worrying. Another way to look at it is that the lull in your creativity is actually very valuable because it’s, in a way, it’s like you’re preparing and giving it a break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, there’s many things that you can do that I can recommend to get through these ruts. First, don’t worry. And it’s different for different people. Some people are constantly inspired, like Frank, for instance. It never ended and he was always in the moment of it. But, for someone like me, I’m not always inspired. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’d say maybe 3% of the time, I’m &lt;em&gt;really inspired&lt;/em&gt;, but I can do a lot with that 3%.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, what I do is when I feel something is coming or if I’m playing something and I like it and I feel that it has some “juice” to it, so to speak, I capture it somehow. I have thousands and thousands of talking into a microphone, by my bed I’ve got stuff, and it’s all over the place. The iPhone is usually…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Voice Notes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Every musician’s favorite app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: I’ve got hundreds and hundreds and thousands from before cell phones were in existence. Some of them carry a lot of power for me and that’s where I go to to find a lot of songs. That’s where I find most of my songs. Any of my songs that you might like, I can probably show you the “la la la la la.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And all you need is just a little thread! Just a thread!&lt;/span&gt; And then when you go back and listen to it, even if you’re in a rut, it can pull you out. That’s one thing that can help. So, whenever you feel something is happening, try to capture it or document it somehow and then go back to it when you feel like you’re in a rut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Another way is to listen, completely make a left turn and go listen to some music that you’d never think that you would listen to or expect you would listen to. For instance, if you’re a big metal head, I would challenge you to &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;go and listen to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustav_Mahler&quot;&gt;Mahler &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._4_(Mahler)&quot;&gt;4th &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._5_(Mahler)&quot;&gt;5th symphonies &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 10 times each with an open mind.&lt;/span&gt; That could be more valuable than anything else I’ve given you because that’s really powerful and incredible music. Or listen to the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rite_of_Spring&quot;&gt;Rite of Spring &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igor_Stravinsky&quot;&gt;Stravinsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Just listen to it 10 times. Your world will change. Your world will change. It’s mind-expanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iHlJhuS_3TA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But you have to go into it with an open mind, without criticizing it or judging it&lt;/span&gt;, just like I have to go into country music with that or else I’ll cut my throat or something. Then I’ll enjoy it. I used to be like that, &lt;em&gt;verrrry&lt;/em&gt; rigid. &lt;em&gt;Very&lt;/em&gt; rigid. “This is it!” And when I was a kid, “If it’s not Led Zeppelin, it’s nothing.” And that only stifles your own creativity because the thing that the universe has to offer that’s so plentiful and absolutely at the core of creativity is the diversity. There’s nothing the same in the whole universe! Nothing! I mean, isn’t that remarkable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: It’s incredible, if you think about it. So, with that in mind, your ability to be creative is unique because you are an expression of the universe. So, yeah, that’s some of the things that I do. If you just go and force yourself with an open mind to listen… Like when I was doing &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alive_in_an_Ultra_World&quot;&gt;Alive in an Ultra World &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, it was a glorious project because I was listening to all of this music from different countries, this cultural music. It was really beautiful because you taste the flavor of the country, you taste the people and the way the music is structured, because I have a musical ear (in a sense) I can hear the time signature, I can hear the technical aspects, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when you’re listening to it, you’re not listening to the technical. You’re hearing the thing that’s deeper than their technique.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, if you go listen to a Bulgarian women’s choir, you think, “I don’t want to listen to a Bulgarian women’s choir, sounds like women making weird noises.” Listen really carefully. It will just change your world. That, then, can inspire you. Or if you’re a blues player, go listen to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Just listen to a few of their records–soft, if necessary. Just listen to the creative aspects of it and it’ll have a huge impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qc98u-eGzlc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Your music ranges from straightforward (just you and an acoustic guitar not doing anything super technical, chords and singing beautiful melodies)…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: I can’t on an acoustic guitar…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Hah! But then some of your other songs are very influenced by Stravinski and Ravel and these kinds of complex, more modern composers. Do you get in a mood and say, “I really want to channel some of that.” Or do these things just come out through listening 10 times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, both. Sometimes what we hear has an impact on us and then it comes out unconsciously. Somehow it flows out into what we do. Somehow it does. To some degree. And then there’s the actual listening to something and being moved and saying, “I want to write something like that,” which is the way most people write music. There’s nothing wrong with that because it will still sound different, but that’s how things evolve, too. I do that occasionally, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes it works if there’s enough unique ideas that flow into it. If I just go to plagiarize a song, you wouldn’t know it was the original song, but usually it doesn’t carry–for me–the kind of thing I’m looking for in my music. Sometimes it does. Like, for instance, take something like &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VlexYog2kZA&quot;&gt;Building the Church &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. My kids were listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linkin_Park&quot;&gt;Linkin Park &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I, immediately, when I heard it, I said, “That’s some nice big fat guitar. I like that. I gotta do something like that.” You know, those heavy chords and the tuning? I was inspired by that and that flowed into &lt;em&gt;Building the Church&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VlexYog2kZA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There was enough other stuff, like the tapping thing, which originated 35 years ago with the song &lt;em&gt;Upanishads&lt;/em&gt; and that was just a–I needed to transcend the gimmick nature of it. So, I put my technical mind to work and I said, “Well, I know that if I create these chords…” There was that. And then it had to have a particular melody that felt a certain way and then it had to have something else a little special, so there’s a little thing in the end… So you might be able to hear that it was [influenced].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You take something else like &lt;em&gt;Dying for Your Love&lt;/em&gt;, which is on that record, that wasn’t inspired by anybody. That was just me listening to my inner ear and following a melody based on an emotional state of mind. That started out fooling around on a sample thing until the drum beat came. Then I took it from there. So there’s different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you ever feel that you compromise in your music? Do you listen to something and go, “I could go in this direction, but that might bother some… my audience?” Or something like that? Do you ever feel sensitive to anything other than what suits you when you’re composing or performing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, it has to suit you first. Why do it? Why do it if it doesn’t suit you? If it suits you–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you make &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; the most important thing in what &lt;em&gt;you do&lt;/em&gt;, then the audience that comes to it will be the right audience for you&lt;/span&gt; as opposed to trying to say, “Well this genre here likes this kind of music, so let me throw some of that…” That’s insane thinking! I shouldn’t say it’s “insane,” it’s very common. And I do do it sometimes! But those songs just do not carry that thing that I like the most, which is, “Whoa. Oh my God, did that really sound real?” That’s what I like. Sometimes that happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That piece I just played you, the second half of &lt;em&gt;Mighty Messengers&lt;/em&gt; [from an upcoming anniversary release of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passion_and_Warfare&quot;&gt;Passion and Warfare &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; ], to me it’s just so beautiful. It’s so beautiful, you know? I just love sitting there and just hearing those rich, thick chords with all these guitars and the melody, the way it moves. The solo section, which every little piece (for me) is… I mean, I worked on every piece until I did something different than I’d ever done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s what I do. I’ll sit with a solo sometimes, I’ll do that so that when I listen back–and you hear yourself doing something that you haven’t really ever done, you’re just like, “Holy mackerel, wow! That’s so cool! So cool!” And it’s okay to feel that way about what you do. Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The thing that says in you, “This sucks,” is your own ego. What it’s &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; saying is, “This is not better. This will not be proclaimed as making me mightier and greater of a brilliant creator than everybody else on the planet so it must suck.” It’s this weird shit in your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Creating something and then listening back and critiquing it, that’s a different story. “Oh I hear… I like that, I don’t like that, let me see how I can…” That’s good. I can only speak for myself because I used to go through every kind of emotional dynamic. Now it’s really: You gotta please yourself first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: We’re in a day and age where there are countless options, countless guitar tones, software that can manipulate every single thing you do and now it’s so easy to use that it’s almost more difficult not to get caught up in it. How do you feel about the evolution of what has been available to you from 30-some years ago to what you have now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: It’s amazing. It’s wonderful. It’s based on your attitude. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Whatever your attitude on it will become your reality.&lt;/span&gt; So, if you’re looking at something… There’s three basic ways to look at something. Take new technology that’s come in and it’s suddenly there and it’s endless and it keeps developing every minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One perspective is: “This sucks. Why can’t we all just go back to just picking up the guitar and just playing it?” Well, go ahead and do that. Nobody’s telling you you have to record it with reverse flanges and chop it up and have it up on YouTube within 10 seconds. But, usually that kind of perspective carries with it a lot of baggage, like, “Not only does this suck, but the whole business sucks because how can I sell music anymore with this new technology, streaming, I can’t get paid at all. Why make music?” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you have to ask yourself that question, don’t make it! Go do something else!&lt;/span&gt; Because you’re not really compelled to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People that make music under any circumstance &lt;em&gt;have no choice&lt;/em&gt;. It’s like, “This is what I wanna do and that’s it.” So, perspective of “everything is sucking” isn’t just what you’re observing in the music business, it’s what you’re observing in most of your life usually. And it’s just your perspective. You could say, “But Steve, no, this is real. This is true. Streaming has destroyed the ability for artists to make money.” Well, on one level, that is true. There’s a lot of things that are true, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a lot of other things that are true. For instance, right now is the best time in history to be an independent musician. You have more tools at your disposal than has ever been before. If you have the goods, if you’re creative enough, you can create your work. There’s so many people now to network with, you can get with other people… You couldn’t do that in the past. There’s so much you couldn’t do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that’s the second perspective: Looking out and seeing, “How can this serve me? How can all this wonderful–wonderful!–technology serve me?” And I can tell you &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m doing better now than I’ve ever been doing and I’m selling a lot less records&lt;/span&gt; because records don’t sell, but I’m just doing gangbusters. I had my best year ever in my life this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Congratulations! That’s amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah. The government likes it, too. They’re very happy for me. Because I look and I see, “How can this serve me?” And that’s just a shift, just a simple shift, and then other things that are true are now on your radar. And whatever belief you have becomes your truth, but they’re all just thoughts in your head anyway. So, you have the ability to shift the vibration of your thoughts from that first perspective to the second perspective, which is much more advantageous to you. And there’s a lot of truths in that, too! Write a list of them! Write a list of all of the truths that make you feel good. There’s nothing better you can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then there’s the third perspective, which is usually reserved for those people that breathe very thin air. That perspective is: “This is wonderful technology that’s going on in the world. How can I improve it? What does it lack? Where can I take it? What is impractical about it?” And there’s no end to where that ladder climbs to, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you look to the past, you’ll find at any time in history, most of the time people feel like wherever they have evolved to with a particular technology, they feel like they’ve arrived. “How can it ever get better than vinyl?” Now it’s like, “Great Steve, but how is it ever going to get better than streaming anything you want?” It’s gonna get a lot better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know what that is, but I know that what we look for as a species is convenience, simplicity, and immediacy. There’s nothing wrong with that, but it’s never going to happen because even when you’re at that stage, even if you can say, “&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_II&quot;&gt;Queen II &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Liar&lt;/em&gt;…” Oh that’s on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_(Queen_album)&quot;&gt;Queen I &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; You can just say, “I wanna hear &lt;em&gt;Queen I&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Liar&lt;/em&gt;.” And all of a sudden, you just start hearing it. That’s pretty immediate, no bills to pay, or maybe there’s bills to pay, but nothing to touch. That’s a lot more convenient than what we have now, which is a big pain in the ass, really. It’s still completely inferior as far as I’m concerned. I tried to do the streaming and, no, it’s not good enough. It doesn’t work every place, I have to reach into my pocket and grab something and fiddle around, I don’t want to do any of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Hope you have a connection, hope you’re logged in…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Hope you’re logged in! It’s so inferior! Come on, guys! So, there’s somebody sitting there right now going, “Nah, nah, it’s just not right yet. What can I do to make it right? What can I do to make it better?” And that’s the third way of thinking. So, look at the vast contrast in the person that’s saying, “Okay all of these great toys, now I’m going to focus on this and make this. I have a vision for something that’s much better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And that’s how it always works to the guy that “everything sucks.” And they’re talking about the &lt;em&gt;same thing!&lt;/em&gt; The perspective that you choose is not just reflected in the thing you’re looking at, it’s reflected in all the other things in your life. All you have to do is change one little perspective in some place one little bit and then everything else changes too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Has your music always been so influenced by these softer skills? These emotional approaches, spiritual approaches to your music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, whenever we enter that creative zone in our heads, we’re always attracted to the things that we’re most interested in at the time. So, when I look back, like I’m doing this 25th anniversary [of &lt;em&gt;Passion and Warfare&lt;/em&gt;] and I’m going all the way back to &lt;em&gt;Flex-Able&lt;/em&gt; and I’m listening to all the tracks that I recorded and stuff like that, there was a period of discovery for me back then when I was going through changes and I was studying metaphysics and spirituality and all these things, so a lot of the symbolism flowed into the music, but a lot of it was really just symbolism and surface value things. I didn’t really understand at the time–well how would you? Now, a different kind of interconnection flows into the music, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: When you hear that older music, are you still as proud of it as you were when it was new? Do you listen and you’re excited by it, or is it like, “Well, that’s cute Steve.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah, a lot of “that’s cute. That’s funny. I remember that guy.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t really feel proud, I feel gratitude. I’m grateful that I did it.&lt;/span&gt; I see that kid sitting there working his ass off, same thing I’m doing now, and just having fun. Just being creative and getting an idea and having to do it. And that’s never changed. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;All the technology’s changed, the way you do it, the tools you use might change, but still the arising of an inspired idea, you need that.&lt;/span&gt; And back then, I was cutting my teeth in the studio learning how to record, learning how to decorate the stereo real estate, so I hear all that too. There’s still something in there that I get a kick out of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Were you a musician before you picked up the guitar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah, I believe so. I mean a “musician” is a big word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I don’t mean as a profession, but as your identity, your form of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: I know that I always had a deep attraction to music. A lot of people do. Most people do. I think when I was 4 years old, I remember walking up to a piano and hitting a note and realizing to the right, the notes go higher, and to the left, they go lower. And immediately, I had two great epiphanies right at that moment. One was I understood instinctually the construction of music, so whenever I would hear, I would think, “Oh, that’s what music is!” And then, “These are all the notes.” I could see them, I kinda knew what staffs were and those kinds of things, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I heard anything, I could say, “Okay, that’s that and oh, that’s cool.” But then the other realization was I was overcome with the reality that musical creativity is infinite, that no one can tap it out, that it’ll never end. Within me alone are infinite musically creative ideas. I knew at that moment, that flooded through me, and I knew I was going to be a musician. I didn’t know the word “musician,” I didn’t know what that meant, I just knew that “I like this, I want to be one of those creators forever. This is what I like.” It was an epiphany of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, absolutely. That drives so much creativity, when people have that epiphany moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah. And you can point to times in your life where you have them. It’s like a moment of clarity. You can even picture, smell what was going on, or see what was going on. So, I loved the way music looked. I thought it looked like beautiful art and I would doodle musical notes and I just started writing. I didn’t know what I was writing, but it looked like music and it didn’t have any sense to it. Then I started to learn, “Okay, this is that and that’s what that means,” and I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; that information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I had no interest whatsoever in virtually anything that I was learning in school.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;[Author’s Note: Do yourself a favor and read &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Element-Finding-Passion-Changes-Everything/dp/0143116738&quot;&gt;The Element &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; or watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/speakers/sir_ken_robinson&quot;&gt;Ken Robinson’s TED Talks &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on this subject.]&lt;/span&gt; I couldn’t retain things like history. I could not retain anything. I’d sit and I’d listen to the teacher and I’d just say, “I don’t care about any of this shit. And I don’t want to know about it. It’s crazy people at war! Why do I want to know about that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And you’re graded on it. And your success is determined by how you memorized it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: And the level of your intelligence is based on it… Now, if it’s interesting to you, that’s great! And I can understand that there’s certain things that are probably a good idea to know and I know those, but spinning wheels learning about “things.” I like math, but if you don’t like math, no worries! Don’t study it! But, that’s unfortunately not where we’re at right now. But, that was the thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You asked if I knew I was a musician. No, I didn’t, I just knew that I loved music and I had all these musical ideas. Now, I didn’t realize until later in life that most people don’t hear and see music that way unless you’re a musician. And then there’s this more visual/audible understanding in your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It took me many years before I could call myself a musician because it was always such a sacred word. You know the word “musician” to me meant somebody who &lt;em&gt;really knew music&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;really immersed themselves in the musical experience&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;had command over the technique and the technology&lt;/em&gt; and could just &lt;em&gt;hear this and see that&lt;/em&gt;. And I said, “Yeah, that’s what you are. That’s what you like. Go with it.” There was always this apprehension to call myself a musician because I was afraid of sounding pretentious. Like, “Ohhh yeah? Now you’re a musician? Oh yeah?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: “Can you do this?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: “Can you do that?” Then I realized that’s another egoic mind structure. Then that went away and it was just, “Yeah, I play music. I’m a musician.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you still face any of these inhibitions or these things that block your creativity or the good voice that tells you who you are and what you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, the little voice that tells you who you are and what you do is an identity that you created for yourself through your life. You know what I mean? It’s not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It’s your idea of who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: It’s your &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; of who you are. Yeah, it’s the… You have a name, which is just funny sounds that come out of the mouth, and you picture your name as a hat, all the things you went through you throw into that hat, and then you look at these things and you create an identity for yourself. “I am this guy that this happened to, or this one man/woman, or this happened to me so that means I am this and I have these issues and I have these strengths,” so you create this identity for yourself, but it’s not really who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;On one level, it’s fine, you know? But people say, “Music is your life.” “No, it’s not. Music is what I do in life. Life is something much deeper than what I do in it. Not just me, but everybody.” So, your question was…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you still face these things that torture many &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; people and perhaps tortured you in the past?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: There’s various aspects of things that torture me and one of the things I’m getting over right now, as stupid and as simple as it might sound: it’s little frustrations that have always driven me crazy when I’m at work. I’ll be into doing something, all of a sudden a string would break or a battery would go dead or something where I have to go and deal with it. It would always create this frustration. And it’s funny because I can be really solid on so many levels. People come to me with problems, or I have a problem, but run out of &lt;em&gt;battery&lt;/em&gt;?! “Why can’t you?! Why does it?!” It’s a form of suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I realized I don’t want to suffer at all in life, so how do you deal with it? These things happen, all this stuff happens, so you just deal with it, but you don’t need the drama. And then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you use going up and changing the battery as part of the process of making the record and getting to your goal and &lt;em&gt;it’s fine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; There’s things that are challenges, I have similar challenges as many people, but through the past 5, 6 years I’ve been undergoing a huge change. We all do. This is profound change for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the biggest things a person can go through is when they &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;start recognizing in themselves their own destructive thought patterns&lt;/span&gt; that have been in place sometimes for many, many, &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; years. And they’re just thoughts in your head, but you believe them! But they’re relative. Once you realize that, you’re starting to access freedom, liberation because you’re not a prisoner of your own thoughts. That’s really what meditation helps with, all those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, do I suffer through a lot of the things that everybody else does? I go through them, but I can’t vouch for the way other people suffer. When I look into the world, I see there’s a lot of it. They take things very seriously and I used to, too. Very, very fiercely intense. Now I don’t! Hah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: A lot of people write music in response to an emotional trial or something. It sounds like you’re getting to a point where the creativity is more pure and less reactive. It’s creative for the sake of being creative, not “I need to express how pissed off I got when that battery died.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;No, I don’t do that because that perpetuates that frame of mind.&lt;/span&gt; I’ve always felt, and I don’t criticize anybody because everything is a process and it’s different for different people, but emotion is… Let’s say it’s a vibration, which it is. We’re really just vibrating energy, any scientist will tell you… Well, not any, but you know…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: [Points to Carl King] That scientist will…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: So we’re just vibrating energies and a thought is like an energy and it has a vibrational quality to it, so to speak. Those thoughts create corresponding emotions. That’s what emotions are: emotions are just indicators of what you’re really thinking. So if you want to know what you’re thinking, ask yourself how you feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;are you in touch with the way you feel?&lt;/span&gt; In order to be in touch with the way you feel, you need to be able to put your attention into your body and see how it feels. With thoughts being of various qualities, they create a resonance in your body, which then turns into an emotion. It’s not the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of people think, “I’m just feeling shitty.” You’re feeling shitty because of the thoughts you’re thinking. You don’t realize it because there’s this natural momentum that has happened over your whole life. Actually, it’s the collective consciousness of humanity for thousands of years, thousands and thousands of years. They’re not even your thoughts really. But they are, they’re thinking you. So, that has an effect in the body as an emotion, so when you then enter the creative zone in anything you do and you’re basing it on an emotional charge, that flows into whatever you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you can hear that in certain music, people are very happy to tell you how miserable they are.&lt;/span&gt; They’re very happy to create music about how fucked up their life is and how fucked up the world is. Oh, that’s a good one! Because when you proclaim that the world is fucked up, what you’re really saying is, “Because I know better. Because I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; better. I’m better than the world and I can show you how. The world is fucked up!” It’s a form of insanity, but it’s the ego and it only brings suffering to yourself and others and that flows into your work and that work carries that energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now the reason why so many people are attracted to brokenhearted love songs is because most people are brokenhearted. They’re looking for something in another person that you can’t find because it’s not there. You have to &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;find it in yourself and then you can share it, that’s when you can become really useful and helpful.&lt;/span&gt; When you enter a particular emotional frame of mind and you create within it, you’re perpetuating that particular frame of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You need to decide how you want to feel. Do you want to feel miserable?, which the ego loves. Some people really love feeling miserable. They don’t want to not feel miserable. They don’t want to not feel drama. They don’t want to not complain about something. It’s because it’s a sense of identity. With complaining you’re telling the world that you’re better than whatever it is that you’re complaining about. Or, do you want to put all that emotion aside and just get real with it? Enter that zone…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now I use “emotionless” but it sounds on one level like a coldness, but really it’s pure joy, really, because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when you enter that ultra zone of creativity, you’re resonating at a higher vibration&lt;/span&gt;, so to speak. What comes out may not necessarily… It’s comes out through the filter of who you are, too. That’s what I focus on. Now, do I like to create things that sound really intense and wild? Yeah! Sometimes yeah! I like to, the best that I possibly can, find the most beautiful stuff that I can write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What I love doing, I was just telling Pia the other night, I love cultivating delicacies and I like to find little… And I’ll do it with one little kind of thing that I’m the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; one that’s going to get it. I am the &lt;em&gt;only one&lt;/em&gt;, but oddly enough, there’s this small group of people that get it. And that’s nice. But that’s what I like. I like it to feel powerful and joyful all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now when I look back on some of my music, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s some real tortured stuff because I was really tortured at some points in my life.&lt;/span&gt; But if you stay in that, you perpetuate more of it. Now some people might say, “Well, no that’s how you work it out. Get angry! And you do that!” Yes, if you’re using the anger to escalate yourself to the next higher emotional state, and then the next one, and then the next one…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Not to just &lt;em&gt;replace&lt;/em&gt; the torture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah, but if you stay in the anger, no it’s not good for you, it’s just going to perpetuate more of it and you’re going to be more miserable and you’ll love being miserable more and more until there’s a collapse because nothing can withstand the weight of that kind of suffering. Your ego has a built-in self defense mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Wow. Some deep stuff. Carl, do you have any questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Carl: Did you just make all that stuff up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;C: No, I do have a question, actually, that popped up. Somehow, this sounds a little bit like, and I don’t mean this in any making-fun-of-you kind of way, but some of this sounds like &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dianetics&quot;&gt;Dianetics &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Things that you’re referencing, elements of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Well, it could be. I read the &lt;em&gt;Dianetics&lt;/em&gt; book 35 years ago along with many other books. What I realized is that, at the core, religions basically have fundamental truth that resonates with all of them. I can’t really comment on &lt;em&gt;Dianetics&lt;/em&gt;. I have some friends that are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology&quot;&gt;Scientologists &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I read the book many years ago and I actually was audited when I first moved out to California. I was, like, 20 years old and they were out on the street and it was a very interesting process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think I understood that the basic principle was–now I’m using different terminology, but it’s the same terminology, it’s a parallel terminology with anything that Christ might have said or Buddha or any of that, and basically is: You’re not your thoughts. Your thoughts have an energy to them and who you are is under the thoughts, it’s your consciousness itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When you realize, and it’s not something acquire, you already are, but it’s obscured and in &lt;em&gt;Dianetics&lt;/em&gt;, the process is to eliminate those mind patterns that are obscuring your true presence, your true consciousness. They have terminologies for it, I don’t know what it is… What do they call it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;C: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thetan&quot;&gt;Thetans &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Thetans! Whatever it is. And then you reach a stage where you’re clear and that means that you have conquered the world the way Jesus said it in that there’s nothing in the world that’s gonna disturb your peace. And that’s the destiny of all of us, hopefully. I don’t know these things for sure. So, you can say the same thing about Buddhism, or Christianity, or any of these. They’re all pointing to one thing, but the ego of man is not satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Everybody’s at a different level of understanding and they’re all ranked. There’s nobody that’s wrong because that’s what they see! And to them, this is their reality. And there’s always people below them that they’re pulling up and there’s always people above them that they’re being pulled up by. So, it’s all relative wherever you are in your religion, even if you’re a right-wing fundamentalist. It’s fine, “fine” until you suffer and you might start hearing the truth of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, maybe that’s some analogy with Scientology. But, Scientology, like very many of the others, there’s also an egoic contingency that the reason I didn’t pursue it more, I saw the deep ego in it. When I was being audited, I understood the processes of explaining certain situations in my life that were painful in order to work them out and confront them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But then there was this suggestion that I felt from the people that were interviewing me where they were holding something over you because whenever you express something that’s personal, you are being vulnerable, you’re allowing yourself to be very vulnerable and there’s people who will abuse that, and that’s what I was feeling. And I don’t think that’s the case with everybody in that religion, whatever it is. I have friends that are Scientologists, amazing people, and it’s worked for them beautifully. And then there’s zombies, and it’s like that in all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, it’s really interesting to hear how this all feeds into your creative approach and your composition. It’s fascinating and that’s what I’m learning through these interviews. Everyone’s approaches are so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: Yeah, my creative approach, I didn’t really talk to much about that. One of the things that I do that I want to share and I think you’ll really enjoy, I think &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;my greatest talent is the ability to visualize.&lt;/span&gt; I didn’t realize I was doing it all these years, but that’s what I would recommend people focus on when they want to be creative. Visualize how you want to feel about what you’re going to create. Visualize yourself performing it, visualize yourself creating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes what I do is &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I write a list of the things that I want a particular song to have.&lt;/span&gt; I don’t know what the song is going to be, but I know that it’s going to happen because I’ve been doing it so long I’m conditioned to know that “if I want this, it’s going to happen.” So, one of the things you can try that’s really exciting, and I do this sometimes, is you just write a list of the kind of things that you want in a song and then watch it come together. Enjoy the process of it coming together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The most important thing that you can feel when you’re creating is enthusiasm for the unique creative ideas that arise in you. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you don’t have the enthusiasm, wait until an idea comes that gives it to you.&lt;/span&gt; Don’t block it because of your ego. That’s hard to do. And the other thing that I might say very simply is you can only do one thing at a time, even if you have plans to do hundreds of things, you can really only do one thing in this moment and if you give it your full attention while you’re doing it, there’s a quality that flows into it that’s very powerful. You lose psychological time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Right. You’re in the element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: You’re in the now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: All right, well thank you so much. I really appreciate you getting into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;S: You got it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s a wrap!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/steve-vai/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/steve-vai/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mike Keneally Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an epic, huge, deep 90-minute interview with Mike Keneally conducted on September 9, 2015 at 3PM. It was filmed/engineered by &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/carl-king&quot;&gt;Carl King&lt;/a&gt;. The story behind the interview is kinda funny, so I’ll share it &lt;a href=&quot;#story&quot;&gt;in a later section&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Mike Keneally is? Check out our Discover post about Mike!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Laughing about talking about making weird music with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MikeKeneally&quot;&gt;@MikeKeneally&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/9aIE1jK07T&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/9aIE1jK07T&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/642148128154517504&quot;&gt;September 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally/keneally-interview-mwm-20150909.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally/keneally-interview-mwm-20150909.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/essLZ2eFqnc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may notice some issues with color and editing; that’s totally my fault. Carl did the filming and audio editing (the good stuff). I did the rest (the amateur stuff).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;glowing-reviews&quot;&gt;Glowing Reviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten such great feedback on this interview!! Thank you to the hundreds of people who watched/read it in the first couple days!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Much thanks for doing the interview! It was by far, hands down, the best interview I have seen with any musician - Ever! Really unbelievable. - &lt;em&gt;Lucas L.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks so much for doing this! I haven’t enjoyed an interview that much for a long, long time. - &lt;em&gt;Andre L.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This might be the best MK interview yet. Thanks to all for making it happen! - &lt;em&gt;Jeff S.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have to admit that I was completely unfamiliar with his music and hadn’t heard much of the bands he’s recorded with but that wasn’t an issue because I could really appreciate Mike’s insight to the creative process behind the music, especially as a designer. Shortly after watching the video I spend another hour into the night exploring his music catalog, and wandered over to Zappa, Vai, Satriani and was completely blown away. - &lt;em&gt;Will M.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is all put together with generosity and care. A good team enabling a great interview. Most outfits would put their cold pruning shears on such a thing – “What? Go 90 minutes? We wouldn’t stretch our format for Thomas Jefferson or Martin Luther King, let alone this Mike Keneally guy.” I hope they feel our gratitude. - &lt;em&gt;Doug S.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A fine interview. A capital interview, yes! Thank you Anthony Garone! Please check out MakeWeirdMusic.com for all your weird music needs. - &lt;em&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sponsors&quot;&gt;Sponsors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting started, I want to take a moment to thank the sponsors of this interview, without whom I wouldn’t have been able to afford to conduct the interview and have the hardware to do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://softwareplusplus.com&quot;&gt;Cory Berg at Software++ &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;Ed Heisler at Mad Hatter Guitar Products &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://carlkingdom.com&quot;&gt;Carl King Creative &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cory is a software development and management expert who’s written a fantastic book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Software-Must-Have-Skills-Engineers-ebook/dp/B00U4ZRQC6&quot;&gt;Software++: Must-Have Skills for Engineers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There are a lot of software people I’ve met via Make Weird Music and Guitar Circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed is an electrical engineer and business management consultant. He runs Mad Hatter Guitar Products and has developed a great &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com/pages/mad-hatter-solderless-tone-shaping-system-kits&quot;&gt;solderless electronics kit for guitars &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I purchased one and installed it in my white Ibanez Jem. It’s never sounded better. I’m not a tone connoisseur, but even I can tell that the guitar sounds &lt;em&gt;so much better&lt;/em&gt; than the standard, low-end stock components that came with the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl is an expert filmmaker, author, and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/carl-king&quot;&gt;former musician&lt;/a&gt;. His book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Youre-Creative-Genius-Now-What/dp/1932907920&quot;&gt;So, You’re a Creative Genius… Now What? &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, has been a huge inspiration for me and many others. He filmed this interview and provided lots of great equipment and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;story&quot;&gt;How this interview happened&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kencoffman.com&quot;&gt;Ken Coffman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a fan of Make Weird Music, saw &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;our interview with Andy West&lt;/a&gt; and recommended I email Mike to request an interview. While encouraging, this request also seemed a little far-fetched. Instead, I emailed Mike sharing the Andy West interview basically saying, “Hey, pardon the interruption, but I thought you’d be interested in this interview I did with Andy West.” Oddly enough, he wrote back saying he’d not only seen it, but he shared it on his facebook page!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also agreed to doing an interview. I was so freaking excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the day of the interview, I left my home in Phoenix at 1AM to arrive at Carl’s house in LA that morning. We then started driving out to where Mike wanted to do the interview, but there was an excessive heat warning and chance of rain and Mike wanted us to come to his place instead. This wouldn’t normally be a big deal, but Carl and I left his house without lighting and he also forgot his lenses. So, we had to buy lighting and a lens on the way to Mike’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took us a while to adjust to the changes (or at least, I did since I was a little nervous and super-tired), but as the interview went on, it just got better and better. Admittedly, I was exhausted from both lack of sleep and from introversion, but it was &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I transcribed the interview, I came to realize how deep the conversation really was and I was probably too tired to recognize it at the time. Nevertheless, we captured it all on tape and I am just beginning to really appreciate all Mike’s wisdom. I’ll try highlighting important stuff in the video and transcript below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the transcription process, I also came to realize how similar the approaches and language and even tone of voice are between Mike’s interview and Andy’s. If you haven’t heard Andy’s, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;definitely check it out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Are we rolling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Cool! All right. This doesn’t need to be formal or anything. I just want to have a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Right on. That sounds cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I don’t know how to start these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Let’s try a formal introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;. You wanna tell people about some of your background?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Okay. I’ve been a musician since age 7, so that’s 46 years. Oh my God! Played with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt; in the late 80s and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dweezil_Zappa&quot;&gt;Dweezil &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the 90s. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; in the second half of the 90s. Been working with the group &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dethklok&quot;&gt;Dethklok &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; since 2007 and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Satriani&quot;&gt;Joe Satriani &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; since 2010 and I’ve been making solo records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Starting in the mid-80s I was doing home cassettes. I started making CDs in the early 90s and I’m up to about 25 solo releases at this point. I’m about to put out the latest, which is called &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt;. That will be out before the end of the year. I’m about to head out on the road with Satriani for months and months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Very cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: There’s the thumbnail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Great! So, in this conversation, I’d just like to cover some of the more creative aspects of who you are, what you do, what motivates you, what gets in the way of motivation, how you compose… So, I think composition might be a good place to start. Your music kinda explore…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Got it! I think we’re done here. Thank you, Mike!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You’re welcome. It’s been a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, your music explores a lot of different territory. You’ve got some straightforward rock songs and then you’ve got some really exploratory surrealistic music. But, even in your straightforward music–more mainstream kind of rock stuff–you still digress into a lot of exploratory themes and motifs. Can you give us some sense of how you start with the composition and when you decide something’s going to be…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s all so instinctive&lt;/span&gt;. It’s never until it’s all done that I can look back and se what the heck it is that I’ve just done because with everything that I do, it’s always about that first step. You think, “Okay, is this a worthwhile starting point? Does this seem like it has any kind of legs and is it going to keep me interested for the entirety of the time that it’s going to take to reach whatever the completion point is?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It always starts with that seed of something. And that can be a lyrics, or an idea for a kind of song. “This album really needs something that’s six minutes long and that feels something like this.” And that could be something. Or it could be a melodic idea that just landed in my head and that’s increasingly–in the last few year has been–I’ve built up this archive of these little snippets on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Just using the Voice Memo app where I could be in Target in the middle of shopping and all of a sudden, I’ll say, “Hold on a second.” I’ll just go somewhere where there hopefully aren’t too many people and just go, “Dugga diGAHHH. Dugga diGAHHH.” You know? Later on, I’ll take just that mumble into the recording studio and I’ll listen to it and decide if this is a worthwhile starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We were talking about the last album, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/you-must-be-this-tall/&quot;&gt;You Must Be This Tall &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, four of the songs on that album were derived from voice memos while I was out on the road with Satriani or Dethklok. These little psychotic-sounding ramblings into the phone. Then I set myself a challenge, which is to go into the studio for a week, and each day–well, it was four days–each day of those four days, complete a song structure based on this little germ of an idea. So, for that album, there’s a song called &lt;em&gt;The Rider&lt;/em&gt; and another one called &lt;em&gt;Pitch Pipe&lt;/em&gt; and another one called &lt;em&gt;Kidzapunk&lt;/em&gt; and then a fourth one, which… I can’t remember what it is. Ah, &lt;em&gt;Cavanaugh&lt;/em&gt;. And these all started as just four or five seconds-worth of stuff on the phone. And then I listen to that and think, “Does this want to be a guitar song or does this want to be a keyboard song?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m lucky that I can kind of turn to both of those things and that they’re both so different and each instrument inspires me in completely different ways. Obviously &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;with a keyboard, you can build up much more dense harmonic information&lt;/span&gt;. On the guitar, at any single moment, you’re pretty much limited to six notes at a time unless you’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Frith&quot;&gt;Fred Frith &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then you start hammering things on and nailing stuff into the instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that’s step 1. “What instrument does this song want to be born on?” And then you just begin this sort of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papier-mâché&quot;&gt;papier mache &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; process of laying on strips of information and each one, to me, lead inexorably to the next. You have your starting point, you listen to that, and the analogy I tend to use is: I’m putting a needle on a record and I’m a fan of music, as we all are, and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;what do I want to hear?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that tends to determine for me whether I think a song needs to be written. It’s like, put down the needle and what’s the first thing that I hear and does it excite me? Does it make me want to keep listening? So, that helps me decide where a starting point of a song is. And then, every time I’ve got one piece of the puzzle in place, I just listen to it and try to feel what the next thing is supposed to be and all of that is–I know entirely that process is really informed by all the music I grew up listening to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And you say that I write these songs that, from all appearances appear to be kind of straightforward, and then they’ll take this crazy detour. That makes sense to me because I grew up loving &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_beatles&quot;&gt;The Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rolling_Stones&quot;&gt;The Rolling Stones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Cooper&quot;&gt;Alice Cooper &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but then at a certain point, I started hearing Frank Zappa and then things started to get even weirder. I started listening to &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/captain-beefheart&quot;&gt;Beefheart&lt;/a&gt;, listening to &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/the-residents&quot;&gt;The Residents&lt;/a&gt;, listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Cow&quot;&gt;Henry Cow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Then I started listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis&quot;&gt;Miles Davis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&quot;&gt;John Coltrane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But at the same time, I loved &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Dylan&quot;&gt;Bob Dylan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I loved &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_%26_Garfunkel&quot;&gt;Simon &amp;amp; Garfunkel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I loved &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joni_Mitchell&quot;&gt;Joni Mitchell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I loved &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sly_and_the_Family_Stone&quot;&gt;Sly &amp;amp; The Family Stone &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And it’s all equally valid to me. So, to me it fulfills something that is exciting to me to allow all these influences to exist on equal footing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I let something into a song that seems kind of anachronistic compared to what has been in the song prior to that point, it’s just me answering the question, “What does this need? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;How do I best serve this song?&lt;/span&gt;” And also, to not have it feel like a pastiche of all this music that I love. Hopefully, it all gets synthesized into something that is me. And the more albums I’ve done, the more I think what I am has kind of crystallized, so then the challenge is to not be so influenced by myself because I get really restless when I think I’m repeating myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s the additional challenge. Every time I am trying to write something or record something, I think, “Does this sound too much like something I’ve done before?” And if it does, then I kind of lose interest and I’ll either abandon it or I’ll try to find ways to subvert it and turn it into something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Does the computer play into how you compose or are you primarily on the instrument when you’re composing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: The computer really is a huge part of it–increasingly. As least it has been, which is in the sense that I’m obviously playing an instrument and just about everything on my records is played in real time, I’m not doing very much–I’m doing very little in the way of sequencing and there’ll be some drum programs, maybe some manipulated drum patterns, but then I’ll edit the heck out of them and turn them into something else than what they were when they went down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s no doubt that it’s increased the flexibility factor so immensely that it’s affected the songwriting process hugely because now arranging and composition and mixing are all sort of taking place at the same time. You’re not just writing a song, you’re crafting a final product and that can take a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The album that I’m just about to have mastered by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goldenmastering.com&quot;&gt;John Golden &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt;, has been in the works forever. Some of the songs that are on it–the earliest music was recorded in 1999. A lot of it was recorded while I was working on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/scambot1/&quot;&gt;Scambot 1 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; starting in 2005. And then a big chunk of it was created just over the last couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That process of putting all the elements in the right proportions–from the standpoint of someone who’s really interested in sound and really interested in arrangements and layers, you can go way way down a rabbit hole with that, which is part of the reason why I’ve been working on this album for such a long time. But, I’ve been working on other albums at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; was in the background while I was doing &lt;em&gt;You Must Be This Tall&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/wing-beat-fantastic-songs-written-by-mike-keneally-andy-partridge/&quot;&gt;Wing Beat Fantastic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Scambot 1&lt;/em&gt;, obviously, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/bakin-the-potato/&quot;&gt;Bakin’ @ the Potato &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and the thing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Minnemann&quot;&gt;Marco Minnemann &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/evidence-of-humanity/&quot;&gt;Evidence of Humanity &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and all this stuff. Those were foregrounded projects, but &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; was happening in the background and I was nudging it forward the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These things take a while and then finally you reach a point where you realize that what a song needs to feel complete is to turn the bass up .1db, then I say, “I think I’m done.” And I’m interested, actually, in taking a step back from that approach because I’ve really mined it so thoroughly over the past few years–this computer-based approach to composition and arrangement–that I feel like it’s time for some kind of a paradigm shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Plus, we’ve made this big stack of albums over the last couple of decades. It’s a lot of work and I’m so happy with &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt;. I’m really delighted with it. I’m hopeful that people enjoy it and once that’s released I’m pretty excited at the idea of letting it be for a little while. I’m not saying that I’m stopping writing and actually I’m more excited at the idea of just sitting in a room with one instrument and turning the clock back to when you hashed out a song structure from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s true that because you can get results so quickly with the computer that much more frequently I compose in sections, get one section honed exactly how I want it and then move on to the next part of the song. That’s not the way they did it in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brill_Building&quot;&gt;Brill Building &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I realize that it has an impact on the final result. You get a different result when you discipline yourself and say, “Okay, I’m going to write an entire song structure from start to finish just sitting here with nothing but a guitar or nothing but a keyboard.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I find myself eager to get back to that approach, which is much more the way I did it back in the days of my first albums, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/hat/&quot;&gt;Hat. &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/boil-that-dust-speck/&quot;&gt;Boil That Dust Speck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/sluggo/&quot;&gt;Sluggo! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. All that stuff was recorded in recording studios with the clock running on tape, much less flexibility in terms of how you can manipulate the sound after the fact, and with all the musicians putting basic tracks down at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You get a completely different result than in this sort of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auteur_theory&quot;&gt;auteur theory &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where you find yourself doing a lot of the stuff yourself and then applying other musicians to what you’ve done as opposed to everybody tracking basic tracks at the same time with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudy_Van_Gelder&quot;&gt;Rudy Van Gelder &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; standing in the corner and everything going to tape. You’re asking one question and it’s leading me to tons of tangents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, this is what it’s all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: All right, that’s good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s no formality, so just go…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I’m finding myself excited when the time comes when it feels like, “Yeah, it’s time to make another album,” and I don’t know when that’s gonna be because right now, the thing that excites me more than anything is not having “I have to make an album” in the back of my head. I’m about to go on the road for a few months and the thought that I won’t be working on an album while I’m on the road fills me with relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you ever suffer from the creator’s curse where you’re working on it, it’s the greatest thing you’ve ever done, and then you finish it and you’re like, “Oh yeah!” And then a month later, you hate it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: No. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I go through all those phases during the making of the thing&lt;/span&gt; and I find that as time goes on that that happens more and more, which I think might be another indication that it’s time to step back and try some new methodology. It’s because I focus so hard on every little detail of this stuff, there have been times during the making of this record where I–I’ll be in the studio at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moosenet.com/scott1.html&quot;&gt;Scott Chatfield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s place, working on stuff all day and I’ll have rough mixes and I’ll listen in the car on the way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Some days I’ll listen to them and I’ll just be in heaven, it sounds so good. And then other days I’ll listen to the exact same thing and feel like, “Oh my God, what am I doing?” Once it’s all done, once I get everything to a point where I know that it feels done to me, then I can listen to it months later and, even though I may (by that point) be in a completely different place, I can understand where I was when I signed off on it and why it felt done to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, there are albums that I’ve completed and released–you know, obviously we look back on the discography and some rise in your estimation and some fall in your estimation–and sometimes it doesn’t have to do with the music itself, but it might be extra-musical components that color the experience. Sometimes it’s just the sound of a record that I might have been really happy with. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/dancing/&quot;&gt;Dancing &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is an album that is a lot of people’s favorite album of mine and I find it the hardest to listen to of all my work even though there’s a lot of really solid songwriting on there and great performances on there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s one where it was such an ambitious project. I had an 8-piece band, brought them into an analog recording studio, and captured most of the album live and then minimal overdubs and a very, very short time to mix it. I think that’s probably the thing that, if I’d had the luxury, which we didn’t because studio time is expensive, to do remixes of the songs that, for whatever reason, didn’t float my boat…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At the time, too, I was in a state of mind that I was really full of piss and vinegar and sure that I was practically doing God’s work. So, there are aspects of my mindset at the time that I look back on with almost disbelief now. I feel like I was self-deluded in some pretty significant ways. But, the result of it was an album that, for some people, might as well have been the only album I’ve ever made. At a certain point, you have to let go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You have to create work to the best of your ability at that moment.&lt;/span&gt; It’s the only thing you can do. You can’t suddenly become someone else. You are you at that moment for better or for worse. Of course, you go through life and there are changes and when you look back on the work, you realize you might do things very much differently now. But that’s, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right. But you wouldn’t know that now because you did it the way you did. I just tell myself now: Done is better than perfect. I know I can tweak all day long with the computer, but I’m doing that for me. I’m not doing that for the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: In my head, I honestly feel like I’m doing it for the music. All these little tweaks… Just because the songs have layers and they’re intricate and there’s a lot stuff to manage. When you’re in the studio working on one particular thing, maybe you’re focused on the drum sound one day, and you come back to the studio a week later you might find that the guitars are really suffering for what you did with the drums. Then you just have to take a step back for the wider cinemascope view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, time is the only answer to that, the only way you can hope to corral all these elements, at least for me because my ambitions are kind of big musically. The type of stuff that I’m trying to do. And just to balance all the stuff that I… What I’m trying to do is: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I want the material to pay off close attention.&lt;/span&gt; I want it to be dense. But I don’t want it to be so dense that it doesn’t make sense. I don’t want it to sound cluttered. I want it to have layers. I want it to be something that’s worth diving into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Overall I want the listening experience to be kind of smooth in a way. I think I’ve probably approached that ideal with the &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; mixes more than I did on &lt;em&gt;You Must Be This Tall&lt;/em&gt;, which is an extremely dense record and maybe ultimately does have some clutter-y stuff, maybe in the midrange there’s too much information and I could have carved some stuff away to allow the musical essential meat of the thing, the nutritional content, to speak more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that’s what I want to do. Ultimately, I want people to be able to play the record and have the stuff just kind of slide by in a way that sounds pleasant, not so that I want it to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elevator_music&quot;&gt;muzak &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I did this album called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/wooden-smoke/&quot;&gt;Wooden Smoke &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which may be my most pristine recording in terms of the sound of the thing. There’s wide spaces in the music and it’s mostly acoustic guitar, so the frequency conglomeration in that music was easier to achieve that kind of smooth listening experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, what I’m trying to do these days with &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; is to take sometimes very hectic musical information but ultimately boil it down so that it coheres in the same kind of way that &lt;em&gt;Wooden Smoke&lt;/em&gt; did. It might be a complete fool’s errand, but that’s the kind of conversations I’m having in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Obviously music is extremely personal to you. Just hearing the way you talk about your music and what it means to you… it’s near and dear to your heart, it’s your life’s work, it’s your passion… How did you go from listening to music and loving music and emulating–Usually the phases of creativity are enjoying and emulating and then you kind of find your own thing–Can you tell us a little about that? You said you started with music when you were 7…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, well, my parents sensed before I did that there was probably something worth pursuing in me musically. I was singing all the time when I was a kid and I was listening to music all the time when I was a kid. It was the 60s, and I had a teenage sister and she was listening to The Beatles all the time. Then I started listening to The Beatles all the time, especially at the point when they became too weird for her, when they start getting into &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revolver_(Beatles_album)&quot;&gt;Revolver &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sgt._Pepper%27s_Lonely_Hearts_Club_Band&quot;&gt;Sgt. Pepper &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and all that stuff fired my imagination so heavily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was really involved with listening to that music and it kind of ruled my life. I didn’t think of myself as a musician or a potential musician at all, but on my 7th birthday, there’s an organ. My parents got me this organ and I didn’t question it or even… Instantly, I realized, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Oh, that’s correct. This is exactly what’s supposed to happen right now.”&lt;/span&gt; And I walked up to it and started playing &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paint_It_Black&quot;&gt;Paint It Black &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; [by The Rolling Stones].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Just by ear?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, because it’s a keyboard. I looked at the keyboard and it was so–there’s the music. That was a really perceptive thing on my folks’ part that if they hadn’t just sensed that that was something that should have happened, it might not have ever happened. Four years later, I got a guitar because I was very enamored of mostly guitar-oriented music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At the time that I got the keyboard, I was super-excited about it, but I was still really in love with The Beatles and all these guys who were playing guitars. Then, when I was about 9 years old, I started hearing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emerson,_Lake_%26_Palmer&quot;&gt;Emerson, Lake, &amp;amp; Palmer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith_Emerson&quot;&gt;Keith Emerson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was maybe my first musical hero from a strictly sort of instrumental standpoint because I’d already been playing organ for a couple years at that point and I didn’t necessarily think of organ as a delivery system for particularly modern music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My teacher was teaching me standards from the 30s and 40s. I thought that the organ… You were just supposed to play &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Begin_the_Beguine&quot;&gt;Begin the Beguine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; with it. There were these standards that were really useful for me harmonically because they’re really actually dense harmonically. A lot of altered chords, a lot of strange information in the backing of those old tunes. Plus, it got me on this path early on with this idea of doing multiple things at once because the organ, you’re providing melody with your right hand and you’re providing harmonic content backing with your left hand, a bass line with your foot, and if you’ve got a drum machine in the thing, you’re basically a one-man band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That kind of got me excited about the layered aspects of music. The fact that it’s not just a two-dimensional thing and you can go real deep with building a piece of music and trying to do as much of it as you can on your own in real time. That, as I started playing guitar, it was sort of another arrow in the quiver in terms of how many textures you can apply in music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then my brother and I got reel to reel tape recorders. I had a brother, and still have a brother, who’s 3 1/2 years older than I am. We’d get together and learn all these songs that we just loved off of records and try to record our own versions of them together on reel to reel. So then we were learning about overdubbing and figuring out how to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: 1/4” 4-track?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Mm-hmm. And then a two-track machine for mix-down. So that was what I was doing during the time period where all my friends had social lives and were going out and meeting girls and stuff. I was just fascinated by music. That was the most fulfilling, life-enriching thing and way for me to spend my time. It was just listening to music, recording music, and then gradually from the experience of trying to record our own versions of these other things, then I started to gain more interest in composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then initially you just write things that sound exactly like songs that you love. Then it’s just a process of refining, refining, refining and gradually finding something that sounds like you. Your own voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And as you were finding that voice, were you finding that there were things you were hanging on to that prevented you from really getting there? Old habits, parts of songs you just loved and kept reusing, things you had to say no to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I guess the toughest one was this endless fascination with Frank [Zappa]’s music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;No other composer had that degree of impact on me.&lt;/span&gt; Things that sound like Zappa sound so obviously like Zappa that once they start to get into your own music, there’s no way around it. Obviously, when I started making my own records, anybody who knew who I was came at me from the Zappa angle initially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s an additional sort of motivator in both directions. If I put out this music, with these kind of obvious Zappa signifiers in it, that will be appealing to the audience that came to me from Zappa and maybe they will their friend, “Oh, if you like Zappa, then you’re gonna dig this.” But then, you’re trying to create something that has some kind of a fingerprint on it that is you and not too heavily reliant on one’s influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Especially in my case, Zappa was just so huge in my life. From the time that I discovered him, he was introduced to me when I was 9, I couldn’t believe that he exited. It was like a dream come true when I first heard his music and I was obsessed with him growing up. Then I got in the band and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;he placed this big, big imprint on my whole existence.&lt;/span&gt; It was kind of inevitable that it’s going to leak into my music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are still times when I’m trying to create something and I just keep asking myself the same question over and over again, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“What does this moment require to reach fruition?”&lt;/span&gt; And there are times where it seems like the only answer is something that sounds very much like something Frank would have done. So then it’s a question of: Do I stick a marimba sound on here or not? It’s the perfect timbre, it’s the perfect attitude for some melodies. In some ways, it’s like, “Dammit, why can’t I use a marimba?” The moment I do…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s Zappa!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: So, it’s just this dance that’s ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Over the years, do you feel that your music represented a point in time or do you look at your catalog and say you’ve been navigating and finding yourself? And the followup question is, when you hear what you’re doing now, do you think “This is more me than ever?” or do you think, “This is me now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I think the latter. I believe that at every point alone the line, I was attempting to be as much me as I could possibly be. There are times where allowing these other influences to filter in was entirely conscious and a knowing sort of homage to music that I love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s sort of a sharing thing sometimes because if other people listen to the record and they recognize, “Oh, that sounds like They Might Be Giants right there,” there’s that little shared moment, “Oh wow, he loves them too!” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt; was a huge, huge thing for me&lt;/span&gt; and there are still times where that kind of architecture seems to be the best kind of way to approach an arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These interlocking moments where a guitar does something and it’s answered by a keyboard, which is then answered by a bass and it becomes this construction. That stuff is exciting and just because somebody else discovered it first–and hell, Gentle Giant’s not making music anymore, so as long as it doesn’t become an end in itself and the only thing that the music appears to be offering is a carbon copy of something that was done better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you are allowing in kind of a loving way, or at least that’s what I tell myself about these influences, to come in and partly because it’s what the song requires at that moment and also partly as a conscious acknowledgment and tribute of beautiful things that have happened in the past and hopefully still adds up to something new in the present. I don’t think about this stuff too deeply in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;A lot of it is just trying to have a good time.&lt;/span&gt; You’re just trying to enjoy yourself and music is fun and when you are dealing with a tricky passage and all the myriad choices, how to maximize the potential of this passage, and you arrive at the solution that maybe sounds like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crosby,_Stills,_Nash_%26_Young&quot;&gt;Crosby, Stills, &amp;amp; Nash &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or maybe sounds like &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;, or maybe sounds like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grateful_Dead&quot;&gt;The Grateful Dead &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;To me, that’s just a way of saying, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“These are legends and adventurers that went before us and found answers to certain musical questions that were correct and these answers will always be correct and they will always be available to all of us who do music.”&lt;/span&gt; It’s just about how artful you are in deploying them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Obviously, the name of this website is Make Weird Music. “Weird” can mean many things. Sometimes it involves sacrifice in the sense of “I could be making music that doesn’t have anything ‘weird’ about it,” sometimes it can mean, “I’ll throw things in that maybe only music fans will notice,” and sometimes it means, “I’m not going to touch anything that sounds commercial.” There’s a whole bunch of definitions of “weird,” and every musician has their own brand of that. How do you see your music and explain it? Do you feel like you are a “weird” musician in any sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I do. I think that’s been shown to me by the response to it that even when I think I’m doing something that’s quite commercial–this is something that comes with time and with age and perspective. I look back at songs I may have done 10 or 15 years ago and thought, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Why isn’t this a massive success? Why would this not be on the radio?”&lt;/span&gt; And then, now I listen back and compare to anything else that was on the radio and I think, “Well, it’s because you didn’t do this, this, and this and because you did do this, this, and this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s funny because you can get away with a lot of weird stuff and still be commercially successful, but there is still this sort of base requirement to get away with it. Sonically, people will handle a lot of strange noise these days that would have been very off-putting in the past. That’s a function of the craziness of life nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Everything is weirder than it used to be.&lt;/span&gt; I think as long as you’ve got a certain kind of production and a certain kind of rhythm and a certain tempo happening and a few sonic signifiers that are familiar to people, then you can load on a lot of really strange information and people will accept it. In my case, I’ve never, even though at times I’ve thought, “This is like a pop song, people will totally dig this,” but I’m dealing with signifiers that combined to build me 40 years ago. So, to me, when I think “pop song,” yeah that might have got on the radio in 1974.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m not going out of my way to familiarize myself with modern studio techniques&lt;/span&gt; and programming and the same sound libraries that a lot of people are using and this specific type of over compression that makes some people feel comfy and the exact guitar plugins that produced the exact guitar sound that makes you allowed to play a guitar nowadays during a time where I think people are a little more accepting of guitar, but there was certainly a time where the mere idea of a guitar in your song was seen as terribly anachronistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I keep returning to the idea that if there’s anyone I’m going to look at as a hero musically, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s going to be somebody like John Coltrane who was entirely uncompromising&lt;/span&gt; serving nothing but what he felt the music required and also working through any number of musical questions that he had and tried to answer them for himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think that the sum total of the music that I love and try to create, there’s no avoiding that there are times that these strange specters raise their heads. Even the most mainstream prog rock that was selling hundreds and hundreds of thousands of copies in the 70s that I bought all of–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yes_(band)&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Emerson, Lake, &amp;amp; Palmer and stuff–it’s fuckin’ weird! It’s weird music! There’s no way you’d get that stuff on the radio these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The first time I heard &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarkus&quot;&gt;Tarkus &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; on the radio, a guy said, “Hey, we just got this new Emerson, Lake, &amp;amp; Palmer album, let’s play it!” And he played all of side 1 of &lt;em&gt;Tarkus&lt;/em&gt;. Then there’s me as a 9-year-old organ player getting my head blown off. Then it got into Zappa and that opened up huge new avenues of weird. And you can think, “Well, that’s gotta be the limit, right? That’s about as weird as you can get.” Then you learn about The Residents, then you learn about all this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock_in_Opposition&quot;&gt;Rock In Opposition &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff, then you realize, “Oh wait a second, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trout_Mask_Replica&quot;&gt;Trout Mask Replica &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; exists.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That stuff is just so exciting to me!&lt;/span&gt; It’s real evidence of how cool life can get. It’s absolutely exhilarating. Then you listen to it on a record and that’s one type of exhilaration. And if you’re lucky enough to see any of that kind of stuff live and you see a group of musicians that have worked together to execute this music–it’s not an accident that they were called Captain Beefheart and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain_Beefheart#The_Magic_Band&quot;&gt;His Magic Band &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because that stuff does sound like, “How could you possibly do it?” Well, you learn, you do it by abusing a group of musicians in a house for months and months and months, so that’s unfortunate that there was psychological warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sometimes that’s what it takes, man!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I guess! I’ve tried to do things a little more kind-fashioned. Having said that, I have to express my extraordinary gratitude towards everybody who’s played my music for not a tremendous amount of financial reward, ever. And to &lt;a href=&quot;http://harrisrecording.com&quot;&gt;Mike Harris &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who has engineered and been there in the studio with me every moment of all this insane detail work on my records for the last many years. And to Scott Chatfield, especially, who has given his home and his time and his money and his heart to so many of these projects that I’ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I could just be sitting here with the laptop making all kinds of weird shit, but it wouldn’t have the same quality of sound and I don’t think it would have reached people in nearly the same kind of way. At all times, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m dependent upon other people being willing to help me make this stuff come to pass.&lt;/span&gt; So grateful for that, especially given how weird this stuff can be. They’ve been helping me take these strange little impulses and really arcane super-super-idiosyncratic personal things and I think, “Why am I trying to accomplish this stuff? What is the feeling that I’m trying to convey?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It just goes back to things that I saw and experienced, probably a lot that has to do with television. When you’re a kid… I watched a lot of TV when I was a kid and then you would experience these little things, sometimes they’d be in a cartoon like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beany_and_Cecil&quot;&gt;Beany and Cecil &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something. It’s just fuckin’ weird! Or even a Bugs Bunny cartoon. You dig deep into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Stalling&quot;&gt;Carl Stalling &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raymond_Scott&quot;&gt;Raymond Scott &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and what it took musically to make those &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Looney_Tunes&quot;&gt;Warner Bros. cartoons &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; happen. And these moments you can’t explain by they strike deep in your soul and they turn into a memory that, years later, it’s almost like scary in a way. These little dark, strange unexplainable things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think back to… very rarely anymore are there closing credits because the moment the show’s over, they slam to a promo for the next thing and the credits are going a million miles an hour and the bottom of the screen, you can’t even read a fucking thing. Back in the day, shows were allowed to end. There would be a closing theme and the credits would roll and then there would be a logo. 9 times out of 10, that logo was fucking terrifying. It would be some kind of loud music that would slam into your ears and some visual that was rushing into the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Here you are as a four year old and you’re being traumatized and that stuff has an impact. To this day, I can still feel and I get chills when I think about that shit. I think some of what I’ve been doing with the weirdness of some of my music, and maybe it’s not kind or fair, is to try and share some of that feeling. “Do you guys feel this too? Can I share this with you?” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s like a way of not being so alone in that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I almost feel like those production houses were intentionally trying to hurt me in some way. I look back on it, in the same way I can wake up from a bad dream and think, “Yeah, that was great, that was exciting,” I look back on that with this kind of perverse mix of fear and delight and gratitude that I have such strong memories that are just the building blocks of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It can be thrilling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, it’s like a thrill ride. All enclosed in one terrifying little screen gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK to Carl: You know what I’m talking about with that stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Carl: Oh yeah, I just discovered some old TV themes like Buck Rogers and the 25th century or something. The theme for that suddenly brought back all this, “Yes! That’s what I’ve been trying to do all this time!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s weird how television is thought of as sort of low art, although that’s certainly not the case anymore. People are recognizing that a lot of the work being done for TV goes deeper because it’s a long-form thing. Obviously &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breaking_Bad&quot;&gt;Breaking Bad &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; can accomplish more in 5 seasons of insanity than any 2-hour movie can hope to. I don’t think necessarily this reflects a bias against television.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think a lot of my aesthetic was formed by mainstream entertainment in the 60s and 70s. But at the same time, as I expanded my horizons and the stuff I was listening to, it just became this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bouillabaisse&quot;&gt;bouillabaisse &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the most obvious mainstream TV stuff as much of the weird peculiar underground stuff you could find on records. And alternative forms of comedy is a huge thing for me, too. I was so intensely involved with trying to understand every bit of what the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Firesign_Theatre&quot;&gt;Firesign Theatre &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were doing and what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Python&quot;&gt;Monty Python &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was doing and what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Lampoon_(magazine)&quot;&gt;National Lampoon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and later on, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr._Show_with_Bob_and_David&quot;&gt;Mr. Show &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I’m sure we ended up hanging out and watching a lot of that. That stuff is as rich to me and layered and exciting as any number of really intricate musical experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;CK: Talk about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Negativland&quot;&gt;Negativland &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And Negativland, which absolutely combines all of it. When &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_Joyce_(musician)&quot;&gt;Don Joyce &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; passed away a short time ago and I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Hosler&quot;&gt;Mark Hosler &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had posted how much he was inspired by the Firesign Theatre. The Firesign Theatre were a rock band even though they didn’t play instruments. So, Negativland took all these impulses from comedy and from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musique_concrète&quot;&gt;musique concréte &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, pop music, and social commentary, and complete mistrust for everything that is sacred and true and combined it all into this powerful, powerful statement, which is still ongoing. That’s an incredibly worthwhile decades-long art statement that those guys have made. Very inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, you’ve talked a lot about things from the 60s and the 70s, and you’ve talked about some evolution of going from analog to digital, and growing older and wiser and all these things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I laugh at the “wiser.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The lay of the musical land today is very different than it was 10 years ago, which is very different than it was when you started. Do you look at today’s landscape and see more opportunity? Do you see things have changed in a way where you’ve established a base and if you started again today, it’d be much more difficult?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I don’t know. It’s really hard to say. I’m sure that if I were just coming out of nowhere now, maybe I’d be able to make something happen. It’s really tough to say because there’s so many circumstances that have combined to make now what it is for me. Plus, I’m really fortunate in that I’ve managed, for the majority of my career, to land these mainstream gigs that subsidize me and allow me the luxury and time when I’m not on the road with Satriani, to work away at my peculiar personal obsessions musically. And when possible, to get out on stage with these brilliantly talented musicians who are there doing it only because they think that it’s worth their time musically and not because of any perceived career benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now is an interesting time and I think that I could, arguably should, be more savvy about the way I could be utilizing the sort of modern landscape of promotion online. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I find that every time I take a step in that direction, it starts to feel untrue&lt;/span&gt;. Although I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MikeKeneally&quot;&gt;Twitter &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/mike.keneally&quot;&gt;Facebook &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to promote my stuff, I don’t want to do it in a way that is crass. I’m still trying to look at everything I do as–again this is such a thing that was influenced by Frank, realizing starting after I’d been obsessed with Frank for a couple of years and reading interviews and really understanding his concept of &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.killuglyradio.com/wiki/Project/Object_concept&quot;&gt;project/object &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and what that means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In his instance, he defined the project/object as, basically, everything he did! It’s not just the albums, and the themes that were repeated from album to album where you could trace the conceptual continuity of different motifs over a series of records, but also the ways those pieces were conveyed live on stage and things that he said in interviews and things that he did in film and in video…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And owning the rights to his music, the totality of his business plan…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That, but even apart from that, looking at if from a strictly art installation angle, he just said, all of these things are part of his life’s work and they all combine to create his total art statement. He said even the secret raising of an eyebrow in a recording studio where nobody else could see it. I remember the interview and the interviewer said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“But Frank, you’re the only one who’s been there when all these things happen, nobody else could possibly understand it,” and he said, “Riiiiight!”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, as far as he’s concerned, he was sort of creating for an audience of one in terms of who he felt could truly understand what he was trying to create. That was exciting to me and I have certainly been inspired by that and I, too, want to believe that the totality of my work adds up to a larger statement when it’s combined. That includes whatever stupid thing I might send out in a tweet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m a little maybe overprotective and maybe a little secretive is the way it might come off. I don’t have as large a presence online as a lot of my friends do who are constantly posting things and stoking the fire and keeping the message moving forward. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not in my nature to do.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One thing I’ve always appreciated about your method of communication is: I’ve been reading the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/fans/keneallist/&quot;&gt;Keneallist &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for, easily, 10 years. It’s such a personal way. You reach out, it’s like you’re writing a letter to me! And I’ve always appreciated your approach, a very personal approach to your fan base. Did that arise from a local fan base and people started going online? Or is it just who you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I think it was always my inclination from even when I was doing the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/the-tar-tapes-vol-1/&quot;&gt;Tar Tapes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which were these mail-order cassettes that my brother and I started putting together first in the early 80s. Being personal about it, trying to make that connection beyond just the sound. Some of that was born out of a longing that I always had when I was growing up and listening to these records and they meant so much to me, so the people that were making these records meant so much to me and I wanted to feel like I knew something about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, whenever there was something in the liner notes that sounded like they were just speaking, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd_Rundgren&quot;&gt;Todd Rundgren &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was somebody that did that a lot. I remember when I got &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something/Anything%3F&quot;&gt;Something/Anything? &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and there were the liner notes inside &lt;em&gt;Something/Anything?&lt;/em&gt; and he says a little something about each song. He does this fake rock opera in there, and it’s funny and it’s personal and you learn something about the person. It’s just like a peek behind the curtain in a way. That was really important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Nowadays, that currency is almost worthless. Everybody is putting everything out there, so it feels like it’s more valuable to withhold a little bit. My inclination over the past few years as the tools have been made available to reveal all has been to reveal less and less and try to let the music do more of the talking for me. But, the Keneallist is an example of one platform, one location, and it’s obviously preaching to the choir because we’re only talking about those however-many-thousands of people who have subscribed to the mailing list. It’s not necessarily an outreach project, it’s more just staying connected to the people that we’re just so grateful to continue to pay attention after all this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s now 23 years since my first album came out. It’s a lengthy career. One good thing about doing this kind of music is, I think, when you do weirder music (as you call it), you’re going to reach not as many people, but I think that the people you do reach, it connects with them so heavily that they stay with you longer. It’s not an ephemeral following, it’s not a fashion-based thing that’s going to go away any time soon unless you start putting out albums that really suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s the other part of it, I really don’t want to be an artist (and there are so many) where you look at their newer work and say, “That is absolutely and empirically inferior to stuff that they did 20 years ago.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I try to keep my standards really, really high&lt;/span&gt; and that’s why the more albums you make, the harder it gets, in a way. If you’re dead set on not repeating yourself, and on keeping the quality at a certain level… &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not about topping what I’ve done before.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve never put out an album and said, “Yeah, this is better than anything I did before.” I look back on so many albums. I look back on &lt;em&gt;Sluggo!&lt;/em&gt; and I just think, “Man, everything just kinda fell into place right there.” I was at a place writing-wise that I don’t know if it can ever be replicated. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;All you can do is try to write the best stuff you can and try to play it the best that you can and try to record it as well as you can and then mix it as well as you can and then end up with a project and a statement that is gonna reach people and touch people somehow.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I keep doing that and doing that and doing that. And that’s why I feel like I need to take a breath because there’s this huge stack of albums that I’ve made over the last couple of decades. In some ways, it kinda reminds me of when Frank broke up &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mothers_of_Invention&quot;&gt;The Mothers of Invention &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the late 60s, and he did it in a kind of bitter way, and he said, “My audience wouldn’t know good music if it bit them on the ass and I’m not going to do any more work until the audience has assimilated what I have done to this point.” And then I think it was probably a week later when he was making another record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I definitely reserve the right to suddenly feel like, “Oh, I gotta make another record.” But I just want to take that moment, that breath, where I don’t have the word “album” in big neon lights in the back of my head for a little while. I suspect I’ll be writing songs and stuff–I know I will–when the muse hits. I want it to be more like a caveman approach where it just happens. Just sitting around the campfire and this music comes out because it absolutely has to, not necessarily where you’re working to fill in the blanks of this album-length statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And it’s true that I’ve done a whole lot of albums that a whole lot of people haven’t heard. I would be happy if there was a way to take a break from constantly creating new stuff and find a way to maximize the visibility, or at least increase the visibility, of the existing body of work because there’s so much of it. I do think there’s stuff in there that a lot of people would like if they get a chance to hear it. So, once &lt;em&gt;Scambot&lt;/em&gt; is truly done, then maybe we’ll take a look at ways of dealing with the catalog in such a way that maybe we increase its profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Ultimately, I’m really looking forward to, because I’ll be on the road for a majority of the next year with Satriani, and I feel like it’s time for a little breather where I can just be a guy in Joe’s band. I’ll have a new album to promote because &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; will be there and I’ll be doing interviews for it and trying to get people to listen to it. It’s not like I’m going to be making believe like I don’t have a solo career. In every case when I’ve finished an album over the last couple of decades, I start thinking about the next one. Or, it’s already been in the works. Ever since 2008, I guess, every time I finish an album, I’m already part of the way towards recording the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, with &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt;, I’m essentially clearing the decks. We’ve created two albums of music: there’s &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; and there’s additional music recorded at the same time, all of which was at one time or another considered for inclusion on &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt;. But, &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; crystalized into the thing that it is and I ended up with this big bunch of music that forms a perfectly acceptable album in its own right, which is actually what &lt;em&gt;You Must Be This Tall&lt;/em&gt; was. It was all a bunch of music that was created at the same time as &lt;em&gt;Wing Beat Fantastic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Most of the songs in that album were, at one time or another, I was trying to slot them into &lt;em&gt;Wing Beat Fantastic&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Wing Beat Fantastic&lt;/em&gt; wanted to be this really sleek, 40-minute (for me) pop album and then all the twisted stuff landed on this other album where, to me, it all feels like a piece and it all belongs together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, I have to say I completely… One thing I really love about you and your music is just that you have that standard and so many times I listen to “the next album” and I just think, “How does he do it?” It’s almost like a mystery. It’s wonderful in the sense that it’s full of wonder and it’s also really great. I just think it’s so incredible how you continue to find these new things. For me, as a musician, it’s almost like a little overwhelming, like “How does anyone stay that creative? How do you keep the juices flowing?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I just love music so much and I know that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I feel like I’m just scratching the surface.&lt;/span&gt; I know that, even though I’ve done a bunch of albums and written a lot of songs, I feel like I’m just that far along in terms of what can be accomplished and what I would like to accomplish musically. I really appreciate you saying that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;On this new record, the &lt;em&gt;Scambot&lt;/em&gt; concept is this overarching concept that is intended to be three installments. The first album, &lt;em&gt;Scambot 1&lt;/em&gt;, is extremely dense. It’s kind of overwhelming in the amount of information that it puts across. This album, I wanted it to be this measurable clearing away of this certain amount of audio clutter so that over the course of listening to &lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt;, you feel things being lifted away and, hopefully, it’s arriving at something that feels like some kind of an elemental truth, which gets dangerously close to the stuff that we were talking about without being messianic about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I no longer harbor any delusions that the stuff that I’m doing is significant&lt;/span&gt; and like the cosmic sense other than that music in and of itself is a beautiful thing that can help people achieve personal insights in that they can feel like they have cosmic significance, but I don’t think that that’s a function of anything special in me. It’s just that I’m trying to be a worthwhile participant in the ongoing project that is “music” as a whole. I’m trying to remain aware that music can have a higher purpose in terms of what it does inside people’s heads and hearts without being super-fuckin’-precious about it and without feeling as though that means that God has pointed at you. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Although, maybe God has pointed at all musicians.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s the other important thing is that we don’t fucking know what’s going on. We are just this very small percentage of what’s happening in one of many universes. There’s no way any of us on this plane at this phase of existence can have answers to anything. People who think they know what’s going on in the grand cosmic sense are a joke. Apologies to anyone who might be offended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, we’re here to present you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I do know that, because it’s happened to me, you can achieve real transcendence through the listening of music, the experience of music. That’s how I know a song is done. That’s what I’m reaching for every time I’m making a record. If I feel as though I’ve somehow gotten all these elements lined up that it feels like it’s resonating with some essential truth about something, even though I don’t know what it is, but it feels like it’s aligned with the natural hum of the universe in some way. It’s like when you’re tuning a guitar and you finally don’t hear that beating anymore. You try to get everything to smooth the fuck out. So, that’s when I say, “Yeah, the song is done.” That album is done when I can listen to it from start to finish and it all feels like it’s vibrating that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: That’s cool. How are we doing, Carl?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Carl: Terrible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Everything’s out of capacity and we’re recording on paper now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, that’s a lot of heady stuff. I love it. I feel like that’s the meat of what I want to get at with this website. But, Carl has some stupid trivial questions to ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s a terrible thing to say. That’s truly terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AG: I’m just kidding, we were discussing on the way over here things to ask you about specifically and I know Carl has some specific questions about the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/vai-piano-reductions-vol-1/&quot;&gt;Vai Piano Reductions &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;CK: Yeah, I do. I’m really curious to understand that process, if you could go through the steps of how that actually happened. You guys went into a room? Or, how did what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, literally from point A, it was him just sending me a list of songs he wanted me to reconfigure for solo piano. All the songs were Steve’s choices. He wasn’t in the studio. I spent ages and ages doing the arrangements at home and at that point, dealing with each arrangement of each of those 11 songs independently. I would listen to a song and I would say, “Okay, is this a song where I’m going to do a radical reharmonization? Or is this a song where I’m going to let the song really speak for itself and just stay really close to the meat of what he composed there?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So a song like &lt;em&gt;Sisters&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Touching Tongues&lt;/em&gt; is done with very little elaboration. I just wanted to present a real, basic and simple display case for the beauty and simplicity of what he did there. And then there were other things, like &lt;em&gt;Salamanders in the Sun&lt;/em&gt;, where I just found there was so much potential for a lot of harmonic playing around, so I radically rearranged that song and came up with a lot of different ways of setting that melody so that a lot of times when that melody is coming around, it’s being supported in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it is the hardest album I ever made&lt;/span&gt;. Absolute pain because of the nature of solo piano. It’s so naked and completely unadorned. You’re just out there with all the bright lights on you musically and there’s nowhere to hide. You don’t have an amazing virtuosic drummer bashing away. You don’t have a bunch of super saturated gain on your guitar so you can hold a note forever. It’s all right there and there’s nowhere to turn and you better be on your game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I would go into the studio with Mike Harris, this was all recorded on tape at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signature_Sound&quot;&gt;Signature Sound in San Diego &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and I recorded multiple takes of each song so that Steve would be able to have a bunch of different renditions to choose from. He ended up doing editing on this stuff for… I think I recorded in ’98 or ’99 and he didn’t release it until 2004. He spent that whole time editing those takes together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, when I look into that, it’s like I wasn’t able to nail a take from start to finish that made him happy, but the other way is that he’s like I am. He’s always searching for the magic key to some ultimate rendition of a song that is going to answer every question that he has musically and fulfill every goal that he has for that piece and end up with something that feels elementally true in some way. So, he spent a lot of time with the different takes and that was a time in my life, late ‘90s, where I was not as settled a person, or centered a person, as I strive to be now. I would get really ferociously angry if I fucked up in the studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And it’s exacerbated by the fact that it’s just such a naked format–solo piano–and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m trying to please myself, I’m trying to please Steve, I’m trying to do something that justifies this concept that he’s come up with: solo piano versions of Steve Vai songs.&lt;/span&gt; Does that mean that all Steve Vai fans are going to buy this and say, “What is the point of this? I don’t want to listen to Steve Vai on the piano.” So, it’s already potentially a hard sell, so you’d better do something worthwhile while you’re messing with this concept. All this is playing in my mind and I’m trying to execute these insane manipulations and combinations of movements that I’ve come up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My training is as an organist, keyboard-wise. I’m used to the luxury of: you put your hand down and that chord will hold for 9 1/2 hours if you want it to. The piano, action is required and I’m not &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Art_Tatum&quot;&gt;Art Tatum &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with the most insane left hand. I’m not endlessly gifted in that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This stuff is hard. I would fuck something up and I would just recriminate self loathing verbally. And all that stuff was on the tapes. So as Steve was doing these edits on these takes, every time he would come up to a part with these sections where I’d say, “Mother fuck… fucking… Oh God… How could you be so…” just hating myself, he would snip it out and put it in a special file. Eventually he did a construction of all of these moments put together, which he still has not played for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;CK: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=seCkv_aqSF8&quot;&gt;The Casey Kasem edit &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah! Exactly! It’s just the collection of every juicy bit of self-hatred and invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Saving it for a special occasion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah! I’m terrified to hear it, but I know it’s gotta be an entertaining listen. But, ultimately ended up with an album that both of us were really, really pleased with. I gave him the recordings and I didn’t hear them for five years until the album came out. So, all the time I’m thinking, “Is it any good?” And it came back with all the edits and constructions that he put together and I was so glad to find out: Yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There is great value in this thing. It’s not an embarrassment.&lt;/span&gt; And he was just incredibly generous with the things that he said about the record. He indicated at one point that that’s the record he reaches for when he wants to listen to Steve Vai music. That’s all I can hope for. So then he wanted to do a second album and he sent me another list of songs. I did arrangements for the first two pieces, one of which is &lt;em&gt;Under It All&lt;/em&gt; and the other is &lt;em&gt;Ooo&lt;/em&gt;. Both of these are incredibly lengthy, intricate, multi-leveled, multi-episodic creations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;CK: It’s a long solo in Ooo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, which I learned every note on the piano and re-harm’d and did all this crazy stuff. You can see them on YouTube because in 2010 there was a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vai.com/steve-vai-festival-3/&quot;&gt;Vai festival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Groningen, Holland. He premiered some orchestral stuff and there were other artists doing stuff and I came on and did some of the arrangements from the first album and did a premiere of some stuff from the second album-to-be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Actually, I had to leave a Satriani tour to go perform on this festival because I signed up to do the festival and then I joined Joe’s band and it just so happened that they conflicted, so I had to arrange for a sub for the two or three Satriani gigs that I had to miss out on in order to do this festival, which I really wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I did the live premieres of three new Vai arrangements, which were &lt;em&gt;Under it All&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ooo&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;San Sebastian&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;San Sebastian&lt;/em&gt; I never really finished to my satisfaction. And then I went back to the tour with Vai and then more touring with Vai and then I went on the road with Dethklok and then I’ve got albums to make, so I’m making those albums, and the &lt;em&gt;Piano Reductions, Vol. 2&lt;/em&gt; just kept getting pushed back, pushed back and it’s not because I didn’t want to do it, although it is a very painful thing to do. And the end I think justifies the means, at least in the case of the first album, I was very happy with the way it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But I found with the second album, I was torturing myself to do these arrangements and I still wasn’t finding myself with enough time to do them properly because it takes dedication and weeks and weeks and weeks, really, thinking about nothing but that. And financially, it makes no sense for Steve to pay me what it really would require for me to not do anything else and devote my time to that. So, I regrettably said to Steve, “You know, I don’t think I can do the second volume,” and he, bless him, totally understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Since then, I saw online this Japanese woman who does amazing solo piano versions of Steve Vai music. She actually contacted me on Facebook and it was right around the time when I was feeling that I didn’t have the time to do the second record. So, I said, “Hey Steve, do you know about this girl?” and he goes, “You know what? Actually, I do.” And so he’s been working with her now. I think that if there is a Piano Reductions, Vol. 2, it’ll be her doing it, which I think is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I like the idea that the concept can continue to exist even when I’m not there. And I also am extremely relieved. I can’t tell you what it took out of me to do that first record. It was absolutely the hardest thing musically that I ever tried to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think that it paid off. I was listening to it two nights ago and I played my wife &lt;em&gt;Ballerina 12/24&lt;/em&gt;, Steve’s version and then your version, and I said, “This is why Mike Keneally is a genius.” And she said, “That’s incredible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, it’s note for note, even though a lot of those notes are generated by an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eventide,_Inc&quot;&gt;Eventide &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing, it’s note for note with what he did with the guitar. And that was done in a sense of, “All I need to do with the piano is exactly what was done on the original recording and the magic will all be there.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It was insanity trying to learn that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I bet the Gentle Giant fugue stuff you probably learned over the years helped with that. I was listening to it going, “Okay, now that I’ve been trying to play &lt;em&gt;Experience&lt;/em&gt;, now I get how that piece can happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, that’s true! I never would have made that connection, but you’re right. I spent the summer of my 16th year doing nothing but listening to Gentle Giant learning every guitar part and figuring out how it fits into this lattice work. And that, I know, was something that laid a groundwork for all kinds of stuff that I’ve been able to do since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I am extremely grateful that I managed to keep it together long enough to get one album of stuff done. And I do regret that I haven’t recorded versions of the two arrangements that I did that I’m really happy with for the next record. But, they are on YouTube and people can check out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;CK: Two other little questions about that. Do you remember what kind of piano it was that you played on? How did that feel? You mentioned somewhere in an interview that you felt like you were hitting it too hard….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, that was in that sort of mid-90s, messianic period where I was just full of feeling like I was conveying the Truth of the universe through everything that I was doing. This is what I was referring to earlier when I was referring to self-delusion. So, I think that I got a little…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s real easy to get into a thing where you are self-aggrandizing and advertising for yourself as opposed to serving the notes at hand and performing as sensitively as you can.&lt;/span&gt; Especially in this particular situation where I’m dealing with another composer’s work. It’s not like I have distaste for what I did there, but I’ll say that when I heard that, I thought I could have been more sensitive in some of the choices that I made in terms of dynamics. It could also be that because that’s what Steve found to edit together to make the ideal versions that he could out of what he could, it may be that I just fucked up four takes and out of just sheer hatred of life at that moment, by the time I was finally able to execute it properly, it was this defiant, “Fuck you! I’m gonna play! Dammit!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;By the time I actually played it right, I was just beating the hell out of the keyboard from anger. So, that might be why in some instances that’s the way that record comes off to me because Steve collated where I finally arrived at being able to do the thing properly and I might have been just a little too much in my head and not… You know, when you feel like you’re doing God’s work and you’re doing it wrong, you can get really angry with yourself. It’s sort of all tied up in some of the weird things that were happening in my head at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;By the time I heard the finished album, I remember thinking, “I could have done some of that stuff with a little more gentle touch.” But the piano is the same one that I used on &lt;em&gt;Sluggo!&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Nonkertompf&lt;/em&gt; and other albums that I was recording around that era, which is the Yamaha grand piano. I’m not sure what the model number is, but it’s a big Yamaha grand at Signature Sound Studios in San Diego. It’s a beautiful instrument. I recorded a lot of stuff on that piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;CK: Is there a level of texture or harmony that you can use in these piano reductions that you can do with that type of music that you can’t do with a rock band? Because on Pig, it’s so dense and so many things are going on. Such ugly chords… Can you really do that with a guitar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You can, but it’s not going to read in the same way. And sometimes that’s what I have tried to do with a quartet or a quintet is use the available resources to try to construct stuff that is that dense, but it is hard to carry off with guitars compared to the piano because there’s so many other sonic anomalies that enter into the picture with amplifiers and pedals and strings and conglomerations of frequencies when you start adding guitars to guitars and stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s another Frank quote, “Timbre rules.” The same exact chord on the piano is going to have a different message than if it’s played on a fuzz-tone guitar and different than if it’s played by a bassoon ensemble. The delivery system has a lot to do with what the piece of music ends up meaning. It’s not just all about notes. It’s about so many other dynamic and timbral elements that all play into the final thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;CK: So is that something you get to exercise enough in your own music with a rock band? Or is there some part of, “Man, I wish I could do that more?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I think I’ve managed to get my rocks off to some degree on the stage. In the studio I can certainly make that stuff happen with overdubbing and different orchestration. The sky’s the limit in the studio. On stage with one of my bands, especially if it’s a trio, it’s not gonna be as dense as if you do “this” on a grand piano and hit every note and get some crazy cluster. Although I’ve got a keyboard there if I need to do that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s the other thing that I was talking about. Playing the organ as a kid and getting used to this certain idea of doing multiple things at once in some way, my modern extension of that is when I do stuff with the guitar and the keyboard simultaneously live, which I like to try to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Skip to 4:30 in the following video to see Mike shredding on both keyboard and guitar at the same time…]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/m3LrVvV03Jk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I haven’t really explored that–and maybe again that’s a discipline thing–I’ve only specifically composed a few things for guitar/keyboard simultaneous stuff. My delight and excitement is in the moment on stage during an improvised section to see what I can do, how far can I push this technique, what can I get away with? I do a certain amount of it with Satriani, but there’s a spanner in the works there, which is that we tune all the guitars down a half step, but I’m playing concert pitch on the keyboard. So there’s a number of songs where I hit a chord on the guitar and then follow up with a passage on the keyboard or conversely, I’ll sustain a chord on the keyboard with the pedal and play on the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, at that point, I can’t be thinking strictly harmonically because I’ll be playing in C# on the guitar, but it sounds as C natural on the keyboard, so at that point it’s just points in space. You have to just memorize, “this is what I do” followed by “this is what I do” and try to ignore the fact that “this is that” and that’s a completely different note, but they sound the same. At that point, the notion of the fretboard becomes a little more abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I can’t get too abstract with the keyboard because you’ll look at it as exactly what it is, but with the fretboard you can maybe convince yourself you’re playing an Ab, but you’re really playing an A. Nonetheless, we just rehearsed a whole bunch of new material that we’re about to premiere live and there’s still some times where I’m supposed to play something in C# on the keyboard and I’ll accidentally play it in D, which… whoops. I’m sure there’ll be some exciting avant garde moments early on in the tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool. Mike, I can’t tell you how much I value your time and how much I appreciate you doing this. It’s really special to me. Thank you so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You’re very welcome. This is entirely pleasurable, so thanks for coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you, I really appreciate it. And thanks for opening your home. It’s very nice of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You’re welcome. My pleasure. Make weird music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! Make weird music, or else!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discover Steve Vai</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks-to-our-sponsors&quot;&gt;Thanks To Our Sponsors!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://softwareplusplus.com&quot;&gt;Cory Berg at Software++&lt;/a&gt; and to &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlkingdom.com&quot;&gt;Carl King Creative&lt;/a&gt; for sponsoring this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cory is a software development and management expert who’s written a fantastic book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Software-Must-Have-Skills-Engineers-ebook/dp/B00U4ZRQC6&quot;&gt;Software++: Must-Have Skills for Engineers&lt;/a&gt;. There are a lot of software people I’ve met via Make Weird Music and Guitar Circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl is an expert filmmaker, author, and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/carl-king&quot;&gt;former musician&lt;/a&gt;. His book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Youre-Creative-Genius-Now-What/dp/1932907920&quot;&gt;So, You’re a Creative Genius… Now What?&lt;/a&gt;, has been a huge inspiration for me and many others. He filmed this interview and provided lots of great equipment and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-little-about-steve-vai&quot;&gt;A Little About Steve Vai&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Vai is a forward-thinking, virtuosic guitarist based in Los Angeles. He started his career in music with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt; in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-so-weird&quot;&gt;What’s So Weird?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of Steve’s work makes use of the following weird music techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time Signatures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Composition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virtuosity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-care&quot;&gt;Why I Care&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1996, I heard an instrumental guitar song on the radio (!!) that had the most incredible guitar playing I’d ever heard. It opened my eyes to new potential on the instrument and I had no idea that level of technicality, virtuosity, and musicality. The DJ said, “That was Steve Vai with his track &lt;em&gt;Juice&lt;/em&gt; off his new album, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alien_Love_Secrets&quot;&gt;Alien Love Secrets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.” Immediately, I scrounged up all the cash and change I could, went to Best Buy (when they actually had a good selection of music for sale), and bought it for $9.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little did I know, Steve Vai was–and still is–one of the most innovative, inspired, and ambitious guitarists in the industry. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt; credited him with “impossible guitar parts” as the “stunt guitarist” of his band between 1980 and 1982. Between solo releases, he played with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcatrazz&quot;&gt;Alcatrazz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Lydon&quot;&gt;John Lydon/Johnny Rotten&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_Image_Ltd&quot;&gt;Public Image Ltd.&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Lee_Roth&quot;&gt;David Lee Roth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Cooper&quot;&gt;Alice Cooper&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitesnake&quot;&gt;Whitesnake&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ozzy_Osbourne&quot;&gt;Ozzy Osbourne&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His solo releases through the 1990s were mind-blowing. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passion_and_Warfare&quot;&gt;Passion and Warfare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alien Love Secrets&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_Garden&quot;&gt;Fire Garden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; were in my CD player for months. I bought every used guitar magazine and tablature book I could find to learn those songs. There are enough weird music techniques in these albums for decades of worthwhile study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through Steve’s music (especially sheet music), I learned an incredible amount about time signatures, composition, instrumentation, key modulations, humor, crossing multiple genres, experimentation, and virtuosity. He’s been a huge inspiration to my own guitar and composition techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Vai has had a long, incredible history of trailblazing in the instrumental rock genre and he shows no sign of stopping. Every album features intricately planned and executed melodic explorations, rapid-fire blues-based riffage, and new sounds like you’ve never heard out of a guitar. His discography covers all sorts of ground from straightforward blues/rock to completely whacked-out alien noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-should-hear-first&quot;&gt;What You Should Hear First&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve never listened to Steve, here’s where to start:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For groundbreaking guitar rock: &lt;em&gt;Passion and Warfare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For completely weird, Zappa-esque outlandishness: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flex-Able&quot;&gt;Flex-Able&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For compositional complexity: &lt;em&gt;Fire Garden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for an album with one genre/version of Steve, you’re not going to find it. He sticks to no particular genre and offers something for everyone. My favorite pieces of his are the extended-length exploratory pieces, like &lt;em&gt;Freak Show Excess&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fire Garden Suite&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Story of Light&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Lucky Charms&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you’re looking for something REALLY out there, check out his performance of &lt;em&gt;Fire Strings&lt;/em&gt; with the Tokyo Metropolitan Symphony Orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-vai/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-vai/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discover Mike Keneally</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Who is Mike Keneally?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is many things! A multi-instrumentalist virtuoso who broke into the music industry as a guitarist for Frank Zappa in the late 1980s, then worked with Frank’s son Dweezil in the early 1990s, then with Steve Vai in the later 90s, then with Joe Satriani, and ended up playing guitar on Metalocalypse, all the while releasing a bunch of insane solo material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-youtube-play&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Check out our interview with Mike!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-so-weird-about-mike&quot;&gt;What’s so weird about Mike?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike is one of the rare few who is virtuosic on multiple instruments, namely keyboard and guitar (and sometimes both at the same time!). His music ranges from almost-straightforward to hardly-straightforward, sometimes within the same song. His influences are widely diverse from jazz to folk to modernist to progressive rock to Space Ghost. His music covers lots of ground and makes use of various techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time Signatures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surrealism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harmony&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-im-a-fan&quot;&gt;Why I’m a Fan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know nothing about no Mike Keneally until I saw him perform with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G3_(tour)#1996&quot;&gt;1996 G3 Tour &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; concert in Mesa, AZ. Mike came out wearing a gigantic hat and shredded alongside Steve harmonizing Steve’s “impossible guitar parts,” singing, dancing, and more. He was an astounding performer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept up with Mike’s career via guitar magazines, more Vai concerts, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://keneally.com&quot;&gt;keneally.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which has been online since 1994 and is probably one of the first musician websites on the internet. At some point in 1998, I ended up buying a copy of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/sluggo/&quot;&gt;Sluggo! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and fell in love with Mike’s music. His music has had a special place in my heart since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my time as Steve’s studio/guitar intern, I was able to hang out with Mike and a mutual friend. We spent a few late evenings watching &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_Ghost_Coast_to_Coast&quot;&gt;Space Ghost &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr._Show_with_Bob_and_David&quot;&gt;Mr. Show &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars&quot;&gt;Star Wars &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on VHS. Fun times. We also spent some time in Steve’s studio together, but I was a lowly intern and it was more a privilege to hang out than an opportunity to become real friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these years later, I’ve come across many other mutual friends, which led to &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;an interview opportunity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-should-listen-to&quot;&gt;What you should listen to&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Keneally#Discography&quot;&gt;Mike’s discography &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is pretty intense. He’s released many solo albums, and several with different band configurations (with him at the helm). Here are some of my favorite works to get you started as a new listener:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.keneally.com/collections/cd-dvds/products/mike-keneally-beer-for-dolphins-sluggo-deluxe-1-cd-2-dvd-download&quot;&gt;Sluggo! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.keneally.com/products/mike-keneally-you-must-be-this-tall&quot;&gt;You Must Be This Tall &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.keneally.com/collections/cd-dvds/products/lwh-1005&quot;&gt;Vai: Piano Reductions, Vol. 1 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I haven’t listened to it yet, Mike made an album with our friend, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt;, in a band called &lt;a href=&quot;http://store.keneally.com/products/ex-2303d&quot;&gt;The Mistakes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s described thusly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would be futile to attempt to describe this music, except to note that it’s a bravely unsettling concoction born of rambunctious rock n’ roll interplay, the peculiar contributions of four legendarily talented musicians and even a bit of poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like some awesome weird music to me!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/mike-keneally/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/mike-keneally/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discover Bruford</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-bruford&quot;&gt;Who is Bruford?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bruford was a short-lived quasi-jazz-progressive rock band featuring incredible musicianship, innovative compositions, and some of my favorite songs ever. They released three albums of original compositions, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feels_Good_to_Me&quot;&gt;Feels Good to Me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One_of_a_Kind_(Bruford_album)&quot;&gt;One of a Kind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gradually_Going_Tornado&quot;&gt;Gradually Going Tornado&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, along with a couple of live albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/hells-bells&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-youtube-play&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Check out our Learn Hell’s Bells post!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The band was led Bill Bruford (who you might know from Yes and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;) and featured &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Berlin&quot;&gt;Jeff Berlin&lt;/a&gt; on bass, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Stewart_(keyboardist)&quot;&gt;Dave Stewart&lt;/a&gt; on keyboards, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_Holdsworth&quot;&gt;Allan Holdsworth&lt;/a&gt; on guitar, who was later replaced by “The Unknown John Clark.” Bruford’s extremely complex music is made to sound effortless by these virtuosic performers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One of a Kind&lt;/em&gt; is a groundbreaking instrumental album and my favorite of all their releases. Each song is memorable and has something great to offer. It opens with the track &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/hells-bells&quot;&gt;Hell’s Bells&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which I dissected in another video. That song is followed by &lt;em&gt;One of a Kind&lt;/em&gt;, a two-part song that is very near and dear to my heart. The song &lt;em&gt;5G&lt;/em&gt; is so good it’ll make you want to stop playing music. Honestly, every track on the album is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gradually Going Tornado&lt;/em&gt; features Jeff Berlin on vocals, making a… Uh, best effort. Despite the vocal performance, the songwriting is awesome on this album. &lt;em&gt;Age of Information&lt;/em&gt; is a great rock song, but the song &lt;em&gt;Joe Frazier&lt;/em&gt; is probably the highlight of this album. It’s an instrumental track that explores some cool, fun territory and Bill Bruford lays a great foundation to let the other band members shine, particularly Jeff Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feels Good to Me&lt;/em&gt; showcases &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annette_Peacock&quot;&gt;Annette Peacock&lt;/a&gt; on vocals, which may be a bit of an acquired taste for some. Either way, this album was innovative in how it paved the way for dry-mixed, up-front female vocalists, particularly in the avant garde genre. There’s a lot of great instrumental content on the album, including some songs that remained in Bill Bruford’s repertoire for the remainder of his professional career, like &lt;em&gt;Beelzebub&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the weird techniques employed by this band are: odd time signatures and polyrhythms, genre mixing, virtuosic performance, key modulations, extended improvisation, and more. There’s a ton you can learn from listening to Bruford and even more if you put some effort into learning the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its short-lived existence, this band made a lasting impact on musicians all over the world. Musicians all over the world are posting YouTube covers and transcriptions of several songs. I plan on publishing some more content in the future covering some more notable Bruford moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, give a listen to each of their releases and see what inspires you to create something new and different.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/bill-bruford/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/bill-bruford/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discover Anthony Garone</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who am I?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s kind of a deep question. I think the best answer is, “I’m just this guy, you know?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way I could get my music written about was to start my own site. So here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/harnch&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-youtube-play&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Check out our Share Harnch by Anthony Garone post!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-me-weird&quot;&gt;What makes me weird?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know. I run this site. That’s weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music has been one of the few consistent anchors in my life. My father was in a band throughout most of my childhood and many of his friends were musicians. I started learning drums and keyboard early on, then picked up the saxophone until I started playing guitar at the age of 14 or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a miraculous turn of events, I heard a &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; song on the radio in 1996 and my life was forever changed. I bought his latest release at the time, &lt;em&gt;Alien Love Secrets&lt;/em&gt;, and my father told me that his friend, John Sergio, had grown up with Steve and even introduced him to &lt;a href=&quot;http://satriani.com&quot;&gt;Joe Satriani&lt;/a&gt; when they were teenagers. We called John and ended up visiting Steve at his house weeks later in LA. A few years later, I ended up working for Steve as a studio and guitar technician for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for Steve taught me so much about making weird music. While my father and his band influenced my foundational interest in weird music, working for a successful, professional musician was eye-opening. I could go on for pages and pages about what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked on a few albums, none of them successful but some of them are good! I’ve helped a couple of indie rock bands with engineering and production, done a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/tony-garone/id4470162&quot;&gt;work with my father on most of his releases&lt;/a&gt;, and have released several albums and singles on my own. My most recent album, &lt;em&gt;10 Decent Pieces&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.carlkingdom.com/collections/digital-downloads/products/anthony-garone-10-decent-pieces&quot;&gt;is available on Carl King’s online store&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/sXhvsZDbK2c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had the undeserved privilege of working with several amazing musicians in my brief time on this planet, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://paulsears.net&quot;&gt;Paul Sears&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Muffins&quot;&gt;The Muffins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dixie_Dregs&quot;&gt;Dixie Dregs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jonfinn.com&quot;&gt;Jon Finn&lt;/a&gt; of The Jon Finn Group and Boston Pops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sebastianlanser.com&quot;&gt;Sebastian Lanser&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neilcitron.com&quot;&gt;Neil Citron&lt;/a&gt; of Quiet Riot, Bangtower&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chris Misterek of Lovers and Fighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many other talented professional and amateur musician friends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/anthony-garone/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/anthony-garone/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Harnch by Anthony Garone</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-harnch&quot;&gt;What is a “Harnch”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harnch&lt;/em&gt; is the name of a guitar instrumental jazz fusion song by me, Anthony Garone, owner and proprietor of this very website. The performance being shared in this post is an acoustic guitar quartet arrangement I performed in Robert Fripp’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_standard_tuning&quot;&gt;New Standard Tuning&lt;/a&gt; [NST].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song gets its name from the crazy section at the end with all the time signatures. It’s the only non-swear word I could think of while recording it that adequately expressed how difficult it was to perform and record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/anthony-garone&quot;&gt;Check out our Discover post about Anthony!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;music-video&quot;&gt;Music Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video with some “fun fact” overlays, including all the time signature changes. Playing this piece in NST offered a new challenge that was accommodated by the tempo decrease from the original performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hKxuR7x4JrE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;original-recording&quot;&gt;Original Recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original song was performed a bit faster in standard tuning on electric guitars. I played all the instruments except for the piano, which was sequenced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qQp9uzCcFug?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheet-music&quot;&gt;Sheet Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in the sheet music for this song, I have it for guitar quintet in normal standard tuning (what Fripp calls “original standard tuning”) and for guitar quartet in Fripp’s “New Standard Tuning” (CGDAEg, low to high).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/tree/master/share/harnch/ost&quot;&gt;Standard Tuning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/tree/master/share/harnch/nst&quot;&gt;New Standard Tuning&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/tree/master/share/harnch/ost/midi&quot;&gt;MIDI&lt;/a&gt; (includes &lt;a href=&quot;http://musescore.org&quot;&gt;MuseScore&lt;/a&gt; file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch out for the coda! &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.garone.org/guitar/harnch-for-five-guitars&quot;&gt;Here’s some additional context on my old website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/harnch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/harnch/</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
