<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:55:01 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:55:01 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Patrick Grant</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Patrick Grant is a composer based in New York City. He founded the musical group, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiltedaxes.com&quot;&gt;Tilted Axes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and has worked with with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cage&quot;&gt;John Cage &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Robert Fripp and the Orchestra of Crafty Guitarists, Billy Joel, and Quincy Jones. I met Patrick in Mexico while I attended the Guitar Circle introductory course. He was attending the Ochestra of Crafty Guitarists preparation course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this interview and Patrick offers so much wisdom and insight. Lots of great stuff in here, so make sure you read/listen/watch the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; for pushing me in Patrick’s direction!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickgrant.com&quot;&gt;Check out Patrick’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0VBDV0YxGUg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/patrick-grant/patrick-grant.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/patrick-grant/patrick-grant.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and we have a special guest with us from New York City. His name’s Patrick Grant and he’s a composer. Thank you for joining us, Patrick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Thank you for having me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, no problem. It’s my privilege to have you on here and I really appreciate you taking the time this early morning to chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: We’ll see how you feel about that a little later…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs] So, I know you’ve been working in music for 30 years now and you’ve got a lot going on now. A lot of momentum in your career. Can you talk about some of the projects you’ve got going on right now and some of the highlights that you care to share with us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Sure! I was born in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit&quot;&gt;Detroit &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was making music there. No child prodigy by any means. I was always interested in visual art, but I made this shift to music when I was around 11 years old because it just seemed to be another way of creating universes within which to dwell, which is probably a good way for a first-born child to go when you have no other playmates. You just create these universes. But anyway, I’ll be jumping ahead many years here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I moved to New York in 1985 to continue schooling at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juilliard_School&quot;&gt;Juilliard School &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to finish there as well as to play in bands because I was also interested in rock and pop music, which is a real Detroit thing to have a foot in both worlds. I continued to have a foot in both worlds ever since. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If I had three feet, I’d be sticking that in a third world, too.&lt;/span&gt; It seems that every five years or so, I take my work into a different direction, but it’s all part of the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the things that really got me going here in New York City was the opportunity to work with theater companies. They always need composers. Avant garde theater companies were creating original work as well as having an opportunity to put on concerts and perform in art galleries because that always attracted me as an idea. I still produce a lot of shows myself, so I’ve always had that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Our_Gang&quot;&gt;Little Rascals &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “Hey guys, let’s put on a show” kind of feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I like the fact that a lot of the composers I admired–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cage&quot;&gt;John Cage &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Glass&quot;&gt;Philip Glass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–at the time in the 1980s, they drew a lot of inspiration and resource from the art world here in New York City. So, that was a way for me to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Along the way, I found myself creating music for theater and dance, working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamelan&quot;&gt;gamelan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, writing a lot of electronic music. For a while, I was known mostly as being a keyboardist, but when I decided to try out with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Circle &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and get back into my guitar playing, I created this project, Tilted Axes: Music for Mobile Electric Guitars that has most people now thinking of me as a guitarist or working with electric guitars more than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sQ78iTKSFkA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Generally, I feel that when people feel a little too comfortable in terms of what I am, it’s time to shake things up. Maybe that’s what lies ahead for me in 2017. Time to shake things up again.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s great. That’s how you and I met–we were at the Guitar Circle course in Mexico. You were in the Orchestra of Crafty Guitarists Preparation course and I was in the Introduction course. That’s how I found out about you, just playing guitar. Obviously, you’ve done much more than guitar. I absolutely love on the Tilted Axes CD how much you blend a lot of the Guitar Circle-oriented material, or just some of the kind of thematic concepts from that style of music, into a kind of a rock-oriented context or groove-oriented. I really appreciate that about your album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah, well, I would say that one of the things that drew me to the Guitar Circle was I was working with large–I had just started re-examining large ensembles a year or two prior to joining the Guitar Circle or even really knowing about the Guitar Circle and created the Tilted Axes project. What drew me so much to the group was its similarity to my work with the Indonesian gamelan and creating music in circles and how working within a circle inspires music that’s created by geometric and visual patterns, which I’d done a lot of before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_0-_3pcwC-Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Yeah, I definitely have absorbed some of the techniques from the Circle, but I also say at the same time, I’ve also admired how the Circle has absorbed other techniques from the gamelan itself, which doesn’t seem surprising because when I look at a lot of their work–or, I’m happy to say “our work” in the Circle over those number of years–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s just a lot of parallels there in terms of how music can be made in circulations, in terms of breaking up music made in a circle into different patterns of 2s, 3s, 4s, 5s, 6s, even 9s and have it all work out equally well in terms of 360-degree music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I definitely have incorporated or synthesized a lot of stuff. That’s probably something I got from working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Living_Theatre&quot;&gt;The Living Theatre &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The Living Theatre is–if one doesn’t know, they should definitely look it up because one of the things that attracted me to working with them is they have a long history, but they’re also the venue upon which composers like John Cage and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lou_Harrison&quot;&gt;Lou Harrison &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were able to peruse their first concerts in the 1950s and 1960s and they would always give a lot of trust to their composers to really create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Being a composer for them also meant that I had a space to work within. So, there was a parallel there in terms of working with and synthesizing a lot of different elements. In fact, Living Theatre is probably most known for and have been credited with being synthesists in that whatever’s going on in their environment, not just as individuals, but in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitgeist&quot;&gt;zeitgeist &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, finding a way of pulling everything together under a larger umbrella and showing the bigger picture. The Tilted Axes picture was definitely a part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a lot of different kinds of music I was working with that appeared on that album as well as a lot of guitar stuff that, as you said, yeah I did. In terms of becoming “groovified” in terms of the greater good come together in what I hope is a cohesive album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s a fantastic record. &lt;em&gt;The Kneadle Variations&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Coda&lt;/em&gt;… I laughed for minutes, not because there was anything comical but just because I love what you did. It brought such joy to my heart hearing those pieces reinterpreted in that style. It was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah, those were two themes. One’s a very famous Guitar Craft theme, &lt;em&gt;Eye of the Needle&lt;/em&gt;, by Robert Fripp. This other one was just a riff, a way of breaking up rhythm that had a lot of resonance with what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Béla_Bartók&quot;&gt;Bartok &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; does in terms of what he gets from folk music that I just put a blues scale into. Then with &lt;em&gt;Eye of the Needle&lt;/em&gt;, I was playing that–at least its core riff being the same fingering, but played in standard tuning as opposed to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_standard_tuning&quot;&gt;New Standard Tuning &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–which, in one position, it’s all whole tones. In another position it’s all pentatonic. And then writing melodies that pulled it all together. Robert was very generous in saying, “Go for it,” because I think he knew it wasn’t a goof but it was really a sincere experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right! It’s great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Thanks! I was definitely very happy to have his support of that with a bit of a wink and a nudge, but I think he’s glad how it turned out as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. Can you tell us about some of your other musical releases that might be available for purchase or listening online or outside of a theater?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Sure. I have been self-releasing and they’re available–four other albums. One shows a period of time about, jeez, in the late 1990s when I was doing a lot of work combining my love of gamelan with chamber ensembles, so I was playing a lot of keyboards that might have been tuned according to the gamelan. Or, I’d be using pure just intonation tunings mixed in with violas and guitars and–I think there’s one piece on there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/m7Vua_1xhSU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of music for film. I did music for a horror film that, for a while, was the essence of what was called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m7Vua_1xhSU&quot;&gt;Patrick Grant Group &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was 13 musicians and that in itself was a mini-orchestra using three keyboardists as its foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That I got from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P._D._Q._Bach&quot;&gt;PDQ Bach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when I was a kid. He wrote this opera, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schickele.com/composition/monksaria.htm&quot;&gt;Hansel and Gretel and Ted and Alice: An Opera in One Unnatural Act &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was impressed because they had a piano, they had a harpsichord, and they had a calliope and the sound of those three keyboards was a perfect mini-orchestra. So, I’ve always used three keyboards in my ensemble augmented with violin, cello, trombone, electric guitar, flute, clarinet, and two percussion. So, a lot of work in that time period. &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/7351293&quot;&gt;You’ll find that work out there &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then the work for gamelan proper, some of the scores that I’ve written for theatrical visionary, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Wilson_(director)&quot;&gt;Robert Wilson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, most famous for his creation &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Einstein_on_the_Beach&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Einstein on the Beach&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Philip Glass. For me, that was a huge influence in terms of what could be done on the stage and in terms of how music could be used and the creation of non-narrative narrative, which was fantastic. Bob Wilson said to me, “Patrick, everybody always asks me: &lt;em&gt;*What is Einstein on the Beach&lt;/em&gt; about?” I’d just tell him, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variation_(music)&quot;&gt;Themes and variations &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Themes and variations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dKEXZ0YCNkI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;As a musician, that’s all I needed to hear.&lt;/span&gt; I thought, “That’s the story.” And that’s how we can create a lot of narratives. Themes and variations. So, I decided to try something different this year and I put together the Tilted Axes: Music for Mobile Electric Guitars album and it did better than I expected. I was happy that the public and the press really responded to it. There’s all kinds of music blogs out there I never knew existed who wrote some nice things about it, but also larger organizations like the Boston Globe, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/tilted-axes-music-for-mobile-electric-guitars-by-patrick-grant-and-rushing-past-willow-by-nick-zoulek-reviews-1476827463&quot;&gt;Wall Street Journal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://teamrock.com/review/2016-10-29/review-roundup-this-months-best-new-progressive-music-releases&quot;&gt;Prog &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the UK, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/chris-kompanek/on-the-culture-front-musi_b_13807228.html?&quot;&gt;the Huffington Post &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… They really were able to see what I was doing, I felt, in terms of “it’s not a rock album, it’s not a classical album.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you look beyond the veneer of, “Hey, electric guitars,” there’s actually composition elements happening there that I’m happy people were listening to. So, now the trick is, how do I follow that up? The good news is: there is a plan and that plan is that I have a number of tracks that I’m finishing now and a number of tracks that have just been sitting around for the last year waiting for a reason that showcase the other kinds of music that I do that I’m working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I would say, compositionally, whether you like it or not, it sounds like me or it sounds like what I was influenced by or working with that week. I’d say it’s mostly, for a lack of a better word, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chamber_music&quot;&gt;chamber music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.” A lot of music for ensembles. There will be some electric guitar, percussion, and bass, but also violins, and cellos, and wind instruments, and some singing. One of the “hits” is this one piece that uses this very, very old public domain recording of one of those &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smithsonian_Folkways&quot;&gt;Smithsonian Folkways recordings &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that were made down in Louisiana that I added elements to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/j1PxYB0wqSE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I figured that, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;while I have people’s ears, let’s put out some other stuff to balance that&lt;/span&gt; out because on its heels, the album after that is the next Tilted Axes music, which is gonna be a little bit more thorny and convoluted than the first album. The first album dealt with themes and variations of different kinds of genres that one would associate with electric guitar. The punk ones, the blues ones, bass ones, even some that border on jazz to some level or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I would say that I’m trying to showcase what I can do in a contemporary classical way with the next album, and the Tilted album that we’re already working on, is going to be a sort of mix of the two in that the composition forms might be a little bit–I wouldn’t say “longer,” but I’d say “broader” or “more convoluted” because one of the reasons why the Tilted Axes album was so long was there was a big body of material, but I wanted to put it out on one album, so it’s 75 minutes long, but it’s almost a one-act theater piece in itself from beginning to end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Still, the pieces are more or less, with a few exceptions, sort of based in 4/4 and the reason of that is because, since this began as procession music, when Tilted Axes began 5 years ago for an event called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makemusicny.org/winter/&quot;&gt;Make Music Winter &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as a public parade–I like to call them “processions” because, as it’s written in the album note, “What is the difference between a parade and a procession? Intention.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s amazing how just putting it that way into the minds of the players, everyone all of a sudden shapes up a little bit, stands up a little bit straighter, and projects a different kind of vibe.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of that music had to be in 4/4 because that is the tradition of being a biped and playing music that is mobile, going back to all kinds of marching bands, processions, going back a lot further than that… I have found out that, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;while it’s possible to play in 7/4 or 13/4 when we’re moving around, it is more challenging.&lt;/span&gt; This album’s not going to be concentrating on that as much as I want to create music that might not be as mobile, but can be used in a fashion–I like to say I’m concentrating on music for planetariums because for me, that’s sort of the dream gig because most museums have planetariums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We have had a number of Tilted Axes events where we were mobile inside of a museum. There’s plenty of room to move, you can be inspired by the art, and for me, as a producer, I don’t have to worry about the weather. That was always a huge concern because, when you go through all this effort and it’s a one-day or two-day event and if you have the weather go bad on you–but I never have to worry about this inside of big museums. And most big museums do have planetariums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zAmv0-eeoYI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I have written a number of theater works and chamber works that are based upon elements from science&lt;/span&gt;, whether it’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickgrant.com/genome.htm&quot;&gt;the human genome &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdbaby.com/cd/patrickgrant22&quot;&gt;CD Baby &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)–I actually had a piece called &lt;a href=&quot;http://patrickgrant.com/BigBang.htm&quot;&gt;Big Bang &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Big_Bang_Theory&quot;&gt;the hugely popular CBS sitcom &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came on the air and pretty much killed that title for anybody else. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That was actually created, like a lot of this work, in collaboration with scientists. That’s very important for me, too.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Whether it seems that these pieces are whimsical, because I’m doing my poetic interpretation of these scientific things, still as it’s presented, the science has to be correct and accurate. That’s very important to me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can bust me on a whole number of things: “Why did you use that chord?” “Why did you decide to use that rhythm?” But you can’t bust me on the science.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I’ve found a lot of inspiration in my gamelan works and other pieces in structural models found in science. That was another phase I went through. I was finding structures and forms in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaos_theory&quot;&gt;chaos theory &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Music that is self-similar and self-described, where it may be finding one measure of the music, in a way, becomes the DNA for a larger piece. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s just a matter of scaling it to different discrete levels, moving at different speeds. But that kind of stuff really interests me and is the stuff that gets me motivated.&lt;/span&gt; But, first and foremost, if you’re just a casual listener or a deep listener, it’d be nice that there’s a level or layer there that you could find worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’ve mentioned gamelan music quite a bit and, for people that are unfamiliar, I thought it might be helpful for you to define what that is. Part of our mission is to educate people and to expand their horizons with music, but also you’ve mentioned in other interviews that music is such a social event and in this day and age where you’ve got people like me who sit in a bedroom recording interviews and guitar things on my own…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Am I in your bedroom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Not MY bedroom, but a bedroom in my house. [Laughs] It’s just interesting to me that I grew up just playing an instrument not thinking of it as such a social thing, but music to you is clearly very social and almost all of your work is for a group, mostly large groups it sounds like. At least, large compared to normal band sizes of 3-5 pieces. So could you talk about gamelan and your concept of music as a social event?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-6YWAZwI9Sk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: First of all, I’ve been talking about gamelan. “Gamelan” is the Indonesian word for “orchestra.” If you’re saying “gamelan,” you might as well be saying “the Indonesian ensemble.” Their indigenous ensemble, whether it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java&quot;&gt;Java &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bali&quot;&gt;Bali &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is made up of a series of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallophone&quot;&gt;metallophones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or as I tell people, “Like xylophones, except all the keys are made of bronze.” It has a really nice metallic ring and shimmer to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These are all arranged from tiny little ones that play in very high octaves of 5-note scales. There are some with 7, but that’s getting a little too “inside baseball.” Pretty much one octave per instrument. So as you go down in octaves, the instruments get progressively bigger and bigger until you get to the very lowest octaves and you have, maybe, huge slabs of bronze that are playing these low notes and then the foundation that holds it all together are huge, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gong#Nipple_gong&quot;&gt;button-faced gongs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that–not to be confused with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gong#Chau_gong_.28Tam-tam.29&quot;&gt;Chinese tam tam &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that you see at the beginning of old movies. These are gongs that are tuned to specific pitches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of the music centers around some kind of a tonal center. So they have all these instruments. Sometimes 30-40 players playing these and they’re held together by two drummers playing something that I guess would look like congas held across the lap on the side. What makes this ensemble sound musically interesting to me is that all the instruments are played in pairs. The reason for that is that if they have two little ones, then two next size, two of those… the players playing in pairs are able to produce very blindingly fast passages by–I guess the western word is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hocket&quot;&gt;hocketing &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where they each divide up a melody, so if they want to play something that’s 16th notes, one player might be [playing one pattern and the other filling in the gaps].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rp2yRpC2AR4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When you put the two together, it becomes a great thing to listen to having two ears because you hear this melody broken up. To complicate matters even more is that these two guys also have another two guys playing their same parts. They are tuned a couple of cents, depending on the village. Some villages like a large number of cents apart. Some a smaller number of cents. But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when you have those two bars that hit at the same time, the same pitch, and they’re off a number of cents, there will be a vibrato that happens between the two.&lt;/span&gt; So instead of just having a dull ringing tone, they’ll actually produce a shimmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of gamelan aficianados feel that–well, some villages feel like, “Oh, we’re more rock and roll than you because we like a wider vibrato, so we tune ours 15 cents apart.” Other people say, “Oh no, that’s too brutal.” There’s all kinds of different styles, like any other kind of music. There’s many different uses for it, but one of the things that I found attractive and lent my ear to listen to it was it was one of the–along with West African drumming, which similarly concentrates on patterns that fit together in a hocketing kind of fashion–that attracted composer &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Reich&quot;&gt;Steve Reich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He was attracted to Indonesian gamelan, too, because a lot of the rhythms can only be described as very bebop sounding when you go to the island of Bali, which is interesting in that they’ve had this long tradition of creating the music in Java. But then in the 1920s when the Dutch–and a lot of Dutch artists have taken advantage of it being a colony and hanging out there for inspiration–but a lot of the Balinese gamelan music was really a 20th century creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;They actually, in the way that people used to chop old cars and turn them into hot rods, they pretty much melted down the Javanese gamelan and rebuilt it for speed. At the same time that some people were having a problem in the western world that classical musical instruments were being bastardized by being used to play jazz in the 1920s, and those rhythms were “barbaric” and “not for lofty purposes…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The exact same thing was happening in Indonesian in terms of the beautiful court instruments of the Javanese gamelan were being melted down and were now being played by those “barbaric” Balinese as a kind of “moron music.” That’s what jazz was being derided as in the 1920s. But to pull that whole thing together and to put an umbrella over it all is that this music doesn’t exist in an abstract fashion in these societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HfrOSJRCsfM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Whether it’s the courts of Java or the more ceremonial use in Bali, they’re always for a specific purpose and they’re still not, like a lot of West African music, they’re still not divided from the dance. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s not “the dance,” there’s not “the music.” They’re one and the same thing.&lt;/span&gt; That division has not been made yet. If it was the afternoon ceremony doing an offering for the gods, there’s a specific song and dance for that. If there’s a special ceremony for the full moon–which full moon? Well, we’ve got a ceremony and a dance for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And there’s more social ceremonies that would always have their village gamelan and their dancers dance for weddings and feasts and all these other things that every society has used to mark their calendar. So, that’s the one thing that interests me very music was that the music had a purpose in every society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I first went to Bali–I’ve been there three times to study the work–was that as you pass through the different villages, you can hear each village having its own gamelan perform its evening music or taking part in some kind of ceremony. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s for real and that’s why I liked it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And they have their own tuning system, which I found very interesting, too. They’re using 5-note scales, but they’re not at all tuned like the 5 black keys on our piano. They may be technically pentatonic scales, because they use five notes, but they break up the octave very differently. So when you do hear it, all of a sudden, there’s no such thing as “harmony.” A lot of it is “horizontal” movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyways, this obviously was hugely impactful upon what I wanted to do. When I studied those rhythms and studied how those things were put together, I did join &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamelan_Son_of_Lion&quot;&gt;Gamelan Son of Lion &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a new music gamelan that’s been around since the 1970s here in New York City and it gave a chance for young composers to write for these ensembles and experiment, but I was also interested in using those kinds of rhythms and non-standard tunings with my electronic keyboard ensemble because I felt like I owned that more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I didn’t want to be grabbing someone’s music, but I was happy to learn about how the rhythms could interact and apply that to a lot of the other music I’d been using. A lot of that still carries forth when needed in everything I do today. A lot of that can be heard on this last Tilted Axes album. Here and there, it’s there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZXJWO2FQ16c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: As Steve Reich’s Music for 18 Musicians is one of my favorite albums of all time, you’ve also mentioned it in a couple of places…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;a friend gave that to me when I was 14 and that’s maybe too young.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But, I would imagine these kinds of ensembles that have had such an impact on you have greatly informed your composition style. In going to Juilliard, did you study orchestration or something or write pieces for larger ensembles or is that just something that you felt personally inclined to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: I always say, “I went to Juilliard,” but I never claimed to have finished Juilliard. So anyone who says I’m a Juilliard graduate is putting out a fiction that I never put out. But, I did go to Juilliard for two years but I never finished because I had to work here and I did that by working for a classical music publisher, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edition_Peters&quot;&gt;C F Peters &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who also published John Cage’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that’s how I was able to meet with the people who were working with John Cage and work within that circle, but I was taking private composition lessons when I was 15 because that’s all I was doing. I was just trying to–even if I didn’t know what I was doing, I still had a facility for writing music and I thought I was drawing pictures sometimes. The patterns were there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vFYdNMXJOsE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, how orchestration really came about for me–not having an orchestra–was having electronic keyboards and synthesizers. It seems that the way our ears work and the way physics works that you can find any possible sound-making device and you can pigeonhole it into, “Well, is it string-like? Is it percussion? Is it brass? Or is it a woodwind sound?” That pretty much covers the spectrum of how sound is made. But, working a lot with orchestral scores and working a lot with composer composers contributed a lot to just understanding orchestration and how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;One of the things that was useful was moving to New York City and just knowing a lot of people really doing it.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like, “Read this book because everybody here read it and that’s how we’re doing it.” That becomes a whole little culture in itself, but a lot of that… I did grow up playing violin and viola and playing in an orchestra, so I had a pretty good idea for how these instruments work and I was writing for these instruments since I was a kid, so–it didn’t happen overnight, but that was definitely part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But getting back to what you’re saying, I’ve always liked the idea of music for ceremony. Working with The Living Theatre who was influenced by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theatre_of_Cruelty&quot;&gt;Artaud Theater &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as ritual, John Cage himself would say that every performance is a form of theater. I take it as seriously as that. So, I’ve been able to apply that and of course my love of Indonesian music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not just a gig for me. It is a kind of a ceremony.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nBFnK82yyOI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Even the smallest performance should be taken that way. I think that whether it’s expressed to the public or not that this is the reason behind the performance, it comes through. Even &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Byrne&quot;&gt;David Byrne &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talking_Heads&quot;&gt;Talking Heads &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; wrote a book called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_Music_Works&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Music Works&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it’s got some good sections. The one section that I think he writes near the beginning reinforces what I’m saying is that he’s coming out of playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CBGB&quot;&gt;CBGB &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s in the late 1970s, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;any music that ever seems to work has to come out of some kind of a scene. If there’s no scene, the music doesn’t go very far.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So maybe his work has come out of a scene, but I think that’s a form of a ceremony. You look at something like CBGB’s in the 1970s, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was like a church in a way. It was a ritual. People knew how to dress for it. People knew how to act for it. There was a whole code that went along with those serious performances.&lt;/span&gt; That had its code as well as performances in Indonesia as well as at a rave in Amsterdam has its code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, whether you want to call it ceremonies or scenes, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s important and that’s one of the things I like about producing the shows is: you are creating a scene.&lt;/span&gt; If you’re going to do that, it’s good to know what all your forbears did before you. Not just in terms of their successes, but a lot of times in terms of their failures, too, because you don’t want to fail when you don’t have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But if you don’t try, you’ll never know. You can’t be afraid to fail&lt;/span&gt; because I can’t say that everything I’ve done has worked, but you can dust yourself off and learn something from that and move on. I’m happy to say it seems like there’s been enough things that we’ve done that when we synthesize and pull things together, it’s been having a decent impact on a large number of people. So, despite 2016 being such a year of extremes, there has been good parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely. And to wrap things up, can you tell us where to find your music and where to find more information about you and your projects?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/njifOZB74A8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Yeah. I’ll take this as an opportunity to tell you that as a result of my interest in chaos theory and such, the name of my production company has been Strange Music. So, you’ve got the “weird music,” I’ve got the “strange music.” I used to put on concerts and say, “Strange Music Presents.” When I was with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadcast_Music,_Inc.&quot;&gt;BMI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Strange Music was the name of my publishing company. Now it’s Peppergreen Media with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Society_of_Composers,_Authors_and_Publishers&quot;&gt;ASCAP &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But still, my larger company, the one I file with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncle_Sam&quot;&gt;Uncle Sam &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; every year, that’s Strange Music, Inc. The reason why is because I was finding–a number of reasons! First of all, the word “strange” contains my last name, “Grant.” Also, I was thinking of the strange attractors that were found in chaos theory in terms of patterns that are created out of seemingly random events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also influenced very much by a Samuel Butler quote that John Cage was particularly influenced by, and that is, “The only things that we truly hate are the unfamiliar things.” Especially when you apply that towards music, a lot of people–they want to be pacified. They don’t want to be challenged, you know? I remember that even albums like Steve Reich’s 18 Musicians…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I mean, I was 14 years old and I can’t say that I &lt;em&gt;liked&lt;/em&gt; it the first time I heard it, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;like most things I really end up liking, I get challenged, I don’t like it at first, but you keep on coming back like, “Oh, let me listen to it again to be sure that it really sucks.” As it turns out, it grows on you because it ends up changing your mind. It’s that laziness that a lot of people are battling with when they’re challenged.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kIAtNak16KU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, anyways, that’s the name of my company. All websites lead to Rome. Or, at least, all websites lead to the same place, so if you go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://strangemusic.com&quot;&gt;strangemusic.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that’s the same as &lt;a href=&quot;http://patrickgrant.com&quot;&gt;patrickgrant.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is the same as &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiltedaxes.com&quot;&gt;tiltedaxes.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So, that’s one way of centralizing things because I find that after a 30-year career, people stumble upon my work or are looking to get from my work different things. So, there’s different ways of putting it out there. So, that’s pretty much information central for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you go there, you’ll see that we have our own podcast called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stringsandthingsshow.com&quot;&gt;Strings and Things podcast &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that we have Facebook fan pages and all the usual stuff you’d expect to find. But, it needs a revamping, but all the information is current. And I have to say, speaking of such, you really do a fantastic job at Make Weird Music. Your stuff looks great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, thanks a lot! I appreciate that. It’s really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: I notice those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you, Patrick. There is so much more I want to talk to you about, so if you wouldn’t mind, I’d like to have a follow-up conversation with you in a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Sure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Plenty to think about from this and plenty of places to diverge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Oh, absolutely. But, thanks for letting me spout off. I hope I was helpful. One thing I did have to say, being thorough, but not too thorough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, it’s perfect. Thank you so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PG: Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/patrick-grant/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/patrick-grant/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Steve Vai&#39;s EVO &amp; Mad Hatter Terminator Kit</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LETPKHwA7AY&quot;&gt;Here’s a video &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about the installation of the Mad Hatter SVST-HSH Terminator Kit in EVO:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LETPKHwA7AY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/terminator-single-volume-kits/products/copy-of-single-volume-single-tone-complete-kit-with-a-5-way-selector-switch-for-humbucker-single-humbucker-svst-hsh&quot;&gt;You should buy yourself a Mad Hatter Guitar Products Terminator SVST-HSH Kit &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the same as what we put into EVO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;podcast-audio&quot;&gt;Podcast Audio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/evo/EVO-mad-hatter.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/evo/EVO-mad-hatter.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Russell Muller for joining me on some of this escapade and engineering the A/V stuff for the installation video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preface&quot;&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda promised myself I wouldn’t make this a sentimental/nostalgic post, but the content means so much to me that I’d feel inauthentic doing otherwise. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt;’s guitar, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evo_(guitar)&quot;&gt;EVO &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, can be heard on on some of my favorite music of all time. I was &lt;em&gt;obsessed&lt;/em&gt; with the guitar as a teenager when I found out about the guitar in 1995. Seriously, I carried &lt;a href=&quot;http://ibanezrules.com/catalogs/us/1995/index.htm&quot;&gt;the 1995 Ibanez Guitars catalog &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; everywhere I went in junior high and drew pictures of EVO in all my art classes (and other classes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EVO was all I would talk about with my friends and family at that time. In 1997, my grandmother, parents, and I pooled our money together and bought my Ibanez Jem7vwh, new in box. I’ve had that guitar ever since. That was 20 years ago now!! Sheesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, you may remember &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/mad-hatter&quot;&gt;my interview with “Electric Ed” Heisler&lt;/a&gt;, owner of &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Guitar Products &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I told Steve about Ed’s patent-pending potentiometer designs and what a difference it made in my Jem. Steve immediately said, “Would you install it in EVO?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, um… We did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a little nerve-wracking leaving the venue with one of the most valuable guitars on the planet. I joked with Ed that I would rather Steve handed us a bag with 1 million dollars cash because cash is replaceable. I think Ed double-checked his homeowner’s insurance after he brought EVO home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installation&quot;&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[You really should just watch the video to see what we did.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Ed installed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/terminator-single-volume-kits/products/copy-of-single-volume-single-tone-complete-kit-with-a-5-way-selector-switch-for-humbucker-single-humbucker-svst-hsh&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Terminator SVST-HSH System &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he took note of the existing wiring configuration. Steve was using a push-pull volume pot configuration with a 331K (.0033 microfarad) ceramic capacitor modification that rolled off some of the low end frequencies when engaged. Also, his tone pot had a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guitarelectronics.com/product/TCO033/Orange-Drop-022-Microfarad-Tone-Capacitors-for-Guitar-Bass.html&quot;&gt;Vishay orange drop .022 microfarad tone capacitor &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed customized a &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/pages/yin-yang-push-pull-pot-mods&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Yin Yang 500K push pull volume pot &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by placing the ceramic capacitor in parallel with the pot. He installed the Vishay capacitor on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com/products/mad-hatter-universal-cts-dual-value-potentiometer-with-stss-tone-lead&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Killer Tone dual-value pot &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and wired it to 500K. He replaced Steve’s output jack with a new Mad Hatter Switchcraft output jack and replaced the existing 5-way CRL selector switch with the Mad Hatter Terminator 5-way CRL selector switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Terminator system design is solderless, so Ed connected everything to the appropriate terminals using the Mad Hatter Little Ass Screwdriver and gently tugged on all the wires once installed in the terminals to ensure secure attachment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before restringing the guitar, he used the Little Ass Screwdriver to ensure the pickups and switch configuration were working as expected. Once it passed inspection, we restrung the guitar and demo’d the new hardware. It sounded great to our ears, but only one set of ears truly mattered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed and I brought the guitar to Steve’s studio about a week later and he loved the upgrade. He said, “It’s like EVO has a bigger set of lungs,” and specifically commented on an increase of clarity in the mid-range frequencies. Thomas Nordegg, Steve’s guitar tech, was also very happy with the tone. Ed and I were both smiling for hours afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this was a huge deal for me because Steve’s music, instruments, and friendship have played a significant part in my life. To play a small part in the history of this incredible instrument is an indescribable honor. And it was awesome to get to hang out so much with Ed, learn even more about his awesome products, and get to know him better on a road trip to LA. He exposed me to some cool weird music I’ll be sharing at some point, too!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/evo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/evo</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mike Keneally Talks To Andy West</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conversation took place in my dining room on Sunday, November 13, 2016. It was the day after Mike and Andy performed a concert in that same dining room. I just thought it’d be cool if the two of them sat down and talked to each other on film since they’re old friends who hadn’t played together in years. It was a cool conversation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Check out our interview with Mike Keneally!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;And our interview with Andy West!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/omJhldQT-JQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west/mike-keneally-andy-west.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west/mike-keneally-andy-west.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks so much to Julie Cord, co-founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bluemouthpromotions.com&quot;&gt;Blue Mouth Promotions &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. BMP is hosting the &lt;a href=&quot;/link/x-jamm-2017&quot;&gt;2017 NAMM X-JAMM&lt;/a&gt;, featuring a slew of great artists performing for 6 hours the Saturday of NAMM in Anaheim. Julie works with Mike in all sorts of ways and BMP is a great company worth supporting. Check them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Andy West: So Mike, I was listening to the radio on the way over here, and um, it was kind of a, uh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally: They played a bunch of my stuff, didn’t they? [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Yeah, exactly! It was fascinating, but there was a lot of this doom and gloom scenario about science and this kind of stuff, but you know, overlaid with this sense of hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right, in terms of how technology can actually help us instead of hurt us. So, my question is: as someone who’s been a lifelong musician and in the business for so long, how do you… not a business question, but how do you see music evolving? Because it’s really struck me recently as I kind of continue to sort of look backwards and forwards at the same time, particularly with YouTube, you know, you can go see the videos of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thelonius_Monk&quot;&gt;Monk &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all the classic guys that are just extreme, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Right. [Chuckles]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And then, here we are now. So, do you ever think about or do you have any sense of kind of an evolutionary sort of thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I don’t have a shape or a pattern in my head. I do think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s fascinating to think about. But, I don’t know. I mean, you framed that by starting by talking about technology, and I recognize definite luddite tendencies in myself, you know, when I compare things that are happening now compared to… I mean, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I tend to idealize the early seventies as a period where musicianship was really fresh&lt;/span&gt;. The influences were still new enough so that the way they were being processed and recontextualized was really fresh feeling, and audio technology was just at a point in history in the early seventies that it produced a sound that seems amazingly good to me and a lot of other people. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think there’s a reason why a lot of people intrinsically are so affectionate for the music of that era, and obviously a lot of it has a lot to do with what people were playing, but a lot of it also has to do with the way it sounded.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Just this really full and warm–and it’s very clichéd to use the word ‘warm’ when describing analog sound and analog technology, but most clichés have more than a grain of truth to them. I think that as digital recording technology started to take hold in the eighties, that it caused some kind of mass hypnosis, and many musicians with great ears that have been proven to have great ears got seduced and hypnotized a little bit by the clarity of digital. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you listen to that stuff now and it’s almost unconscionable what was done to music&lt;/span&gt;. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And that was accompanied by people starting to ratchet up compression in order to make things louder. So obviously everybody recognizes that the earliest digital recordings, especially in pop music in the eighties, a lot of it sounded really strange. So I think a lot has been done to compensate for that since then. And newer digital recordings are warmer, but they do arguably feel less human than the stuff that we were in love with and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that that humanity is lost now&lt;/span&gt;. I say all that being super grateful for the flexibility of digital recording and the availability of the tools. All that is fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But, as with so many things, it’s hard not to mourn what’s been lost, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well I wonder if people are looking for that through various forms of live performance and things where people actually can attend. There’s kind of a renaissance of certain sort of jazz styles that are not like a rebirth of an old thing, but kind of an approach I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I don’t know if you’ve heard somebody like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vijay_Iyer&quot;&gt;Vijay Iyer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something like that where it’s just kind of piano jazz but not really a standard jazz form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK. Sure. Oh yeah, sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: So let’s hope that that’s kind of mediating that other kind of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, yeah. I mean, definitely it’s out there. As with anything, there’s going to be an equal and opposite reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Which is why you’re going to see a huge rise in progressive activism over the next few years. But I love that format that you’re describing. My friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Mitchell_(pianist)&quot;&gt;Matt Mitchell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s a keyboardist and composes for small jazz groups, sounds nominally like jazz but it heads in directions that are unpredictable, and you can feel the acquired knowledge and the exposure to all kinds of culture and music over the last many decades. It gets soaked into it. People will hear the word ‘jazz,’ and they think it’s going to sound like &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But it’s all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: “It must swing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: You know, I’m hearing a lot of things with more straight time and interesting rhythmic kind of things with these sort of harmonic overlays or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I love that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I mean, that’s fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, that’s kind of cool. The other thing I’ve noticed, and maybe you can comment on this is…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I don’t mean to make you ask all the questions, but I’m enjoying this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Ok cool. We’ve all…you know, people who have…I don’t want to say ‘studied music’, but sort of watched the evolution of players and musicianship over time. So in that time period when you were talking about, to actually discover a great musician was something that happened almost by serendipity or through some kind of filtered process of editorializing. I remember the first time I ever heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahivishnu_Orchestra&quot;&gt;Mahavishnu Orchestra &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for example, was in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creem&quot;&gt;Creem Magazine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s amazing that that’s where you went, because that’s…when you said that I precisely went to the first time I saw Mahavishnu Orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, but now it’s YouTube, right? As a bass player, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve sort of had to come to grips with the fact that I could go on YouTube and find a hundred people that are just monstrous players that have technique and abilities that you just couldn’t find thirty years ago. It just didn’t exist.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Uh-huh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And now it does. So there’s some some cause for that effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m wondering if it’s kind of like there’s a lot of noise out there, and there’s this very high level of musicianship along with the noise.&lt;/span&gt; So it requires a filtering mechanism of say, “This is something that I can actually connect with, or not.” And the only way that I’ve found to do it is through my own trial and error, literally just going through and listening to stuff. And maybe that’s part of the evolutionary process that needs to develop here or something, which is some way to sort of… I don’t know if ‘editorialize’ is the right word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, you can only rely on your instincts, and you’ve only got a limited amount of time in a day. It’s so much stuff to process and filter, that you kind of have to. Everyone does it. You go by first instincts when you get a link that someone has forwarded to you, and it’s one of 30 links that you’ve been momentarily intrigued by that day. And you don’t have time to watch them all. You have to, and that’s informed by all kinds of prejudices and things that you have to decide. “Am I going to listen to this thing that probably sounds like something I’ve heard before, or am I going to go this direction that might be more challenging?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And knowing you, I’m sure you probably tend to go for the more challenging things if you have a limited amount of time. But, if you have the time, you might say, “I just want a cross-section of what’s going on.” Or there’s a million reasons why you might be tempted to click on a link and see what’s going on. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And there’s so much that I don’t see. I made peace with that many many years ago.&lt;/span&gt; And if someone hands me a disc on the road or something, I accept it graciously always and with gratitude. “Thank you for sharing this work with me.” And, you know, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s probably a little part of me that’s like apologizing in advance saying, “There’s a good chance I won’t hear this.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You know, I don’t say that out loud ‘cause I don’t want to, I don’t want to corrupt the moment, or…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And you may!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Or negatively influence anything. I might very well listen to it. But I know that at the end of every tour I end up with a stack of stuff and not the time to listen to all of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: OK, so actually, this leads to a story that Anthony can edit out if he wants. But it’s how I met him. Did I tell you this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK. Um? Tell me again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: OK. So Anthony and I worked at the same company down here in the Phoenix area. And he came to my office one day kind of cold and said, “Excuse me, but are you Andy West the bass player?” Which happens maybe eight or ten times in my entire thirty year computer career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. [Laughs] Not very often, but you know, interestingly more in the last ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That makes sense to me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It takes time for this stuff to soak through the water supply.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: But the point is he came in, and he said, “Oh, well, that’s great. You know I’m a musician, blah blah blah.” And he gave me a CD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And he said, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ahab.garone.net&quot;&gt;“This is a CD I made with my dad.” &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And I said something to the effect of, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Ah that’s great. Yeah, I’ll definitely listen to it. By the way, I hate almost everything.”&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs] You know, or something to this effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs] That’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: “You know, don’t take it personal, but I’ll definitely listen to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And I listened to this album, and it was…I had probably a year earlier reread &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moby_Dick&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moby Dick&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; again. It’s kind of like one of these books that I go back to every now and again. And it turns out that this album was conceptualizing the story of &lt;em&gt;Moby Dick&lt;/em&gt;. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Mmm hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Written by his dad, and Anthony played all the parts, and produced it, and all this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Too cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And this was like one of the… I’m looking for an adjective here. I can’t find an adjective to describe how I felt about this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: It was really interesting. Of course I love the story. And the lyrics and the melodies were very unusual, and it turns out his dad was you know, proudly unschooled. [Laughs] Like he would say, “Don’t ever try and teach me how to read music” or something, you know, “because I’m afraid it will corrupt me.” You know, kind of a weird attitude but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He had a voice, and he wanted to preserve it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah! So it was like he was in the Amazon living in the forest and did not want to come out. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: He liked it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: So it was just a very interesting story because this album, it’s not like something I would coldly recommend to anybody because it’s very eclectic and weird. So I was like, “God, what do I do with this? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love this, but I’m not going to tell everyone like ‘go listen to this album’ because they’ll think I’m nuts.&lt;/span&gt;” [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I’ve run into that and I’ve become involved in projects specifically because I thought that the music was was so amazing and how could the world not love this, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Mmm hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Sometimes I get a little clouded about that just because I think something is so amazing. I don’t know if I ever feel frightened that people will question my own sanity by recommending something. [Laughs] But then I know, yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you don’t just tell anybody that they should go check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trout_Mask_Replica&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trout Mask Replica&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You gotta read the room. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, well Trout Mask… Ok, so just to jump haphazardly to another topic, you know when we first met, and you mentioned this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crazy_Backwards_Alphabet&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crazy Backwards Alphabet&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right. That I did with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Kaiser&quot;&gt;Henry Kaiser &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s a really good album. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That album was a real complete statement. And I like that record a lot.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. It’s a pretty neat thing. Now, because of course &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;on the internet, you’ll see all kinds of people say things, just really horrible things, about this stuff.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Like, “What were they thinking?” You know, this kind of thing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But we were thinking all kinds of things and just sort of playing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs] That’s a good answer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] But it was fascinating to me because of course &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/captain-beefheart&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beefheart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was not part of my past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I was sort of into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allman_Brothers&quot;&gt;Allman Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cream_(band)&quot;&gt;Cream &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you know, that whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Right on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mothers_of_Invention&quot;&gt;The Mothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; too, for sure. But not, like, beyond The Mothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It didn’t go far… yeah, yeah. Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. So Henry had me playing all these Captain Beefheart songs that I had never heard. And also the approach to the songs was so different because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was not grounded in the kind of musical education that I had, which was very precise and harmonically, cohesive, and all this kind of stuff. So, it was very eye opening to me…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s ’cause they’re tone paintings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: In a different kind of way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. So that was pretty cool, and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, what I enjoyed hearing you play that kind of stuff, not just the Beefheart stuff, but the sort of Beefheart-influenced, uh, “Henry stuff” and whatnot, is how perfectly matched your approach and tone was for that kind of music. Like, I listened to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rockette_Morton&quot;&gt;Rockette Morton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, his bass playing on Trout Mask, and I see a taste of lineage…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: A parallel universe! [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, well just that. I see a link between your style and his style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well that’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And it’s something to do with the attack on the strings and the musicality of it and the solidity of the sound and all this stuff. When I heard you in the seventies with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dixie_Dregs&quot;&gt;The Dregs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it was all about precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And The Magic Band, the Beefheart stuff, is about discipline, because they had to practice those songs a million times to get all these disparate events to line up in any kind of way. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But it’s not about precision in the accepted sense.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But in a way it is ‘cause you gotta drill that stuff endlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well ok, so in line with the original evolutionary sort of commentary, do you hear anything that is, I mean… What could you comment on besides yourself–which we can go to another topic on; I want to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/scambot1/&quot;&gt;Scambot &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before you leave. But, do you hear any trends? Or is it just kind of like isolated, “Wow, this is a really interesting approach that these folks are doing or this guy is doing?” I mean, do you hear any kind of overall trending?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I’m so out of touch. I mean, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I regret the fact that I don’t make the time to listen to everything that crosses my path.&lt;/span&gt; I would find it im…I clearly do find it impossible to do so, but there’s so much that passes me by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But I wouldn’t presume to indicate my awareness of a trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well, ok, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But I hear good things a lot. Something will come out, and it might be years after it’s current, but I hear relatively new music. Like, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Thunes&quot;&gt;Scott Thunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gave me a recording of the band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Field_Music&quot;&gt;Field Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; like eight years ago or something. And I really enjoyed it. And then I sort of didn’t think about them anymore. And then &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Minnemann&quot;&gt;Marco Minnemann &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; became obsessed with the band Field Music, and then started playing it on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Satriani&quot;&gt;Satriani &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I realized I was aware of them. I had even heard their music years ago, and I went, “Yeah, that’s really good.” But then when I heard it a couple years ago again, I was reminded it’s actually really brilliant. It’s exciting. It’s beautifully constructed pop music, that, you know, in its field, it definitely deserves to stand alongside &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XTC&quot;&gt;XTC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the best of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd_Rundgren&quot;&gt;Rundgren &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and all that stuff. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love super well-constructed, non-predictable pop music very much.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love a chord progression that is just beautiful. You don’t see where it’s going, but when it arrives, you realize, “Oh, that was the perfect solution nailed.”&lt;/span&gt; That stuff is so much fun for me. And Field Music has that in spades. So that’s reasonably new music that’s brilliant, and always my response when I hear something great unexpectedly is to be, you know, a little shocked. [Laughs] And then to be super super grateful to be reminded that I can be a curmudgeon as much as I want. But I can never really have the whole picture of everything that’s happening, and there’s always great stuff going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well maybe it’s part of this evolutionary thing I keep harping on. The fact that there is a lot, but you have to discover it. Maybe it becomes more of a–it’s like a localized thing, you know? If you go back to the reason music is important to people, or why people love music, there’s an emotional thing there. There’s a human connection kind of thing that’s going on, or there should be. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Ideally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I guess there are people that have never experienced a profound feeling from listening to music, but that would be very sad to me. You know?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh, it would be. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s only occasionally that something hits me that makes me need to go on the old social network platforms and share it.&lt;/span&gt; But when I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kendrick_Lamar&quot;&gt;Kendrick Lamar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the Grammys earlier this year… Did you see that performance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Maybe the single greatest musical performance I’ve ever seen on television.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Oh my God, ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And so I saw this and had to spread the word. It’s like, if you think nothing’s going on, wait ‘til you hear this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s amazing. Not just the content of the words, which is powerful and huge, but also the actual content of the performance, and the band playing which was… They’re just like deadly great. And the musical conception, which is really evolved, and it’s endemic of now, what’s happening in the the sort of intersection between hip hop and DJ culture and jazz and spoken word and activism and all the stuff that’s coming together in an insanely powerful way. And which, you know, will continue to do so. That’s just like, I…I…Kendrick Lamar at the Grammys. That’s all I can say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. I’m going to have to go look at that. That’s awesome. Here in Phoenix there’s a–I mean, I’ve looked, and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s kind of a dearth of opportunity for people to hear live music.&lt;/span&gt; You know, it’s really spare. There’s a local club here that is set up as a non-profit called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thenash.org&quot;&gt;The Nash &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is about jazz. But it’s purely jazz. Do you know what I mean? They’re not going to be doing other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Which I think is kind of unfortunate ‘cause I think that there’s room for other stuff. And kind of like a pure music venue where people don’t need to go to buy drinks or, you know, the stupid thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s why Anthony’s going to open the MWM Club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah! Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: He’s not in the room. OK, we can, we can divulge all of his clients now. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Yeah right. It’s uh, it’s going to be right here in the living room. Of course his wife has got something to say about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: No, it’s cool though. But you know, I think in New York or Boston there seems to be more of–maybe it’s just the concentration of cities. LA, you know, has the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Baked_Potato&quot;&gt;Baked Potato &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I guess the other side of that is really that now you go to the issue of musicians and artists creating and how do they support themselves? And then that opportunities become–well, you have to be very creative about this, and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if live performance is the only thing that’s gonna really do it, that’s an issue. But yet, we still do.&lt;/span&gt; I mean, people still create stuff no matter what. They’re driven to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Maybe that’s really the filter. You know, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the filter is, “What are your motivations? What are your reasons?” And if they’re strong enough in the pursuit of expression, it’ll happen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You find a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yep. If that was a question, you just answered it. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] I guess so. I’m just sort of musing on it, you know, because…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, it’s good to think about, and it’s definitely good to check yourself every once in a while. Does your drive remain strong? Check your motives. And just keep putting one foot in front of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And you know, people who…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s why I keep asking us that. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] I have to put in a plug here for pragmatism too because I know a lot of musicians, and myself included, who have sort of taken a path of providing for themselves and their family through other means, having a day job, whatever. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And back in the day, that used to be a real sort of sign of failure or something.&lt;/span&gt; You know, not necessarily a sign of failure, but it was not a sign of success. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And now I feel like it’s great if people can figure out how to make it work. There’s a lot of ways to do this, but again it kind of goes back to your motivation. And then sometimes they can kind of merge into a commercial successful thing, and sometimes not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, it’s your motivation and also your specific intent. And, if your desire is simply to make music and not necessarily be out on the road for months at a time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: …then all of a sudden it becomes very practical and real smart to find a way to fund those activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You know I definitely have. I got involved with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/School_of_Rock&quot;&gt;School of Rock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2007 and that was my attempt for a year at doing precisely that, holding down a day job. And it just became un-unworkable because by the end of that year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dethklok&quot;&gt;Dethklok &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was touring, and then suddenly there was an impasse that couldn’t be breached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: There’s certainly no stigma attached to it now, and I think it’s obviously laudable and quite necessary in a lot of cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well you know, it’s, it’s another means, although um, you know, people who have a family and a job, and want to do music…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: …it’s really, you know, it can be a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well it is. I absolutely admire anyone who has the psychic space to encompass all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. So, what else is on your mind? [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh man. I’m just grappling with my schedule all the time, which is challenging, so I’m a little self-centered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Right now. So as soon as you said that all, I saw was stuff I have to do. You know, and that’s not at the expense… I don’t want this to be a political conversation so, obviously the, the election is on my mind, as it is on everyone’s. And, just going to have to see what happens there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But, I’m feeling good. I just did a lot of live playing. I was out touring with &lt;em&gt;Beer for Dolphins&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryan_Beller&quot;&gt;Bryan Beller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.killuglyradio.com/wiki/Joe_Travers&quot;&gt;Joe Travers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and then we wound up on election night at The Baked Potato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: With &lt;a href=&quot;http://rickmusallam.com&quot;&gt;Rick Musallum &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; joining us.  We were a trio up until that last show, and then we were a quartet which I saw as sort of crossing the threshold in Beer for Dolphins activity next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Oh really? Awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I want it to be a quartet with Rick whenever it’s possible. But then, it goes into finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Touring just now on the east coast and in the South and in the Midwest was so much more feasible with three players than it would have been with four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Even in terms of van space and just all kinds of logistics. And I’m looking at the really scant amount of money that I maybe made on the tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] Oh man. I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: But then I had–I say that only because it’s fresh and on my mind. It’s an answer to your question. So, in December I’m out on the road with Satriani, for the month in South America. And that covers my expenditure that I just put out on my tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: So that’s the balance of my career anyway. You know, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m lucky enough to have these mainstream touring gigs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: With people that you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: With people that I like, and actually really enjoy playing with. And it’s like, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;playing Satriani music is so different from playing my own. I gain so much from it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s the way he approaches these concise song forms and how he, with very small gestures melodically, just paints this complete picture that everyone responds to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah! Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And that’s really thought-provoking for me because I’m always searching for that thing way out there, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Joe finds something right here next to you, and when you hear it, you realize, “Well that’s the perfect thing for that moment.”&lt;/span&gt; And then you watch people’s response to it in the audience, and it’s fascinating to me. What would be endless recombinations of musical information and what you can do. It’s so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] I know. When I listen–so of course I have all of the Satriani stuff, and I’ve seen you guys play with him many times. Well several times at least, and I also have a similar reaction in the sense that I’m in the audience so I’m kind of experiencing the music, but I’m also experiencing the audience and kind of fascinated by the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Mmm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well, it’s like: what is it that these people are really responding to? They’re responding to something that’s not something that I would normally conceive of, nor would I normally expect them to respond to what I’m hearing in the way that they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Mmm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: So it’s, it’s really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah. Well, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the basic themes are generally quite simple so people grasp that immediately take it in. The treatment is endlessly varied.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s like there are subtleties of articulation when he approaches the same melody in different parts of the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: He’s really attuned to the emotional arc of a piece of music which a lot of anti-guitar hero people might be surprised to even consider because they think it’s just about fireworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And of course the fireworks are a huge part of it, and that’s one of the things that keeps the audience kind of catalyzed and into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s just these sounds and occasionally flagrant displays of technique because it’s exciting. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;People respond viscerally to somebody who’s really good doing something really well.&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] If they happen to show up, they will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, exactly. Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And, and that’s the other thing about Joe. Because of the way he conceives things melodically, he puts out music that people embrace. And so, he still has a major label deal after all these years, and still is able to do touring at a nice level of comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And believe me, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;as a musician who is very reliant on well-paying jobs in order to feed my addiction of making my own music, I’m so grateful.&lt;/span&gt; You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: …That that there is something like the Satriani gig where we get to tour nicely and play for a lot of people playing instrumental music that’s not the most immediately conventional thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And that he gives me, and Beller, and Marco a place to be ourselves within this framework. It’s not a completely orchestrated thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah I definitely notice that. And you feel that. And I think that’s super smart and appropriate. And you guys have something to add. [Laughs] Obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And Joe enjoys it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Joe enjoys the fact that we’re adding that and the audience enjoys the fact that Joe is enjoying it, and that we’re doing whatever we’re doing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: The chemistry in the Satriani band right now is really cool, and kudos to Joe for wanting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And accepting it so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I agree. Oh, You want to wrap it? [Laughs] Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: You got any requested topics, Mr. G?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony Garone: No, I think this is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Can we talk about the first three &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_(band)&quot;&gt;Chicago &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; albums? Were you into them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs] You know, I think I was, but I think I was &lt;strong&gt;then&lt;/strong&gt;. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: OK, when’s the last time you heard that stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah? Check it out. Actually, I really like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_V&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chicago V&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The first five…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: They’re playing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Some version of Chicago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, some version of them is playing here. I mean, I’m sure they’re playing those songs and probably better than they did then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I don’t know. I’m a real &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terry_Kath&quot;&gt;Terry Kath &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; enthusiast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Oh, ok. All right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And I’m also a real &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny_Seraphine&quot;&gt;Danny Seraphine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; enthusiast, the drummer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: So there was, there’s a chemistry on the way those players sounded together on, for me, the first five records especially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I saw them play at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlanta_International_Pop_Festival_(1970)&quot;&gt;The Atlanta Pop Festival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh, well that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And they were great. And you know, horns seem to be making a comeback. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Well, I was just thinking about popular music that stretches the conventions and they popped into my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. Nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Those records–just to wax nostalgic for second about a time when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia_Records&quot;&gt;Columbia Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would fund the first three Chicago albums, which were double albums with all sorts of weird musical experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: With, you know, a million different genres and then just doing whatever they wanted. The fourth album was a live album that was four disks. [Laughs] You know, the four record set…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: …with about eighteen pounds of posters in it. You know, they could do whatever wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the marketplace was supporting that.&lt;/span&gt; And, I don’t know, I wouldn’t argue with anybody who doesn’t dig Chicago, but I have a real–obviously sentimental, but also I think somewhat logical–affection for them and that early Chicago stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Cool. Well, it’s at least added to my YouTube list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: There ya go! Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I’ll check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: [Laughs] Well, ok. We good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Thank you. Make weird music! [Everyone laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: All right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: See ya.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Decay of Cities by Henry Cow</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZvwNC4cmP5E?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soundslice-notation-and-tablature&quot;&gt;Soundslice Notation and Tablature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living sheet music brought to you by &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Wanna know more? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;our interview with Soundslice co-creator, Adrian Holovaty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/61172/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://thegabrielconstruct.com&quot;&gt;Gabriel Lucas Riccio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for his help with this transcription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Cow&quot;&gt;Henry Cow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Culture_(album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Western Culture&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is one of my favorite records, if not my absolute favorite record ever. It’s extremely challenging for the first several listens. Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold_Bloom&quot;&gt;Harold Bloom &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s first attempts at reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cormac_McCarthy&quot;&gt;Cormac McCarthy&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood_Meridian&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blood Meridian&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where he threw the book across the room three times before he could finish it, this album was unlistenable noise to me for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I started to understand &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motif_(music)&quot;&gt;motivic composition &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I began to understand this record and appreciate its beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’ve wanted to transcribe this piece for a long time and the idea had been eating away at me for the past few weeks, so here we are. There are lots of tricks to playing it, so make sure you listen to the original recording before you try playing through the transcription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the feedback I got when I posted this video, there’s more demand for Henry Cow transcriptions than I ever thought imaginable. If you’d like to see more, let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/the-decay-of-cities</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/the-decay-of-cities</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Courtney Swain</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Courtney Swain is the singer from the up-and-coming experimental/prog rock band, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bentkneemusic.com&quot;&gt;Bent Knee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You might recall Bent Knee from our interview with their guitarist, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/ben-levin&quot;&gt;Ben Levin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.courtneyswain.com&quot;&gt;Check out Courtney’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our interview with Courtney Swain of Bent Knee:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/R7oCz8oFhZQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/courtney-swain/courtney-swain.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/courtney-swain/courtney-swain.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Casey Wiliams, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/the-residents&quot;&gt;Residents&lt;/a&gt; enthusiast based in Kansas City, for her help in transcribing this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have &lt;a href=&quot;http://courtneyswain.com&quot;&gt;Courtney Swain &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with me, all the way from Rhode Island. Courtney, thank you for joining us today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Hey Anthony, hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’d like for our audience to get to know who you are and a bit about your musical background, so would you mind introducing yourself and then telling us about some of the projects with which you’ve been associated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Sure. My name’s Courtney Swain, I live in Rhode Island right now and my main lead project is I do lead vocals and keyboards for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bent_Knee&quot;&gt;Bent Knee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is a Boston-based sort of art rock/experimental rock band. I also perform in &lt;a href=&quot;http://ben-levin.squarespace.com/&quot;&gt;Ben Levin Group &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/ben-levin&quot;&gt;Ben Levin was on Make Weird Music recently&lt;/a&gt;. He’s a wonderful guitarist and he also plays guitar in Bent Knee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I also have a solo project that I have mainly been pursuing as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RPM_Challenge&quot;&gt;RPM Challenge &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; kind of capacity, where I go and record all my ideas in one month, sort of as a challenge to myself to just put it out there without judging and see what happens. So those are my main things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you sing and play keyboards. Anything else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: No. I wish I played a guitar or something, but I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And how did you meet Ben?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I was at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berklee_College_of_Music&quot;&gt;Berklee College of Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Boston at the same time that Ben was. Berklee has really changed over the last five or six years, they have a bunch of new buildings and a nice new cafeteria full of sunlight now but before, it used to be in this basement 2 floors below ground level. No one got service and it was really dank and everyone would just go there and talk to each other and it was sort of like a forced “meet people” - well, it wasn’t forced. Anyways, that’s where we met. Ben was a year ahead of me and his roommate was Vince [Welch] who is the producer of our bands and he kind of had a huge community of people and our group of bands sort of grew out of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. I know Ben’s in like, 20 bands or something, and I know you’re in several of them. Which acts are you in besides Bent Knee and Ben Levin Group?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Those are the only two right now, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, really?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Nac_Wn9djNc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah. I used to be in our drummer’s group, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mrgavinsmeatfarm.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Mr Gavin’s Meat Farm &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and I also, for a hot second, was in our bassist’s group, &lt;a href=&quot;https://justicecow.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Justice Cow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but I’m very impatient and I can be sort of a bitch to work with and I sort of had to leave. This was four or five years ago and I don’t think there’s any bad blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you guys have been doing a lot of touring. You just toured Europe, you’ve done a bunch of U.S. shows. Can you tell us about your new album and what you’re promoting on the tour?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yep. We released our third full-length record from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cuneiformrecords.com/&quot;&gt;Cuneiform Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in May, that was our first album that came out through them. The album’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://bentknee.bandcamp.com/album/say-so&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Say So&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and we were touring from the first weekend of May until the last weekend of September. We ended up playing, like, fifty-three shows across six countries and it was a lot of fun. We played about fifty shows last summer too, but that really was an arduous experience because we didn’t take any breaks, we never went back. There were times where we stopped on the road and we didn’t have shows for three days and it was a vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, I think, when you spend that much time with people in such close quarters, you really just need time away from them so when we got back last year it was just like “ahh…” But this year we took breaks and we paced it much better so we did three separate tours instead of one huge tour. So it went much better. Bent Knee’s been doing really well. There’s been a lot of great things happening to the band and so it’s really exciting to go out and actually see people at our shows because it was not that long ago when we we were playing to like, three people - we still loved it but it’s even better when there’s like thirty people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. The new album is just amazing. I was listening to most of it yesterday while driving around and my wife has heard some of it and she’s the biggest critic of the music that I listen to but one the thing that has stood out is your vocal capabilities. She’s a singer, too and she’s like “The singer of Bent Knee is such a great singer.” Can you tell us about your background and formation as a singer and piano player?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Sure! I was a piano player for way longer than I was a singer. I started playing piano when I was in kindergarten, when I was four or five, and I studied classical all the way up to middle high school. And I used to practice an hour a day, not because I liked to but because my parents were very patient and made me do it. I sort of started singing–I grew up in Japan and when you’re in high school in Japan the two big social things you do is you go bowling and then you go to karaoke. I don’t know if that’s the same here, but–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0hpU8Jwp5ic&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: That was a thing to do and so I started going to karaoke a lot and I really loved singing, and I felt like it was something where people were very encouraging and they were like “Yeah, this is something you can do!” and my brother had gone to–he’s six years older than me, he’d gone to an ivy league school and the experience was a lot to for him to deal with, and I was just thinking about going to a liberal arts school, too, but I was sort of got worried that I was going to be crushed by the academics, and it was just sort of like “Well, I’m only going to get one chance to go to college so I want to go to music school,” randomly because my mom suggested it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I applied to Berklee after the audition cutoff for Tokyo. I emailed them and I was like “Hey, I know this is too late, like you’re coming to Tokyo in three weeks, will you let me audition?” and they were like “Yeah, whatever, sure.” So I went to Tokyo and I auditioned with singing to which all my relatives were like “What are you talking about? We went to all your stupid classical piano recitals for fifteen years and you’re not going to use any of those skills?” but I accompanied myself and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m pretty sure I got into Berklee because I could play piano, I don’t think it was my singing that got me in&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then, I got to Berklee and my first class, they were counting off, they were like “Alright, we’re gonna play this song.” and I didn’t know this was two and four. So I was like “Why do I keep coming in a beat before everyone else?” I’d be like [way off] and I was like “I don’t know anything!” and so it was like a real awakening for me because my parents didn’t listen to jazz or anything besides like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cream_(band)&quot;&gt;Cream &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creedence_Clearwater_Revival&quot;&gt;Creedence Clearwater Revival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Amadeus_Mozart&quot;&gt;Mozart &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&quot;&gt;Bach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_van_Beethoven&quot;&gt;Beethoven &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I was learning all this and I was trying to sing and learn to sing better and it was sort of a real downer. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I just kinda got really depressed at my ability to sing because I just had had no formal instruction.&lt;/span&gt; The only thing I had going for myself was that I had good pitch so I could sing everything in tune but my tone was not very good. I was not doing it in a healthy way and also I think Berklee’s voice department tends to gravitate towards supporting people who have a big R&amp;amp;B, kind of pop diva kind of voice and I really don’t have that yet. I also wasn’t really interested in having that type of tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I ended up just sort of feeling like an outcast but a large part of my development as a singer really came from working with Ben in a way because the reason Ben and I started collaborating was he wanted to do an improvised choir, sort of like what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby_McFerrin&quot;&gt;Bobby McFerrin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was doing, essentially, with his singers. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But Ben wanted to do with his guitar and a group of singers so he would be like, “Let’s sing in the color of blue.” And I was there with a couple of my friends and I was like “This guy is cool!” Like, I get it, you know?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I felt like no one else did so I told him “Dude, you know, we should pursue this connection.” And then we started writing and in that process when we started recording I started sitting down with myself in a practice room with a microphone and I would record and then listen back and be like “No, this is not right, this is not right.” So I would just keep doing it until I thought it sounded exactly the way that I wanted it to. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And I think that’s the real way that I learned how to sing and to really develop my style was through this feedback loop of need and what I wanted to sound like.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TCfU_WkJ1KM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s great. And do you have other responsibilities in the band than just performing? Do you help write the songs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah! We all write together. Even the lyrics. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;someone will bring in a seed of a song and then we’ll pull it apart and re-expand it into like, this thing.&lt;/span&gt; And things come in at different degrees of doneness, so sometimes it will be an entire song with all verses, sometimes it’ll just be an idea, sometimes it will be a song with one verse. But there’s three that mostly contribute the songs. That’s Ben, our bass player Jessica, and myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I try to write and bring in some stuff that will be good for the band. I also do a lot of e-mailing. The violin player Chris and I have been doing a lot of the admin side work which luckily, now that the band is gaining an audience is being offset a little bit with some outside help, which is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely. Can you tell us about how much growth you’ve seen with this new album? I’m seeing it pop up all over Facebook and Twitter. I know I follow you guys, but it seems like you’re getting lots of rave reviews. Can you tell us where you were before this album and what do you think happened as a result of it and why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah, that’s a great question. I would actually take a step back further to talk about why this album happened, in a way, if that’s okay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sqx3xfVQXSo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I think, when we put out &lt;a href=&quot;https://bentknee.bandcamp.com/album/shiny-eyed-babies&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on November 11th in 2014, we were invited to do &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.converse-music.com/rubbertracks/&quot;&gt;Converse Rubber Track &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; sessions at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.qdivision.com/&quot;&gt;Q Division &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Somerville, Massachussetts and so we recorded a version of &lt;em&gt;Leak Water&lt;/em&gt;. There’s a version on &lt;em&gt;Say So&lt;/em&gt;, which is the newer one but this was the first song that we had already finished off the new album back in 2014. So we tracked that and then we had this big meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt; was the first time we got a real press hit. We were actually gonna release it in July but &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Needle_Drop&quot;&gt;The Needle Drop &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Anthony Fantano, featured it and then we got this explosion of attention and we were like “Oh, this is what it means to get a press hit.” And so we were like, “Okay, let’s push the release back 4 months to see if we can get a PR company and get more buzz.” And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;through the experience we sort of learned what it means to have a release timeline and to work with a publicist.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So when we sat down on November 11th, we were like “This is good, &lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt;, great album, okay. What are we gonna do next?” And we laid out this timeline of when we wanted to have the music and what we wanted to accompany the release like music videos and a PR agency or a label, all this stuff. So it was very much kind of a planned, deadlined focus production as opposed to &lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt; which took like, 2 or 3 years because we were learning to write with each other and there was no deadline. It was just like, it will be done when it will be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we wrote really, really hard in the beginning of 2015. Vince and I were commuting up from Providence to Boston to rehearse and you know, we would be in Boston like 2 or 3 nights a week. Winter is exhausting in New England, too, just because there’s so little daylight and it just gets really dank and it was really hard to finish the album but we did and then we played 50 shows of that album, just trying it out in front of audiences to see if it works. And after we got really good at playing it, we went in and recorded it right after we got off of tour and we were so good at playing the songs that it took us one day to finish basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/o7mERyfchWE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we got in the studio and they set up until like 11 or noon or 1, we got all the sounds. And by nine or ten we were done tracking all 10 songs. It was pretty crazy. And right around that time, this guy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anil_Prasad&quot;&gt;Anil Prasad &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who has a great online music blog called &lt;a href=&quot;http://innerviews.com&quot;&gt;Innerviews &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you probably know about it. But he found out about us and posted about us and people started hearing about us and Anil was like, “Why isn’t more stuff happening for you?” And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;he connected the dots so that we were able to work with Cuneiform Records.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Cuneiform has been around for about 2 decades, maybe more. I forget. And they have a really close following of people who are really interested in what they do. They’re not a big label but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;they’re a really honest label that is really built on relationships.&lt;/span&gt; So when we got signed to Cuneiform, even before we were anywhere close to releasing the album, we started seeing more people at our shows. People were just interested just because Cuneiform was interested. And for that I am really eternally grateful to Cuneiform because they were the first real big tastemakers that said, “Check this out, this is a band that people should be listening to.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So the baseline of how many people we see per show just went up wherever we went, even if we played a new place. And we’ve been playing our music really hard and we play a lot so one thing that we can always rely on is that we always play our music really well when we play live. And I think it’s served us well because those new people who came to see us because of Cuneiform were, I think, always really blown away by our performances. We have this running joke in the band that everyone’s always really nice to us after we play because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we are a really weird bunch of people and sometimes people have a bad day or something, but after we play, they’re like, “Hey, we like you guys!”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;With Cuneiform, the kind of baseline of people coming to our shows went up and we were also able to secure &lt;a href=&quot;http://girlieaction.com&quot;&gt;Girlie Action &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a New York-based PR company that worked with us. They helped us put out our music videos and live videos to more people so that there was a bigger audience waiting for that stuff as it was being rolled out. I guess a big lesson we learned during &lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt; is that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;news and press really don’t care about an album once it’s out. They want to be the first people to know about it, so they want to do premieres, they want to premiere videos, but once your album is out, they just don’t want to touch it. They’re like, “It’s out. Anyone can listen to it. No big deal.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9s7XwPw4Ie4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But with Girlie Action, they have a lot of firepower and the biggest thing they got us was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/say-so-by-bent-knee-review-1464125585&quot;&gt;the Wall Street Journal feature &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We had a writeup in the Wall Street Journal and this was huge. It’s actually still huge as we are working with more people and as we are working towards our next album. I guess Jim Fusilli, the writer who did the article, is this guy who’s really well respected as a writer and a lot of people try to get him to “write this, please!” and he doesn’t. So people sort of turned heads at the fact that he wrote this piece on us. Again that was one of those things that kind of bumped our baseline of how many people are showing up to shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The biggest thing that happened recently on the heels of &lt;em&gt;Say So&lt;/em&gt; and after all the touring was that we got an opening slot for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dillinger_Escape_Plan&quot;&gt;Dillinger Escape Plan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s final tour. And &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; really bumped it to the next level. We’ve been seeing people from a different demographic, too, because this whole year we’ve sort of been receiving a lot of love from the prog community. They’re so wonderful and it’s funny because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;every time we play a show, there’s always this one older person in the back and they all joke like, “Yeah, I’m the old guy in the back.” They’re so easy to spot and they’re so kind to us, but we, being young, never thought of ourselves as “prog.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s kind of a concern where we thought, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Are we going to get stuck in prog?”&lt;/span&gt; Then the Dillinger thing happened and it was perfect timing. So we’re seeing a lot of younger people. It’s interesting now going onto the Facebook page of Bent Knee. It’s a different experience because I have no idea who the people are that are talking about us. It’s not just our friends and our moms and dads and uncles and aunts. It’s actual people I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah yeah! They sort of treat us as such, too. When we put something out, they’re like, “Oh shit! New Bent Knee!” It’s really exciting that that’s happening. Yeah, so that’s sort of how it feels on this end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So tell me a little about how growing up in Japan has influenced your songwriting and your musicianship and what that brought to your Berklee experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah, really interesting question. I think it’s hard to say what it really is because I don’t have the experience of not growing up in Japan. I don’t know what it would be like if I had not gone through that. I think it’s made things a lot more complicated, for better or for worse. When I listen to the first Bent Knee album–I’ve spoken English all my life. I was double schooled, so I went to Japanese public schools, but my dad was also home schooling me in English. So, it’s my second language and I speak it fluently, but it’s not quite native. When I first came to college, people were like, “What’s your accent?” And I never realized that I had an accent, so I was really wigged out by that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Now, when I go back and listen to the first album, I sort of understand what people were talking about.&lt;/span&gt; I don’t finish my words. I don’t know if that makes sense, but when you listen to it, the vowels sort of drag on, but the consonants don’t come at the end at the right time. I think that’s because in Japanese, consonants get placed in a different place. When I went to Japan in February–my hearing is fine, I’m a musician but I have fine hearing, but I kept missing my friend’s words. I kept saying, “What’d you say? What’d you say?” I wasn’t hearing them. I just wasn’t used to listening to where their consonants were that I wasn’t focused on hearing those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had a real identity crisis growing up in Japan because there’s just no one who looks caucasian in my town. My dad, my brother, myself… And I knew maybe 5 or 6 other people who weren’t Japanese. But, I heavily identify as being Japanese inside. I’m really interested in Japanese history and I’m really interested in Japanese mannerisms and colloquialisms and sort of wit and humor. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was a real struggle feeling rejected from a culture that I felt like I’d really earned and I really identified with.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BAmUFbE93Is&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I came to college, especially in collaborating so closely with other people, I really quickly learned that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Japanese communication is not a very good communication style to have when you want to work within the arts and be really honest and forthcoming and brutal and also emotional with other people.&lt;/span&gt; There is an episode of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_American_Life&quot;&gt;This American Life &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/597/one-last-thing-before-i-go&quot;&gt;they were talking in this phone booth in Northern Japan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where the tsunami hit and it’s not connected to anything. People just go there and talk to the deceased or the lost just to talk about it and in that piece, they did a really great job articulating how–I’ve never told my mom or my aunts that I love them. It’s just not something that you say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t think I ever hugged my grandma. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It doesn’t mean I didn’t love her or have an understanding that we were both there together, but that sounds really absurd to an American. It’s like, “WHAT? You never hugged your grandma?!”&lt;/span&gt; It’s that kind of disconnect where something I thought was so normal that I didn’t even think about or realize is just so far removed from what the social norm is in terms of communicating with people in the US. So, I really had to re-learn how to express myself at all. For a long time, I felt like I never had an opinion and I just was going with whatever everyone else’s opinion was. It’s a very Japanese groupthink kind of thing. Whatever is the predominant opinion, we’ll go with that. Bow and smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think that was the biggest thing for me in college and in music, just learning to communicate in a different culture. It’s the most difficult thing. It’s been difficult, but at the same time, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s really helped the group establish ground rules and a deeper understanding for how we communicate with each other.&lt;/span&gt; And also the openness and honesty to be able to call each other out and to excel in being better friends and better people. Or at least that’s how I like to think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You said you didn’t have a whole lot of musical variety growing up, but Bent Knee is such a musically diverse band. I would imagine when you got to Berklee, you were exposed to all sorts of genres and bands and even instruments that you might not have had growing up the way you did. Has that been kind of a musical awakening or do you feel like you’re pretty firmly set in the roots you established in Japan and that’s what you bring to the songwriting and lyric writing experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/c16ya0MXXjE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I think I’ve definitely moved on from my roots. I think they’re still very important albums to me on an emotional level, but I always am surprised in a way when people talk about Bent Knee being so “jazzy.” Then I go and listen to songs like &lt;em&gt;Nakami&lt;/em&gt; from the new album. It’s like, “Okay, I get it,” but when I came to Berklee, I couldn’t improvise. I was a classical player so I couldn’t improvise on the piano. So I’ve had this infatuation for the last decade since I came to Berklee, like, “I want to play jazz.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was one of those things that really opened my eyes. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think a lot of my musical awakening is really fueled by Ben, our guitar player, and Chris, our violin player. I’m not a very good music listener. I am at music performing.&lt;/span&gt; That’s what I love doing. I love performing music. I love writing music after that and then at the end, I like listening to music. That sounds really sad, but I just realize that especially with Bent Knee growing, there are people who are listening to Bent Knee because they love listening to music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve never really had that experience where I’m just listening to music hungrily looking for something new. I get tired of my own playlists or my own albums all the time because the way I listen is I’ll find something new and I’ll listen to it until I just stop listening and then I won’t listen to music for a while. In times like that, and the way I find new music, is through Chris, who’s an avid music listener. He’s always, always listening to and reading NPR, he watches all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NPR_Music&quot;&gt;Tiny Desk Concerts &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He listens to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Song_Exploder&quot;&gt;Song Exploder &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a great podcast. Stuff like that. Through him, I have been exposed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Son_Lux&quot;&gt;Son Lux &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; whose &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/We_Are_Rising&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Are Rising&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the RPM album he did, is really cool. That was a really big influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then Ben also, whenever he gets into something, he really digs deep. His influences show very clearly on the music writing of Bent Knee. If Ben gets into something, it’s inevitable you’re going to know it really really well, whether you like it or not. You also get the whole commentary and discussion on what is really happening and what is the significance of a texture and what is the historical background of something. He ends up really breaking it down. So that’s where I get most of my musical awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My biggest influences right now are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esperanza_Spalding&quot;&gt;Esperanza Spalding &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiona_Apple&quot;&gt;Fiona Apple &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I guess one influence that I haven’t been able to–not “get rid of” like it’s bad–but it still sticks with me is a Japanese artist named &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ringo_Sheena&quot;&gt;Shena Ringo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Her second album is really deep and really wonderful. When I listen–I went back and listened to it recently and I thought that when I listen to it, I don’t feel like I’ve moved that much because the different creative sampling and the darkness and the depth of the lyrics and the emotional delivery of what she’s doing doesn’t really seem like it’s that far, but at the same time, I think I was always trying to get there. Now I can actually do that, but in the past I don’t think I was able to make that quality of material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4BUfvoQjza4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Have you ever crossed paths with Esperanza Spalding? She’s incredible, Berklee grad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: No, I have not. When I came to Berklee, everyone hated Esperanza Spalding. I shouldn’t generalize, but people were talking about her. I went to see her once and I was kind of like, “I don’t get it.” I think she was playing solo and I heard a lot of “doo-bee-dee-ba-doo-ba-doo-bah.” And I was like, “What?” I think maybe I was just in a bad place, but when she put out this new album, I was like, “Urrrggghhh.” I had sort of judged her without really listening to her music or really digging deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emily&#39;s_D%2BEvolution&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;D+Evolution&lt;/em&gt; album &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah, I heard her on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wait_Wait..._Don%27t_Tell_Me!&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wait… Wait Don’t Tell Me!&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/2016/03/26/471846283/not-my-job-jazz-bassist-esperanza-spalding-gets-quizzed-on-bases&quot;&gt;She was hilarious &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and–what’s his name? &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Sagal&quot;&gt;Peter Sagal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–was like, “So you were the youngest professor at Berklee. What was that like?” She was just like, “Yeah, it was great. I just don’t think it was great for my students, though.” They were just like, “Do you want to teach?” and like any good musician, I was like, “Yes!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You say yes to everything. When she said that, I was like, “That makes sense.” I have definitely, as a musician, walked into things that I’m way underqualified for just because someone offered it. I was like, “Yeah, I’m going to do this. I’m going to rock it.” I was so impressed that she just owned up to it and was so relaxed about it. Then I just went and listened to the album and was like, “WOW. This is crazy!” I haven’t gone through her back catalog, but I’m still really enjoying and savoring this &lt;em&gt;D+Evolution&lt;/em&gt; album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, there are so many great songs on several of her previous albums. I do encourage you to invest in some of it. It’s extremely different from &lt;em&gt;Emily’s D+Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, but really good stuff. If I remember correctly, you were a key part of some of the music videos you guys have made recently, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah. I was involved heavily in the &lt;em&gt;Good Girl&lt;/em&gt; video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you have a photography or film background?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KCSsuwHpYo8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: No, not at all. As Bent Knee, we tried to do a music video for our first album. We actually tried to do two. There is one out there called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KCSsuwHpYo8&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Urban Circus&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we did with a friend who was a film student. There’s another one that got canned because it just didn’t come out right. It was such an arduous and difficult process that we didn’t even really get to doing any music videos for &lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt;. I think it was just because we tried to apply the same concept of writing music to writing a music video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;With writing music, the difference is that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we’re able to articulate and sort of make an example of our ideas really well so that it makes sense to each other what we’re trying to envision.&lt;/span&gt; A lot of times, if you say a musical idea, it sounds so stupid. So we have this rule in rehearsal where we always have to try everything. You just have to try it and you can’t just be like, “I hate it.” You have to try building up on it instead of slashing it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;With music videos, I think the problem was when we discussed it together, no one could really articulate their ideas fully without relying on other videos or ideas or imagery.&lt;/span&gt; We just weren’t on the same page about what we wanted to do, but we would do the same thing we do with music where we just hodge-podge it together. “Okay, let’s start with Gavin’s idea here and then we’ll switch over to this idea here, which was Jessica’s. And then we’ll put Courtney’s idea here.” We were trying to create this Frankenstein and it just wasn’t working, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When we were trying to do videos for &lt;em&gt;Say So&lt;/em&gt;, this was in December and January of 2016–my mom is a dancer and she has a non-profit type of dance and arts kind of organization in Fukuoka, Japan. I was going back in Japan in February. We always sort of joked about collaborating. As long as I can remember when I started playing piano, my mom would be like, “Oh, one day we’ll collaborate.” It was just this running joke and then I was like, “No, this is something I really want to do.” I had brought it up to her when we were thinking of doing a video for &lt;em&gt;In God We Trust&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’d just sent her an email a couple years back and she called me back on FaceTime and she was crying because she was so overwhelmed by the emotion of someone seeing her as a dancer and respecting her art. She’s not a lifelong dancer, she started later in her 30s and 40s, more as a health thing. Then she really got into it. She’s older now and she does more admin and organizational stuff than actual physical dancing. So, seeing that, it was kind of like, “Wow, this is really something that means a lot to my mom.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FgUNBRFnYM8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So when I was going back to Japan, I really wanted to do a video with her and I thought &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FgUNBRFnYM8&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Good Girl&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would be great because I wasn’t sure how many resources we’d have when we’re back in Japan. I was trying to think of something that could really just rely on her dancing and not a lot of props. I just wrote the storyboard myself and I sent it to everyone for feedback. My approach was just like, “I’m going to make this. I’m going to make it the best I can and I’m going to hope everyone likes it. I don’t want to do the process we’ve been doing where we hodge podge ideas because I think I have a really good vision for this and I want to try making it a thing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, my mom being in the arts, she has some great connections. We were able to find a really good videographer who also did the editing, and also the lighting and stage tech guy who provided the lighting and the smoke machine, which makes everything better for the shoot. Yeah, we did it in Japan in this sort of empty gallery space that’s in the same building as my mom’s office and also sort of in the backyard of one of my mom’s best friends who has a house in the mountains. About that shoot, if you go look towards the end and you see my mom dancing in nature, she has this wig on backwards and she’s wearing barely nothing and it was February in the mountains with ice melt and she’s dancing in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Myself and the two videographers are wearing these heavy coats and just walking around weeping at how cold our feet are because we’re in this water. Of course the first thing that happens when my mom starts dancing is she falls and slips right into the water. We’re like, “Oh shit!” But she was just in a different plane where she didn’t even feel cold. She was like, “It doesn’t bother me.” It also made me realize I have that thing, too, when I start performing, I have this switch that goes on and I just go to a different place. I realized, “Oh, this is where I get it from.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I could not get my mom to rehearse to save my life. She was just not there, but when we put her in the environment and we said, “Go, do your thing.”&lt;/span&gt; She was just there and it was such an amazing experience to see your parent really being a person and an artist as opposed to being a parent. To get to collaborate on that artist to artist level was a really extremely rewarding experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. One final question: About that switch you just mentioned, the intensity switch, you’re such an intense live performer, when you’re singing, there’s nothing else in the world happening. Have you always been that way or is that something that Bent Knee has brought out of you in terms of singing and performing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah, I think–I don’t know. I guess for me, I haven’t really found a different way to perform. I really am a performer. I think that’s the thing that I do the best and the thing that I really love doing. Bent Knee material is becoming less cathartic. It’s not as brutal. I don’t think anything else will ever be quite as brutal as &lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt;, save for some tragedy that I hope won’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shiny Eyed Babies&lt;/em&gt; we wrote just as we were graduating college. It was a really tumultuous time. We weren’t sure what was going to happen with our lives. We were working really hard on the band, but nothing was really happening yet. So, a lot of emotional stuff and I felt like it just had to be delivered that way. It wasn’t a conscious decision that I made. It’s just something that I’ve always done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool. Well, thank you so much for giving me about an hour of your time. I really appreciate that. I really hope you have a great birthday today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Thank you so much. I really appreciate your really thoughtful questions. I’m sorry I’m such a rambler. I feel like you should have asked more questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I told you: Everyone says that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I know! I know! You’re just such a great listener. That’s the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s the cross I have to bear I guess. All right, thanks so much Courtney.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/courtney-swain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/courtney-swain/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Morgan Ågren Releases</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-releases&quot;&gt;New Releases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2016, we did &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/morgan-agren&quot;&gt;a lengthy interview with Morgan Ågren&lt;/a&gt; and he mentioned a couple new releases to be released later in the year. Well, it’s December 2016 and the releases are–well, released. I thought it’d be cool to hear Morgan himself tell us about the new CDs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/through-the-eyes-of-a-morgchestra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/35th-anniversary-collection-2cd-25-hours&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mats/Morgan 35th Anniversary Collection&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Morgan for chatting with us again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/irRvqSiasPI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/morgan-agren/morgchestra/morgan-agren-morgchestra.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/morgan-agren/morgchestra/morgan-agren-morgchestra.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcription&quot;&gt;Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have with me today, all the way from Sweden, Morgan Ågren. Morgan, thank you so much for joining. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Well, it’s my pleasure. I saw some other people that you have online here, so it’s my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you have two new releases out and I thought it’d be cool to hear in your own words what they are and what they mean to you. So, go ahead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah! Actually, two albums happened just very recently and neither of these albums were really planned as a regular release. One of them is this one [holds up the CD], which is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/through-the-eyes-of-a-morgchestra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it features the music that we performed with the symphony orchestra two months ago. I started to compose for this project a year ago, like in October 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;While doing that, in order to be able to do music for the symphony orchestra, I needed to have sounds to allow me to hear how it could possibly sound later. So, I installed good string plugins and bassoons and all the orchestra. Then slowly I started to try to build up the music and 6 months later, without having even thought about it, I just realized one day when I went through the material, “Hmm, this sounds like an album.” When I realized that, I started to work on the music so it would be good for release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DyfNjA7ApCs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At that moment it was almost good enough for release, but I did some more changes. I replaced some programmed clarinet, bassoon, and stuff with real bassoons, clarinets, violins, upright bass, and some other instruments replaced by real musicians who came to my studio. I wanted to give that extra push to everything. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In one way, it’s the best work I’ve done in my life, I think.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s quite different from what Mats and I do regularly or my own stuff. When I composed for this, I had to think about the fact that it’s an orchestra that will perform it. It’s a bit different because the sound from an orchestra is fantastic. Even when they tune, you have this incredible sound. Then there are some limits rhythmically speaking. You don’t want to do anything too complicated, rhythmically speaking. That’s one thing to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I added my strings in Pro Tools and then I started to fool around with clarinet. Simple sounds, like standard clarinet sounds, and then the music came out. I didn’t really know that I would be able to end up with material because this is not the typical way for me to compose. I think it’s one of the best things I’ve ever done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s great! &lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; is available now through BandCamp and through your website, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should purchase &lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/through-the-eyes-of-a-morgchestra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; via BandCamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, there are hard copies to get through my home page and I have a box ready for Steven at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cuneiformrecords.com&quot;&gt;Cuneiform Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He will sell them and make them available through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waysidemusic.com&quot;&gt;Wayside Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And sometime in late January, it’s going to be out on all the iTunes, Spotify, and stuff. I also gave up the good and bad thoughts about streaming. Finally I just–well, never mind. I’m going to put everything there, finally. I don’t know if that’s good or not. It’s probably good beacuse people are going to be able to hear it and people don’t buy that many CDs, but some still are. This is a separate discussion for, like, a 2 hour discussion on streaming or not. I decided to use it. It’s going to be there in the end of January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent. And then you have a second release, the &lt;em&gt;35th Anniversary Collection&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ljqNLREnXnM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, this is the anniversary collection [holds up the CD]. This was very natural for me to put together because I realized last year that next year is going to be 35 years that me and Mats have played together. Then we wanted to plan some cool things to do because of that fact that we’ve been playing together for 35 years. So, we had only a couple weeks ago, we had two concerts in Stockholm in this old, super-nice theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Usually, we used to play at the local jazz club called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fasching.se&quot;&gt;Fasching &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We played there for 25 years and it’s easy and it works. I would just call them and then we’d play. You know, 330 people maximum, so usually we’d set up and play and it’s super nice. But this time, having an anniversary, we wanted to have a little more like a celebration edge to it. So, I got in contact with this theater and we had two dates there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then I started to try to put together a “best of” collection. That took quite some time, actually, because it was not easy. There is quite a lot to choose from and you have to use this “kill your darlings” thing. There’s stuff you maybe want to have, but it’s only 77 minutes per disc. It’s a double CD, but it was still really hard to pick. After finding which songs to use and after putting them in a nice order, it’s like a new album. Track number 1 fits well with track 2 and there might be 10 years between them as to when we recorded them. Now I think it’s like a new album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I spent time with a really expensive guy doing remastering. He got me a really nice deal and I think that now it’s a 6-page digipak and a 60-page booklet. Super good and remastered. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I would say that this is the only Mats/Morgan album you need.&lt;/span&gt; If you want only one album, this will be pretty much everything you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should also purchase &lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/35th-anniversary-collection-2cd-25-hours&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mats/Morgan 35th Anniversary Collection&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; via BandCamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wLmtuhaCc2c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s really, really cool. When does that come out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: The physical copies are all ready. They’re available on my homepage. I’m going to send Steven at Wayside some copies, too. That one is also going to be available on iTunes and Spotify and stuff in January. I should also take the opportunity to thank Steven at Cuneiform because all the releases have 5-year contracts and a bunch of the tracks that I really wanted to have on this collection–I printed both of these myself, so I needed to ask him permission to use different songs on the album. He was fine with that, so I’m happy because of that. Now it’s really good, I think, and it has some nice pictures inside. I had to go through a lot of hard disks to find photos and stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. How was the Morgchestra show? We talked last time and it was shortly before the shows, so we wanted to wait and talk again. So, how did it go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: I was very happy. It’s a mixed feeling because when I came to the rehearsal hall the first day, I heard the orchestra rehearsing my music even before I got to the stage. I was leaving my bags and stuff behind the stage and while doing that I heard &lt;em&gt;my chords&lt;/em&gt; played &lt;em&gt;by them&lt;/em&gt; and that’s a really unreal feeling. It’s huge and it’s fantastic and all that. At the same time, it’s scary because you want this to be–it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be good. I would prefer it to be perfect, but it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be good enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Somebody decided that we were going to get this request, it costs money, there are lots of people involved and it’s a big thing. Very few people get this kind of request at all, so it’s not something that you take lightly. It has to be good. Even a year before when I started to compose it, I thought, “This &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to be good.” Everything has to be good in order for it to be worth it for the people who asked us and in order for us to feel that we can do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are limits, rhythmically and there’s a rock band with an orchestra, so it can be loud and all these possible problems that can happen. But, I think I would definitely say that the orchestra in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umeå&quot;&gt;Umea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.norrlandsoperan.se/sve&quot;&gt;Norrlandsoperan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a very good orchestra. The conductor told me that he works with tons of orchestras and this is one of the top 3 that he’s worked with. The median age is quite young. So, the typical 60-year-old Mozart-only guy won’t want to do anything other than Mozart wasn’t there. There were maybe a few, I don’t know, but it was a very positive vibe with happy faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The volume wasn’t as big an issue as a month before when we were in Germany. Mats and I went to Germany to do a separate project with the orchestra in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leipzig&quot;&gt;Leipzig &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That was different because then you can feel that as soon as they saw the little Marshall combo and the drums, it was like they put their fingers in their ears. But, this was really good here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IqvWwwUxz5U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But then there is three short rehearsals and there’s always very few hours to rehearse and there’s tons of music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Also one thing that I noticed was that I know this music in my sleep because I spent so much time with it. But, when we started to rehearse, everything sounded different.&lt;/span&gt; My own computer versions I know, but the real thing with all those sounds that were supposed to give me cues to the next part weren’t there any longer. So, suddently I was feeling unsure where we were in certain parts of the songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The timing is different and there is always the conductor “thing.” You have a conductor and there’s always a delay with “one.” [Conducts in the air.] The delay is incredible sometimes. The orchestra is used to that. They just play. For me, I played exactly on the one, but the orchestra played with a delay. There is a balance. You might have some patterns you’re supposed to play with a tuba guy fifty feet away and you can’t hear each other really. All those kinds of things. It was better than I dared to hope for, I think. It was really good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. So, for anyone who is just getting exposed to that, the Morgchestra CD is a recording of you and musicians in your studio and your computer. But, the show was a live representation of that music and more, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, it’s the same exact compositions in form and themes and everything, but performed by a full-sized symphony orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And I imagine you recorded it and, hopefully, will release it at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, that was another thing. When I decided to release the pre-production, I thought, “It doesn’t really matter if we end up having a good recording of the live thing. We can release that later because it’s going to be different with a full orchestra.” So, yeah, I did record it. That also required some telephone calls because this was performed during the jazz festival in Umea and Swedish radio was there to record most of the stuff that happened during the festival. Then there is always this big radio bus outside the festival house that records everything and there’s no way they’d give you a hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know some people, though, you can always try to have a split cable and record your own audio files on your own hard drive. Then there is a different situation. But, yeah, so I have 64 tracks and I have everything on video. At this moment, I don’t dare to listen to it because I want to keep the memory alive. I worked so much the last couple of months I don’t have the energy to even go into it yet. But, I will open it up next year, for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. Man, congratulations Morgan. That’s really fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomtrapp.net&quot;&gt;Tom Trapp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was a super nice conductor who also was the arranger. We did another project this year with this symphony orchestra. It was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Duke&quot;&gt;George Duke &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tribute. So, same symphony orchestra and then a big band, me and some other guys. &lt;a href=&quot;http://byronmillerpsychobass.com/&quot;&gt;Byron Miller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on bass (George Duke’s old bass player), me and Mats and some other guys. Then for this George Duke project, it was also the same conductor and we liked him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;After the first coffee break at the first rehearsal, I said to Mats, “This guy is easy to follow.” He plays guitar also. He goes down to his rehearsal space and puts the Marshall amp on 10 and he plays. Not every conductor does that, you know? He has a little bit of both sides, both worlds. So it was a great decision to involve him on this, I think. He did stuff with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropole_Orkest&quot;&gt;Metropole Orkest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Holland. He did some stuff with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd_Rundgren&quot;&gt;Todd Rundgren &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomtrapp.net/for-others/by-artist-name/&quot;&gt;people like that &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And George Duke, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, that’s cool. Did you capture the 35th Anniversary shows?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Same thing. Yes, I did. So, there were a couple of cameras and 36 channels recorded. Same thing there. I’m going to open that up sometime early next year. It was great, because the 35th anniversary concerts were so nice. In the 1990s we were a quintet, so we had a different bass player, keyboard player, and guitar player than now. We haven’t played together in quite some time, but I called them up and asked them if they wanted to join for this anniversary thing. They did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, the quartet that started about 3 years ago kicked off the show and we played for an hour and a half or something, then the keyboard player and bass player left the stage and then I brought in the three other guys from the quintet. We played some old stuff, like three or four songs and then at the end, all of us played together. Then we had another guest that no one in the US knows, I think, but he’s a famous stand-up comedian, super super weird guy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Wahlbeck&quot;&gt;Peter Wahlbeck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He did a couple of projects that Music Für Alle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AR-qgWgrB_M?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What does that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: “Music for everyone” in German, I think. He did some cool things, super underground. We performed two songs with him at the end. All seven of us plus him and again, this really nice theater. People came from a long way. I had people from France and Germany that came to see us. My first teacher from school, who is now 92 years old, she was in the audience. She came there in a wheelchair. Parents from people in the band, my parents. It was a really, really nice thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. Cool! Well, thank you so much for your time and for the update. I really appreciate it. I think there’s some really cool information here. I’ll make sure to get the links and stuff and your promo stuff out on Make Weird Music. Cool, thank you Morgan!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/morgan-agren/morgchestra</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/morgan-agren/morgchestra</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>X-JAMM at NAMM 2017</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 05:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/link/x-jamm-2017/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/link/x-jamm-2017/</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Moulettes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Moulettes are a progressive folk/alt pop band from Brighton, England. They write great music and are even better live than they are on record. I saw them perform twice in Montreal when I &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/kerry-minnear&quot;&gt;attended GORGG 2015&lt;/a&gt;. One member of the band, Dr. Ruth Skipper, played the electric bassoon (a technique she learned from &lt;a href=&quot;/interiew/paul-hanson&quot;&gt;Paul Hanson&lt;/a&gt;) and autoharp. Their performance was so powerful, I couldn’t believe what I was hearing and seeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took several months to coordinate, but our schedules finally aligned and we got an interview set up. I hope you enjoy these authentic musicians and their attitude of wonder toward the world and music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moulettes.co.uk&quot;&gt;Check out Moulette’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our interview with Ollie Austin and Hannah Miller of Moulettes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tx0rhXKXiOg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://alanmillerguitars.co.uk&quot;&gt;Alan Miller guitars &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Alan is Hannah’s father and makes incredible instruments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/moulettes.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/moulettes.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Rod Knowlan, guitarist for the Vancouver, Canada-based indie rock band, &lt;a href=&quot;http://headmusic.ca&quot;&gt;HEAD &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Rod is also a fan of all manner of music, weird and otherwise. I met Rod at GORGG 2015 in Montreal, where I also met the Moulettes! What a day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hi, this is Anthony with makeweirdmusic.com and I have special guests here from England, the band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moulettes&quot;&gt;Moulettes&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve got Ollie Austin and Hannah Miller. Ollie and Hannah, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Thanks for having us Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No problem. So, I’ll let you guys get this started, can you tell us about Moulettes and can you tell us about the history of the band a little and about what makes you unique?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Where do we start? I suppose Moulettes has been the project that Hannah and myself have been doing since we were at college together. It’s a bit more of a band, we’ve grown up with it as well so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s a cult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It’s a cult, yeah, [laughs]. Many people have come and gone over the years, it’s been quite a ride, really, since we were sixteen or seventeen. We’re four albums down and we’re about to start making our fifth album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What makes us unique? Wow, what a question! It’s great that you would say that about us. I think that we are unique, I think that’s what we strive for so hopefully it’s our own type of uniqueness and eclecticism that people like about the band. Just by you saying that, that’s a nice achievement in itself, really. I suppose it’s what we aim to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We don’t aim to regurgitate old things, we certainly aim for the opposite, I would say&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: There’s plenty of bands out there, plenty of artists working out there that, like you said, would deliberately regurgitate stuff…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Or working within already quite familiar parameters, I guess regurgitating has a bit of a vomity vibe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bZTibl44hNg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s a lot of vomit out there…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: There is quite a lot of vomit out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the parameters that you put into play that are unique? I’m thinking around Ruth Skipper and her electric bassoon, the kind of instrumentation that you have, the vocal harmonies… What are some of the things you guys use to make your music sound like it’s not a regurgitation of something else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Well, I suppose one really fortunate thing for me is that my dad, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alanmillerguitars.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Alan Miller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is a luthier. He’s always been really great in that he’s made me these custom instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Look at this beautiful guitar…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, wow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: This is probably the most normal, I could get some other ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: He gets pretty far out, he’s great to experiment and discuss other possibilities of instruments and he’s made some pretty strange things for us in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I subscribed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/alanpmiller&quot;&gt;him on Youtube &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; after I met you in Montreal and I had asked Hannah about her cello. It’s so beautiful, he’s got so many great instruments, and demos on his Youtube channel, it’s been cool to see his process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2JNIXJsnh9o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: He just finished a twin-neck mandolin. In fact, he’s coming to stay next week and he said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“I want to make something new, I’m bored with making things that have already existed.”&lt;/span&gt; Maybe that’s where some of this impetus comes from. He’s always been around being really keen to help build things that haven’t been built before. I’ve got a six-string cello over there which sounds amazing. The bottom string is a low E, which is quite a long way below my normal bottom string, it’s just great, it sounds like a panther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA:  You can always get interesting sounds playing with acoustic instruments and making them do things that they’re perhaps not made to do. You can discover some quite interesting things about acoustic instruments. You mentioned Ruth’s bassoon, and Hannah’s five-string cello, we’ve kind of always been trying to experiment with both acoustic setups, whether it be strings or brass or woodwind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We like to do big rock shows and there a production no-man’s land and in terms of being able to make some acoustic instruments work on a big stage&lt;/span&gt; was to put them through amps. You get feedback problems, you can’t quite crank the pickup up enough so part of the fun of what we’ve tried to do is to look into new ways to, like with Hannah’s electric cello, for example, it’s an acoustic and an electric instrument and you can really crank it up and it’s not affected by the drums. We have a lot of fun with that, experimenting with new instruments. Riding the balance between acoustic and electric is something we’ve done a lot in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For people who don’t know about your band, if this is their first time hearing about you, can you tell us how many people are in the band and what everyone plays and what a live performance is like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re not really sure of how many people are in the band.&lt;/span&gt; [laughs] It always changes! For &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; we made a point of making a record that sounded like the band that was going to tour it. There’s many different approaches to doing albums and we set different parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZBDfcRm2u6U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;em&gt;Constellations&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: &lt;em&gt;Constellations&lt;/em&gt;, the one before &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;, I think has about 30 players on it. It’s got a lot of our favorite players. One of the purposes of the concept of the album was to tell the story of Moulettes up to that point. We kind of got players from all around, from bands that we liked, session players, both players that have been on the scene for years and current players. That was kind of like a big chamber orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; was very much more “let’s get a band in the room rocking out” kind of vibe. That has 5 people on it, electric cello, drums, electric guitar, bass and we all play synths and then the bassoon through distortion. It’s very much a “band in the room.” That was the concept behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, that was the instruments concept. Both of those records are conceptual in their nature as records. The most recent one, &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;, was centered around the natural world and taking each song as a particular creature. We used that as a starting point for inspiration behind the song. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In terms of uniqueness, I haven’t found any songs that are about this specific nematode worm, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halicephalobus_mephisto&quot;&gt;halicephalobus mephisto nematode worm &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; That could be a first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Could be!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; is your latest album. It seems to be getting some pretty good press and it’s very well received. Have you been touring? What’s been the activity around the album?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: We did our first big coast-to-coast tour of Canada, we’d been there the season before but in this case we started at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stan_Rogers_Folk_Festival&quot;&gt;Fanfest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–would you technically say that it’s in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Breton_Island&quot;&gt;Cape Breton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: I don’t know, I don’t think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Then we did &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montreal_International_Jazz_Festival&quot;&gt;Montreal Jazz Festival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was incredible. Then we went all the way across to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver&quot;&gt;Vancouver &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver_Island&quot;&gt;Vancouver Island &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We’re still touring it now, we’ve got a European leg coming up. Because we did the tour of Canada last year and around the release and we’re doing a series of UK festivals and the European ones this time out. It was nice, as well, for the &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; campaign, the welcoming in of it, we sold out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_Chapel,_Islington&quot;&gt;Union Chapel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in London, which was a big deal for us. It’s one of those amazing venues that you always want to play at. I’ve been to several gigs there as a kid, seeing bands, so to actually sell it out it was… it’s this amazing, Gothic-style building, it’s really eerie and dark…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s a beautiful church, massive stained-glass window…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: So it’s good to start off on that positive and it’s been really interesting to see who pops up their head in all the different compartments of the music industry. You often have proggers, indie rock people, folkies. It’s interesting who pops up and says “I really dig this, I really like this.” It seems to happen every time with different people with every album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Quite inter-generational as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8vYHuxYxUGE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When I saw you open for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Friends_(band)&quot;&gt;Three Friends &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Montreal I was just blown away! I had no idea there would be an opening act for the show so it was my first exposure to you and I felt like you guys blew the doors off of that show. It sounded incredible, the performances were incredible and I will never forget hearing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bZTibl44hNg&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Behemooth&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, it’s such a powerful song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;em&gt;Behemooth&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us a little bit about the new album and some of the dynamics going on and some of the concept? I have never heard a song about a massive sound heard in the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: There was a lot of speculation about that particular sound, which is known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloop&quot;&gt;“The Bloop” &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. During the initial stages of writing it, you know when you go down a little Internet rabbit-hole and you kind of get excited about something and it soon becomes more and more obvious that it’s very unclear what the facts are. That’s how this started, there was a lot of speculation about noise because of the people who were talking about it. If you listen to the noise–have you done that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Of course! I showed my kids! I told them all about your album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: The noise itself is very eerie and it does sound like a big, massive mammal. But there are people who say it was an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cryoseism&quot;&gt;ice-quake &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or the sound of a distant ice-quake. But I haven’t had any confirmation on either side as to what it is. The whole point is, we changed the meaning of that song so it isn’t just about that noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Made it about scientific enquiry…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, about the speculation itself…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OA: And the dialogue around it. It’s still a very relevant subject, about how people talk about science and what they think is true and what is not. One of the strands of all of Moulettes albums, including Preternatural, is there’s always a celebration of science or a discussion of science. There’s also an underpinning of some environmental stuff that we are very interested in.{: .interviewee }&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We’re from Brighton, one of the only places that has a Green (Party) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_parliament&quot;&gt;MP &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it’s the only Green MP in the UK. We are engaged on a kind of political level but it’s not kind of in your face, it’s trying to start a discussion, really, about certain issues like animals… it’s great fun, kids love it as well. Like Hannah was saying… it’s great inter-generational stuff. It’s great what some people come up with when you have animals involved. There are some massive animal lovers out there, serious animal lovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Everyone can agree on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Attenborough&quot;&gt;David Attenborough &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as well, that’s a really nice thing. He sent me a letter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Maybe we should show it, it’s one of our proudest moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: This young woman, I don’t know how old she was, maybe 15, who is also a cellist, came up to me after a gig and she was so excited about this nematode worm, and she correctly categorized it as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extremophile&quot;&gt;extremophile &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s one of these creatures that lives in circumstances that we previously thought were impossible (to harbor life). Anyway, we sent David Attenborough the CD and the vinyl (of &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/77WGYFIiryA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: What was amazing about it was that he was celebrating his 90th birthday that week and he apologized in the letter for being slow to reply. It only took him a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And hand-written! That’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, what is your tie to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentle_Giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? You opened up for Three Friends, you hung out with the whole GORGG crew, the Gentle Giant celebration. What is your tie there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: A love of great music, I think. Talking about your [Hannah’s] dad again, he was a Gentle Giant fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: IS a Gentle Giant fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, it was great meeting the GORGG. The obvious connection is Jim (Mortimore), who plays the bass in Moulettes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Jim joined us just at the end of the second album campaign and he’s just been brilliant, he’s a brilliant musician. He’s the son of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm_Mortimore&quot;&gt;Malcolm Mortimore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who was one of the drummers from Gentle Giant and is the drummer on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Friends&quot;&gt;Three Friends &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He’s an incredible drummer. Malcolm has managed to play with incredible players. We’ve met some of the best people in the business by hanging out with Malcolm. We managed to meet &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Flowers&quot;&gt;Herbie Flowers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Herbie Flowers even played on our last record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, wow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: He’s one of the thirty people that we managed to get to come and play. Herbie Flowers is one inspiration, how many good records has he been on? How many good records did Gentle Giant make? It all started with records, I guess… and discovery. We’ve always been into prog music–not that Gentle Giant is just prog music, it’s its own entity…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: And world… The amazing thing about having Herbie play on the last record was that you really recognized that bass, he’s always played the same electric and the same upright bass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It’s the same sound that you hear on the records…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: That sounds like stating the obvious, really, but it was so familiar as well, from things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walk_on_the_Wild_Side_(Lou_Reed_song)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Walk on the Wild Side&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I think he played both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XBXUP5GqYJs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Acoustic and electric when he did the harmony, yeah. As soon as he picked up and played the double bass on &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/moulettes/07-land-of-the-midnight-sun-feat-herbie-flowers&quot;&gt;Land of the Midnight Sun &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and we were listening to it I thought “that’s signature Herbie.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Like some of your favorite records… yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: A great musician. And he’s hilarious, really good company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So for people who have never heard Moulettes, where would you recommend they start and where are you guys going next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Where would they start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: I suppose start with the recent thing then go back. Each album is completely different so if you’re prepared for that and the different instrumentation and all sorts of stuff–it’s all different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: We’re going to say that because you’re always into the last thing you’ve done, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: What’s great is that the recent album, &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;, is more reflective of what the band actually sounds like live. All the other albums we’ve done, we’ve had a flux of players in and out during the session and then see who’s around for the campaign. I would say that to see the show, &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; is a rock show and I think we’re probably going to stay in that realm–probably, we don’t know, really. We like to mix it up but I’m enjoying playing the bigger shows, the bigger festivals and putting out a bigger sound. Crank it up, use some amps… that’s probably where we’re going to explore, I’d say. Who knows, it’s all up for grabs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Well, there’s more to it than that, as well. There’s quite a lot of different moods on the record so there’s something you could find that you enjoyed on it. Each song was built around what we thought the creature would want or what the themes of the song kind of evoked. There was quite a comprehensive thought process between how they all sound. So, obviously, &lt;em&gt;Behemooth&lt;/em&gt;, being this big gentle giant of the ocean wanted quite a grandiose prog anthem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xeYeNdUo3uA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Naturally. So we were kind of guided by that kind of idea, that kind of a theme song for the beast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: You can always depend on a concept album as well from us. We love to get stuck into a concept album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Love of parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Next record, we haven’t decided on the concept, I don’t know, do you have any ideas for a concept, a good concept?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, if you guys are into science there’s that show &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fringe_(TV_series)&quot;&gt;Fringe &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s all sorts of odd topics or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_X-Files&quot;&gt;X-Files &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you could look at extraterrestrial type things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Whoa… [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Or some of the ideas behind quantum physics, like given an infinite amount of time you have an infinite probability that certain odd things could happen… and odd things happen all the time. Media is everywhere now so strange things are reported all the time. There’s that show &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stranger_Things_(TV_series)&quot;&gt;Stranger Things &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on Netflix that’s kind of taking off. There’s a societal or cultural fascination with inexplicable things. I think that’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Do you think we’re alone out here or do you think there are extraterrestrial beings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Definitely…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think the universe is so big, it’s like that line in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contact_(1997_American_film)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Contact&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that says it’d be an awful waste of space…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: If there was only us…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! There’s so much space out there, there are so many planets that have to be supportive of life. I would bank on the likelihood, looking at the universe from a distance (not that I can do that), looking at something that big and I just can’t believe that we’re the only things out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OA: There’s an interesting theory–I mean there’s a lot of theories about the universe, as you know–but one of the ones that I really find fascinating is in, I would say maybe the evangelical Christian world, when I was talking about the size and scope of the universe, there’s a whole group of Christian believers thinking that, essentially, the universe was made to live eternally in it so it’s that big because we have to live in it for eternity, or, at least, it was initially designed to be like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hm…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Which is just nuts–I love all the different points of view of those things–but even if you live forever, you might get bored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: The universe is definitely finite, we’ve worked that one out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: I was reading recently about this topic and what the inference was that we were so low down the scale of intelligence that there are a bunch of other higher intelligent forms of life but they’re not bothering with us because they’re just watching the car crash thinking, “Oh, no.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There are lots of interesting theories, like the one that you don’t want to encounter extraterrestrial life because if you do, they’re likely so far advanced…. I forget, there are something like two or three different perspectives from a couple of scientists that either the other races have already existed and have wiped themselves out or have been wiped out somehow or that they exist somewhere else… I don’t know. There are a bunch of interesting theories that could make for a good concept. Or you could just prime the punch and make an album about that. [NOTE: I was thinking about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi_paradox&quot;&gt;Fermi Paradox &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/553MXNe0wfc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Sounds good, taking a book is a good idea, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sum:_Forty_Tales_from_the_Afterlives&quot;&gt;Tales of the Afterlives &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Brian Eno did a series on that. That’s a good angle as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurie_Anderson&quot;&gt;Laurie Anderson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; did one on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moby-Dick&quot;&gt;Moby Dick &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I actually did one with my dad on Moby Dick and one on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilgamesh&quot;&gt;Epic of Gilgamesh&lt;/a&gt;. We made albums about those stories, it was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah! Good ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: You know that octopuses have the most complex sequence of DNA that we know of, including being more complex that ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! They just discovered that those little water bears…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tardigrade&quot;&gt;Tardigrades &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! They just did a DNA sequence on those and the least DNA in common with any other animal on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: And they can actually survive in space for like…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Three years…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Three years. Those guys are hard-core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Maybe we should just do a post hard-core album or even just a straight-up hard-core album about the tardigrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, with the 5-sting cello distorted..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, man. You got it… [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: 6-string!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, there’s a new 6-string lying around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Alright, well I think we’ve digressed quite a bit. Thank you so much for your time. I really appreciate you guys doing what you do, I think you guys are awesome, I love your music. I hope I see continued growth and success in what you’re doing. Keep it up and if there’s anything I can do to help promote more here in the US I’d be happy to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Whilst we’ve got you on the line, the world is watching, what are your thoughts on the debates and the presidential run?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: In a nutshell. Maybe we could do a whole concept about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Oh, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs] There’s a great concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s tainted with… ehh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z7xuCQGX9iU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think Hannah and I have similar sentiments. [laughs] I just watch it in kind of disgust and I think this is a problem that we’ve created over many decades. This isn’t new, this is the result of behaviors over a long period of time that have allowed these kinds of people to come into power. People say the world is worse now than it ever was. I think that’s a logical fallacy that every generation says that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But I would say people don’t think about the consequences of their behavior or decisions and that can lead to, in a macro-economic-cultural-social sense it can lead to some problematic outcomes where, if we do short-term gain we can end up with long-term pain. Wow, that’s really cheesy, I just made that up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: That’s a lyric, write that down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: (singing) Long term gain…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We feel sorry for a lot of our friends in the US at the moment because they’re going nuts. And, of course, a lot of the world is, you know. It’s been interesting.
I guess one thing to plug, we are coming back to Canada…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We’re doing a theater headline tour in October 2017 and we’re going to try and fit in some US dates but as you know, it’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s a lesson. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It’s complicated with visas and whatnot. Most of the good ones are going to move up to Canada anyway, so maybe you are… no, just joking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Actually, we are going to spend two and a half months in Germany next year, get our toes in the water to see what it’s like living somewhere else. Maybe I’ll catch you on the road there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, in February we’re there. Are you going to be there in February?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It will be May through July. We’re going to try travelling on weekends, I’m hoping I can make it up to London, maybe we can catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, come to Brighton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Which bit of Germany?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Munich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Oh, nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Good beer there! That’s in Bavaria, in the heart of Bavaria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Kaeder(?? Couldn’t understand what she said) Which is just this outrageous cheesy noodle thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: My wife speaks German, she taught German at the local university so I’m hoping that she can help us navigate and we can order good foods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, good beer there…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Good beer and good schnitzel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Germany has a lot of great things about it. Have a great time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I will!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U0Q8k1nhDrU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It would be good to see you in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: We love Canada. We really love coming to Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We’d just love to get out to the US as well, once you kind of get out there. It’s huge, as you know. It’s terrifyingly huge for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Montreal especially, it’s just great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Is it getting cold there yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I live in Phoenix, AZ. It’s probably about 30-35 degrees Celsius today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Fair enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, it doesn’t get cold that much here in Arizona. Thank you so much for your time, I have to get ready for work, I really appreciate talking to you guys. It will be a few weeks before I get this thing online but I look forward to getting it posted and spreading the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Thanks for your help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Thank you, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You Must Be This Tall</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;house-concert&quot;&gt;House Concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing this, I’m still reeling from the high of the house concert we hosted last night with the incredible &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt; and the also-incredible &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt;. It was an incredible amount of work and I’m totally, totally exhausted, but I was so excited I had to make a new video after Mike did this play-through of one of my favorite of his songs: &lt;a href=&quot;http://store.keneally.com/products/mike-keneally-you-must-be-this-tall&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You Must Be This Tall&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is! Mike is playing his one-of-a-kind Black Devil semi-hollow SG copy. It’s absolutely gorgeous (I even got to play it last night). There are LEDs in the fret markers above the fretboard that change color based on the pickup configuration. Cool! See if you can spot ‘em.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ld3rgnNdfoY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcription&quot;&gt;Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Yvan Cluet, a young guitarist in France studying engineering in Lyon. He’s really interested in beautiful and weird music. He writes some of his own music and looks to MWM to expand his knowledge. Super cool! Thanks, Yvan!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/61509/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special thanks to Jack Rosenkrantz for helping me so much this weekend.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/you-must-be-this-tall</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/you-must-be-this-tall</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Julie Slick</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Julie Slick is scary talented. Like, every video I’ve seen of her kinda frightens me. She has so much energy, capability, and fun playing music, it’s intimidating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.julieslick.com&quot;&gt;Check out Julie Slick’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our interview with Julie Slick:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6tMVejtevKY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/julie-slick.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/julie-slick.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Casey Williams, mega-fan of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/the-residents&quot;&gt;The Residents&lt;/a&gt;, for transcribing this interview. Saved me a lot of time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony Garone: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and today we’re here with Julie Slick from Philedelphia. Julie, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Julie Slick: Thank you so much for having me! It’s great to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For anyone that might not know who you are, could you provide a brief introduction and talk about some of the projects with which you’ve been associated in recent years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Well, okay. So, I’m Julie Slick from Philadelphia, I’m a bass player. I’m probably most known for my work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew_Power_Trio&quot;&gt;Power Trio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been doing that for the last ten years, very fortunately. I’ve gotten to travel the world with him, and also through that have worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ProjeKcts&quot;&gt;The Crimson Projeckt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which also featured &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Mastelotto&quot;&gt;Pat Mastelotto &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/markus-reuter&quot;&gt;Markus Reuter&lt;/a&gt;, who I know has been on your program and of course Adrian and &lt;a href=&quot;http://tobiasralph.com/&quot;&gt;Tobias Ralph &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and that’s been for the last couple of years until the king decided to start touring again. And then, of course, I have my own project, my solo albums and also my recent creation, my band &lt;a href=&quot;https://echotest.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;EchoTest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I’ve been doing for the last two years with an Italian bass player, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marcomachera.com/&quot;&gt;Marco Machera &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EMXyuWkrWAU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. Can you tell us about EchoTest and some of the lesser known projects that you have-Philadelphia based?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Sure. This isn’t really Philadelphia-based, but this is actually an interesting international project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: So, Marco lives in Italy. We met at this music camp that Adrian, Pat and Tony put on every year near Woodstock, New York. They do these music camps all summer long at this resort, in Big Indian-Full Moon Resort, and it’s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://threeofaperfectpair.com/&quot;&gt;Three of a Perfect Pair Camp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. They’ve been doing it for five years now, since 2011. There’ve been a couple of off years when we’ve had some other conflicts but Marco and I met there in 2011 and so I knew he wasn’t a total weirdo, but just weird enough in the good way, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And when I was on tour with the Crimson Projeckt in 2014, I’d also, earlier that year, given up my apartment in Los Angeles. I had moved from Philly to LA for a year to try and pursue some other musical things, as we do as artists and so I got rid of the place because I was touring so much with Crimson Projeckt that. What a great opportunity! We’re gonna be in Europe, let’s do some shows. And so I made a status on Facebook and said: “If anybody wants to play some music with me while I’m in Europe, I’d love to hang out after the tour and maybe we can make some things happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/E3iW1RuFtiA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And of course, two bass players wrote to me right after that, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Lawson_(musician)&quot;&gt;Steve Lawson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in England and Marco Machera in Italy. So, I thought that was funny that two bass players contacted me to perform–not typical. You’d think a drummer, or a band or something or even just offer solo, clinic or something like that. But no, it’d be two bass players wanted to as a duo, specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I went to England and I played some lovely improvised music with Steve and did some recordings with him, and then I went to Italy. I really didn’t know Marco that well at all. I just met him at the camp, and that was pretty much it. We had a Myspace conversation in 2007 when I first joined Adrian’s band. That was pretty much it. But, you know, an excuse to go to Italy; why wouldn’t I take that opportunity? I just went on a whim and Marco booked the two dates and I wasn’t really expecting to keep the project going after that week that we booked, but we started writing songs somehow, right off the bat as soon as we plugged in our pedals. It was like this instant magic, and so we kept with the momentum and we finished a record 8 weeks later. We’ve just been going with that momentum ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wOXMxVpwhfw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And for people who have not heard the music, how would you characterize it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: I asked Marco this the other day because we were asked to describe our music in three words and he said “futuristic, artistic and bold.” and I kind of agree with that. It’s very cinematic and it’s unexpected. You think “oh, it’s a bass duo,” you’re gonna have a certain idea of what it’s gonna sound like but I really think it defies what you’d expect because we use a lot of effects and it’s a lot about the tone and the structure of the sound so it’s like taking the idea of these Fripp-ian soundscapes and this Eno quality but then this heavy groove coming from the fact that we’re both bass players. So, I think it marries those two in a very unique way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve heard some of your music, and I love how there’s layered electronic beats and delays and reverbs and it sounds like you’re playing guitar on the bass- I wasn’t quite sure, you might have had a six-string bass that looked like a guitar, or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: When Marco and I first started playing, it was very evident to me that I would be playing more on my six-string bass because he plays a five-string. So he’s got that low B, to get technical, and on my six-string, a lot of people think it’s a guitar because it’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fender_Bass_VI&quot;&gt;Bass VI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so I’ve got two high strings on that beast of a beautiful instrument. I have a high B and a high E, so I have these extra high notes notes, Macro has that extra low note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We have our separation in tonality there, in spectrum, but then we also have the slew of pedals and the longer Marco and I have been working together, the more and more I’ve been influencing him and getting him some pedals that are very similar to mine. We both have these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventideaudio.com/products/stompboxes/multi-effect-processor/h9&quot;&gt;Eventide H9 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; pedals and I love the way they interlock together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Basically, because when we would start recording, that’s another part I was going to get into–when we record, sometimes we are together and sometimes I plug him through my pedal board, so it became a necessity for him to have some of the same pieces that I have so that we could work these ideas together with some of these harmonizing things that we have going on. And then, also, I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_synthesizer&quot;&gt;MIDI pickup &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on my bass so I can make it sound like I put it through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.roland.com/us/products/vb-99/&quot;&gt;Roland VB-99 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that I can access another array of tones, I can make it sound like a Strat or a Les Paul or an organ or different synthesizers, and then of course once I take the output of that and put it through my pedal board so I can make it sound totally crazy, put it through these harmonized pedals, through these different reverbs, through my loopers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1voFbocwKnU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s another reason why I’m saying you listen to the music and you don’t necessarily think “this is just coming from two basses, that’s really something” because so far, the two albums that we have out are pretty much strictly bass and a little bit of programming, except for the one song, “The Drift”, had some guitar on it because it was a song that I wrote before Marco and I started working together. Also, there’s some violin tracks on some of the stuff and viola tracks, but other than that, everything you hear is bass and the programmed drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s another thing that I was gonna get into–sorry to answer your question in such a long-winded way–but growing up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew_Power_Trio#Eric_Slick&quot;&gt;my brother &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who was the original drummer of the Power Trio with Adrian, I’m used to having… The drumset would be right here, behind me, and I would be standing over there, where the TV is, and we’d be jamming King Crimson songs in our living room and recording them. So, I’m used to, like, “Eric, play a B,” when I have an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Whenever I come up with a new idea, I use the computer and the technology in such a way, like it’s my digital brother.&lt;/span&gt; I can’t call up Eric and be like “Hey, can you play this?” We’re getting close to that point but as far as it stands now, it’s easier for me to just open up &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logic_Pro&quot;&gt;Logic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, make a quick program with Ultrabeat or something, and then I record my idea, and then I usually end up making four more drum tracks because I like weird polyrhythm stuff and playing against that and that helps me because playing to a click is obviously very boring and not easy to do when you’re trying to get a vibe going, especially as a bass player.  So that was my long-winded answer for that; that’s why our music sounds the way it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. Don’t worry about being long-winded, that’s what people want, it’s what they like about these interviews. Did you record anything with Steve Lawson?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Yes, we did! Steve always records everything, so I think we put that up pretty quickly after it happened, too. We’re due, though, for some more because I think we really haven’t done anything since then, so we should. But we have put up, I think it was called &lt;a href=&quot;http://music.stevelawson.net/album/marinate&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marinate&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it was a free download for those that bought–I think we were offering it when we released our first Echotest record, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/fourth-dementia&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourth Dementia&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was from before we were called Echotest, it was still Julie Slick and Marco Machera at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4gj4wtmMppg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then Steve had released… I’m bad, I’m forgetting… He releases so much music, can’t remember what specific release it was, but if you bought both of those, we offered &lt;em&gt;Marinate&lt;/em&gt; as a free, four song EP. That wasn’t recorded at the gig, though. I wonder if he has the gig. Good question. I think he put one of the Soundclouds up, like one of the songs up on Soundcloud.  I think that may have been also the gig that we did with &lt;a href=&quot;http://drummerandyedwards.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Andy Edwards &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on drums. So it’s a trio, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Very cool. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;I just spoke with Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; the other night and he talked all about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/tinyorchestralmoments/&quot;&gt;Tiny Orchestral Moments &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and we have some sample audio that we’ll be posting in a week or two or something like that. So, how did you get involved with that whole guitar circle, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Ok, well, the King Crimson world, that was getting involved with Adrian, that’s a whole other thing. That was from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/School_of_Rock_(company)&quot;&gt;Paul Green School of Rock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was a student of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Green_(musician)&quot;&gt;Paul Green &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s, starting back in 1988, basically the year that he founded the school. I saw it grow from this guy’s apartment to an actual, brick-and-mortar school, to another school, another school, a movie, Adrian’s coming to do tours, all of a sudden I’m in Adrian’s band. That’s pretty much how it happened, it’s pretty insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JVQPiVZpxu0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I discovered him, and then was buying microphones because he was endorsing them, and playing bass, wanting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_Man_StingRay&quot;&gt;Stingray &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because of Tony Levin, and my brother was buying a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonor&quot;&gt;Sonor &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because he wanted what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny_Carey&quot;&gt;Danny Carey &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s drums were like, and then we ended up working with Danny down the line and it’s just mind boggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But the Seattle thing; that was just another Facebook connection. You have to give it to Facebook, I mean, I actually made a status that was a little negative and I normally try to avoid doing those sorts of things but I was expressing my frustration with self-management and having to wear so many hats and how exhausting it can be, and Steve took note of that. I was actually gonna delete the post and it’s a good thing I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He saw it, and he saw an opportunity because he was planning this Tiny Orchestral Moments session and gig, I guess for a year. And I didn’t know about it at all and it was the weekend before, I made this update on Facebook and he contacted me, weekend before with an emergency, that his bass player, Amy was going to have to fly out for a gig in Turkey. So he did a replacement quickly, and saw my post and just figured why the heck not reach out and see if I’m available?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7fqrSHYRDAY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I wasn’t, really, because I was really stressed, working on the–I play with this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talking_Heads&quot;&gt;Talking Heads &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tribute band, &lt;a href=&quot;http://startmakingsenseband.com/&quot;&gt;Start Making Sense &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and we did this recreation of the film, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Making_Sense&quot;&gt;Stop Making Sense &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to a T and I had to do all of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tina_Weymouth&quot;&gt;Tina &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s mannerisms and dance moves and I had to sing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genius_of_Love&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genius of Love&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which was insane. So I really saw this as a great opportunity to go to see XXX(insert name here, couldn’t figure it out, around the 15:00 mark) and procrastinate and connect with amazing musicians so I wouldn’t have to practice the crab dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I’ve seen the Instagram posts. I can’t believe how intentionally accurate and to every detail you guys got it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Oh, it was so nerdy. It was completely so specific, making the cut–I straightened my hair. You know that means it’s serious. If someone put a hot iron on my head… Not messing around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I hear you. My wife does it everyday, I can’t believe she’s not scorched all across her head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: I was so scared, putting the blue in my hair and I keep seeing it creeping in more and more and more blue, which I think is cool, but as long as the stylists keep letting me do that, that’s fine. But you know, things like that, like I’m already burning my head. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is the kind of breaking news I know you want to talk about on Make Weird Music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely, yeah. Tell me more about your hair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Yeah, exactly. Like, what’s the actual combination of colors? Like, hue 64, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sT-mqkCrIiM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You know, people get really into the details of instruments. I don’t know why we can’t get it to hair colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: I know. I mean, honestly, I have no idea. That’s why I pay somebody else to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, for someone who would like to get into your music, where do you suggest they start, in terms of hearing Julie Slick, an innovator on the bass, someone who thinks outside the box?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS:  Well, definitely my Bandcamp is the best place right now because &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;I now even have a subscription service available &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So like, for 15 bucks a year, you get all of my music, which is a lot of albums, I think there’s 10 up there right now so that alone is worth it, so you get all of that, plus I update with behind-the-scenes videos and working on new demos in the studio, on tour kind of stuff. And I hope to be putting up more of those sorts of videos up soon; I hope to be on the road more soon, both with Echotest and with Adrian in the coming months. And that’s really the best place, would be the Bandcamp. And there’s of course, you can stream stuff and check it out as well. There’s a few things on Spotify, but I don’t really recommend that people go there, of course, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But maybe an album or two or a few songs to note?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Sure. The latest Echotest record, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/le-fil-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Le Fil Rouge&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I would check out a song called &lt;em&gt;The Drift&lt;/em&gt; on that. It’s one that actually does have guitar. And also the last track, &lt;em&gt;Pleasant Torture&lt;/em&gt;, is quite nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vAtT4F5I0so&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then, there’s the other album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/terroir&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terroir&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which looks like this, my second solo record, which came out a couple of years ago now and that one features a bunch of awesome guests like Adrian and Steve Ball actually, and Pat. A lot of people. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Torn&quot;&gt;David Torn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; plays amazing guitar on that as well, so… That’s something a little bit different, a little bit older but I think it’s cool to check out the sort of evolution of the way things are going with my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent! That’s great. Thank you very much and I look forward to seeing you on tour. Hope you’ll come through Phoenix at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Oh yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I missed the last Crimson Projeckt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Oh, that was with Danny too, when we were playing in Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I know. :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Aw man!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I punched myself for it. But, awesome. Thank you so much for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Thank you so much. And hopefully you’ll get to work on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
