<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 10:12:32 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 10:12:32 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cupcake by Robbie Seahag Mangano</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robbie Seahag Mangano and I got together in early March to film a bunch of stuff. We laughed for hours making a video that has yet to see the light of day. This performance of “Cupcake” was filmed at the end of a long, fun day of recording together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bumbleweenie.com&quot;&gt;You should buy Robbie’s new album, &lt;em&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should also check out these videos we’ve made together: &lt;a href=&quot;/share/weasel-shake&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weasel Shake&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/33-in-buffalo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;33 in Buffalo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;music-video&quot;&gt;Music Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vMaI93cYsh0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/cupcake</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/cupcake</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>David Singleton</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Marco Machera is an Italian musician/songwriter. He likes to say,  “I don’t play music – I make it happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s played bass for Marillion, Paul Gilbert, Tony Levin, Markus Reuter, and many others. He’s rather prolific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His new album is due out September 1, 2017. It’s called &lt;em&gt;Small Music from Broken Windows&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;{ data.artists.marco-machera.website }&quot;&gt;Check his website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UftXn22rQ08?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/marco-machera/marco-machera.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/marco-machera/marco-machera.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Marco Machera is a bassist in Italy. He’s known best for his work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/slickmachera/&quot;&gt;EchoTest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/julie-slick&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt;. We are very lucky to have him here today to talk about his new album. Marco, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Thank you for your interest. It’s a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, you’ve got a new album and I thought it’d be cool if we talked about it here. Why don’t you tell us about it, what it’s called, and some of the story behind it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: The title is very long. It’s maybe not good for promotion, but it’s called &lt;em&gt;Small Music from Broken Windows&lt;/em&gt;. It’s my first solo record since 2014. Since then, I started the EchoTest project with Julie and I’ve been very busy with that. It’s obviously a priority for us, but I’ve always been working on my own stuff, which is usually quite different from what I do with Julie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_2UZ34eNgEo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s more singer-songwriter-oriented music. I thought it was a good time now to put it out because we just published the new record with EchoTest called &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/from-two-balconies&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;From Two Balconies&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I have it right here. [Points to EchoTest CD.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: That’s awesome. And I hope you listen to it, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah, it’s great. I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: It’s doing very well. Then Julie got busy with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. She tours with him a lot, so I used that time to work on my record and put the final touches to it. It’s going to be out very soon. I don’t know what will happen next, but for sure there will be more touring with EchoTest, so I don’t know if I’ll ever have a real chance to promote my own record, but that’s not something I’m doing because I want to get something out of it. You know what I mean? It’s more like a need I have to put my music out and then whatever happens happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZqLkAwDnT2Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us about the style of the record? I think you said it’s mostly singer-songwriter-oriented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, it starts with that. Usually my interest is in pop music and that’s also, I think, what makes EchoTest work very well because both me and Julie have strong pop sensibilities. When I work on my own music, it’s even more evident. I really like to write songs. At the same time, I want to make them interesting somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think Adrian Belew is a master of that craft. He’s an inspiration and that’s what I try to do with my own music. I start with a pop song formula and then I try to expand that and have different influences in it. I try to make it a little more adventurous than it should be for the music business world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the things that you do to your songs to make them “weird” or interesting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: I don’t have to really think about it that much. It’s more of an inner thing, I think, because I have a melody and maybe I have a chorus and then I have a verse, but sometimes they just don’t follow a strict rule. even structure-wise. I’m driven most of the time by the mood of a song and I try to follow that and get inspired by the mood and the song itself. I don’t really think about, “Oh I wrote a verse and a chorus and now I should make something weird and not be too standard with it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bwHAr4kaFNw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, usually, it’s just a matter of being inspired and using the imagination and something will be out there and I can just grab it and use it for my record. Most of the time, it’s just a bunch of ideas and then I’m very interested in working with editing the songs and using weird sounds and sometimes a sound will just inspire me with a whole song. It could be a loop or some really weird, strange sound and I’ll make a song out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us about some of your favorite moments from the record and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: I think there’s one particular song called The Things that features another vocalist. It’s the first time, at least on my own solo records, that I have another singer. She’s a girl, a female singer. It’s a very personal song. I think it was the first one I wrote for this record. It was a kind of departure musically from what I had done before, in a way, because it started very minimal, just on an acoustic guitar and a drum loop and no bass, which is strange for a bass player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was the start of the whole record. That’s the start of the whole record and it kind of suggested to me the whole concept of the record. It’s inspired by a Lovecraft story to tell my own story. So, yeah, I will choose that song as the most representative, maybe, from the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: In what other ways is this album a departure from what people might expect of you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: First thing is a concept album. So, I’m telling a story throughout the songs. As I said before, it’s inspired by a Lovecraft short story called The Outsider, which I think is relevant these days because people like me and Julie feel like outsiders sometimes. I thought it was a very cool concept to put music on. It is also connected to the ups and downs in life and how you deal with depression, stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0d4GJEON3B8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So in a way, it’s a very personal album like it has never been before for me. The other two albums I made were more a collection of ideas I had throughout time. Then I collected them on the record and somehow I made them work as an album. But this time I just had a whole plan in my head, like a whole concept, and it’s like I wrote the music for that idea I had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us more about this feeling of being an outsider. Does that apply as a musician or is it because you’re a bassist and you’re doing more with the bass than a lot of people do or what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: It definitely has to do with being a musician, I think, because first of all, I feel like I’m a musician. Even before being a bass player, I feel like I’m a musician and I’m doing music. And sometimes you feel very–I speak for myself. It doesn’t have to apply to any musician, but sometimes you feel very disillusioned. You go through ups and downs and you feel like an outsider in that it’s like you’re at the periphery. Is that the right word?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Mm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: The periphery of things. And sometimes you make the mistake and you think that’s a bad thing. You think you’re not part of something bigger. You do your own thing on the periphery, on the side of things. But as you do more of this and as you grow to be more confident in your music and what you have to share with other people, you actually start to perceive it as a positive thing because you have more freedom, first of all. Then, you carve your own space and you have people reacting to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You have feedback and it’s your heart, 100%. You’re an outsider because you tried to do something that’s different in a way, but that also speaks to people. But sometimes you can’t help feeling a little bit disillusioned. Last year, for example, I was in a place where–I still am in that place, where you do your music but then you have to do other music to survive. I work often as a sideman for other people and I do corporate gigs, I play at weddings and stuff like that. They are two very different worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wOXMxVpwhfw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I’m home and I work on my own music, it’s pure heart and I believe in every single note I make and I create. And then you have this whole other world, which is something you do to survive and I’m not saying that I don’t like it, but it’s not like your own music. You would like to be out all year doing your own tour and playing your own music in front of people around the world. Unfortunately, that’s still not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Last year, I was feeling very bad about that situation, so I wanted to do something very different and I went to England to study to become a teacher of the Italian language for foreign students. I didn’t play a single note for a couple of months, but that kind of helped me because when I got back here, I had new energy, fresh energy for music. I’m enjoying doing both now. I enjoy doing music for the sake of doing music and I enjoy being more artistic with my own projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did this album arise from that period or has it been in the works for quite some time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: It has been in the works for quite some time. But before that period, before that time when I decided to go to England and disappear for a while, I was like, “I’m not even going to put this album out. It’s not even worth it.” But then I did that. I got back here and I felt like, “No, I should work on this and get it finished and put it out sometime next year otherwise I won’t do it anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I think you learn by–everything in life is an experience and it will teach you something. It’s not–to go back to your question about the outsider, there’s always a positive side of things. The bright side of life, as Monty Python said. It’s actually good to be an outsider sometimes. It’s good to not be like everyone else and do something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, that’s what this site’s all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1WmBahJM_RM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m very happy to have you talk about that. I think that’s a great note to wrap up on, but I’d like to find out how to get the album, when it’s coming out, all those relevant details so we can help fund you and keep you doing what you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, it will be available very soon on Bandcamp. I have my own Bandcamp page. If you go to my website, marcomachera.com, there is a link to the Bandcamp page. That’s the most direct way to help me and fund me. It will also be available in all the usual digital outlets, like iTunes, Google, Amazon, Google Play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is there a physical copy coming out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, there’s a physical copy. I’m very happy with it. Also the artwork really represents the concept well and all of the dark imagery behind the record, but also the positive turnout it had on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent. When is it coming out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: September 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/657IiLDk5TY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Just a couple of weeks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much, Marco. That was really insightful and I can’t wait to hear the new record. Hopefully other people chime in and let you know what they think, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, hopefully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, man. Thanks a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/marco-machera/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/marco-machera/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tiny Orchestral Moments Press Release</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-immediate-release-august-1-2017&quot;&gt;FOR IMMEDIATE RELEASE AUGUST 1, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seattle Circle and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waywardmusic.org/?p=3422&quot;&gt;Wayward Music Series&lt;/a&gt; present:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TINY ORCHESTRAL MOMENTS with JULIE SLICK, NIGEL GAVIN, JANET FEDER, PAUL RICHARDS, NORA GERMAIN, ALEX A. FAIDE, AMY DENIO, STEVE BALL – IN CONCERT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evening of collaboration and Structured Improvisation featuring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.julieslick.com/&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt; – bassist with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8V-2stZe_kM&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew Power Trio&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bq7ShX_M6uY&quot;&gt;Echo Test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LFQaiiDm2Nc&quot;&gt;Nigel Gavin&lt;/a&gt; – New Zealand composer and world-renowned fretless / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5VgbvAj7Cpk&quot;&gt;Crafty Guitarist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janet_Feder&quot;&gt;Janet Feder&lt;/a&gt; – Denver-based composer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xa0P41jRrUM&quot;&gt;prepared guitarist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4HqFdQEK6_o&quot;&gt;Paul Richards&lt;/a&gt;  –  LA-based guitarist from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cgtrio.com/&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M9vLWtLR8Sw,&quot;&gt;Nora Germain&lt;/a&gt; – LA-based jazz violinist, improvising collaborator with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vcXo3owlGpY&quot;&gt;Orchestra of Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MH_AfwF2JrM&quot;&gt;Alex Anthony Faide&lt;/a&gt; – Argentinean guitarist and founding member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JW9MFQpFtsY&quot;&gt;Electric Gauchos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P1qq06ajsqM&quot;&gt;Amy Denio&lt;/a&gt; – well-known Seattle Jazz Hall of Fame member, composer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3b9PiD6d4zo&quot;&gt;Kultur Shock&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QSnc1yMw1bw&quot;&gt;Tiptons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4VbyYMcWB94&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; – founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://steveball.typepad.com/diary/2005/12/seattle_guitar_.html&quot;&gt;Seattle Guitar Circle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0zNDF_l3_k0&quot;&gt;C3&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TFdCzkPMa8s&quot;&gt;Electric Gauchos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickgrant.com/TADCofC-musicians.html&quot;&gt;Aileen Bunch&lt;/a&gt; – Philadelphia guitarist/pianist with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NyznFRBek68&quot;&gt;Symphony of Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiltedaxes.com/&quot;&gt;Tilted Axes&lt;/a&gt;, music for mobile electric guitars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YG8iIVXYXVI&quot;&gt;Martin de Aguirre&lt;/a&gt; – Madrid-based guitarist and founding member of Argentina’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/bigtimetrio/&quot;&gt;Big Time Trio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/sonia.wilson.184&quot;&gt;Sonia Wilson&lt;/a&gt; – Auckland-based Parisian singer and Uke player, and member of New Zealand’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dDRB8Sc56Q0&quot;&gt;Gitbox Rebellion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LQuLdREXxNo&quot;&gt;Dev Ray&lt;/a&gt; – Boston-based guitarist and former member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eNC4EaJpVwM&quot;&gt;Guitar Circle New England&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The performers present collaborative repertoire for layered guitars, voices, violins, percussion and drums&lt;/em&gt; – including structured improvisation that sounds composed, and composed collaboration that sounds improvised. The show unfolds in 360-degrees as musicians move in and around the audience. Immersive surround-sound is complemented by three walls of ambient video, and supported by an orchestra of precise guitarists drawn from the Seattle community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-and-where&quot;&gt;When and Where&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday August 17th from 8-10pm (doors 7:30pm)
The Good Shepherd Chapel
4649 Sunnyside Ave N
Seattle 98103
Tickets $15 at the door&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-performance-recording&quot;&gt;Post-Performance Recording&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this performance, the team will move into &lt;a href=&quot;http://bearcreekstudio.com/&quot;&gt;Bear Creek Studio&lt;/a&gt; for two days of lock-out recording with a series of invited guest-producers from the Seattle music community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-tiny-orchestral-moments&quot;&gt;About Tiny Orchestral Moments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.O.M. began in 2016 as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V0o8Fb-jThw&quot;&gt;twelve-week series of performances initiated by the Seattle Guitar Circle&lt;/a&gt; that ran weekly from January 7th – March 24th at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Seattle-Creative-Arts-Center-142947199172829/&quot;&gt;Seattle Creative Arts Center&lt;/a&gt; in Ballard. Each week, the ensemble of ~12 (former) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt; presented a dynamic show based upon an intricate and evolving repertoire spanning Bach to Fripp to Ives, punctuated with pockets of Structured Improvisation with guitarists flowing, moving, Circulating and playing in and around the entire performance space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In August 2016, a global &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/stevebal/videos/10155200416731562/?hc_ref=PAGES_TIMELINE&quot;&gt;TOM v1 team spent a full week working in Seattle&lt;/a&gt;, and presented a major show at the Chapel – then recorded &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com/TOM&quot;&gt;five CDs of music&lt;/a&gt; and a documentary film at  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.londonbridgestudio.com/&quot;&gt;London Bridge studio&lt;/a&gt; – all releasing in Fall of 2017.&lt;/em&gt; This new show continues the previous Tiny Orchestral Moments format by inviting an expanded array of world-class players from around the globe to continue collaboration within an evolving repertoire of Structured Improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-seattle-guitar-circle&quot;&gt;About Seattle Guitar Circle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seattle Guitar Circle was founded in 1993 by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.allmusic.com/artist/steve-ball-mn0000032276&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; (in collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Rieflin&lt;/a&gt;) after the first generation of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thelcg.net/&quot;&gt;League of Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt; disbanded near the end of a three-year world tour in 1992. Over 24+ years, the Seattle Guitar Circle community staffed spin-off projects like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AwJSKUkNUjI&quot;&gt;Atomic Chamber Ensemble&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K-jgqh1WKmA&quot;&gt;Steve Ball Roadshow&lt;/a&gt;, and the acclaimed seven-year weekly performance project: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OZDi1KOIQOM&quot;&gt;Tuning the Air&lt;/a&gt;. Tiny Orchestral Moments is a new, recurring performance workshop developed by Steve Ball and the evolving Seattle music community. T.O.M. is building on a multi-decade tradition of unique, large-ensemble composition techniques such as Circulation, Group Loops and Structured Improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-seattle-circle&quot;&gt;About Seattle Circle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seattlecircle.org/&quot;&gt;Seattle Circle&lt;/a&gt; is an active 501-C3 organization founded in 1999. SC mission is to develop and promote appreciation of music throughout the Puget Sound area by hosting public education, workshops and music events. Our mission is achieved by providing professional facilities, performances, presentations and instruction in an inclusive, educational atmosphere. We provide instruction on both an individual and group level, and we regularly share the results of our work with the public through recurring events, weekly rehearsals and frequent workshops complemented by concerts, presentations and performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inquiries-interviews-press-and-project-contact&quot;&gt;Inquiries, Interviews, Press and Project Contact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Ball
(206) 660-0055
steveball@steveball.com
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com/TOM&quot;&gt;http://www.steveball.com/TOM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/tiny-orchestral-moments-2017</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/tiny-orchestral-moments-2017</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture, Ep. 5</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-5-alex-anthony-faide&quot;&gt;Episode 5: Alex Anthony Faide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Anthony Faide is the only person on the internet who can actually play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. Here’s an interview highlighting his learning history and insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vum4Z8YvR3E?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fracture/id978457922?i=978458012&quot;&gt;Purchase King Crimson’s &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.nexternal.com/dgm/starless-and-bible-black-c228.aspx&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Robert Fripp’s website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the video of our interview of Alex for this episode of &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C8a526gujK0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-failure-to-fracture&quot;&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a video series I’ve put together about all the things that have stood in the way of my successfully playing the song &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; despite years and years of study, practice, writing, and making videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-list&quot;&gt;Episode List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Episode 0: Introduction&lt;/a&gt; (includes notation/tablature)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/stress&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Tension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/picks&quot;&gt;Episode 2: Picking Picks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/inefficient-picking&quot;&gt;Episode 3: Inefficient Picking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/overzealous-precision&quot;&gt;Episode 4: Overzealous Precision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide&quot;&gt;Episode 5: Alex Anthony Faide Interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and today I am in Seattle, Washington with Alex Anthony Faide. Thank you so much for joining us today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Thank you, guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, Alex, I found out about you on YouTube looking for people who could play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; and you had the only video–and it probably is still the only video on the internet–of someone successfully playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; so I thought it’d be cool if we could talk about that because I have a series about my failures in playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. I’d love to hear about some of the challenges you went through in trying to learn the piece. Mental, physical, musical… Go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Great to be here, Anthony. It is my pleasure. Yeah, it’s a long story in fact. Learning the notes took me about two weeks. I got involved in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in ‘95 and prior to that I never heard that piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Prior to 1995?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Prior to Guitar Craft, I had never heard it. I will also add that prior to 1995, I’d never heard &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; before. It certainly rang a bell, but I wasn’t into that or prog rock. I had no idea. I liked more shoegaze stuff or heavy metal or whatever kicks ass. Also, old guitar music, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Django_Reinhardt&quot;&gt;Django Reinhardt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or old American music like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duane_Eddy&quot;&gt;Duane Eddy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, through my parents. They liked cowboy kind of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hank_Williams&quot;&gt;Hank Williams &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chet_Atkins&quot;&gt;Chet Atkins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Not that obscure. That came later on from my own research. But they liked &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elvis_Presley&quot;&gt;Elvis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a lot, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Haley&quot;&gt;Bill Haley &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, some blues or jazz. I came in contact with American roots music very early, as well as with tango and other stuff. Later on, I liked many bands, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatles&quot;&gt;Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolling_Stones&quot;&gt;Stones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ACDC&quot;&gt;AC/DC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That kind of stuff. Mainstream rock and roll from the 70s. But up until 1990-something, I had no clue who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was or Guitar Craft or King Crimson or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SZiWvjRj1AY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A friend of mine back then invited me to a concert that happened in Buenos Aires in 1993 or 1994. It was the Robert Fripp String Quintet with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Guitar_Trio&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Gunn&quot;&gt;Trey Gunn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Robert, of course. That blew my mind. I was like, “What is this? What kind of music is this? Wow!” It just blew me away from the first tones coming from the instruments and the boxes. The theater was packed. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It was sort of a revelation, this shimmering sound.&lt;/span&gt; At that moment, I was into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocteau_Twins&quot;&gt;Cocteau Twins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and dream pop and ambient rock and slow dive. This must have been 1989, 1990, somewhere in there. I liked a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_Mortal_Coil&quot;&gt;This Mortal Coil &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4AD&quot;&gt;4AD &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, average bands…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I found some mesmerizing effect from the acoustic guitars these guys played. This harpsichord-like sound and then Fripp would do his soundscaping with Trey and all this dreamy ambient shimmering guitar music with arpeggios. That got me like, “Wow, this is really moving. I feel something.” At the end of that concert, there were some people with flyers about a Guitar Craft course happening the next year. I took one and read it, it seemed okay. That got me in. I applied for the course and got in but not really having an idea of the King Crimson stuff and the repertoire and the records and the different incarnations. I had no clue whatsoever about it. No idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, first was the change of tuning, which wasn’t really a problem for me because I’ve always been out of tune, so changing it a bit wasn’t that bad. Soon I thought, “Oh, this is much better. I can play things and they sound kind of okay.” The old tuning, I played it already It was fine for me to switch. For my way of playing, I always tried to not sound like a guitar back in that day. Lots of distortion, fuzz, dropped strings. The new tuning wasn’t that much of a surprise for me. I felt immediately at home with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had no clue we were using a different tuning back in the day. Some had said it, but I didn’t pay attention. Then I took a lesson with one of the instructors there prior to the course and he said, “Oh, you should tune differently.” “Why?” “Because it’s in 5th.” “Okay, well let’s do that and see what happens.” At first it was weird, but after a few minutes, it sounded nice. I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4HqFdQEK6_o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;First course… there were all these King Crimson-heads and everyone knew everything about–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Who was in the band–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: The genealogy of this group. I must admit, I didn’t have a clear idea of what “prog rock” was or what kind of rock came to be in the day in Britain. All these progressive rock–I knew about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yes&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd&quot;&gt;Pink Floyd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but King Crimson was really obscure for me. I didn’t have a clue about it. So, in that context, I began to become familiar with some material and I found a few things that really blew my head off. One of those was &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, of course. Another one was &lt;em&gt;Larks Tongues in Aspic, Pt. 1&lt;/em&gt; and the other one, I think must have been &lt;em&gt;Red&lt;/em&gt;. All instrumentals. The singing is fine. I like it. But I really like the instrumentals. They’re really intense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CVb2tnFN5AA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; I came across probably during that year after my first course in Argentina. I thought, “Oh, this is cool.” I saw some people would play some similar patterns or exercises. I didn’t know what to call them. Maybe it’s a Guitar Craft piece, maybe just an exercise, who knows? I was asking and then it somehow happened that I began to learn and pick up the pieces because some older students knew some of it, but they’re in a new tuning, so it’s different. And the arpeggio part is extremely difficult to play in the 5ths because it’s super-stretchy. So, they sound similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I began to pick up the pieces and learn the notes from people orally. There was no score at that time. It happened gradually. Then, learning the piece was not that long. It wasn’t a long time to learn the notes and the form. It’s an excerpt. It’s not the whole piece, which is 13 minutes long with an improv and other parts. The only part I always enjoyed playing is the intro a little bit and then the moto perpetuo. So, being able to play that from A to Z, that part–well, being able to develop a way of playing that with a degree of relaxation took a long time. And I’m still working on it. I think it’ll never end. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think, “Okay, I might twist my right hand just 0.0003 nanometers,” and then it sounds different. Or, “I can do that upstroke and it sounds different.” I don’t know.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Well, that being said, practicing… &lt;a href=&quot;http://historyproject.orchestraofcraftyguitarists.com/the-primary-exercises&quot;&gt;There are the 7 primaries of Guitar Craft &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Are you familiar with them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KOKRkyeBzN4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I know a couple of them, but I’ve never seen them written out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: One of the first seven primaries implies a motion sequence where certain notes will be held while others are not. This has a particular name and we don’t want to discuss that right now. But that is the principle of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. So, that appears in the system of Guitar Craft and the Guitar Craft lore as one of the first 7 primaries. I think it’s the 6th. I’m not sure now. Notes are being held down and kept ringing while the others are not on an adjacent string. It takes a long time to acquire the flexibility inside of your left hand that allows you to articulate like that. It’s super extremely difficult. Little tiny movements. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It should have this quality of effortless effort.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you look at it, it’s as if there’s no movement almost. Just a little bit more than no motion. Then you begin to learn how to play. Up until then, it’s only work and labor. Like, 10,000 hours. Maybe more. This is not music. This is just notes and how to play them on the fretboard. Then there’s the right hand. This is particularly difficult because of inside picking. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you need to think inside the space between the strings instead of the strings themselves.&lt;/span&gt; This is something very refined. Very highly developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I never before in my life had a guitar teacher that was so precise about the right hand and how we may hold our picks.&lt;/span&gt; I’ve been to many guitar teachers in my life, but no one could explain as exactly as Robert did what might be an efficient way of holding a pick. No one claims they have the most efficient way. This way allows you to remain relax while dispatching incredible acrobatics. Cross-picking and alternate picking systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I did this, learned the piece, then practiced a lot, then abandoned it for quite a time. Then I got back to it and then just abandoned it and worked on some other aspects. I always revisited it over the years. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There was a point where I was able to play from the beginning to the end of the moto perpetuo with a degree of comfort and not fainting&lt;/span&gt; and still being able to keep up with the tempo, which originally is a lively tempo. It’s quite something. I recommend a speed where the piece begins to lift up around 120-126 bpm. It seems to be a threshold for all players who begin working with this type of acrobatic picking technique, which I find to be very unique. It’s a unique approach to picking. For me, it was a complete revelation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ih3VbHo_A2Y?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It also helped me to develop a sense of rhythm that was otherwise not available.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like an old-school made new. It’s super old school. I think in the 20s and 30s, dance band guitar players would just be rhythm players. They kind of developed a lot of these, maybe in a rougher manner, but maybe strumming effectively for about 3 hours without falling apart because people wanted to dance. There were no CDs, no mp3s, no mp8s. Bands had to play really long. So, I think it’s coming from a place and evolving and that place is live practice, in a live situation. Then I went offline with school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I moved to Germany and began playing some other kinds of dialects in Robert-ism language. I sort of needed a grounding in terms of guitar playing and guitar tone and sound. That was my quest. I wanted the purest electric guitar sound I could find in recording history. So, I went back and back in time and began to listen again to the twangy guys like Duane Eddy, Chet Atkins, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merle_Travis&quot;&gt;Merle Travis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–all these people who could really play well with a clean tone. Not only jazz players, but a lot of country picking. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy_Bryant&quot;&gt;Jimmy Bryant &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Link_Wray&quot;&gt;Link Wray &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, is shockingly powerful with very little effort. Not very technical, he just gave a damn about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N8vOTKMqzw4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I began collecting all this information of playing purely in the old tuning with all the Guitar Craft background. I thought it might be interesting to revamp &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on it original tuning and positions and transitions. That gave me, again, a whole overview that was amazing. I had to “relearn” the piece from scratch on the old tuning. It was nice to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Still, I’m having the idea of having a double neck guitar with NST and OST and see what happens. As I was revamping &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on the old tuning again, I had my NST on my lap and kept switching. From there, I thought I needed a double-neck. Not a monster like a big Gibson, but something like a small Telecaster. It doesn’t need to be fancy, just something I can switch to properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then, I don’t know why, I came across an old Guitar Player issue from 1986 or even older where there was a transcription of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. It was the time when Robert was collaborating with them and presenting some Guitar Craft proto concepts. So, I learned it properly from that. That took not long to learn the notes, but to articulate inside of that, it took 15 years, maybe, to build up the muscles. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Maybe if I just practiced &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, it might not be the right thing to do.&lt;/span&gt; You might need to practice &lt;em&gt;Hey Joe&lt;/em&gt;. It’s all about the feeling. If you don’t feel it, it’s worthless to play it. You have to play it. This happened to me, weirdly enough, with &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, which is a piece that sounds like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stravinsky&quot;&gt;Stravinsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on acid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MH_AfwF2JrM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One thing in my efforts in learning it, I remember Robert saying, “Your relationship with the pick changes your relationship with the instrument,” or something like that. At first I thought, “This is ridiculous.” One of those deep-sounding quotes. And now that I’m into the study, post Guitar Circle technique, I feel like it’s changed my life. The way I think about using my hand, the way I hold the pick, even the way I type influences how I hold the pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Paramount. It’s paramount. The fingers and the thumb… It all has an influence on the tone it produces. If the fingers are set up to sound nice, then everything will sound nice. Why does it sound so good? Because you’re playing good. Why are you playing good? Because you’re sounding good. You’re listening, basically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He said to me, “Until you can do &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; [moving thumb from the bottom thumb knuckle], you cannot play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.” I thought, “Okay, what could possibly be so important about moving a straight thumb from that knuckle?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Capital. Capital importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! I couldn’t believe it. Can you talk about whether you had to go through physical change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Yeah, when I went to the first course, I held the pick like most guitar players. [Floppy hand picking] As if I was putting whipping cream on something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, loose floppy fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Right. Trying to play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; like that would be impossible. Maybe my bones would fracture or something. Then, I think in a personal meeting with him–back in the day he would kneel before you and take a few minutes of accommodation of your arm, wrist, and every joint. Once he found a middle road of relaxation, he would adjust your thumb and not allow you to loosen your thumb, then put the pick on the index finger in a perfect balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Every hand is different. Every body has a different feel, so he would very gently and generously do this and bring your hand to the guitar. He did that and he said something like, “Oh, you’ve really lost it.” That kept on popping up, like, “What was the meaning of that? What was lost? What exactly did he mean?” So I went back home and I began noticing that there are joints that we never use, I don’t know why and maybe that’s not important, but we don’t use them as requested by this technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But once you begin noticing the points inside–this is something you also need to feel or be aware of–then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I began noticing a change in the tone that I was producing only in the right hand.&lt;/span&gt; Not to speak of the left, which is also another body of work. So, because the angle at which the pick hits the strings and moves back, it defines the world. It makes a huge difference. A tiny huge difference. Every little correction I was able to bring inside made a big change in the sound. It was able to sound rounder and fuller at will. Or smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/deS70z5IsG0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I began to understand a little bit. I noticed where I had too much pressure, too much relaxation, what made a horrible sound on the guitar. I practice this still, every day. I don’t know if I’ll be able to achieve a perfect right hand because I like to do fingerstyle and other things on the guitar. But, for this particular approach, I prefer to have a sound that is cultivated. Regardless of what I play, I have a high standard of how I play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I found that it took me about a year and a half to figure this out. When I was practicing, the point of the pick would start moving forward. I found it was just because on my upstrokes, the pick wasn’t flat, so it was pulling the pick forward, and when you’re playing a zillion notes per minute, every fraction of a millimeter adds up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The Guitar Craft pick is a precision tool.&lt;/span&gt; It’s as if you have a very sharp soul. It’s a precision tool, unlike the regular rounded pick, which is more like a hammer. This is rather like a scalpel, so you do exactly what you need to. A good thing is that no one will die if you do this wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No one except the song and your reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: And your audience. [Laughter] I noticed your approach to picking has changed radically in the last few years. I must also admit that I’m not an internet nerd. I don’t look at everything. I apologize for that. I’d rather go and play guitar. I don’t like to spend too much time on the internet. It drives me crazy. But, still, I think it’s a powerful tool to connect with others and share and exchange. It’s a super powerful weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, any other things? One particular frustration with the pick? A story you can tell?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Well, not a frustration. It was very interesting as I became more familiar with the whole bag of information, which is inside of this piece, to practice with reversed picking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Start with an upstroke?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C2MY5UA-NLg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: To practice it with reverse picking was crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Because it schools you again about something you thought you already had. We guitar players have a particular talent to take things for granted. Especially guitar players. Maybe some other instrumentalists, I don’t know. But we guitar players have a tendency to take things for granted all the time. This gives us an opportunity to look at how much we assumed are able to, but are not. That’s not a frustration, though. That’s something that I find exciting always. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t get frustrated with guitar. Guitar is always loving. She’s fine. We are not.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Beginning to practice this with the reverse picking gave me yet another boost in terms of knowing and experiencing the space between strings, rather than the strings themselves. I had a feeling that, “Well, finally, that’s where music comes from, from the space between strings.” You know? Something happens there. You play the string. You pluck the string. You hit the string. What is the space in between? The twilight zone? This gives you the opportunity to visit all these unknown regions of string spacing. So, you have all these beautiful strings and the 5 spaces, or the 7 spaces if you go beyond the strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Practicing reversed picking sounds super different. But, when you go back to straight normal flat picking or alternate picking, something remains. I think it’s the quest for lightness. Light, not heavy. This is a piece you cannot play in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zakk_Wylde&quot;&gt;Zakk Wylde &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; manner. It won’t work. Maybe he can play it, I don’t know. Maybe he can. For sure, he’s great. I love him. But, he’s always like a bodybuilder. Fantastic. He plays amazing stuff, but I cannot play like that and keep a whole show doing that. I’m mortal. He might be a viking or something, I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But, &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; is clean first.&lt;/span&gt; Then, you can hit a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Muff&quot;&gt;Big Muff &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something. On the first run, it’s much better you do it clean. On an acoustic guitar, it’s extremely hard because of the action and the general construction, the strings are heavier than electric guitar. To play on the acoustic guitar and with this tuning, it’s close to a pain in the ass, but it is possible and it sounds okay. I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much for taking the time to talk about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: You’re welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Markus Reuter Q&amp;A</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-markus-reutermwm-content&quot;&gt;More Markus Reuter/MWM Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to check out &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/markus-reuter/2016/07&quot;&gt;our July 2016 interview with Markus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Check out Markus’ music &lt;a href=&quot;https://markusreuter.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;on Bandcamp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s free stuff and a ton of stuff to stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OMsfHTg3M5U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/markus-reuter-201706.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/markus-reuter-201706.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here in Germany with Markus Reuter. Markus!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Hi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s good to see you again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, this is kind of different. This is the first time we’re trying this. We have a bunch of user-submitted questions. User? Listener-submitted questions! (I’m from the software world, so I think of users.) Let’s get started. The first question is from &lt;a href=&quot;http://in-disciplined.com/&quot;&gt;Cameron Piko &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Australian guy, really cool dude. He says, “I’m always fascinated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_music&quot;&gt;generative &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithmic_composition&quot;&gt;algorithmic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; approaches to music and am always eager to learn more about it. So maybe something on that or your classical compositional technique in general.” Question mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Really, that’s such a huge question. But what I can say is that even in the most simple ways, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we always do apply some sort of generative approach, even if it’s just our very own way of doing things. It is a generative approach.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It is algorithmic. It’s what we know how to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It is algorithmic. Exactly. And so &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;what I think you should do is just become aware of how you’re doing things and as you become aware of how you’re doing things, you can find ways to do things differently.&lt;/span&gt; Or, you can decide to do things differently at some point and that’s where it becomes interesting. That’s why I’m using generative approaches, just to be aware of the choices I’m making and to have the freedom to also say, “No.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In a way, the funny thing is that I just had a thought that when I first learned the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Technique&quot;&gt;Alexander Technique &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, there’s the idea of doing and non-doing. In a way, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I see some sort of relationship there between the Alexander Technique and how I approach making music because when I become more aware of what I’m doing naturally (or not naturally), I have more choices to act differently.&lt;/span&gt; And “differently” doesn’t mean necessarily that it’s out of the reach of what I’m capable of doing as a human being, but it’s not what it’s suggesting to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JzBGfUOs70A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s really a huge question when it comes down to my very own techniques of making generative music. The simple answer is that you can start looking at permutations of ideas. For example, if you are writing a song and you have a chorus that is using four chords, you can use the same four chords for the verse, just start with the second chord and the first chord becomes the last chord. Something like that. It’s these simple ideas that lead to new creative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did this arise out of determining that you were too formulaic? Too many patterns?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: No, it wasn’t like that at all because for some reason, I started out with this sense that I want to be inspired not as something that just happens inside of me that I would want to create a framework that I could sort of rely on and would help me having to find certain solutions. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t think I’ve ever thought about music or life differently.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I remember sitting there as a 10-year-old with a little keyboard with small keys and figuring out these changes that I didn’t know back then. I knew that if you had all the white keys, that’s a C major scale and you can play an A minor and a D minor, but then once I started playing the A minor and the F minor chords, I realized, “Okay, that’s not the same scale, so it’s not supposed to fit into one framework.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s kind of how I arrived at this idea that harmony and music and the rules can be in a flow of change. Where the progression becomes sort of the guiding element. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not about the actual freedom to have a choice of what to do, but the choice is always limited to the flow that you’re in.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In a way, that’s just the perfect way to describe what life is like, really. You’re always in a new situation and that’s what my music represents for myself, that the situations and the circumstances change all the time. Rather than being perplexed by that, I’m just opening myself up to that reality and that means that the rules and actions that I’m allowing myself to make are always in constant flux. It’s really the opposite of randomness, somehow, funnily enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Even though the results can sound like things are changing all the time, you can say it’s random, but it’s always derived from the state that was there before. That was the actual circumstance, the actual state of things in the “now.” But, then the “now” is the past already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay. &lt;a href=&quot;http://mellamojefe.com&quot;&gt;Jeff Evans &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; asks, “Does Markus have a compositional process he prefers over others? Does he ever compose based on an algorithm?” I guess we should have looked at these first. [Laughter.] “If so, can he provide an example? And who would he like to collaborate that he hasn’t already?” So, maybe you could talk about a couple of pieces that use algorithms and then the collaboration one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes. For example, a very simple approach I know a lot of people play around with, you just have a fixed bass line and one of the very first pieces I wrote, it’s called &lt;em&gt;Ten Years&lt;/em&gt; and it’s on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europa_String_Choir&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Europa String Choir&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album, has the idea that the baseline descends chromatically. It starts on an F and goes down to Bb chromatically and then I just wrote chords on top of those bass notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mffn1EfRMy8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, really, there’s just a simple rule and everything else is open. The chords were written freely, the melody was written freely, but the rule was the bass line goes down chromatically from F to Bb. Really, the ratio between what is being determined by a generative idea versus what I write freely, that can change. There’s some pieces like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todmorden_513&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Todmorden 513&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where it’s 100% generated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The musical material, in this case, of the piece &lt;em&gt;Ten Years&lt;/em&gt;, you could say the bass line is maybe only 10%. You could also say it’s only 50% of the composition, but what I mean is that there’s always freedom within generated structures if you allow yourself to change them, but there’s also two ways of changing things. You could either say, “There’s something here.” Let’s say there’s suddenly an A major chord and you could say it sounds better as a minor chord. Or you could say, “It is an A major chord and I’m breaking the rule. I’m going to keep the A, the C#, and the E, but what I’m going to do is put an F# underneath and turn it into a minor chord that way.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So there’s always the freedom to either change the generative structure in the way of changing something that has been generated, like you are basically breaking the rule, or you are adding something so the rule can stay intact, but by adding, you’re changing the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: With &lt;em&gt;Todmorden 513&lt;/em&gt;, you said it was 100% generated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: At what point do you take credit? What was the generation process and how did you as a human influence the generation of the music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I take all the credit because it’s not different. You can compose an algorithm, you can compose some rules that then create the piece of music. So, the credit is there from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did you create musical axioms and establish those first? Or did you use some software and choose some parameters? What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It may sound much more complicated than it actually is. It’s just a permutational process that I’m using, which creates a chord sequence, you could say. It’s a permutational process because it goes through all the combinations of the initial intervals. The way that it can be explained–for example, people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Eno&quot;&gt;Brian Eno &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when he came up with the ambient music, still the way he does it is that he works on the sound level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He might have two different loops of different length and let’s use the example again. You have the A and the E in one loop and you have C and C# in the other loop. So, depending on if there’s a C or a C#, the harmonic structure is either minor or major. An A major chord or an A minor chord. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s on a sound level, but I’ve moved this idea to the symbolic level, which means to the underlying structure where the pitches are being defined by loops that are interacting, but not sonic loops, but loops of instructions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, you could have, like in the example of &lt;em&gt;Todmorden 513&lt;/em&gt;, the way it works is you have a center note of a 3-note chord modulated in a certain pattern. Let’s just say it’s a 3-note pattern, so it can be a C, a C#, and a D. Then there’s an interval that’s added on top of the center note, which goes by a pattern that can be 5 notes long. I’m not going to make the full thought experiment, but you have a pattern here, so that means that already by adding 5 notes to 3 notes that modulate here, you get a sequence of 15. And then I’m also using a note that goes underneath, which has a pattern of 7, for example. So, you have already 15*7 for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nkT-Metg2jg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That means this generates a structure of chords that is very, very deterministic, very simple for our subconscious minds to understand, but musically it is always logical and always fulfills the rules of logical resolution, I would say. Not necessarily musical resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Because it comes back to the first and resolves itself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes, and even within the structure, even though we have three cycles intersecting, we have the interaction of the one in the middle and the one below, would be 3 against 7, and you have the 3 against 5 on top, and even though the relationship moves with the modulation of the center note, you basically have repeating patterns there. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The funny thing is that I swear that I believe, let’s say, that human beings will instantly recognize these rules and can kind of imply what the next chord would be, but it’s not happening on the conscious level.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s the basic idea, but then you can use this and put it into feedback. You could say, from one trigger we’ve generated this sequence of chords, but then we can take each note from that generated file and apply the same process to each note again, which would then make it bloom in a way and you get these interesting chords like &lt;em&gt;Todmorden 513&lt;/em&gt;. And then, to get more into detail, you could also say, “Okay, we have these chords here, but the chords, rather than just being chords, can become filters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, you could write melodies on top of that, which are then being filtered through the chords. Basically, the chords become scales then. What I also do is I use the opposite–for example, the notes that I’m putting in the melody are “not allowed” to be notes that are in the chord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, they’re the inverse of the safe notes. The black keys when you’re in the key of C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Exactly. Yes. And then obviously you can start shifting things. You could say that the filter lags behind by a bar or something like that, which really creates just wonderful things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool! And collaboration. Who would you collaborate with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: That’s really a question I can’t answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lcarrQOUdxI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Too many? That’s my guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Too many and I just want to keep doing what I do. At this point, it’s really about who the people are that want to collaborate with me. I would love to play with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam_Jones_(musician)&quot;&gt;Adam &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin_Chancellor&quot;&gt;Justin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny_Carey&quot;&gt;Danny &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tool_(band)&quot;&gt;Tool &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for example. I would love to play with them. I think that would be really fantastic. I’ve recently been to their rehearsal studio and they played and that’s something that I would love to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then there’s always the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Oldfield&quot;&gt;Mike Oldfield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing, I would love to produce an album with him. And then, I guess it’s more about collaborating with ensembles, like great string quartets and string ensembles. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I would really love to work more with artists that don’t have a name because I think there’s a little bit of a problem in the musical culture right now that everything is kind of tied to names. So, let’s say there are a lot of people I want to collaborate with, but I don’t know their names yet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I like that a lot. Especially on this website. I feel like with MWM, it’s not about celebrity. It’s about making music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Exactly. Yeah. I’m just so shocked sometimes that people really stop listening and they just respond to the name. It’s frustrating for me as well because I have worked under my own name for a long time and I feel like I have to–not that I &lt;em&gt;have to&lt;/em&gt;, but I want to stop doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Bruce Roop! Big fan. “I’ve wondered how different it is to record music with others when they are together as opposed to sending files of music. Which do you prefer?” I guess you could talk about the experience as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Really, for me, in the end it’s the same thing because we are making music, but it just allows for a different sort of interaction.&lt;/span&gt; Where the collaboration at a distance is more of a generative approach, you could say, in the sense that you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; actually take your time to find your way into something where you don’t have to respond in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I like that because it opens doors that normally you would be able to respond that way. Maybe sometimes you need time to practice a part in order to be able to play it. If you don’t allow yourself the time, like being together and recording is one thing, but being in a rehearsal room and actually having the time to learn your part, it’s something that hardly ever happens anymore these days. At least for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qBCpf-Z5EoA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, really, I enjoy both and this album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://markwingfield-moonjune.bandcamp.com/album/the-stone-house-24bit-88-2khz&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Stone House&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was recorded in January 2016, is a very good example. It’s just great music created right on the spot. There’s always the joy of doing that. It’s also very time-efficient. We’ve all grown into this–when I say, “we,” I mean &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Mastelotto&quot;&gt;Pat Mastelotto &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for example–when we started making music, he was inviting me out to his studio and we were working there. We realized that we can do some of that work at a distance. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s how projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stick_Men_(prog_band)&quot;&gt;Stick Men &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; can actually work and create new, exciting music because it’s really cheap to be working at home. We don’t have to pay for studios.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Or flights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Or flights! It’s been a blessing, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m not going to read the “boxers or briefs?” question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: You just did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I know. [Laughter] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/ALL-NEW-Dont-Think-Elephant/dp/160358594X/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don’t Think of an Elephant&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! [Markus and I were talking about that book earlier before the interview.] When can fans expect an album between yourself and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Gunn&quot;&gt;Trey Gunn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? From Shawn Sutherland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Trey and I have been talking about that for a while and I think I asked again two years ago if we should start doing it. He said, “Yes, let’s do it.” But we haven’t started yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I don’t know if you realize this, but a year ago, you didn’t know what would happen with &lt;a href=&quot;https://mastelottoreuter.bandcamp.com/album/face&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FACE&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then after our interview, &lt;em&gt;FACE&lt;/em&gt; came out. So, hopefully this can be an instigator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes. And I like Trey a lot. He’s a very unique human being. I think it would be great. It’s just that nowadays, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I have stopped making musical projects just for the sake of doing them. Like, there has to be some sort of purpose and I know that as soon as there is this purpose, it will happen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Shawn also asks, “Why do you think &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; believed &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Touch_guitar&quot;&gt;Touch Guitar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would be well-suited for you?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: To be honest, I am not exactly sure if I remember this correctly because I was 18 when I had this conversation with Robert Fripp about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chapman_Stick&quot;&gt;Chapman Stick &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was just inspired by the fact that &lt;em&gt;he said&lt;/em&gt; that he likes the concept of the Stick so much that if he were starting over, he would like to learn to play the Stick. I’m 100% sure that’s what he said to me. I remember that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If he actually suggested–I mean, he suggested that I should try. Yes. But, I’m not positive that he said it would suit me. So, that–I can’t remember that. But, I remember that I was really inspired by him suggesting that it’s something worth exploring. And since I never felt like a guitarist, I always felt like a composer/musician (whatever that means) and so it was kind of unexplored territory. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;As I started working with the instrument, I realized that really nobody knows anything about it. Or they don’t dare to say they know things about it. It was just the perfect field of research and I really enjoyed working with it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Shawn has a few more questions. We’ll give other people some air time, too, but, “The internet reports that you have sometimes been hailed as Robert Fripp’s successor. Despite always downplaying and rejecting this idea when questioned about it. Outside of you playing Fripp’s guitar parts with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ProjeKcts#The_Crimson_ProjeKCt_.282011.E2.80.932014.29&quot;&gt;Crimson ProjeKct  &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and you both exploring soundscapes, why do you think so many folks see the similarities between the two of you? No jokes about eyeglasses, please.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I don’t know. It’s really difficult. I love Robert’s guitar playing. I love what he’s done for music in general and it’s just–I don’t even know what to say in this sense that somehow I can hear, in a way, maybe the way that I play is my interpretation of what I would love to have heard him play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0tW_4p5Oilc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Actually, I’ll comment on that. When you played with Stick Men and you played some of Robert’s parts, it didn’t sound like a cover band. Someone trying to play Robert’s parts like Robert. It was clear you were interpreting Robert’s parts as your own. They were musical parts, not Robert’s parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Maybe that’s what it is. I used to say that I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what music is. And that’s just an assumption that I’m making about myself, but it’s a good starting point. I kind of know what you mean. When I listen to a lot of people trying to play King Crimson repertoire or Robert Fripp repertoire, even if they play the notes right, it doesn’t sound right. And so I guess that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; something that he kind of passed on to me even if it wasn’t intentional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t really know what that is and it’s kind of an awkward situation as well, as you can imagine, because for example, I don’t really think that I did a great job at playing his parts. First of all, I play them on a different instrument and I’m not a great &lt;em&gt;player&lt;/em&gt; player. I’m just a musician who uses an instrument to play music. So, it was a great challenge to even get things right and most of the time I didn’t get them right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In some cases, my personal limitations made for something cool because I was bending the rules, let’s say, because of who I am and that’s a good thing. I would never consider myself a successor in that way. I don’t know. There’s one of his guitar solos that I studied, which is–I’m not exactly sure what the name of the track is. It’s the re-release of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_League_of_Gentlemen_(band)&quot;&gt;League of Gentlemen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album and I think it’s &lt;em&gt;God Save the King&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a long droning track in E minor or something. He plays a free-tonal solo on it and he’s using all 12 notes and playing melodies over this drone. It’s a rhythmic drone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I started to study on which notes he stopped and basically learning the essence of his style of soloing in a way. It’s all kind of represented in this piece. Somehow by going so deep into that composition, I acquired some knowledge about the note choices and so it’s still in there when I play. But, I know of other players who &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; more like Fripp in terms of the actual sound, but they’re not capable of playing the right notes. I’m not sure if that’s a good answer or answers Shawn’s question. Probably, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Let’s see. A lot of good questions, but some repetitive. This is interesting from Leibeck Jacob. “Is Markus interested in interactive music at all? Music that alters with user input.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes, I’m very much interested in that and much of the compositional ideas that I have are actually based in that field. For example, in general, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;without user input there is no music. The listener is creating the music in the head.&lt;/span&gt; I don’t know about these things well enough to really have the right words, but I know that there are engines for computer games that you can program to use rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was always dreaming of this idea of having a companion programmer who would be able to work on intelligent music with me. I’m sure that if somebody would explain to me the way that software like that would work, then I could write some new great music with it. As a child or a teenager, I was drawn to text adventure games on the computer. That was before there were graphic surfaces. It was just text adventures. It was fascinating and they were really atmospherically rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The choose-your-own-adventure where you take a path from start to one of many finishes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes. And you would have to solve simple problems, but it had to be done in a certain sequence. Just the text that was describing the situations, the rooms you were in, was very nice. It’s almost like an interactive book. Back then, I also got into how those were being programmed, how the software worked, and already back then I was thinking, “That would be great to have something like that where your input would actually change music.” So, depending on if you’re carrying a briefcase or not, the music would change. Going into a meeting or not. I find that it’s just fascinating. I would like to work more in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s a programmer near here. He’s in Linz maybe in Austria named Jens-Christian Fischer. He’s a fan of Make Weird Music and he did a whole presentation on generative music with user input. I’ll have to show it to you. He built a website and allowed users on their phones or laptops to choose shapes and move the shapes around and those shapes represented sound. I’ll get you hooked up with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cmeunlYCcwM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Bernie, the famous Bernie. “Since the first MWM interview, two holy grails of your discography have finally been unveiled and released. &lt;a href=&quot;https://roninrhythmrecords.bandcamp.com/album/falling-for-ascension&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Falling for Ascension&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;FACE&lt;/em&gt;.” Albums I love, too. “If not yet commercial, then at least to fan and critical acclaim. And a very important component of both recordings, as well as of the symphonic &lt;em&gt;Todmorden 513&lt;/em&gt;, is the fundamental role of structure. &lt;em&gt;FACE&lt;/em&gt; is a fascinating exercise on structure, from the F-A-C-E sequence throughout, to the ‘freedom within a compactly constrained set.’ And the instruction for &lt;a href=&quot;https://sonar-band.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Sonar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tobiasreber.com/&quot;&gt;Tobias Reber &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;FFA&lt;/em&gt; has the same characteristic. &lt;em&gt;TM513&lt;/em&gt; also evolves into specific intervals. Why do you have this seeming fascination with mathematical structure, with framework, and with relative constraints, to inform your work as a composer? Where does it come from?” Wow…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I can still go into the mode of just intuitively creating music, so it’s not like that mode is not available to me. It’s a tool. It’s a tool to get excited by something, really. It’s easier for me to get excited by something that is challenging to me. So, I guess that’s really where it psychologically comes from. In more technical terms, it comes from having read some interesting books as a teenager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6del,_Escher,_Bach&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gödel, Escher, Bach&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Hofstadter&quot;&gt;Douglas Hofstadter &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was really the book that triggered my interest in composing in such ways. I do recommend that book to people who want to just get inspired. There’s also another book by Hofstadter that’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I_Am_a_Strange_Loop&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Am a Strange Loop&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that’s just incredible. If you are a creative person, if you are artistic in any sort of way, I think it’s impossible for those books not to inspire you. That’s really where it comes from, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Another lengthy setup. “In your “unconstrained instant composition” work, you also seem extremely capable of doing that sort of work to also great effect, as albums like &lt;em&gt;Unleashed&lt;/em&gt; by Stick Men, &lt;em&gt;Stone House&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Wingfield&quot;&gt;Wingfield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/Reuter/&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yaronstavi&quot;&gt;Stavi &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-twitter-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asafsirkis.com/&quot;&gt;Sirkis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://iapetus-store.com/album/modus-novus&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modus Novus&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with the Quartet for the End of Time, or your own solo soundscapes work, among many others, clearly show. And more ‘traditional’ (or less unorthodox) rock composition techniques also abound in your work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Boddy&quot;&gt;Ian Boddy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Stick Men, and the first two studio albums by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuner_(band)&quot;&gt;TUNER &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Are all these different aspects of Markus Reuter the composer always present in you? How do you choose to go one route or the other? Which one makes you more comfortable, less uncomfortable, and (by the comment on the first MWM interview), how does that internal feeling govern your final decision making progress?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Bernie. Well, he does have a Ph.D. So…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It seems like it’s many, many questions in one. But, what is the core question? How do I choose, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, how do you choose? You have the tools available to you as you mentioned in the last question. What inspires you to go one direction or the other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: That is a really good question. I think it’s really I go inside of me and I try to figure out if I’m bored. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I try to figure out which part of the work or which part of the potential work does bore me. And then I attach something to that part that bores me and then the decision is being made&lt;/span&gt;, and not necessarily by me alone, but also by my collaborator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, with the work that Ian Boddy and I are doing together, for example, it’s very simple. That scene, that style of music that Ian is in, it is kind of “boring” in the sense that it has very clearly defined rules. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, what I’m interested in is how I can bend the rules and still stay within the sound.&lt;/span&gt; Ian enjoys doing that with me as well, so we’re keeping the same box, let’s say, but we’re looking at a higher resolution within what is possible there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Or, what happens when you throw a Markus Reuter into that set of constraints? Because you’re bringing who you are and how you operate to the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KIzrmcMnwzk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah. We’ve just released an album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://dinrecords.bandcamp.com/album/memento-din52&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memento&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is really interesting because it uses all sorts of generative processes. I think it is–but it doesn’t really matter that it’s using those–it’s only if you start analyzing it. You can just start listening to it and you wouldn’t really know why it sounds a little strange and you might have a hard time figuring out where the parts repeat. The answer is simple because they don’t. I just like this challenge to give people something new that still works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One thing I find interesting about your listeners and listeners of a lot of the bands that I try to feature on the site, they seem to want to understand the music. Very few of the fans will just listen. Is that something that you notice? You’re on tour with Stick Men…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I’m not exactly sure that’s really the case, but certainly those that do ask questions want to know. That’s why they’re asking questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sometimes they’re musicians and something they’re not, which is interesting too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, that is true. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But I think that it’s important that you still allow yourself to process music completely unintellectually.&lt;/span&gt; I do that a lot. I listen to music mostly coming from the emotional side of things. I think it’s just so important. If you really want to understand my music, you need to study with me, you need to spend time with me. It’s impossible to put into words what makes the music the way I make the way it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qZh2gUOOZ1c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s more than just applying a rule. It’s more important to understand why and when at certain points rules get broken. Know what I mean? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can only really learn that if you are “breathing the same air” as somebody.&lt;/span&gt; As far as I can tell, at least on the Stick Men tours, but also on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centrozoon&quot;&gt;centrozoon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tours, I can tell that people are purely enjoying it. They don’t really need to understand it. Also, I don’t want to say it’s impossible to understand, but you would have to live my life in order to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Here’s a non-musical question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. Thank you, Sharon Rudolph. “What do you do to stay healthy on the road? What’s your diet so you don’t pick up anything out there?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I have to say I’m still very, very bad at that. Whenever I’m at home, I feel much better. I’m more healthy. I eat less. I eat better. On the road, it’s just incredibly hard for me, I have to admit. And it’s actually come to the point where I’m actually annoyed when I have to leave home because I already know that I’m going to get into bad shape. So, really, I’m in a position where I have both. I have the life away from home and I have the life at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People like Tony Levin or Pat Mastelotto, they tour so much, they basically can totally adjust for that one way of living. It’s easier than having to go back and forth. At least, that’s what I think right now. Being on the road, it really helps to allow yourself to get into the flow of being on the road. A lot of things are pre-determined. You know where you’re going to be at a certain time. Things become kind of same-y every day. That’s a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also, what I think happens is a change in the hormonal system of my body where there’s probably more adrenaline. I don’t know about these things, but there’s clearly a change that happens to the body. Also, attached to that are my mental processes where things are kind of easy once you’re on the road. You’re just going with the flow. In a way, it’s a little bit like being in a trance. It can be enjoyable, but just the hard part starts when I’m getting back home. Even though, after a few weeks back at home, I start feeling better again, but it’s really deceptive. You never really know how well you’re doing. I’m not sure that makes any sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it does for me, having witnessed people on the road, touring. And having opened my home to musicians on tour, too. So, let’s see. There’s actually only a few questions left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/w4WG9XtDJSg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Chris Harris asks, “A couple of things sparked by the first interview. I’m glad &lt;em&gt;FACE&lt;/em&gt; finally got to see the light of day because it’s a great piece of work. Okay, number 1: You talked about how important patterns are to perceptions of music - The Crimson ProjeKct and Stick Men push patterns beyond what constitutes ‘normal’ for popular music with pieces with parts in different time signatures that move apart and synchronize together again and you’ve experimented with the algorithmic generation of music in pieces like &lt;em&gt;Todmorden 513&lt;/em&gt; - do you ever wonder how far you can push a pattern before its presence becomes hidden from the listener? Would that alter people’s responses to the music?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, that’s exactly the point. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;What I’m interested in is finding that fine line where things are familiar and surprising.&lt;/span&gt; So, the answer is, yes I’m wondering that all the time. I have actually developed this little bit of an idea of this permutational system that actually does that. It allows you to understand what’s going on, but at the same time, the resulting sounds are surprising. It’s very important because in a way, it’s kind of the ideal ergonomic state of the mind. It’s where the communication between the conscious and the subconscious, where there’s an equilibrium somehow, and yes I’m looking for that. I’m wondering that all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think I am guilty of exploring and not having the balance right sometimes. I’m okay with that because it’s part of my process and it’s part of the process of discovery. It’s not that anybody’s asking me to always be perfect. I mean, I am always perfect in the sense that I do my best. It’s a good question. I do ask myself that question many times. Sometimes I just decide to have a bias from either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It reminds me of the sitting practice from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because sometimes you sit down to focus on breathing and relaxation and it’s like, “I don’t want to do this. I don’t want to do this.” Then you’re okay with it, but you lose your attention again. But it’s a simple pattern of breathing and relaxing. So, musically, I think about that a lot. Like, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Reich&quot;&gt;Steve Reich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes I can listen to his stuff and I think, “Okay, this is too much. Too many loops.” Then other times, I think he could have gone on another ten minutes. So, I think it depends on the listener too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, it does. And really I think a word that has become a little popular is mindfulness. In a way, it’s kind of important for my process of making music, but also what it kind of does as well is almost forces the listener to be mindful, which can be a good thing, can be a bad thing. It might feel patronizing in a way, or people maybe don’t want to get educated by listening, which I totally understand why you wouldn’t want to be educated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;An album like &lt;em&gt;Falling for Ascension&lt;/em&gt;, for example, is basically an ear training exercise. It wasn’t supposed to be that, but it turned out to be that way. People don’t need to know that if they just listen to it. Something will happen, something will change. I’m aware of that. I want to be a little more conscious about knowing where I am on that spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GjG5R8FzJYE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so Chris Harris’ second question: “When you hear the term ‘weird music’ what constitutes weirdness for you? Would a piece that is atonal but strongly rhythmic be preferable to one that is melodic but not discernibly rhythmic (which is where a lot of ambient music seems to lie)? How weird does something have to get before you say, ‘Okay, that’s no longer music?’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Okay, I think first of all, the word “weird” is your invention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, it’s a marketing term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It is. For me, the weirdness is not a factor that really decides over if something’s music or not. It has nothing to do with that. And really, there is no such thing as “weird music” to me. I guess moreso an attitude can be weird, if you know what I mean. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think there’s a difference between the work of an artist and the artist himself, somehow.&lt;/span&gt; The weirdness–for me, there is no “weird music.” Just for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;However, the question if music is music or is not music, that’s something that only each listener individually can decide for themselves.&lt;/span&gt; I have said that before and I’m not so happy about the words that I have used for it and that I’m still using for it, but I think there’s something what I still call “real music” where the motivation is the music itself. Again, this is not judging, but there is music that comes from the love of music and there’s music that comes for the love of something else. And that’s where I see some differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That sound that’s being created, how it appeals to me or how it doesn’t make me feel. Obviously, it’s just purely subjective and really it’s something that you have to find out as a listener. You have to understand that people have all sorts of very, very different motivations to make music. And then, again, even if somebody asks–I don’t know, I don’t have good examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, if somebody makes music just for the–let’s say a male guitarist is trying to pick up girls by playing guitar, and then creates a certain kind of music. You listen to that music, that does not mean that your experience of that music has anything to do with the original motivation, so even though some music might not be “real” in my sense, but &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; as a listener, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you make it real because your motivation or your way of listening changes the sound in such a way that it totally becomes detached from the original meaning of it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool. Kathy Melaas–I don’t know how to say her last name. She’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: She’s great. A big supporter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ceX_BLdR-tM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: She asks, “I’ve always found it remarkable how Markus, particularly when playing with centrozoon or in his solos opening Stick Men shows (that became the &lt;a href=&quot;https://markusreuter.bandcamp.com/album/sultry-kissing-lounge-crimson-projekct-tour-2014&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sultry Kissing Lounge&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; {be still my heart!}), that he ‘composes in the moment’ (I think that’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernhard_W%C3%B6stheinrich&quot;&gt;Bernhard &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s explanation actually) and draws from the atmosphere and vibe of the room and audience to guide the piece.  That’s the magic part for me.” There’s no question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, but I sort of know what she’s asking about. The funny thing is that she makes the assumption that I’m drawing from the atmosphere and I’m not. I’m not. I say I’m not, which means I’m not consciously doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But there’s no way you can’t be influenced by your environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: That is very true. However, how I’m doing that is by not being concerned with that. And actually, that’s maybe the trick where some sort of channel is being opened by not being concerned of not by trying to do that. So, in that moment, I’m just trying to establish a good connection with the parts in me that are listening. Then I’ll let my body respond almost intuitively so. It’s not about thinking which note to play next. It can be, but it doesn’t have to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s almost like using the body as somebody that is acting as a reflex. Its action is a reflex to what I’m hearing. So, it’s more of a gestural approach to responding. It’s not about making choices.&lt;/span&gt; It’s about–I think the word “reflex” is interesting in that sense because there’s a certain sound and it leads to a certain response. I think that I have a relatively wide range of responses and that means the music is relatively alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Shawn Sutherland says, “I would love to hear Markus talk about Mike Oldfield, specifically what drew him to Mike’s music, how it influenced and inspired him.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: First of all, it was like the first music that I really fell in love with and I think it’s just incredibly rich music that is packaged in a way that is very interesting and very beautifully crafted and deceptive in several ways. Chronologically, since I have followed Mike Oldfield’s music for several decades, it’s interesting also from the point of how his music develops. The biographical aspect of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m just learning a lot about music by being true to one artist and following his works.&lt;/span&gt; I still have this–it’s kind of music I can go back to in order to recharge my creative energy. I can listen to the music and get goosebumps. I know that it is highly likely when I listen to a certain piece of music that it actually gives me that release–it’s almost like a drug to me. It’s really difficult to not be a fanboy if you’re a fanboy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, I really think that there’s something really uniquely special to that music that I do not find in other music. It’s probably just because of the way that he thinks about music or just the way that he does it. I like structure, I like complicated structures, I like ideas like canons and stuff, and his work is just full of that kind of thing. It still keeps inspiring me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e0qrRmiFRWI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What is special is that I think Mike’s music–or, just the way that he comes up with melodies–is just so inherently folkloristic. It’s something that I never really had. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Growing up in Germany after the war, I’m second or third generation after the war, but still we didn’t have folklore. We weren’t really singing songs at home or even at school. There was just too much attachment to the third reich with the German folklore. So, it somehow kind of got erased from the curriculums at school, I think. It could also just have been my school, I don’t know.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Once I discovered the Irish roots of Mike Oldfield’s music (I think it’s Irish), it just gave me this instant connection to traditional music and the power of the soil, I would say. The music or traditions that have grown for hundreds or thousands of years. I find that fascinating and that’s what I find in Mike Oldfield’s music. I just don’t get the same with blues music, for example. I don’t know why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For me, the tradition, you could trace it back as many years, but somehow being a European–and blues and rock and roll is close to my heart, but then I like King Crimson more than Led Zeppelin for obvious reasons. Just the European style of writing, the European style of understanding, using the harmony–it’s just closer to who I am. And obviously, Mike Oldfield being a prime example of going through all the phases of the music business from the early 1970s until now, I find it fascinating to see how the business has had an influence on the music and how one artist dealt with that–unsuccessfully and successfully, you could say. It’s fascinating for me. I would really love to talk with him. I don’t think there’s hardly any–there’s some good material out there now of him talking about things, but he would be the kind of person I would like to talk with about music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And our last question from Bill Campbell, “I’d be interested in hearing Markus speak about music after a concert. Especially in relation to the music he’d just played moments before (improvisation, solo, centrozoon, etc context).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: First of all, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that the musician hardly knows anything about the music he played right after.&lt;/span&gt; You can listen back to recordings. I think it’s actually wonderful that if you have an audience that there are people who are multiplying what you’re doing. They’re not multiplying it just as a pure–it’s not just multiplying. It’s to the power of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Exponential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, exponential because each listener builds his or her own world around the experience of listening, so that’s really what I think is beautiful about the arts in general. Ideally, I’m exhausted after a performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Because you’ve put so much into it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It’s not that I’m putting anything into it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It just gives me the sense that I was available, but doesn’t say anything about what happened, really.&lt;/span&gt; You know what I mean? It’s just providing the potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. That was a great Q&amp;amp;A. Thank you so much to all of the people who submitted questions and have followed Markus and his career and have followed what Make Weird Music is trying to do, too. Thank you so much to everyone. We’ll have a lot more Markus content coming to the site that we filmed actually last year that I still haven’t gotten to. So, stay tuned and we’ll look for you in the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MR: Ciao ciao.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/markus-reuter/2017/06</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/markus-reuter/2017/06</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Three Legged Dog</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;warning&quot;&gt;Warning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you’re ready for a total shred-fest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;music-video&quot;&gt;Music Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/PnszBQqGyg0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-download&quot;&gt;Audio Download&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming soon? &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;Reach out&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested in downloading the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheet-music&quot;&gt;Sheet Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/71558/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this song in 2013 as a fun counterpoint exercise in music notation. As with most of my music, it started in the piano roll in Logic Pro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started with a silly idea imagining &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chet_Atkins&quot;&gt;Chet Atkins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Howe&quot;&gt;Steve Howe &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Petrucci&quot;&gt;John Petrucci &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; doing drugs and writing a song together. Do I really need to say more than that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me several weeks to practice and learn the song. I send it to my friend John Landy, who literally recorded his bass part overnight. My mind was blown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote a crazy drum part for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/sebastianlanserofficial&quot;&gt;Sebastian Lanser &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as a follow-up to &lt;a href=&quot;/share/bwv-1060r-mov-1&quot;&gt;our crazy Bach piece&lt;/a&gt;, but he didn’t have the time to work on it. I sent it around to a few other drummer friends and none of them were up for it. A couple of drummers told me it was too hard. I only mention this because I sent the song to &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/morgan-agren&quot;&gt;Morgan Agren&lt;/a&gt; in 2017 hoping that he might be up for it. He agreed without issue and “squeezed it in” between some other recording he was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a testament to the kind of musician he is. Some drummers said the song was too hard, Morgan fits it in some gaps during another project. Incredible. My mind was blown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I got Morgan’s drum parts, I thought it’d be cool to have &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Jan Zehrfeld&lt;/a&gt; record a guitar solo on the piece. He’s a big fan of Morgan’s and was happy to add to the song. I gave him total creative freedom over the solo section I wrote for him and he re-wrote it, giving it a &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; feel that’s much better than what I wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got Jan’s parts, my mind was blown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When John heard Jan’s and Morgan’s parts, he re-thought and re-recorded his bass parts and they really elevate the song to a new level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the lesson I learned is that there are some incredible musicians on this recording that really know what they’re doing and make me proud to release this song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend Russell Muller agreed to mix and master the song, for which I’m very grateful because I have put more energy into this song than I want to admit. The idea of doing the audio aspects was just too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the video, each musician kindly and wonderfully filmed their parts! Morgan’s adolescent son Alvin filmed the drum video. Nice work, Alvin!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we are. Four and a half years after I started writing the song and it’s finally finished. I’m so, so, so happy with it and with the video. I think it’s one of the best creative works I’ve had the pleasure of completing! Here’s to “slow and steady wins the race.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;song-structure&quot;&gt;Song Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone keeping track, most of the song is in 6/4 with a few measures of 7/4 scattered about. Morgan does a lot of cool stuff with the rhythm and I had written some odd rhythmic stuff in the song as well. Aside from the shredding, the hardest part to learn was the middle of the song (before Jan’s solo) where the main guitar rhythm moves to a dotted eighth thing instead of steady quarter notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more or are interested in the sheet music, let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/three-legged-dog</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/three-legged-dog</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>David Singleton</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;David Singleton is a multi-talented songwriter, producer, audio engineer, record executive, tour manager, author, and more. He is best known for his work at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgmlive.com/&quot;&gt;Discipline Global Mobile &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [DGM], the company behind &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;. David is also behind a semi-fictional persona in the music industry called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Vicar_(music_producer)&quot;&gt;The Vicar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, producing not only a very interesting album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://shop.schizoidshop.com/the-vicar---songbook-1-cd-p1324.aspx&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Songbook #1&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but a whole universe around the character including &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/graphic_novel.html&quot;&gt;graphic novels &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/novel1.html&quot;&gt;written novels &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/videoblog1.html&quot;&gt;video blog series &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s extremely creative and huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met with David during the Seattle Guitar Work Weekend in June 2017, a collaborative music effort led by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; including around 20 ex-&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft/Circle &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; participants. The work weekend culminated in a &lt;a href=&quot;/share/king-crimson-concert-2017&quot;&gt;King Crimson Friends &amp;amp; Family concert&lt;/a&gt;. David and I talked in the historic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Lang_Studios&quot;&gt;Robert Lang Studios &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about his music and what’s going on with King Crimson through 2019, making a living as a musician, digital music streaming, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy this very enlightening conversation in video and podcast formats below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;More King Crimson content on the site: &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/a&gt;, a series about my decades-long effort to learn &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;/share/king-crimson-concert-2017&quot;&gt;my review of the June 2017 Friends &amp;amp; Family show in Seattle&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a href=&quot;/share/erudite-eyes&quot;&gt;my cover of Robert Fripp’s song &lt;em&gt;Erudite Eyes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com&quot;&gt;Check out The Vicar’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tnCu8N4Zmuc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/david-singleton/david-singleton.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/david-singleton/david-singleton.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have a very special guest with me today. It’s David Singleton, all the way from England. Thank you so much for joining. We met last night and had a great conversation about music. I’d love to continue that, but can you introduce yourself and talk a little about what you do for yourself and for King Crimson?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Well, I’m David and probably the main thing I do is I run DGM, which is not really a label, but the company I run with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which we started in 1993 as a way of bringing music into the world and trying to solve the always-clumsy relationship between music and commerce. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s really our core being: to try to find ways of honoring the music, bringing the music into the world, and trying to ensure that–if there is money involved–that artists get paid correctly.&lt;/span&gt; We started that in 1993 and we’re still at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We handle three artists. We formally handle King Crimson, Robert Fripp, and The Vicar. In effect, we handle King Crimson and then the personal music of Robert and me. That’s probably the best way to put it. I don’t think we’re perfect, but I think over the years, we’ve found fairly good ways of accommodating the dilemma because it isn’t simple music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Music really has to be made for the right reasons, which are artistic reasons and therefore, I think when music is driven by commerce (rather than the other way around) it often isn’t perfect.&lt;/span&gt; It’s always challenging, actually, trying to figure out how you marry the two. That roughly is what I do. My background is as a songwriter and producer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I listened to The Vicar &lt;em&gt;Storybook #1&lt;/em&gt;. I loved it. I heard lots of influences from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andy_Partridge&quot;&gt;Andy Partridge &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XTC&quot;&gt;XTC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to some &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatles&quot;&gt;The Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Can you talk a little about your musical background and your involvement with The Vicar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pmuNV7GlKsY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Okay, so The Vicar is a fascinating project. My background is a songwriter and most of the songs on that album I wrote about 20 years ago. There’s a song on there called &lt;em&gt;Twenty Two&lt;/em&gt; that I wrote when I was 22. At the time, I was trying to write songs thinking that I might play them and I never liked any of the results. So, I wrote the songs and I didn’t know how to produce them and nobody else was playing them in a way I liked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I revisited them more recently, I surprisingly discovered that the person who could actually arrange and produce the songs that 22-year-old David could write was actually me in the future. In fact, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The Vicar is a strange collaboration between a younger me and an older me&lt;/span&gt;, both parts of which are really valid. I think, generally, younger people write very good pop songs. I think there’s a simplicity and an idealism that’s harder and harder to find as you get older. In fact, if you look at most of the things that most of us sing from the arts we love, actually were written most of the time before they were 30, whereas after that you develop other skills that are just as important, particularly musical skills and production skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I love this collision between a raw thing that I wrote–a lot of it did change, but there was a raw genesis written then and you produce it. With one of two of the songs, they were very changed. I always laugh at–there’s the story of the broom when someone says, “I’ve never replaced my broom ever. All I’ve ever done is replace the head five times and the handle four times, but I’ve never replaced my broom.” To some extent, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve always said there is no such thing as a bad song. There might be a bad melody and a bad lyric and a bad arrangement, but if you just change all of those, you’ve probably got a good song.&lt;/span&gt; So some of those songs have been slightly reinvented since the 22-year-old me wrote them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hNlHVGry9Wg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did you write them with the orchestration in mind? There’s so much going on…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: “No and yes and no” is the answer. When I was younger, I couldn’t have conceived of those exact orchestrations. I wouldn’t have been good enough to write them. But, some of those songs have been done with bass drums and guitar and I thought they died. People have played on them, but they were never intended to be played like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, the big decision with The Vicar album, which I didn’t realize, was the fact that there are no drums on it. That was a conscious decision partly because I hate it when you–if you have drums on something in particular, you start by laying down a click track and it’s this mechanical thing that everybody’s playing to. I’ve always hated that. I realized that I don’t hear drums in my head. This is a fault with me, I’d like to point out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If I ran a Beatles song in my head now–I could run you &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penny_Lane&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Penny Lane&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I can hear &lt;em&gt;Penny Lane&lt;/em&gt; in my head, I could talk to you about all the instruments, and oddly enough, I wouldn’t ever mention that there are drums. That’s not true of all Beatles songs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strawberry_Fields_Forever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strawberry Fields&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something, but most Beatles songs, I realize I hear the orchestra, I can talk to you about what the guitar’s doing, the piano’s doing, the wonderful orchestration is doing, but I don’t hear the drums in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Even in something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Come_Together&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Come Together&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: No, there are songs where the drums are such a thing. That’s one song like that. But, a lot of them, I suppose where the drums are just holding the backbeat, I sort of take it for granted, but I don’t run it in my head. I thought, “Rather than this rule of being guided by drums, let’s imagine there are no drums.” Really, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;all of the orchestrations on the album were as a result of that one decision because the moment you take the drums away, now it’s great fun.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now your string part or whatever has got to fill in for what drums would have been doing for carrying the beat. I didn’t want to have any strummed guitars or drums. There’s nothing solidly strong carrying the beat. The album was what it was because of that very simple decision. I am a huge Beatles fan, but I think a lot of the reasons people hear it, even in the songs that I don’t think are particularly Beatle-esque actually, and they say, “Oh, but it’s so Beatle-esque…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think that’s simply because there aren’t that many people who’ve done that. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor_Rigby&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eleanor Rigby&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a classic example. But there aren’t a lot of artists who’ve gone away and done things that are obviously pop songs. Andy Partridge also goes to that interesting land. Oddly enough, I wanted him to sing &lt;em&gt;The Girl with the Sunshine in Her Eyes&lt;/em&gt;. I may yet persuade him, but Andy isn’t really comfortable singing over other people’s stuff. But, we’ll see. I’m still working on him for &lt;em&gt;Songbook #2&lt;/em&gt; because it’s an obvious match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you get into production and audio engineering and mixing and all that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: In the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s not much history out there. It’s just, “This is what he does.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Okay, well, it’s odd because I’ve always done it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My background is as a musician that doesn’t like practicing.&lt;/span&gt; That’s probably where I started. I was like that in school. I used to play instruments for about a year or two and once I thought I sort of understood the instrument, I wanted to compose for it, but I wasn’t interested in being able to play it. So, I played the cello for two years, I played the french horn for a bit. I played the piano quite a bit. I played the flute for a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Lo and behold, at some point or rather, the teacher said, “Really, you should be the conductor.” So at one point, when things were really bad at school, I used to conduct because I roughly understood all the instruments and I roughly understood the arrangements, but I couldn’t play very well. Then I started playing in bands. I used to play bass in bands. And similarly, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;because I had an overview, I ended up producing and saying, “Okay, I’ll produce it.” That’s why I first met Robert.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I really started as a sound engineer with Robert, but actually I was never–other than for him–I was never a sound engineer. I was really a producer. I started as a songwriter who became a producer and then I drifted into sound engineering, I think partly because it’s where the money is. The technology drove it like that. So the day when you were a producer and you sat in a studio, which I used to do, with an engineer sitting in front of you, was great, but actually after a while, the budgets were tighter or as things moved into computers, they said, “Actually, you’re now the sound engineer and the producer. It’s the same job, do them both.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So when I very first met Robert, it was purely as a sound engineer to mix a tour. I think the very next album I worked on was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sunday_All_Over_the_World&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sunday All Over The World&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I remember because they were struggling with the sequence of it and I said, “Well, try this sequence.” And Robert said, “Oh, okay, so you’re not really a sound engineer.” So, that’s really my background and Robert has always said that it’s inevitable that we would probably meet because he’s from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorset&quot;&gt;Dorset &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I was running a studio in Dorset. He said, “Actually, it’s a very small county, so hopefully if both of us were good at our jobs, it was inevitable at some point or another that we would come into the same orbit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And now you run a record label together. How has the transition been for you to go from music creation to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Ooh, I think I’m still in denial about “the suit” of my job. I was told the other day, “David, you’ve become a suit.” I’m still in denial about that part of the job. The label itself went through a cycle of being a label and we stopped. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, with DGM we started with this kind of attitude of, “Let’s start the label and we’ll bring the music into the world, place it into the world without having to obey market constructs.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/erWR2-_L_C8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When we make an album–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thrakattak&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thrakattack&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a perfect example. I don’t think any major label–I’m assuming here, by the way, that some of these people will know what I’m talking about. It’s an album based on King Crimson improvisations for one hour and I don’t think any sane record label would have said, “This is a really sane record release. That’s the one you should make.” But, actually with DGM, that’s not what we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We thought, “This is the album we should make. We’ll make it and once we’ve made it, we’ll work out how we might place it into the world.”&lt;/span&gt; So, we were doing that and because, possibly, we were doing it reasonably well, other people were keen we did it for them. There was a period of DGM–about the first 5 or 6 years–when it kept expanding. We had King Crimson, then we had the solo albums. We had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; solo albums, we had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Bruford&quot;&gt;Bill Bruford’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; solo albums, we had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Paul_Jones_(musician)&quot;&gt;John Paul Jones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This was fine and there was a point when I realized I now got out of bed and all I did was I ran a label and we had 20 employees. We had offices in LA and whatever, and I said, “This is not what I set out to be.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You can’t pretend anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: “I can’t pretend anymore and I don’t like it. This is taking me away from what I’m put on the planet to do.” So, we fortunately quietly persuaded everyone that they might like to find another home. It was in an honest way. And we moved DGM to what it is currently, which is just King Crimson, Robert Fripp, and The Vicar. It was wonderfully liberating. I still get a lot of calls from people saying, “Oh, you’re a label and I want you to do this,” and that’s not the business we’re in now. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is what we do because otherwise I’m just a suit trying to solve your problems for you. That’s not the business I want.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Last night you talked about bucking the trend of the industry. Can you tell us a little about what that means and how you’re getting there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: What I meant by bucking the trend–we were discussing how you make a living out of music and generally, music sales have been falling. Downloads, I think, are doing okay, but certainly overall, physical sales have been falling. If you go talk to one of the major labels, it’s been falling for a while. And ours are rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Personally I don’t think that’s surprising. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that there are perfectly good sales out there provided you want to do some work&lt;/span&gt;, which I’ve told the major labels when we go to conferences. In other words, if you want to be lazy and sack everybody and say, “I own this CD and all I want to do is just carry on selling this exact CD tomorrow,” you won’t. Those sales are disappearing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People are now moving to downloading and streaming them–and not stealing them as much as they were. Whereas, if you’re willing to add value and create things that people want to buy, there’s a very good physical market out there. So, the two things we’ve done is: the catalog really has been remastered and remixed and put out in surround sound, and every Christmas we’ve been doing a box set working through the albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Similarly, this isn’t a good example of what I meant about how you live with the market. This isn’t a crass, “We can make some money by putting the album in a box,” which I know some of the labels have tried and it doesn’t work. They’ll say, “Here it is and we’ll stick in a brochure and an extra CD of this, and here’s your box.” Whereas actually we do it in reverse. We say, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Okay, let’s look at this period and empty the archives and lovingly redo them.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2kfwJ8ExFJo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttps://www.dgmlive.com/news/the-road-to-red-tracklisting&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Road to Red&lt;/em&gt; box &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had about 24 CDs of all the shows from that tour plus the album plus the album in surround sound and a booklet that’s full of pictures. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, if you’re willing to seriously go through and honor the albums and present each of the periods, they work very well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Just to show how little we really allow the finances to run our world: it wasn’t until we’d done a few of those boxes that I realized that actually we unwittingly created a fairly major grossing item. Most of them are roughly 10,000 limited run. We can only make so many, so we make about 10,000 of these boxes. And they all sell for somewhere around the $100 range, depending on how many CDs we’ve had to put in. I just talked to Robert and said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Actually, you realize every Christmas, we’ve got a million-dollar grossing item in a world where physical sales don’t exist anymore.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right! And you had a great statement… well, “great” depending on who you ask. You said, “The world doesn’t owe creative people a living.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: No! That was the other thing we were discussing. It’s very difficult, I think, because a lot of people look at the world and there are artists making a living. But equally well, I don’t think the world does owe–that’s part of what I think the joint between arts and commerce is so complicated. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can be a very talented musician and the world doesn’t owe you a living.&lt;/span&gt; Each person has to come up with their answer to how they solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I suffer from that with The Vicar. The Vicar, I suppose, is my genuine heart, lifelong project and I’ve long since let go of the fact that The Vicar owes me a living. I’m dying to find ways of finding ears to listen to it, but I don’t think, “Hey wow, I’m going to become a rock star and the world’s going to listen to The Vicar.” If you go back in history, most of the composers probably had day jobs. They were either teachers or taxi drivers or… So, there is a living to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Oddly enough, I followed up on that conversation this morning with Robert, summarizing what we’d discussed. I realized there was another way of expressing it, which I didn’t use last night, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there is a difference between musicians and artists.&lt;/span&gt; You have to define those two terms. Artists, the world will often give a living to. But, musicians, it often won’t. You can be one of the greatest musicians in the world. Often artists may be, technically, a less good musician, but what I meant by that is the people who somehow speak to the soul of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s why, whoever it is that floats your boat, they speak to the soul. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Those people generally are giving people something they need.&lt;/span&gt; If you’re giving people something they need, they usually will pay for it to some degree, whereas there are a lot of other people who are called to music and are just as passionate about it–“I have to do music and music is what I am”–it doesn’t always earn a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: DGM just put &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radical_Action_to_Unseat_the_Hold_of_Monkey_Mind&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Radical Action&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; out &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttps://open.spotify.com/album/0ga8Q4tTXaFf9q3LvT8hrC&quot;&gt;on Spotify &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-spotify&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and for any King Crimson fan, it was almost sacrilegious. It was like, “How can this possibly have happened?” Can you talk a little bit about the years of…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: The wonderful thing about that with Spotify is that when we–I’ll come to why we did it, but I’ve had at least five emails from Spotify saying, “Excuse me, are you sure? Can we really put this up?” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Because we have spent so long berating them for doing it illegally that when they were finally offered it, I think they were terrified to actually put it up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, suing a record label…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Oddly enough, I think we mixed a trick because–well, we don’t actually like suing people, but the one people we never chased for money were Spotify, who did several times put up King Crimson illegally. And I’ve been told this morning, this band I didn’t know, so they can’t be that large, has just settled out of court for millions with Spotify for the fact that they did use their music illegally. So maybe I should have continued!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A few years ago, long before we were &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttps://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/king-crimson/id627204&quot;&gt;on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-apple&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, when we were a complete digital musical stop-out (we weren’t in downloads, we weren’t on streaming, we weren’t on anything), we were at a conference with EMI, who were at the time Virgin/EMI, and they asked us about our digital music strategy. I said, “I have a more profitable digital music strategy than any of you. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My strategy is quite simple. We don’t put it anywhere. We wait until one of you puts it up illegally and then we sue you.&lt;/span&gt;” For a while, it was an incredibly successful policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OrLC125cGdo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The download world matured into something where we thought, “This is somewhere we should be.” The streaming world is more nuanced. So, within the various people who contribute to the conversations within DGM, Spotify remains a hot topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s the spectrum of views?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: The biggest fear on the left, probably from the people who do our physical distribution, is that it might carve into our physical sales. The danger of that is that physical sales require volume. So, if you lose 10% of your physical sales, you possibly lose all of them. What happens with distributors, is if you’ve got enough stuff, they order that stuff and buy your stuff, but it actually doesn’t have to drop very much before it’s worth not sending a lorry at all. So there’s always been a fear of whether streaming eats into physical sales. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My feeling for a long time is that actually it’s two completely different markets and the one won’t pillage the other.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you’re on the other end of the spectrum?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I’m on the other end of the spectrum where actually I think we should be doing this and I don’t think it’s going to eat into physical. In the middle, I think &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Robert has always been uncomfortable simply with the money flow back out of Spotify.&lt;/span&gt; Not simply, “Is it right?” I was speaking to a very famous producer the other day who has had 14 million downloads last year and was sent a check for $1,000 from Spotify. So, there’s an argument that says, “Is Spotify playing its fair way?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_Wj0c5SqGWE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My children are all Spotify users, I have a young family and they’re all Spotify users. For Christmas, my son gave me Spotify. I suspect I gave myself Spotify since I’m probably paying for it, but he gave me Spotify and he set me up so that on my iPad I can play it and I’ve got a speaker in the sitting room. He said, “Oh, you want to play that on your thing, and it comes out of the speaker.” I’ve always maintained that subscribing to a music library is one of the ways we will all enjoy music. I went to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_La_Land_(film)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Have you been to see &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Mm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I was a lover of &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt;. Musically, I was a lover of it. We’d gone and see it and I was on a high. It was 10 o’clock at night, I went onto my iPad and played &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; and danced around the sitting room. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Why is this not a wonderful thing to do?&lt;/span&gt; So it seemed to me that it was slightly perverse that in my home life I was doing this and in my professional life, I was saying, “But you can’t do it with King Crimson!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So the compromise situation seemed to be that we would put &lt;em&gt;Radical Action&lt;/em&gt; onto Spotify because it doesn’t risk suddenly–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_the_Court_of_the_Crimson_King&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the Court of the Crimson King&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “Hey no one’s buying it anymore because it’s now on Spotify.” If I’m right, then we will add &lt;em&gt;In the Court of the Crimson King&lt;/em&gt; because we will be able to show that it doesn’t eat into physical sales, but with &lt;em&gt;Radical Action&lt;/em&gt;, it’s there so if you’ve gone to see the concert last night, you can go and listen to what it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FhKJgqxNDD8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If young kids want to talk, “You should listen to King Crimson,” there’s King Crimson out there. And actually, I love the fact that the King Crimson that’s out there is the new band and not something historic.&lt;/span&gt; I love the fact that if someone says, “You should listen to King Crimson,” if you did it on Spotify, what you’ll get to hear is &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; band, not some other band from 40 years ago. In fact, the same thing is true since we’ve been adding tracks to YouTube. I think Starless has just hit 2 million, which is a lot of views for King Crimson. And I love the fact that the highest viewed item on YouTube, where there is quite a lot of King Crimson, is a brand new track by the brand new band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. What is happening with the rest of The Vicar’s work? It’s not just a CD, it’s a graphic novel…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: So the irony of The Vicar is that–me, the songwriter, I’m a writer at the core, both a word-writer and a song-writer–I wrote those songs and the excuse to finally make an album was because I wrote a series of books. The Vicar is whodunnits in the music industry. It’s all these wonderful stories about corruption that you hear about and are based around the character, The Vicar, who’s a music producer and his assistant, Punk Sanderson, who writes the books, who’s far wittier and obscene than I would ever dare be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The genesis of that actually was I was in a studio with Robert and somebody called and as usual it was some horrendous story about someone being ripped off. I turned around to him and said, “Why has no one written whodunnits about the music industry?” It’s just such a wonderful thing to set a story in and all these stories exist. And this voice came up from behind me, Robert was sitting behind me, and he said, “It’s because you haven’t written them yet,” which was a challenge I took.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IIAWfL48bQU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/novel1.html&quot;&gt;the first Vicar book &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was actually published as a diary online. And then &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/novel2.html&quot;&gt;the second one &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, well the two of them were put together into a book and put out. I realized that actually having created the character of The Vicar, which is a whole world of semi-fictional real-world however-you-want-to-put-it. Now this was a wonderful opportunity that The Vicar could make an album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s very weird. You start saying things and you realize you’ve got to say, “Hold on, I’m going to start saying things that sound a bit odd now.” But, ironically, Punk Sanderson, who writes The Vicar books, writes a much better book than I write. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve written books by David Singleton and Punk Sanderson writes (although I am Punk Sanderson) a much better book than I write.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve considered previously several times–in fact, at the height of DGM, I considered lots of times putting out a David Singleton solo album and I thought, “Well, what’s the point and who would even be interested?” And The Vicar, even though I am The Vicar, produces a much better album than David Singleton would produce. I know that probably sounds slightly screwy, but it’s undoubtedly true. There was something about the whole–partly, the character was well-defined so even that fed into the album and it’s going to have a particular English sensibility because that’s who the character of The Vicar is–but, it was liberating and had I approached it as a David Singleton solo album, it would not be anything close to what the album is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Last night you mentioned that one of the biggest challenges is not selling, but finding an audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Yes! And oddly enough, I think I’m boring your viewers because we’re talking about a conversation that they weren’t party to last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Actually, the viewers love in-depth long things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: So, you’re hearing the second half of a conversation at a dinner table that you weren’t there for. But, yes, I came away from last night, oddly enough, thinking that we didn’t have at the table the more challenging and interesting half of the conversation. A lot of people are talking about, roughly, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;how do we make a living out of music? To which the answer is, “You don’t.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But we had a lot of conversations about that, but actually I think the other half of DGM is more interesting and more challenging because there are two halves. One half was to try and make the commerce work as well as we could, but the other half was to bring music into the world and to try and find an audience. And, ironically, we never tapped really on that last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t have any secret answers to this. If I did, you’d have all heard The Vicar album by now. I think that is a much more interesting challenge and I think that the way the music world is going is quite exciting. The same way that you can get quite depressed about “how do I make a living?” I think there are more opportunities now for artists to be heard than probably there ever have been. There’s a lot of noise out there and I think probably there always way, but you have to rise above it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8eBmRcVMu74?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And yes, I think similarly, Robert said to me this morning when I was paraphrasing, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“The difficult thing to learn in life is that you may choose music, but music may not choose you.”&lt;/span&gt; It’s harsh, but there is a point at which some people make great records and it isn’t the type of music goes and speaks to a huge audience in a wonderful way, which is very horrible. But, assuming that maybe we’ve made a record for which there is an audience and an audience that would like it–which I believe about The Vicar wholeheartedly, by the way, otherwise we wouldn’t have made it. Cut me and I bleed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I think there are more ways out there now than there have ever been and it’s just as tough as it’s ever been because there is a lot of noise out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But the playing field is so much more level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Exactly. So, previously, really unless you had a major record deal, it was a nonstarter. The irony of The Vicar is that when I was 22 or 23, had EMI come along, I would have cut my hands off if they said “Oh David, do you want to do this?” I would have said, “God! Thank you!” Just when I had just about finished The Vicar’s &lt;em&gt;Songbook #1&lt;/em&gt;, I started having conversations about EMI whether they wanted to license it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I suddenly realized I was having a conversation that was pointless because what were they going to offer me now that I don’t have? I can make the record, they aren’t telling me they have a secret answer on how to promote it, so actually what is their role in this? So, you’re right, it is a much more level playing field where, unless you have a huge, major record deal behind you, nothing is going to happen. Whereas the likes of Spotify and YouTube and social media, it is a much more level playing field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As I said, there are no answers, and obviously there are no answers because if there was one, everyone would be out there trying it and it would stop being the answer again. The moment somebody does something clever, they’ll say, “Oh! That worked!” and it’ll never work again because everybody’s doing the same thing now. I think if you’ve got the right music, the same things that make music challenging financially actually open up avenues for people to hear music, which overall means I think all these things are good for music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think the music business is always a clumsy construct. It’s better out of the way, in a funny way. If the music can flow, that’s wonderful. Artists don’t like being ripped off. That’s Robert’s thing. The core of DGM was because people were being ripped off. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if stuff is being sold, I firmly believe that the artist should get their fair share of it. I don’t think the artist should be ripped off. But, equally well, it’s not wrong that music should maybe be free. If music is completely free, that’s different because the artist isn’t being ripped off necessarily. If music is free, well, music is free. I don’t think free solves anything, either, by the way. If you’ve got real great music, people will pay for it. If you’ve got shitty music, people won’t listen to it even if it’s free and the price is slightly irrelevant.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So we’re running out of time. I wanted to get a sense from you because I recall Robert posting something about planning tour dates through 2018. Is there a longer timeline than that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Oooh, there is a longer timeline than that. There is no set end to this King Crimson. They were originally proposing to maybe take a break and then maybe start again. The break is no longer proposed, so over breakfast this morning, we were discussing what we might be doing in 2019. We don’t have an answer to that, by the way, but I do know what we’re doing in 2018. I don’t think I’m going to tell anyone right now, but there is a full year’s touring in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/a5CQIRSRkyQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Right now, there’s this tour, so there’s the–roughly, it’s a west coast tour, then we zoom across to Chicago, so I don’t know what you want to call it, but there’s this half of a US tour and we still have tickets available. It is not totally sold out. Let’s get that in there. But, then I think in the next couple of weeks we will be announcing an Autumn run that ends in New York, so if this is the “west coast” then we’re doing the “east coast” starting in Austin, just to make it confusing for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s on a coast. [Sarcastic.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: “Yeah, it’s on a coast.” So, this year is entirely in the US. Two tours in the US. Next year, I think, will be Europe and Japan. No, I know it will be Europe and Japan. 2019 we’re excited to try and do South America. Always problematic just in making it happen. We’re excited to try to make it happen because that will be the 50th anniversary to do some radical ideas that I haven’t had yet. I proposed a tour of London the other day and that might happen, as in 7 dates touring London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So there is an exciting future! That’s great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Yes! I think the band are up for it. I think the 8-piece is inexplicably far, far better than the 7-piece. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Rieflin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; will tell you it’s because he’s in the band. I don’t know what it is, but yeah, every year this band reinvents itself and gets better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: David, thank you so much for taking some time. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/david-singleton/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/david-singleton/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>King Crimson Concert Thoughts</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;warning&quot;&gt;Warning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a music critic, nor am I particularly qualified to deliver musical criticism, so these are my personal thoughts on attending the King Crimson Friends &amp;amp; Family concert on June 11, 2017 in Seattle. My intention is to be positive. I have some criticism of the show at the bottom, which I didn’t include in my Facebook note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts&quot;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, I saw King Crimson perform in its new 8-headed beast configuration (3 drummers, 2 guitarists, 1 woodwind, 1 bassist, 1 keyboardist). It was an absolutely incredible concert. They performed for more than three hours across two sets of complex music proving themselves to be one of the most present, focused, energetic, and powerful configurations of the band’s 48-year history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true highlight of the evening for me was a ripping performance of Fracture, a song I never believed I would see KC perform in my lifetime. &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;I have been studying and failing to play this impossible song for almost 20 years&lt;/a&gt;. This band, with its 71-year-old founding guitarist, performed it with new life at a breakneck pace (I’m guessing 136-138 beats per minute during the grueling moto perpetuo). The performance of this song was an unforgettable life experience for me and left me stunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9ySAvqgX0Rs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arrangement included a beautiful passing of notes between &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakko_Jakszyk&quot;&gt;Jakko Jakszyk &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, incredible percussive and drum additions across the three (three!) drummers, a deeper exploration of the song’s motifs, and a new musical direction after the moto perpetuo. The performance and arrangement were so impressive, the performers received a near-immediate standing ovation. The friends and family crowd were screaming, standing in the aisles between seats, clapping above their heads, and shaking their heads in disbelief. It was the kind of performance that kicked you out of your seat and made you feel like you could run a marathon. It was overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t spoil any more of the setlist, but it is worth noting there is brand new KC music being performed and some great additions to the band’s repertoire. And the decades-old music being performed takes on a new life. Robert has said that the music is new no matter when it is being performed, which is philosophically true, but I can personally attest that this lineup brings new life to many KC “standards.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8-headed Crimson is significantly better than the 7-headed incarnation I saw in Los Angeles on September 30, 2014. They clearly have much more internal alignment and practice as a band. I remember several rough spots during that show, which was still a great show but did not make quite the impression this new KC made last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every band member contributed meaningfully to the performance. Throughout the show, I would look at someone in the band and think, “Wow, what an amazing player! I love what he’s doing tonight!” Near the end of the first set, I realized I had done that for each of the eight members. I entered the second set with complete admiration and respect for the musicians on stage, each performing at the top of their game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FhKJgqxNDD8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mel_Collins&quot;&gt;Mel Collins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was the highlight of the 2014 show for me, and he was equally impressive last night. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was shredding on the Stick and bass like I’ve never seen, even after catching &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stick_Men_(prog_band)&quot;&gt;Stick Men &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in January in Phoenix. Jakko played several extremely difficult guitar lines, offered a very solid and passionate vocal performance, and still had energy through the end of the encore. He clearly gave his all. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Riefin’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; keyboard parts were great and contributed a lot of atmosphere that rounded out the songs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeremy_Stacey&quot;&gt;Jeremy Stacey’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; drums were a beautiful complement to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Mastelotto&quot;&gt;Pat Mastelotto’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; percussive exploration and sound library. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gavin_Harrison&quot;&gt;Gavin Harrison &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was… well, Gavin Harrison–a precise master of his craft with excellent tone and clarity at every tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, of course, there’s Robert. This is a man that has had such profound impact on me and many others. In fact, I was in Seattle for a “Seattle Guitar Work Weekend” led by Steve Ball (&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-ball&quot;&gt;see our interview with Steve on MWM&lt;/a&gt;). What struck me most about Robert last night was not his playing nor his smiling throughout the show (some smiles of joy, some smiles of laughing at mistakes). What struck me most about Robert was the community he has built around the world, particularly in Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seattle Guitar Work Weekend was a wonderful event bringing together a group of guitarists (and a few non-guitarists) from across the globe to make and appreciate music together. Some of the musicians in the group have known each other and performed together for decades. These are people who connected via Robert and his Guitar Craft/Guitar Circle efforts. Steve Ball and several other Seattle-based guitarists have familial relationships through music, craft, and love. What Robert has brought together in these people is so special and so far beyond the music. I am awed and humbled to have been invited to take part in a very small way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert’s impact on these good human beings is profound. He has helped foster an adoration of silence, understanding of self, mastery of craft, and love for others through music, relationships, and study. And these achievements have changed the course of my own life and my own relationship with music and the guitar. I cannot overstate the significance of what I’ve experienced through the Guitar Circle teachings and through the relationships I’ve been privileged to have through the Guitar Circle. And I cannot overstate the impact I’ve seen in others much more experienced than I. Several of us flew thousands of miles just to participate in the Guitar Work Weekend and to attend the KC show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Robert played incredibly last night. Yes, he wrote some great music. Yes, he has assembled a cadre of expert musicians that will melt thousands of faces this year. But most importantly to me, he has selflessly given himself to music and to others in a way that’s only understood when you spend some time with his friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[NOTE for KC fans, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/david-singleton&quot;&gt;I filmed an interview&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Singleton&quot;&gt;David Singleton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before the show and another interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/instrofreak&quot;&gt;Alex Anthony Faide &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube-play&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the only other guitarist in the world that can play Fracture. So stay tuned on the site for more KC-related fun…]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/227L6FW30ZA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the live show in 2014, the sound was poorly mixed in Seattle. It was really the only disappointing part of the experience, but it was a clear disappointment for myself and many others. For the first half of the first set, Tony’s bass and vocals could not be heard. For most of the show, Pat’s electronic drum pad couldn’t be heard. Robert’s guitar parts were hard to hear. Jakko’s amp sounded like it was submerged in a lake and key guitar parts were indiscernible in the mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the three drummers at the front of the stage is amazing for stage setup and visual presence, but it’s pretty brutal for the audience. When all three are playing at the same time, it’s nearly impossible to hear anything else, especially when the cymbals are blaring (there are a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of cymbal crashes throughout the show). Nearly all the frequencies of the band are smothered by the drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mix got much better into the second set, but it still wasn’t great. That being said, having done some live sound, I do not envy the work of a sound crew working with three entire drumsets and unamplified instruments. It’s an incredibly difficult task, but some of the mix was difficult to excuse. Key guitar parts were too quiet or inaudible in certain songs, which made me feel like the sound engineers were unfamiliar with the music. In fact, two of my favorite/most anticipated guitar parts were nearly inaudible in the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept wondering if Robert or David had sat in the venue to listen to a song or two being performed because it was legitimately distracting. Everyone I talked to was disappointed with the sound. The show in 2014 was so, so badly mixed, but that may have been due to the fact that I sat up front. Nevertheless, I remember I couldn’t hear bass or vocals at that show, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that as they get further into the tour, the sound and mixing quality improves. Part of the risk of attending a Friends &amp;amp; Family show is you are the testing audience, but the performances all night were so strong that the sound issues stunted the potential of the performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/king-crimson-concert-2017</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/king-crimson-concert-2017</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Iguesman &amp; Joo</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago (probably around 2010), I came across some YouTube videos of an incredible classical music duo called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igudesman_%26_Joo&quot;&gt;Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; showing absolute virtuosity and top-notch prowess while incorporating some of the funniest theatrical material I’d ever seen. The clips were from a show called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.igudesmanandjoo.com/a-little-nightmare-music/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Little Nightmare Music&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a play on Mozart’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eine_kleine_Nachtmusik&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eine Kleine Nachtmusic&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or A Little Night Music or A Little Serenade). It was one of those nights where you spend 2-3 hours going down the YouTube rabbit hole finding every video you can about someone. Borderline creepy, I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.cdbaby.com/cd/igudesmanjoo1&quot;&gt;buy Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo’s first official CD, &lt;em&gt;You Just Have to Laugh&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They played in my hometown of Mesa, Arizona for the first time in 2013 and then returned in 2014. The concert in 2013 was hilarious because my wife and I sat in the front row and Aleksey Igudesman flirted with her all night from the stage. We did not get to sit so close in 2014, but two of my friends sat in the front row and were chosen as participants in the show. It was hysterical and we all had a blast. I brought them two shirts and they sent me an awesome photo afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Make weird music ? Or just weird faces and weird hand gestures? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic&quot;&gt;@MakeWeirdMusic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/IBeKpXA9lN&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/IBeKpXA9lN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo (@igudesmanandjoo) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/igudesmanandjoo/status/722936041661980672&quot;&gt;April 20, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to say I’m their #1 fan or anything, but I’m definitely a big fan of their work. So, it is a sincere and ridiculous privilege and pleasure to be able to present this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xk3y-vNWtZM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/igudesman-and-joo/igudesman-and-joo.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/igudesman-and-joo/igudesman-and-joo.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Wait, before we start, I feel like we have to do this… [Gives me a noogie reminiscent of our &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai interview&lt;/a&gt;] You should have every guest do that. That should be the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/--URKL94KrU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have a very special guest with me. We are here in Germany and I’m really privileged to be here with him. It’s Hyung-ki Joo from Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo. Thank you so, so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: It’s a pleasure to be here. Good hair by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much. I just had it done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, tell us who you are and what you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right. Well, my name is Hyung-ki Joo. I’m one of the rare Korean Joos [“Jews”] in the world. It’s spelled “J-O-O.” My parents are Korean, hence the Asian look, but I was born in England and I guess I’m a musician. I’m a pianist, I’m a composer, arranger, and one of the reasons why we’re here is because you got to know me through my duo, Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo. We are a duo of violinist and pianist. We are classically trained, but we make concerts-slash-shows that combine humor and theatricality with music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. So, I found out about you years ago through a YouTube video and you guys have found a lot of YouTube success. For me, when I look at what you’re doing, it’s clear that you have a mission of turning classical music into something more accessible and entertaining. Can you talk a little about that mission? And how do you feel you’ve done in executing that mission?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The mission is a byproduct. “Mission” always sounds very self-aggrandizing.&lt;/span&gt; I mean, yes, it would be a lie to say that it wasn’t a mission and it would be a lie to say that the mission wasn’t in the back of our heads. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;What I mean by that is that our first goal was to be creative as we were when we were teenagers. We wanted to create a concert that we’d want to go to ourselves.&lt;/span&gt; We couldn’t understand why a classical concert–let alone jazz or rock concerts…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Actually, if you think about it, the concert format, regardless of genre, is quite square. Even rock music… There’s so little humor and so little fun. I mean, the music is “yeah yeah yeah,” whatever, but they’re actually quite serious and it’s quite uptight in a weird sort of rock way.&lt;/span&gt; They’re on drugs and whatever, but there’s a certain type of rigidity, it’s a certain type of format. Of course, not all the groups, but most. And same in the world of classical and jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There seems to be certain formulas and rigidity and some people have become very comfortable with that, just accepting that as, “Oh, that’s what it is.” We couldn’t understand why. Who said that? Where’s the rule book? Show us the book–the book of laws, the ten commandments where it has to look like “this.” Who said?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It wasn’t that we wanted to be radical or rebels, we just felt that there could be more done. And because we were people that were fascinated by comedy, theater, literature, and other types of art forms, we couldn’t understand why these things couldn’t exist side by side, next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We from a very early age just experimented and put on concerts our own way and then about 13 years ago, we sat down and said, “Okay, why don’t we actually really do what we’ve always wanted to do and create this show/concert?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We didn’t always live in the same city and we spent a few years apart, I was studying in New York, he was studying in Vienna. Of course we’d see each other almost once every year. Most of the times, we’d end up doing something together. But now that I’ve moved to Vienna and he lived in Vienna, we’re both living in the same city, we said, “Okay, come on, let’s do this.” And so, &lt;em&gt;A Little Nightmare Music&lt;/em&gt; by Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0jiu0RNizU8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For those who don’t know what that is, could you describe it briefly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Well, that’s the name of our first show officially as Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo. It’s crazy because I’ve been trying to describe this show for 14 years and now, being put on the spot again, you would have thought by now I’d have some perfect press statement. You know, “It is…” and just have it rehearsed. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think it’s impossible to describe because in a way there’s nothing like it.&lt;/span&gt; On the other hand, you could say that what we do is very retro because if you study the historical documents and you look at how concerts would happen in the times of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart&quot;&gt;Mozart &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beethoven&quot;&gt;Beethoven &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liszt&quot;&gt;Liszt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, they were much more open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are very famous documented examples. For example, the world premiere of Beethoven’s violin concerto–this is quite a well-known story in the classical world. The violinist who was performing, his name was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Clement&quot;&gt;Franz Clemen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–in between movements he was performing tricks with his bow, like playing the violin upside-down, undoing the hair [in the bow], doing tricks with his bow–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the kind of thing that would be just frowned upon today. It would be just scandalous, but this was authentic. People talk about “authenticity” and the “authentic movement,” but &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; was authentic.&lt;/span&gt; Also, people stank. They didn’t take showers. You know, there’s this whole movement, at least in the classical world, about authentic period instruments and playing…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, romanticizing everything…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Sure, fine, but then don’t shave for a month and don’t shower and then put on a concert because that’s authentic. Another document is Mozart when one of his piano concertos was premiered. People started applauding after 16 measures, which–he was so proud of it that he wrote a letter to his father, that’s how we know this. “Papa, papa, you won’t believe it, but just now they clapped after 16 measures and we had to stop and start again. What a success!” So he was bathing in this glory that he had to stop for people clapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NOTE: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therestisnoise.com/2005/02/applause_a_rest.html&quot;&gt;The Rest is Noise &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has the content of Mozart’s letter&lt;/em&gt;: Right in the middle of the First Allegro came a Passage that I knew would please, and the entire audience was sent into raptures—there was a big applaudißement;—and as I knew, when I wrote the passage, what good effect it would make, I brought it once more at the end of the movement—and they went again, Da capo. The Andante was well received as well, but the final Allegro pleased especially—because I had heard that here the final Allegros begin like first Allegros, namely with all instruments playing and mostly unisono; therefore, I began the movement with just 2 violins playing softly for 8 bars—then suddenly comes a forte—but the audience had, because of the quiet beginning, shushed each other, as I expected they would, and then came the forte—well, hearing it and clapping was one and the same. I was so delighted, I went right after the Sinfonie to the Palais Royal—bought myself an ice cream, prayed a rosary as I had pledged—and went home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9X0RmNZKj4Y?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If today, if that happened, it would be a scandal. It would be like, “Shh! What are you doing?! How dare you clap?! The composer will be pissed off!” If I was the composer of a work, especially one of those where it’s, “Bee ahh off pfbfbtbtbt” [atonal], and people were clapping after 16 measures, I’d be like, “Thank you, God!” You know? “Wow! Great! I made it!” You should be fucking happy! Instead of being like, “Ugh, how &lt;em&gt;dare&lt;/em&gt; you interrupt my work with applause?!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Liszt! Franz Liszt! The inventor of the recital! He, apparently, would play a piece, he would stop, he would go into the audience–Franz Liszt, the great–have a chuckle with someone sitting there, have a swig of wine and then go back and play something. This was The Great Franz Liszt! The one who &lt;em&gt;invented the recital&lt;/em&gt;. That’s what they were doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, this was the times, and there was less of this elitist, snobbish divide between the artist and the audience. There was more interactivity and we lost that toward the end of the 19th and beginning of the 20th century. And then with the 2nd world war, it was just, pfbtbtbt. And things just got ultra-serious, at least in the classical world.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, as I said, even with jazz and rock, this music that’s so groovy and makes you want to dance, the musicians are actually quite serious. How many rock groups do you know–because that’s your world–do you know who actually would crack a joke on stage or write songs, which are funny?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt; has an album called &lt;em&gt;Does Humor Belong in Music?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Of course, Frank Zappa is one of the rare exceptions, but he doesn’t quite fit in the mold of anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re right. It’s usually, “I can’t hear you! Are you guys having a good time?” Trying to get the audience into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_(band)&quot;&gt;Queen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had humor. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freddie_Mercury&quot;&gt;Freddie Mercury &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had humor. And there’s this kind of stagecraft. Even songs like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One_Vision&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Vision&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has words like “fried chicken.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fat_Bottomed_Girls&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fat-Bottomed Girls&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right! Yeah. And there’s a sort of humor in the orchestration and the sound. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatles&quot;&gt;The Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had humor in the stagecraft, in their introductions, especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Lennon&quot;&gt;Lennon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But also in the songs, you hear it. There’s a sense of fun. Not trying to say that things have to be funny, but there’s a sense of fun. One of my favorite groups is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/10cc&quot;&gt;10cc &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know if you’ve heard of 10cc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve heard of them, but I don’t know their stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh, they’re fantastic. I love their songs. They have this humoristic element, the fun element. A lot of jazz musicians became ultra-serious. If you look at jazz in the beginning, a lot of these guys have so much humor. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_Ellington&quot;&gt;Duke Ellington &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erroll_Garner&quot;&gt;Errol Garner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ella_Fitzgerald&quot;&gt;Ella Fitzgerald &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When they’re scatting, there’s humor, there’s a sense of fun, they’re quoting. Then these guys came around with this very ultra-serious movement in jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I saw this interesting video the other day. It was a lecture that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cleese&quot;&gt;John Cleese &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gave on creativity. Of course, John Cleese, the whole &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Python&quot;&gt;Monty Python &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gang is a huge influence on Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo, as they are on comedy and many things. John Cleese was giving a very serious talk about creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h7fyOLe-xn4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the things he talks about is that there’s a very big difference between serious and solemn. He also says that in order to be creative, you need to open the portal of humor. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Just because you’re talking about something serious, it doesn’t mean that if you make a joke or find humor in it, it doesn’t mean that it’s any less serious.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It is entirely possible to have a conversation about a serious subject, but with humor. He was even saying that there’s no room for solemnity. He said something like, two of the funerals he’s been to in his life were just full of humor and they were the most moving ceremonies that he’d ever been to. So, in this world, somehow humor is laughed upon, it’s not taken seriously, it’s kind of put aside. But, it’s key!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: It’s &lt;strong&gt;human!&lt;/strong&gt; When you ask holocaust survivors what kept them going, because they basically had death staring them in the face all the time–how did they, for 5 or 6 years, keep on going? Most of them say music and humor. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re very lucky that we do both. We do music and humor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I love your shows, everyone I’ve brought to your shows loves them–whether they know anything about classical music or not–but there have to be musicians that do not love what you do. That don’t appreciate you removing the solemnity in classical music that seems to have taken hold since, as you said, WWII.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: You know, we’ve never come across these people, but it doesn’t meant these people don’t exist. And I know these people exist because sometimes I read the comments on our YouTube videos. We believe in free speech, so if you go to our video clips, there are some shitty comments. We leave them. We don’t delete them or paint this image that we are “holier than thou” and only that people love us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are one or two really horrible messages in the comments. We leave them. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We have a saying, which is “not everybody loves chocolate.” It’s something we really believe in. It’s true, not everybody does love chocolate.&lt;/span&gt; Do you love chocolate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I love chocolate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Okay, you love it, I love it, but I know plenty of people who don’t like chocolate. And even those who do, they only like milk, or they like plain, or–so not everybody likes chocolate. And you have to accept that. So, there’s no reason why everybody should like what we do, but usually people who come to our show end up liking it if they didn’t know what they were in for. And those one or two that didn’t, we don’t hear about it, unless they are the ones that go home later and write online, “It was the worst thing I ever saw in my life!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Not to be defensive, but I find that those comments actually say a lot about the commenter, because there are some comments that say it’s disrespectful or that it’s tasteless. I really do not believe we are disrespectful. This is the last thing that we are.&lt;/span&gt; I can understand how people might see it that way, but we’re not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We trained at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yehudi_Menuhin_School&quot;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin school &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is like an elite &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hogwarts&quot;&gt;Harry Potter school &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for menta–er, musicians. We’re very passionate about music. I think that–orchestras, these institutions like the New York Philharmonic or the Chicago Symphony or the London Philharmonic–they wouldn’t play with us if they didn’t think we were serious musicians. They wouldn’t!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If we were just clowns, they’d be, “Oh yeah, those guys are funny. Let’s watch them on YouTube.” But they’d never lend us the keys to their Ferrari. I mean, come on. And people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joshua_Bell&quot;&gt;Joshua Bell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emanuel_Ax&quot;&gt;Emmanuel Ax &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy_Joel&quot;&gt;Billy Joel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, performing with us. They undestand that we’re serious musicians. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Always for us, everything that we do, the number one priority is the music. And then numbers two and three are the humor and theatricality. And if people laugh, great.&lt;/span&gt; If they don’t, well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not our aim to make people laugh or to do something that’s completely out of–let’s just do something weird, just for the sake of being weird. That’s really not what we do. It’s not disrespectful. If you grew up in a very puritan, rigid upbringing, then anything that goes outside of the box is gonna be like, “Whoa! Those radicals! Those punks!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u04nkEJQPqM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I saw a comment just recently on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universaledition.com/composers-and-works/Hyung-ki-Joo/Chandeliers/composer/4521/work/15794&quot;&gt;your &lt;em&gt;Chandeliers&lt;/em&gt; piece &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was a beautiful piece, but somebody said, “A serious piece of music from Hyung-ki Joo!” And I thought, “Everything is a serious piece of music.” Even the music police sketch, you’re playing serious music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That’s true. Yes, that’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Really, really difficult, complex music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: You see, that comes down to–nothing against that person in particular, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it comes down to our general human inability or need for everything to be in boxes. To put things in categories. And that’s why people struggle with things like Frank Zappa and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nina_Simone&quot;&gt;Nina Simone &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; “Where are they? What genre?” Who cares?! Do you like it or do you not? Are you moved by them or are you not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you look at people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Gould&quot;&gt;Glenn Gould &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or Leonard Bernstein or Freddie Mercury or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Brel&quot;&gt;Jacques Brel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. These are guys that are not just singers or just composers, they’re bigger. They’re more varied. You can’t just put them in one slot. It’s like, “Oh, Bernstein wrote a musical, oh he wrote a serious symphony, oh he…” Who cares?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Why can’t someone have many different facets? It’s like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woody_Allen&quot;&gt;Woody Allen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, whenever he tried to do something that was a bit more serious, he was torn apart. Why? It’s like, “Oh wait, you’re that comedy guy! You’re that funny guy with the glasses that goes uh-da-bi-bi-bi-duh… You can’t do serious stuff. It doesn’t make sense.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roald_Dahl&quot;&gt;Roald Dahl &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! Do you know Roald Dahl?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh I love Roald Dahl. I’ve read almost everything!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Have you read the adult stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Some of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Okay, so when you say you’ve read everything, you meant the children’s stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All the children’s stuff when I was a kid, but then when I grew up, I was like, “Oh, no I can find those adult books!” But he wrote great stories for grownups!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: But the adult stuff is like, whooooaaa… It’s screwed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s the one about childhood? [NOTE: It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boy_(book)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boy&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeahhh, isn’t that his autobiography?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, it’s brutal, but it’s wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: A lot of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tales_of_the_Unexpected_(short_story_collection)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tales of the Unexpected&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Uncle_Oswald&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Uncle Oswald&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it’s weird stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shel_Silverstein&quot;&gt;Shel Silverstein &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you ever read his stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: No, I don’t know him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He did &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Light_in_the_Attic&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Light in the Attic&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of these children’s poems. But then he has other stuff that’s about smoking weed. It’s fantastic and not for kids, but even I’m like, “Whoa, who is this guy? Where did he come from?” But he’s a human being with interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Look at Mozart. He wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Requiem_(Mozart)&quot;&gt;requiems &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Magic_Flute&quot;&gt;magic flutes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and he also wrote songs about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart_and_scatology&quot;&gt;licking someone’s ass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Which you have a video of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WP7v66ZnqTA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh, whoa you’ve really seen my stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes! Performing the music…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Performing the music. That’s right. Just to be clear! He saw the video of me performing the music, not actually performing the…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s another channel. The adult channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That’s the Roald Dahl adult channel. Yeah. [Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, can you tell us about your creative process and your inspirations that you haven’t mentioned already? I saw you have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86EoPYNZpbA&quot;&gt;a Prokofiev piece &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HP9Q8v2bQaw&quot;&gt;Shostakovich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… You’ve done a lot of out-of-the-box stuff and I know you compose and you educate. Can you talk about your influences and your creative process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Wow, influences. I mean, we’re going to be here all night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve probably got 4 hours of storage on the camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: From the classical world…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It doesn’t matter. Just your influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: My influences? Well, definitely the greats like Beethoven, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debussy&quot;&gt;Debussy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ravel&quot;&gt;Ravel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Mozart, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rossini&quot;&gt;Rossini &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Then some of the early guys like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_Gesualdo&quot;&gt;Gesualdo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Then from performers, already mentioned Glenn Gould, Bernstein. Then figures like, of course, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yehudi_Menuhin&quot;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St%C3%A9phane_Grappelli&quot;&gt;Stéphane Grapelli &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Jacques Brel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Very interesting thing about Jacques Brel is I fell in love with a French girl when I was 15 years old, as one does, right? I don’t think she knows about it. No, she does know about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, as every Korean British child does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: And one day she sent me as a gift, a tape of Jacques Brel’s 20 greatest hits. I didn’t know who he was. I listened to this tape and loved it. I listened to this tape for many many years and back then, there was no YouTube, no easy access, no Spotify, so I was pretty much stuck with that tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Years later, I started to listen to other stuff, but I would say there was a gap of about 13 years until I actually saw him perform. He’s been dead for a long time, but I actually saw video footage of him. I never even thought to think, “Oh what does he look like? What is he like on stage?” I just loved him. And then one day I was watching TV and there was a documentary about him. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I was just mesmerized by this guy because there was an animal. It was like, this guy was not just a singer, he was like an actor animal, something beyond. A real genuine performer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I happen to understand French, but even if you don’t understand French, there’s no way that you can’t be compelled by this guy. You see him and it’s like, “Augh! He’s so in it.” Certain performers are like that. There’s a lot of jazz musicians that have influenced me, or at least turned me on, people like Errol Garner, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Hancock&quot;&gt;Herbie Hancock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith_Jarrett&quot;&gt;Keith Jarrett &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… I recently heard a guy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brad_Mehldau&quot;&gt;Brad Mehldau &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cnH27mxW0KM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, I just saw him live with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Scofield&quot;&gt;John Scofield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Guiliana&quot;&gt;Mark Guiliana &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Unbelievable. He’s a genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Of course I’ve known about him for many years. I’ve heard him here and there. But, actually going live to listen to him. It was just a few months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: At the Blue Note?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: No, it was in Vienna. The main program was his kind of arrangements, improvisations based on Bach. That was the main course of the program. Very good, very interesting, no question. In fact, I was thinking that every single pianist that studies in Vienna should have been there because it was a masterclass in piano playing. Pedaling, articulation, phrasing, sound, sound quality, production. Everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Even his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bach&quot;&gt;Bach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was wonderful and he’s not a classical player. I was like, “Where is every single student here? They should be just lapping this up.” He played two encores, which were like… He went into his thing. He did jazz standards. He played two jazz standards and I shit you not, I was just like a little kid. I was in between that emotional experience of wanting to cry and wanting to laugh. Not really knowing how to react because it was like, “Ohh hahahaha ohhhh hahaha!” Just amazing. And there’s been very few experiences like that in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So definitely Brad Mehldau is now on my giants list. There’s a guitarist. Actually, &lt;em&gt;you’re&lt;/em&gt; a guitarist. I don’t know if you’ve heard of this guy. His name is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Muthspiel&quot;&gt;Wolfgang Muthspiel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, jazz guitarist. Fantastic. Check him out. Austrian dude. Just recorded a CD with Brad Mehldau. He is definitely a big inspiration. We hung out a lot in New York when I was studying there. He opened up my world to a lot of jazz music that I didn’t know about before. Certainly I’m a fan of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd&quot;&gt;Pink Floyd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, also like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_(singer)&quot;&gt;Pink &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_BKVfbwI3X4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: She’s very creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah! She’s very creative. And she’s also like one of those people that’s like, ugh! She’s there. She’s in the moment. You believe in her. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Even if you don’t like what she does. I think that some musicians, as far as I’m concerned, it doesn’t really matter whether I like them or not. Glenn Gould is one of my favorite artists. I don’t like everything he does, but when he plays, I just shut the fuck up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And people like Pink or Jacques Brel, they’re those type of people that not everything they do I like, but I stop to pay attention. Brad is the same thing. Just listen because these people are not screwing around. They basically–this is what they do. They’re dedicating their whole lives to this and they are hooking into something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I feel like they’re superhuman. I see musicians like that and it’s almost like they forget who they are, they just exist for this music and it’s their identity. That song, that performance is who they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes. Boom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right. You can’t deny it. You don’t have to like it, but you can’t ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I love a lot of things like we spoke earlier off camera about &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;. I love those guys. Obviously I’m a huge fan of the Beatles. Probably not a day goes by without some Beatles earworm in my head. I love a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_%26_Garfunkel&quot;&gt;Simon and Garfunkel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m open to all kinds of music. I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_Enemy_(band)&quot;&gt;Public Enemy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beastie_Boys&quot;&gt;Beastie Boys &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I think are fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not the music I listen to every day, but when I listen to them, it’s also like, “Shut up, pay attention. These are not some dudes in a garage. They’re onto something.” It’s fantastically crafted music. They have fun. There’s a sense of fun and creativity in there. They’re not just out there to make a hit. They’re there to make music, they’re there to make weird music. A lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiohead&quot;&gt;Radiohead &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/F_4fiMIxO2E?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Have you heard &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Day_Is_Done_(album)&quot;&gt;Brad Mehldau’s Radiohead stuff &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes, of course. Ooh! There’s something I discovered quite recently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postmodern_Jukebox&quot;&gt;Postmodern Jukebox &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah, very creative! Very fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; those guys. A lot of those singers are fantastic. Then there are people who are not musicians, but have been incredible influences on me. Certainly people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Chaplin&quot;&gt;Charlie Chaplin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marx_Brothers&quot;&gt;Marx Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (although they are kind of musicians as well, a lot of them). In today’s world, I’m also intrigued by–you know what? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m intrigued by anybody that is passionate about what they do.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes it’s a nameless street performer that I also just shut up and listen. Pay attention to this guy or this girl. They’re playing there on the street and they’re not doing it for fun. They’re doing it because–of course to get a little bit of money, but this is what they do. Some of them are just amazing. There’s no reason why some of those people on the street should not have huge record deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I once saw a guy–and you see these guys everywhere, but you find &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; that’s like the golden child. It was one of those dudes doing this wine glass thing. You see that usually and it’s like, “Yeah, it’s just a party trick and it’s woooooeaeaea wowooooooahaha WOOOOOHHOOO.” It’s like, whatever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I thought I was standing in front of wine glasses just now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: [Laughter, continued wine glass sounds] But this one guy I saw. I even made a video clip of him. I’m so stupid, I should have asked for his name, got his number, his contact because we would have invited him to a show or something because this guy was something. He was a genius. An absolute genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you like everything!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I do! For example, also dance. There’s a dancer called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tamara_Rojo&quot;&gt;Tamara Rojo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. She’s now the Artistic Director of the English Ballet. I actually flew to London to watch her perform. Twice. I’m not a major ballet freak, but for her, yes. There’s also a guy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Thiérrée&quot;&gt;James Thiérrée &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who happens to be the grandson of Chaplin, and he does these amazing theatrical shows. His sister too, Aurelia, actually. Both of them. They created this type of–again, this genre that doesn’t really exist. It’s this type of circus/theater/performance art/contortion/magic fun comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sFFpzip-SZk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you know Barbara Hannigan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: OH MY GOD. I wrote a huge–my first blog, one of my first blogs I wrote was basically a love letter to Barbara Hannigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: She’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: She’s absolutely incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Talk about serious music. She’s doing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gy%C3%B6rgy_Ligeti&quot;&gt;Ligeti &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff in crazy outfits. People are laughing, but it’s that stunned, “I don’t know what to make of this, whether to laugh or cry” thing because you’re so shocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: But Ligeti would have been very happy with this. Ligeti is considered to be one of the greatest composers of the 20th century and he’s also considered to be one of the most serious composers. However, his music is full of fun and humor. He wrote a piece for 100 metronomes. Come on. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The guy is full of fun! He has pieces where the percussionists have to drop plates and stuff. He uses a lot of the types of techniques that those avant garde guys were doing, but because he’s a good musician and he has that sense of humor and creativity, it’s compelling. Then you get someone like Barbara Hannigan, who again is like a golden child, and she puts her approach onto this music. Wow. It’s explosive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So we never got to your creative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh my God, yes. Well I &lt;em&gt;told you&lt;/em&gt; this was going to take forever! But you know, it’s very rare… This is a gift. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s a gift to be able to just talk about people that one likes. And to share that with someone who understands. It’s very rare.&lt;/span&gt; I’ll tell you something, and this is going to sound weird. I’ll tell you something, and I know I’m going off subject here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, go for it. This is &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/T4DCoZRr2SE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Something I realized recently in my world, which is mostly classical. Of course, I know a lot musicians outside of the classical world, but I noticed something a little disheartening, to be honest. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It dawned on me just a few weeks ago that a lot of musicians, my colleagues, people in my world, they rarely talk about music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And it just hit me, like, “Wait a second… We’re calling ourselves musicians. This is what we do. We work our asses off. Our parents spent shitloads of money so we could have expensive lessons and go to music schools. And this is supposedly what we’re passionate about, yet when we site down we don’t talk about music.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You talk about business, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: How did you know this?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m in an industry, too. It’s what people do. They talk about the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;They talk about the business! This is the &lt;em&gt;last thing&lt;/em&gt; I want to talk about. It’s &lt;em&gt;business&lt;/em&gt;. It’s the least interesting part of music. It’s the business! That’s why it’s got that horrible term, “The business!”&lt;/span&gt; And if we’re lucky enough to be in the business, then okay we have to deal with it. But, I want to talk about music! I want to talk about the C major chord, or King Crimson, or lyrics. I want to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felix_Mendelssohn&quot;&gt;Mendelssohn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I realize that very few musicians want to talk about that. In fact, there are even some musicians that will deliberately sabotage and stop you right there when they see you’re starting to talk, and they say, “You know, I don’t want to talk about music. Let’s not talk about music.” …Okay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I could kind of forgive them if the conversation steered toward something at least as interesting, but it either goes to a very low level, which–fine, that’s okay, that’s cool. But, it’s like, “Let’s not talk about music! Let’s talk about very low stuff or let’s talk about the business of music.” That doesn’t make sense to me. So, I don’t really understand. It just dawned on me, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Meeting you and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;being able to talk about music is, like, a rare treat.&lt;/span&gt; I can tell you that, unfortunately, very few people that I come across really want to talk about music. And I find that sad because what are we doing this for? Anyway, back to your question. What is my creative process? By the way, you can cut this however you want…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, I’m just looking at my cameras to make sure everything’s still rolling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: You can cut out all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is the best stuff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rp5jQRyjf5c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: [Laughter] Creative process. Well, of course I’m very, very lucky that a lot of my creative process is done with my friend and partner, Aleksey Igudesman, who today is in the form of fruit [arranged on a small table next to Hyung-ki]. It actually kind of looks like him. We did a pretty good… If &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gualtiero_Jacopetti&quot;&gt;Jacopetti &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Michel_Basquiat&quot;&gt;Basquiat &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; did a high fruit sculpture of Aleksey Igudesman, this would be it! Two apples and a bunch of bananas. This apple represents his sort of chi, and this banana represents his mental state. I know he’d prefer it the other way around. I hate to say it, but it’s more like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, so anyway I’m very fortunate that a lot of my creative process is shared with this guy. Actually, even though we’re doing our own thing a lot of the times, we’ll show it to the other. So if I’m writing a piece, which might be a serious piece or a funny piece or whatever, it’s outside of the I&amp;amp;J umbrella, he will very often make some wonderful contribution and remarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We do that for each other. When we are working together, we call our relationship a ping-pong relationship because I ping stuff to him and he smells, so he pongs.&lt;/span&gt; That’s what it is. No, it’s ping-pong because one of us says, “What about this?” Boom. And the other says, “Okay, but then we do this?” Boom. And it just goes back and forth and there’s a nice rally going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And it always makes it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Always. Yes we do disagree and yes we do argue and yes we do fight. We fight less and less because we’re trying to be more Om about life and more holistic and spiritual and more about love and forgiveness. But it doesn’t always work, so… [Punches fruit scuplture.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BSE-86M_DVk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Man, Aleksey was doing really well until…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: To be fair, he bullied me. No, this is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When you were younger?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah! He actually punched me in the nether regions. It’s actually true. It’s a miracle that I can be reproductive down there because I really thought, “I’m cut off. There can be no Joo dynasty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I wouldn’t have thought he was strong enough to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh, he’s strong. He is strong. He is much stronger. He’s always been stronger than me and he still is. [To the fruit] I’m sorry about that. Yes, that’s… yes. There’s no frustration there at all. No issues that need to be resolved. Of course, we have our differences and we have two very strong personalities, but we believe and we work toward the fact that to try and come to a consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes the fact that you have this friction leads to something better, actually. Through arguing and through contesting, then you actually go, “Wait a minute. How about this?” So, I’m very lucky that I have that. I think that some people who are just working as solo artists maybe don’t have that resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I know that a lot of the Monty Pythons, their creative process was having little writing teams. I think Eric Idle did his own thing, Terry Gilliam of course did animations, and Cleese was with Chapman, and Terry Jones with Michael Palin. But when they got together, they would then give the stuff to the other person and the other person would say, “Oh, I know how to finish that.” Or, “Give that to me.” So then it became a collaborative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’d actually love to know how–you know, a lot of these rock groups that stay together like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U2&quot;&gt;U2 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or Radiohead or Queen, if you look at their song credits, it’s all shared. It’s actually a smart thing to do, also, just for the general harmony of the group because a lot of rock groups split up basically because somebody’s houses were bigger than theirs. There is that aspect, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I am much more someone that likes to take time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kbbi_b5K3d8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think it’s partly because I’m slow [laughs], but it’s also because I believe in the magic of editing. I believe in the power of time and editing. Have you ever had this–I’m sure you’ve had this happen to you and to whoever’s watching this–Um, hi–that you’ve written something, like an essay or homework or something creative, a song, a birthday card, whatever, and the coffee spills on it and you’ve lost it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah. You try recreating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah, and then you’re like “AAAHHH!” But I think 9 times out of 10, or 99 times out of 100, when you try to recreate it or do it again, it’s usually better. So what does that mean? It means that subconsciously, with the passing of time, your subconscious has been working on it. You put it down. Boom, enter, save. While the computer’s stored it, or the handwriting has stored it, or whatever, your creative subconscious is still continuing to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So actually, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s a blessing in disguise, while bloody annoying, that you’ve lost the first draft.&lt;/span&gt; Let’s say sometimes I do that consciously. It’s not like I give it to a dog to chew up, but consciously I kind of will let time sit on it and then think about it and come back to it and somehow there’s a natural editing that’s just been done. I just say, “Okay, let’s get rid of this, and let’s get rid of that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t have–I’m not one of those child geniuses that just–I don’t have perfect pitch, I can’t write down something on one hearing. There are people like that. In fact, when I went to the Menuhin school, I was 10 years old and I thought I really didn’t belong there. I thought I’d get kicked out, besides getting kicked in the balls by people like Aleksey, I actually thought I’d get kicked out, also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Because I arrived after playing the piano for about two years, I was certainly one of the lowest on the food chain. There were people there who were a lot younger than me that were already writing symphonies, they were playing Rachmaninoff, and my audition piece was Bach’s first prelude [sings it]. That was my audition piece and somehow they accepted me, but when I got there, I thought, “Oh, they made a mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Fortunately, year after year, I was still there and I thought, “Oh I’m still here.” And the thing that kept me going was that I believed that I loved music more than anybody else. Of course, it’s a very subjective thing, but that’s what I felt. Looking around at everybody, I thought, “They’re much more talented than me, they’re much more naturally gifted, they’ve been given gifts from God and they’re more trained.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SrR9alVhCNU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the thing that I have over them is that I love music more than they do. I’m sure of it because I just love music so much and I felt that this love of music was lacking in a lot of them.&lt;/span&gt; So I felt like, “Okay, if you just give me a chance, just keep giving me a chance, I’ll get there. I’ll get there.”
And after a while, I guess I did. So there’s a part of me that–you know, insecurities lie strong. Things that you feel as a child, so even today &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s a part of me that feels like I’m not a qualified musician.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Because of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Because things don’t come easy to me. Because everything I do has to be worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is Aleksey the kind of guy you’re talking about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I would say Aleksey is a natural talent. Absolutely. In fact, it’s a miracle he’s such a good musician because he’s had such shitty teachers, in my opinion. He left the Menuhin school when he was 16 and in a way had arrested development. So it’s a miracle for me that he’s such a great musician, because–if he was here, he would probably argue that, but that’s not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He learned his things in other ways. He probably has a right to say that, but I always felt from the moment I met him, even though he was kicking me in the balls, it still made me realize when he was playing that this guy was absolutely a natural talent. Exceptional. The way he played was unlike anything else. And the sound that he has is unlike anybody else. The sound, it’s a unique approach and an unique inflection of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Seriously, he’s kind of not here, but he kind of is, and I’m not just saying this because I’m on camera, but I really feel like &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m one of the luckiest people to play with one of my favorite violinists. I’m just so lucky to play with a guy like that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you look at yourself and–do you ever compare yourself to his capabilities? Or is it a, “Thank God he is the way he is?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: No I don’t really compare. I’ve never been envious of anybody, I’ve never been competitive with anybody. I’ve had relationships with pianists. A lot of people go, “Oh my God, how can you go out with a pianist?” I don’t have any–I have wonderful friends who are pianists. I’ve never felt anything like a sort of competitiveness or rivalry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ddKHdrUktkY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The older I get, I have enormous respect for anyone who plays the piano.&lt;/span&gt; From one side, it’s a very simple thing to do. Every 5-year-old kid can just go play Twinkle Twinkle. And yes, it’s true, there is a certain simplicity to playing the piano, but when you get to a certain level, when you get to the last level of the video game, that’s not simple stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you talk about these funky pianists, these jazz pianists, these people who have to improvise–any other instrument, like electric guitar, saxophone, violin, I’m sorry, but with all due respect, they just have to play one line. It’s just one line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Or just one scale!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: One scale! Yeah, so you can do Dah-dah! Whatever, sure go nuts, man! But when you’re playing a keyboard, most of the time, you have to play the rhythm, the harmony, and that’s usually with the left hand and a bit of right, but then you have to be totally free and inventive with the right and have at least 3 things going on at the same time and be polyrhythmic and polyharmonic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m sorry, but big respect has to be done for those guys. Not taking anything away from the instrumentalists who improvise, but when you look at somebody like these guys like Herbie Hancock or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chick_Corea&quot;&gt;Chick Corea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Brad. What they’re doing is on another level. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I guess I feel that I’m still a student.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin&quot;&gt;beginner’s mind &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, always learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah, I know that sounds cliche and zen and all that bullshit, but it’s true. A few years ago, a student–well, she’s not really a student of mine, but she’s someone that used to come play for me quite regularly, and then there was a hiatus, but–she called me again and she said, “I’d like to come again and play for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I was not trying to be modest or funny or blow her off, I said, “You know? I don’t think I’d actually be good to teach you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;She said, “Why?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I said, “Well, because I’m doubting everything that I’ve ever done before and I really don’t know what the hell I’m doing myself. I’m reinvestigating everything and this would be just terrible for me. All those lessons and all that jargon trash I told you before, just throw it away because that’s what I’m doing. And so I really don’t think I’d be a suitable teacher for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/86EoPYNZpbA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And she said, “That’s &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; why I want to come to you!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did you teach her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I did, yes. How could I not after such a cute comment as that? It’s genuinely how I felt! “I don’t know myself, and I don’t have the answers myself. How can I give an answer to someone who’s looking up to me expecting the answer?” I said, “Uuuuuuh, I don’t know.” I really thought I’d be wasting her time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not a “complex” thing, it’s not an insecurity, I just feel that–yes, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I know I have an access to music and I know that I have a special approach to music. I know that I see music differently. I know that I feel music very passionately. I know those things. I’m not going to be modest about those things and I know that I can put on a good performance. But, because I know for myself how much work I need to get to even do that and I know that some people can just go and pick up the instrument. They haven’t played for a year and they’re drunk and the magic happens. Or they just sit down and write something or improvise something and they have a piece done.&lt;/span&gt; Aleksey is more like that. He’s a faster writer than me because he doesn’t really think. He doesn’t think anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, he is fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: He is a fruitcake. I think that’s also a blessing in disguise. It’s his strength and his weakness that he doesn’t give much thought to thought and he’s more impulsive and just letting it in and just doing it and kind of hit and miss. There’s not that quality control. “It’s good enough.” Boom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He has that midas touch. He’ll write pieces that–and they’re pieces that I listen to and, look, he’s one of my best friends. I love him. I admire him hugely. I listen to a piece and I’m like, “Really? Yeah? Again? The same trick?” But then I go away and I’m humming it and it’s in my head. Well, that’s the midas touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I can objectively analyze it as much as I want and scrutinize and be critical, but at the end of the day, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve walked away and hours later, I’m humming it. It’s in my mind. In that sense, it must be a good piece of music. It must be an infectious piece of music, right?&lt;/span&gt; So, he has that. And I’m a lot more, like I said, I like to tweak things and sit. It’s not so easy for me to say, “Yeah! That’s done! Next!” It’s very hard for me to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vi1JeWrIPeA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The drummer &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Bruford&quot;&gt;Bill Bruford &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; talks about this. He says some people are producers, some people are musicians. Some people can go into a studio and lay down an album in 2 hours. Some people, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Gabriel&quot;&gt;Peter Gabriel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it takes 8 or 10 years to put out an album. It’s not that it’s bad, it’s great. But one guy can put out an album and another can put out 100 albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right! I do sometimes write songs and, again, I don’t consider myself a natural born songwriter. I’m not your &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ira_Gershwin&quot;&gt;Ira &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gershwin&quot;&gt;George Gershwin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not your &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irving_Berlin&quot;&gt;Irving Berlin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but I love the form of the art of song and I’ve written a few songs. But, phew, it’s tough. Really tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I must say I was a little bit heartened, but a friend of mine is Billy Joel. I said, “Man, it’s so hard to write a song. I just feel like giving up.” I even showed him a piece, and said, “I don’t know. Should I do this?” And he’s like, “What are you talking about, man? It’s like giving birth!” He’s one of those people that will just take forever and really struggle with music and lyrics. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He’s considered one of the world’s greatest songwriters, right? If he can struggle, then I can too.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Back to being human, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I guess I can identify more with Beethoven than Mozart. I love Mozart, of course I love Mozart. But the thing with Mozart is he just literally defecated a piece. Maybe that’s why a lot of his pieces were scatalogical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Maybe that’s why there’s so much Mozart chocolate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That’s right! Mozart chocolate balls. But, Mozart, he really just thought it and it was done. A whole opera. Boom. With Mozart, there’s hardly any sketch. It’s like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pablo_Picasso&quot;&gt;Picasso &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; drawing a perfect circle. That’s basically Mozart. The equivalent. Picasso didn’t have any sketches where he’s trying to draw a circle. He’d just go boom. Perfect circle. Straight line. He had that God-given talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Beethoven, on the other hand, sketches like this [gesticulates a huge pile of papers]. He would cross out stuff, try stuff, try different keys, and there’s like 32 or 64 versions of just 4 notes. Probably before he came to da-da-da-DAAAAA [5th symphony], he did da-da-da-DEEEE, da-da-doooo, da-DI-da-daaa, da-DAAA. It’s not that piece, but you actually see that. Sketches and sketches and sketches. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And you feel the struggle. I guess maybe that’s why I identify more with him.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so… We’ve talked a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes! I’ve probably not answered one sigle question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, this is great! But, you’ve got a CD with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And I want to make sure we talk about it because it’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/64aeM7mtFRU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.cdbaby.com/cd/igudesmanjoo1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You Just Have to Laugh&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. [Promotional zooming and smiling.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Where can someone procure said CD?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Umm, here. If you have that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willy_Wonka&quot;&gt;Willy Wonka &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ability if they can just reach into the camera and pick up the disc. It’s certainly available after our shows. It’s available in the one CD store that still exists in the world. Somewhere in Mesa, Arizona or something like that, because CD stores are relics. But, mostly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/You-Just-Have-Laugh-Igudesman/dp/B01CRT7086&quot;&gt;ordered through Amazon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-amazon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/you-just-have-to-laugh-vol./id1152481360&quot;&gt;download it on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-apple&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us about the album. You’ve got a whole &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Malkovich&quot;&gt;Malkovich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes, there’s some actor called John Malkovich on there and he plays our agent. The thing is, because we’re traditional guys, we grew up in the world of radio shows and LPs and concept albums, which now don’t really exist. We’ve been a duo officially for 14 years and only last year did we make this CD. It’s our first and only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When we were at the drawing board, we were thinking, “Okay, what should we do?” And we were looking at current trends, what do people do? The concept album doesn’t exist anymore, but we’ve always loved things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sgt._Pepper%27s_Lonely_Hearts_Club_Band&quot;&gt;Sgt. Pepper’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all those great concept albums from the 60s and 70s, but CDs… So we wrestled with all these conflicting things. At the end of the day, we said, “Why are we doing what we do? Is it to win a grammy?” [In promotional voice] We hope to win a grammy. [Back to normal] But, is that what we’re doing this for? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re doing it because it’s our creative desire and if we’re lucky enough to do it, let’s just do what we love doing. If it’s a success, great. If not, then too bad. At least we’re doing something we believe in.&lt;/span&gt; So we said, “Screw it. Screw whether people care about the concept album. We’re just going to do our own thing.” So we said, “Let’s make an album that has a line, a kind of shape, and a drama to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We had all these pieces in motion and thought, “Okay, how do we string these together?” Because that’s the thing. Our genre is many genres. We are classically trained, yet we love to mix rap, country and western, electronic, heavy metal, funk, 30s/40s songwriting styles. In this CD, there must be a ton of styles. Film music, cabaret. Just a lot. Even Latin. Something for the Latin grammys. The song &lt;em&gt;Uruguay&lt;/em&gt;. Latin grammy nomination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, great, we want to do a concept album, but how do we make all these things tie together? To us, this is our world. If you’re a black or Asian kid, like I was growing up in Norwich full of white, anglosaxons, you don’t think twice. That’s your world. But, actually, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you look at it from another angle, it’s like, “Whoa, I’m the black sheep.” So, these pieces are like our kids. They belong here, but to somebody else, they’re like, “Why? This is already 27 different iTunes categories. The computer’s going to go nuts.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You don’t fit in the box!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: We don’t fit in the box. That’s right. So, one way we thought was, “Okay, well let’s create this character of an agent.” We called this guy Agent Sir and he’s a kind of persoflage mockup of all the kinds of agents that we’ve come across with the kind of traits that basically in this business that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;a lot of these people out there have no idea about music. The people that are “up there.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9A95yzVgBTs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah. They “make decisions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: People who make decisions about who will play next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;They have no idea about music! Which I could forgive &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; they had a passion for it, but they don’t. They couldn’t care less.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Obviously with streaming services…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: They don’t give a shit. They don’t care, so they have no emotional connection to the job they’re supposed to be working on. Also, those who have some kind of influence over the artist, a lot of them really don’t give a shit about the artist. They’re just there to rape and profit from them. If they get burnt out, it doesn’t matter. They’ll just move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Find another one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Find another one. Yep. This character’s not as evil, but let’s say that’s the background of our agent. We wanted someone to play this, so who better to ask than John Malkovich?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Who suffers from the same problems in &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes, of course. He’s and out-of-the-box guy. You’ll see him in &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt;, but that’s not his thing. His thing is doing French theater and weird projects like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;em&gt;Being John Malkovich&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;em&gt;Being John Malkovich&lt;/em&gt;! That’s him. So, that’s where we’re kindred spirits and he’s always so gracious and supportive. He said, “Yeah, sure I’ll do this.” So, he’s kind of the string, the thread. He sends us off to record all the things. He sends us off to Istanbul because he wants a Turkish lamp. He’s like, “I’m flying into Paris. Got some friends over for some wine and cheese. So, maybe you could record some Chopin to go with our wine and cheese.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He doesn’t care. “Whatever. Just do something while I’m flying around the world making money from you guys. Or not from you guys, but something else.” He even sends us to outer space for some reason. He sends us to Uranus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I have to say it was one of the most fun things to get him to say “Yer-anus.” Not that he had any trouble doing that, but we were like little kids writing the script like, “He’s going to say that! He’s going to say that! And I’m sending it to yer-anus!” And he’s reading it! It’s kind of like a mixture of not greatest hits, but songs that people love, like &lt;em&gt;From Mozart with Love&lt;/em&gt;, which is a mashup of Mozart and James Bond. There’s our kind of version of the disco hit, &lt;em&gt;I Will Survive&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RvWsRt8w664?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of people say, “Oh, but does your stuff work on radio? How can you make a CD because your stuff is so visual?” So we said, “All right. Let’s prove it to you.” So not only did we create a kind of concept for it, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we also rethought every single number to see how it could translate into an audio format.&lt;/span&gt; I know you know quite a lot of our stuff, but you’ll see that a lot of things are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh I love the disc!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: We made a 3D space for the 2D listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And it’s fresh! If you watch the YouTube things, that’s one version of it, but then you get the CD, and you say, “Oh, I see how they twisted this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right. It’s totally different. They’re all totally different versions. So, please, &lt;em&gt;You Just Have to Laugh&lt;/em&gt; by Igudesman and Joo. The unmaking of, featuring John Malkovich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much, man. What a treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Shameless plugging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s not shameless. That’s why we’re here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; why we’re here. It’s shameful. It’s full of no shame!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, thanks a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Thank you so much. I feel like I didn’t answer one single question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Then it’s a good interview.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/igudesman-and-joo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/igudesman-and-joo</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quintuplets and Septuplets with Jan Zehrfeld</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-background&quot;&gt;Some Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; is one of my favorite bands in the world and I was lucky enough to meet up with the band’s creative genius, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Jan Zehrfeld&lt;/a&gt;, at his home in Munich, Germany while traveling with my family. I’d met him in person once before at the Baked Potato in Los Angeles in 2013, but we didn’t really connect until I emailed him and asked him to &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;do an interview in 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jan has written some incredibly complex compositions built entirely on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuplet&quot;&gt;quintuplets and septuplets &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We thought it’d be fun to talk in-depth about what he’s done in these songs and how they work. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have with me–it’s a real honor to be with you–Jan Zehrfeld from Panzerballett. Jan, thank you so much for joining me and having me in your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Of course. Good to have you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you very much. So today, what do you want to talk about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I want to talk about quintuplets and septuplets and how I started experimenting with songs, or parts, that are based just on quintuplet feeling and septuplet feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the songs from your catalog that use quintuplets and septuplets in an interesting and novel way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, the first one is &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk.&lt;/em&gt; The idea is the first song that is just quintuplet-based. Another one is &lt;em&gt;Mahna Mahna&lt;/em&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The Muppets song?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, the Muppets song. And then there is an original composition called &lt;em&gt;Euroblast.&lt;/em&gt; I didn’t know in the beginning how to start it all, so the good start was just modifying something you already know into somethig different. Like &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;, modifying it in a way that it can fit into a quintuplet grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For people who don’t have a music theory background or don’t do much beyond a triplet, what are quintuplets and septuplets and how are you using them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: The quintuplet is basically a division of the beat into five even parts. It might be the beat in half notes and one half note can be divided into five eighth notes quintuplets notes or four quarter notes can be divided into five “notes.” Or, for instance, the way I used it was dividing one quarter note, which means four 16ths and instead of four 16ths, use five 16th quintuplets. Can you say it like that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, you’re putting five notes in the space where there’s normally four notes. In standard music notation, you don’t have to use any “signage.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: You can divide the beat into three 8th note triplets, or into four 16ths, or into five quintuplet 16ths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And a septuplet is seven instead of five.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, which is even harder. This already means that the more notes you have, the slower the tempo needs to be to perceive them so it doesn’t get muddy with notes. If you have septuplets and a fast tempo, you don’t notice a difference between septuplets and 32nd notes or sextuplets. And the fast tempo is just “brrrrrrrrrrrrrr.” For seven, it must be slower. And for quintuplets, it’s similar, but it might be faster because it’s only five notes. The thing is that for quintuplets, I didn’t have any other music to listen to that has only quintuplets and you usually learn music by hearing it and getting influenced. I didn’t have something like this, so I had to build my own stuff and it was hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Most people use quintuplets as a rhythmic device for melodies or very small phrases. If it’s used at all in a song, it’s typically used in a short span of time and used to articulate a phrase. But you’re using quintuplets and septuplets as a division of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And then you’re laying time signatures on top of those divisions, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so how does that work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, for instance it might be a good idea to choose one time signature. For guitar, you might choose 4/4 or 3/4, but 3/4… I started with 3/4. Why? Because I wanted something that had 4x4 16ths, which is 16 notes, but I changed it into one bar of 3/4 with quintuplets, which is 15, which means I have to take out one note in some place. So, it resulted in a 3/4 bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: 3/4 using quintuplets, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah. Like 1, 2, 3–DA ga di ga da, DA ga di ga da, DA ga di ga da. For guitar, it’s hard and tricky because usually in funk guitar, if you have 16 notes in a 4/4 bar, it’s [plays a funk rhythm part on guitar]. So, if you have 3/4, it’s [plays a funk rhythm part with the accented 1 beat on up and then down strokes].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And so much of what we do musically is in two because we walk in 2, our hand goes up and down, so you really have to keep track of where you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, because you have five and it changes if you have a constant down/up movement. It changes whether it’s changing to an upstroke on the downbeat in the first measure and then an upstroke in the second measure. And that’s the tricky thing about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you apply this to &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I started with the melody. You have this [plays the melody] and I started to add just two notes [plays the melody with two new notes] in every phrase. It’s like talking a sen-sentence. So you have the same kind of phrases, but more notes in every phrase to get five out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you maintain the integrity if you’re adding notes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I don’t maintain it. I just make something that I can still sell as the melody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So it’s close enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Close enough for jazz. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you count your version of &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;? Are you counting in quintuplets or are you counting in the downbeats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: In the downbeats. In the beginning, I have a 4/4 with quintuplets, which means 20 notes. The original has 16 notes. Somewhere I have to add 4 notes to it somewhere and not at the same time, but really hide it. That’s how it started. And then there is the “groove” thing. I found what fit better was the 3/4 bar instead of the 4/4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JZ: I don’t know why. It just fit better and made more sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;[Demonstration of the quintuplet groove]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: That’s for the funk groove. Then you have the bass line and I found it with 3, 2, 2, 3, which is close to a triplet feel, but it’s not. [Plays triplet version and quintuplet version.] With triplets, the first note is 33% whereas two quintuplets is 40%. It’s a little percent difference of something that’s already quite fast. But with what you call “feeling,” you have to listen closely and play precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I have to say that when I first heard the song, I couldn’t figure it out and then I heard Sebastian’s drum parts, I clearly heard quintuplets and thought, “That sounds like quintuplets. But why would they make a whole song about quintuplets?” Not thinking about you and what you do, but just like, “No one does that, so it can’t be right.” But it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; right and it did turn out after two or three months of listening, I concluded it must be quintuplets and then you confirmed it for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you even approach this? You have a whole band living in this different time space for several minutes. How do you improvise over it? You solo over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you even do that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Soloing was already the next step. The first step took us about half a year to get through the head as a band without any improvising because we were not that far, but we wanted to play it. So the first shows we played the song, we played just the head of it. We said, “Hey, we’ve got something new.” You may not be that far, but your kids will love this, like in [&lt;em&gt;Back to the Future&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Back_to_the_Future]. And then we started adding the improvisational part, which is extra work, but fun work. Exhausting, but fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so how does the septuplet stuff go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, the septuplets was a year practicing to a click like this. [&lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; 2 3 4 &lt;em&gt;5&lt;/em&gt; 6 7] It’s like a fast 7/8 bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You spent a year doing this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I spent a year learning and improvising over this feeling and learning the riffs. Not with a straight click, but with this changing click. The difference between 4 and 3 is smaller as the tempo gets faster. And when I’m doing only 4 over this click, it’s shifting around all the time. [Plays a note every 4 beats over the 4+3 click.] And then stuff like this [improvises with pentatonic scale over the 4+3 click] doing groups of 4 and 3 notes over this whole thing. Well, stuff like this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How does this prepare you for a band context when the whole band is playing? They’re not going to be playing 4+3 over and over again. That’s not how music works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: No, no. I had to learn it again because the band was playing to a different click than this or the band didn’t practice to this click. The rest of the band practiced to a different click and this kind of threw me out again because I practiced it that long with this click. The band’s click was “DA goo goo goo goDA goo goo goo.” It’s counting 8th note septuplets. [Does a rhythmic difference between the clicks.] It’s a different feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It sounds very Indian, carnatic rhythm-inspired kind of thing. I know you had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trilok_Gurtu&quot;&gt;Trilok Gurtu &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on your album. Were you going through some sort of Indian rhythm study phase? Has that been an important part of your rhythmic foundation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JZ: The Indian rhythm? No. Not at all. Not for me, but I should go there one day. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mattias-eklundh&quot;&gt;Mattias Eklund&lt;/a&gt; told me I should go there to South India but I never had this as a primary influence. I just recognized it later. Probably my influences came from there, like Meshuggah. I guess they must be inspired by those kinds of rhythms. So I guess it was a secondary influence, not a primary influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Yeah, but this septuplet thing was really challenging. So, the first rhythm that was in &lt;em&gt;Typewriter II&lt;/em&gt; was this one. [Plays a rhythm over the 4+3 click.] Again you have the first beat starting with a downstroke and then the second measure’s first beat starting with an upstroke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think &lt;a href=&quot;/share/typewriter&quot;&gt;in my cover version of that song&lt;/a&gt;, I simplified it so I could just record it. It’s so complex. The more I’ve studied your music, the more I wonder, “How do you get a whole ensemble to play like that?” And I saw you live, which blew my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, this part took us quite long to rehearse over and over in loops, really starting slowly. Collectively rehearsing this kind of groove I just played to a click and slowly building it up, rehearsing each part separately from each other and then putting it all together, we spent quite a lot of rehearsals… We don’t rehearse very much, but a big percentage of our rehearsal time was spent getting this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Where do you go with this? Is this just an exercise per song? Or is there a whole other world that’s opened up to you guys?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Both. It’s the consequence of starting with quintuplets, then going to septuplets. I don’t know where it’s going to lead, but with septuplets, there is just one example that we did that’s maybe just an exercise. But on the other hand, I think it opened up now that we’ve already rehearsed it so much, the next time we work in septuplets, it won’t take that long, I guess. Having improvised and played these parts a lot now, I think I can build something on top of it, maybe more interesting or sophisticated. I don’t know yet. I will try to go this way, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s really, really cool. I guess we’ll just have to wait until the next Panzerballett album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thanks a lot, Jan. This was extremely insightful. You’re a madman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I know. I know. What a madman? Me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: No, I’m totally normal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/quintuplets-septuplets</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/quintuplets-septuplets</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
