<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 20:12:26 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 20:12:26 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>iNFiNiEN</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;iNFiNiEN is a rock band based in Philadelphia making music for all the right reasons. They are passionate about music as art and have a huge variety of influences. Their music is fun, exploratory, dense, and beautiful. The band’s drummer, Tom Cullen, submitted their music to me via Facebook several months ago. When I finally got around to actually listening with intention, I came to realize what a talented group of people they are. I immediately knew they’d be a great fit for the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jordan Berger: Bass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tom Cullen: Drums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matt Hollenberg: Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chrissie Loftus: Vocals and Keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JTTRX8_lXBo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/infinien/infinien.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/infinien/infinien.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[“If I Were a Song” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Infinien is a really interesting rock band out of the Philadelphia area and I am really delighted that they’re here with me because it’s all I’ve been able to listen to in the last couple weeks. So, thank you guys for joining us today and I’m really excited to introduce your music to our audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Of course! We’re happy to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Thanks for having us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, of course. So, could you guys introduce yourself–names and what you play? And I’m most curious about your creative process because your songs are so interesting and they blend so many different styles and I really want to hear about your creative process for your songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Cool. I’m Chrissie [Loftus] and I play keyboards and sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: And I’m Matt [Hollenberg] and I play guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I’m Tom [Cullen], I play drums and percussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: I’m Jordan [Berger], I play bass and sing some background vocals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool, so your creative process. Who wants to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I think…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: It all started with a big bang, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Well, I guess the main thing to understand about the band is we’re all coming from different areas of music, stylistically. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We started out the band as just an outlet for jamming and exploring with no agenda of making a band, really. We just liked exploring music together and it was fun for us to have an interaction&lt;/span&gt; with–just speaking for myself, I was thrilled to play with them because it was such a different thing than what I was doing at the time, which was more metal stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I got to play all this clean, jazzy guitar style and that was just a totally fresh thing for me at the time. And then I think collectively, we got into the genre-busting music in the beginning. Obviously, we share a love of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr._Bungle&quot;&gt;Mr. Bungle&lt;/a&gt;. I think that’s pretty obvious to certain people that like Mr. Bungle. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_(Mr._Bungle_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;California&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is one of our all-time favorite records. It’s not directly an influence. We’re not trying to recreate Mr. Bungle, but just the spirit of adventurousness, free exploration, boundary smashing, off-the-wall. We love everything about the way they approach it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tUOWTmOP4FQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We got in some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Zorn&quot;&gt;John Zorn&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_Chiefs_3&quot;&gt;Secret Chiefs 3&lt;/a&gt; and that world has a little bit of a quirkiness that we maybe wanted to smooth the edge of. So, we like having the soulful vocals and the deep harmony of sort of more conventional styles of music. Maybe not more convention, but more soulful kinds of music. So obviously we love &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esperanza_Spalding&quot;&gt;Esperanza Spalding&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiatus_Kaiyote&quot;&gt;Hiatus Coyote&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MoeTar&quot;&gt;MoeTar&lt;/a&gt;, and those bands are kind of in their own world compared to Bungle and Secret Chiefs. I guess we’re coming from all over the map and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we don’t like any filler or redundancy in our songs, so by the time we’re all happy, there’s just this mish-mash of different stuff that’s very adventurous to listen to and kind of engulfs you in the sound&lt;/span&gt;. I think we’re just going for an immersive vibe with what we’re doing. I know that was a long answer, but that’s a big question. Just bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I would agree. I think our main objective is to sort of fuse all different influences to where–we love so many different types of music. Like Matt’s saying, we’re inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis&quot;&gt;Miles Davis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weather_Report&quot;&gt;Weather Report&lt;/a&gt;, and Mr. Bungle, John Zorn, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candiria&quot;&gt;Candiria&lt;/a&gt;, you know? When we create, a lot of it–that’s the concept, but the working process is probably like Matt writes material, Chrissie writes material	, and then we kind of write a song as a band based on those blueprints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, that’s pretty accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: If you listen close, you can tell the two different writing styles. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steely_Dan&quot;&gt;Steely Dan&lt;/a&gt; or–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Steely Dan! [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hall_%26_Oates&quot;&gt;Hall and Oates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We don’t sound like Steely Dan or Hall and Oates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I don’t know. If you listen close enough, you can sort of figure out who sparked the original thought for the tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Right. And then there’s other tunes we all write together. Everyone equally. And all three modes kind of have different results, so the albums just end up being all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/S74hBpQZ6LU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I wrote this one song. So…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Which one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Brand New.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: The first track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Brand New” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that’s a great song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: It was based on a rhythm Tom came up with and we all worked it out together in the room. That didn’t come from anybody, it was all working together. So certain songs, that happens. Other songs, Chrissie brings the whole thing and it’s a perfect chord progression and we just orchestrate that together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: So there’s no song that’s complete that’s being brought in. It’s at a certain point and we build it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Yeah, I’d say that. I’d say it’s just–usually the process is however we’re going to express it, being the most honest with what we’re currently feeling or what we’re influenced by. That’s kind of why I think it sounds like there’s a lot of different influences just because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;every day is a different influence and every day we’re listening to different types of music.&lt;/span&gt; There was a period where we were really getting into Indian music together. And then we found out about Ethopian music. “Oh shit!” And then everything just kind of builds on itself. It’s just honest expression, I think. That’s the best…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: We move really fast. We’re always telling each other about new music that we discover. Being inspired and influenced by the most creative, newest, weirdest music keeps us on a roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: As far as my view on the process for us, it’s like we’ve said–a lot of writing comes from Chrissie, a lot of writing comes from Matt. Basically, a lot of the divide, or the separation, is Matt tends to bring in more technically-written instrumental lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, that’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Sometimes some really active chord progressions. Chrissie more often than not will bring in a more chord progression and melody with some lyrics already written. Things like that. There’s been a couple of songs where I’ve contributed a section to, like one of Chrissie’s songs or I’ve contributed a section to a song where we were sort of all working on together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I feel that my role in the process is really more of an arranging kind of role and sort of more like, “Well here’s all these ideas, they’re all awesome. Let’s put them all together, let’s see what maybe needs to change to fit the other things that are happening around it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cb-DseJ-s30?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Or a cool chord progression, like the end of “Bottom of the Food Chain.” The ending is all [points to Jordan.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[The Bottom of the Food Chain excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, I’ve written some sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, that’s an amazing chord progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: That’s on the new record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: It’s coming from everyone. Ultimately, everyone has something new that came completely from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: The third record, especially, everyone has a voice on that and I think that’s why it’s all over the place, but it’s thematic because we play in a certain way together. So, the songs kind of have this thing that binds them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, on the third record, if you look at the inside of it, it does break it down pretty cleanly as far as who wrote what, but also what’s interesting about the song that Tom brought in the basis for, that actually credits all of us including the original bass player. It’s a really old song. That song’s called “Brand New.” It’s the first song on our newest record. That one actually credits Justin Carney, the original bassist and he did some writing in the early stages of the band as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: And Justin did, too, have the initial concept, which was cool. I remember he phoned me one time and I was–I had been playing in really obscure grindcore band called Heinous Anus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: It was a great band. Legendary band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: They were really great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: They’re worth talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: It’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: They’re very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Me and Matt collided in the metal world because his band, Cleric, at the time was doing insane shit. That was cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: They still are doing really insane stuff. Cleric is awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I guess I had broken up with that band and I was just distraught. I was fucked up, you know? It was a bad period of my life. So I started rapping and making beats. I wasn’t playing music. And Justin called me and said, “What if we”–I was also going to jazz school, learning about jazz and harmony, and I thought all the advanced harmony was really dope, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, he was like, “What if we do a really low–something with a lot of power. Heavy funk. Metal, almost. Heavy funk metal and then just christen it with this nice keyboards, jazz harmony, female vocals,” and I was like, “Let’s do it.” So I packed up my cardboard box and I went straight to Philadelphia. I swear to God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: That’s amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Yeah. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Everything except the cardboard part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: I know. I think that’s pretty funny, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: This was years ago. But yeah, Justin Carney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, Justin Carney deserves a lot of credit because he–I didn’t understand any of these chords. He wanted to use these 5- and 6-note deep chords and use polyrhythm and he’s like, “The whole thing will just be, like, swirling, man!” And I’m like, “Yeah, that’s cool!” But I didn’t know anything about that. I didn’t go to jazz school. So he taught me all that jazz stuff and kind of formed the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then through jamming, we all were exploring it together. I don’t feel like I was–I just felt like I was along for the ride. I didn’t come up with the idea because I didn’t know anything about jazz when I was 19. Nothing. I was playing metal. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WsPloykBpo8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think we’re making a lot of assumptions of the listener, so can you tell us a little bit about your band’s history and how many releases you have? What brought you together and what you’re up to now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Sure. We’ve released three–we have three releases. One is an EP, the original. It’s “How to Accept.” The first record that I was involved with is the self-titled, full-length album. It’s our first full-length album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: And the year, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: The year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Oh it was 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Oh yeah, sorry. The original EP came out in 2006. The self-titled album is 2009. And we just put out our follow-up to that. It’s a full-length record called “Light at the Endless Tunnel” that came out last year, or earlier in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: And then between those albums, we played all the damn time. Between the first two records, we played all the time throughout Philly. Basements, World Cafe, jazz cafes, metal gigs. It was tough for us because we were doing something that was totally different, yet somehow we were able, in our networking, to connect with bands that were partially like us. We’re so alienated yet somehow we were able to connect with these bands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xl0xviYz3rM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But when we weren’t in the studio dropping albums, we were out on the road. We did three tours. We went to the midwest, down south–we did three tours. We covered a lot of ground. We never got to go out west. But, yeah man, we’ve got tapes of us playing all this stuff live that we’re hoping to release. We just stayed busy. We constantly–the band’s history, too, we were always playing. We were real stern on rehearsing all the time. A couple times a week, gigging. You know, all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Love for Yourself” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: We met originally with the bass player–that was 2004. Three of us were roommates–the bass player, Matt, and I were roommates with, like, eight other people. So there was always music going on of some sort. Usually it was hip hop because a lot of people at that time, it was in college. Other people wanted to rap, you know? But what happened is we just realized we were all in different bands, so let’s just make music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I think the core, the three of us, realized we were kind of finding a voice that we hadn’t found in our other projects, so we just called Tom in and took it and just started experimenting. You know, sometimes with substances. [Laughs.] And each other, and just realizing that that was a lot of fun. Then we just started playing gigs as those came up. Mostly just playing and writing and having fun and being wild and allowing ourselves to be wild. Then Justin wound up moving to LA and he told us, “Get Jordan. This guy’s right on your level.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, Justin not only kind of helped them to stay together when they were first starting, as Tom was mentioning, but his last contribution was to recommend me, which seems to have worked out pretty well. At least, speaking personally. I’m still thrilled after all these years. I knew Justin through school. We were actually schoolmates studying basically on the same track of Temple University’s jazz studies program. We were both upright bass players at the school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: And I was there, too. So we were all in the same music school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, Chrissie was at Temple as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: It makes sense that we would have–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Matt was at Temple for a week, but that’s a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8L8IfJlgarA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: But that’s where I met him and we kind of opened each other’s eyes to different types of music and we realized that was–we were kind of both geeks in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;meeting Chrissie was way better education than the actual teachers there.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So it sounds like you guys have a mission of blending as much music as possible and that’s, to me, very evident on the third album because one song, “Oasis,” I don’t know who wrote that song but it’s a work of genius. [Laughs as everyone points to Chrissie.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u9iCmqCBXB0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s an incredible piece of music. And then, like, two or three tracks later, it’s like all of “California” from Mr. Bungle without any of the cartoon-y sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Right. Well, that’s kind of what I was saying. We kind of smooth the quirkiness a little bit. It’s more beautiful than quirky and off-putting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But then there’s another song where Chrissie is singing Indian melodies with very fast stepping between notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Light at the Endless Tunnel” excerpts]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Oh yeah, yeah. You know, that song was really influenced by that–you know that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consider_the_Source&quot;&gt;Consider the Source&lt;/a&gt; band?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, they’re awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, we toured with them our first tour and me and Gabe [Marin] go all the way back. He’d just tell me about scales. So that song is just based on this one Indian scale that’s their version of pentatonic. The whole song is that scale, so it’s kind of like our version of a raga or something, mixed with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Glass&quot;&gt;Philip Glass&lt;/a&gt; or something totally not related to that. But that was totally influenced by Consider the Source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, that makes sense. All right, so–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: You kind of hear their influence in “AYA” a little bit in moments. We play more chords than they do, so that would be the biggest difference, but yeah we really like them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s next for you guys? Tom, I think, mentioned that you’re in the studio. What’s going on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: We’re just demoing new tracks that we made, but we don’t have a concrete plans as of now, but we have another record written. So, we’re just in the process of figuring out what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nPg12O61Etk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah, if anyone’s been paying attention to the videos we’ve been releasing online, some of them have the full show of the last couple of shows that we played and there are some songs that are not released on the third record, sort of implying that there is more to come. It’s always a good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, I mentioned earlier, I took my daughter to Costco today and we were listening to your album and I said “What did you think of that?” And she said, “It was weird,” which I think is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: That’s fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But I want to know, as a band that is really focused on “new” and “different” and “mish-mash”–these are all terms I’ve heard many times so far–how are you reaching audiences and how are they receiving what you’re putting together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: I think since the third record, we’ve been amazingly well-received. We went down to North Carolina in September and played &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.progday.net/&quot;&gt;Prog Day&lt;/a&gt; and we sold out of all our CDs, we made a ton of money in merch. Everyone rushed us after we were done. People talked about us on the message board, the word got out more, so that was kind of one of the biggest hitting-the-target moments we’ve had booking-wise. All the reviews have been incredible. So the word’s getting out there. It’s just us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We’re strictly DIY. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We don’t have a promotion team, we didn’t hire PR, we don’t have a booking agent.&lt;/span&gt; It’s just us and considering that, the album is standing on its own pretty well. I got a message from Italy the other day, this guy who’s just obsessed with it, he’s trying to get us over there. I don’t push us over there, it’s just getting around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In the age of the internet and the sort of bleak musical economic environment, for a band like us, that’s a good sign. It’s a reason to be optimistic about the future, you know? We’re not making a lot of money, but our goals were artistic, not commercial, and I think we’re all satisfied in that way. And I think that’s what the band’s about. It’s not about what’s working right now in the industry, what’s selling right now, how many likes and followers we have. No, it’s about the record. It’s about the substance and I think that’s what we’re bringing that’s countering a lot of what’s going on.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Worth the Wait” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I’ll answer this with two answers. It’s difficult for us to attain mass appeal. We gotta understand that from the jump. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But there are millions of people that like weird music.&lt;/span&gt; First thing we did when we dropped the album is we started contacting as many people as we could to get reviews. The reviews were outstanding. We couldn’t–I mean, people were just saying the most amazing stuff. It’s almost like–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We’re humbled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We played last week and someone came up to me and was like, “You’re my favorite band.” I was like, “This is my favorite band!” I couldn’t lie. I was like, “When I go to sleep, I think of music that’s dope and cool.” This is what I imagine.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: That’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: It’s been very well received to the right people. Mass appeal? No. But the people who do like this type of music will love it. It’s been a great year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah yeah. So far, the internet’s been really nice to connect us and we’ve been getting a little bit more word of mouth spreading this year. It’s been fun. It’s been nice to see that we can put an album out and people are actually reacting to it. It’s not just like, “Oh, there’s another album on bandcamp,” you know? Everybody does that, and it’s important to do that because you’ve gotta make your stuff available however you can, but it’s nice to see that people are actually checking it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5qY8arvbQCI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, it’s nice not to be ignored because there’s so much out there and most stuff does get ignored. I feel like the people that are connecting with what we are doing, it really means something to them. And I guess for me personally, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the low-to-the-ground approach is better in the long run because 5-10 years from now, you’ll still have those people whereas if you just make a catchy song and a million people get into it for two months, and then they leave, what did you really build there?&lt;/span&gt; It just seems like, “Let’s go up the roller coaster and get off.” I would want something more permanent than that. I like to think that we’ve attained that. I don’t really know, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I would classify your music as art. And that’s what I’m after. True artists who use music as their form of expression. So, it’s funny. Tom wrote to me months ago, I don’t remember–I think you just said, “Hey, here’s my stuff,” and I get a lot of those emails, but when I heard “Oasis,” I was like, “I gotta check this out later.” And when I listened with real intention, I was like, “Oh my goodness, these guys are awesome.” [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Thank you so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: We really appreciate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so what’s going on in 2018 for you and where can people find out more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Well, we’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=122617694436220&amp;amp;ref=br_rs&quot;&gt;on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, we’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://infinien.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;on Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;, we’re exploring booking options right now, we’re demoing new stuff, there’ll be a new release sometime.. In the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When it’s ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Right, when it’s ready is the key there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: But, way sooner than the other–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, there was a bit of a gap between the self-titled album and the “Light at the Endless Tunnel” unfortunately. But that’s definitely not going to be the case this time. We can say that for sure. We can also say the four of us are very committed to making this record better than the one we just put out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah, that’s very true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We had the same mentality when we made “Light at the Endless Tunnel,” which was like, “We put our heart and soul into the Infinien record,” which is why we had to call it that. We couldn’t come up with a title because it was just like, “Well, this is everything we are,” so that’s why that record was self-titled. But I’m sorry, a little bit of a digression there. But, yeah, when we made the third one, it was like, “It has to sound better, we have to do this, we have to do that.” And it totally fueled us. We put together an orchestra. That was a weird dream–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: That was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: that we took into reality. All of a sudden we were standing–there’s a video of us online recording next to two enormous orchestra-sized harps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aVuFmuShkyE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, there’s like 4 harps on that track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: And it’s real! Those aren’t fake instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: That was a total mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: That was so beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: That’s also in the credits. You can see the list of orchestral players. I was lucky enough to play upright bass on that, too. Saved us a little bit of bread. [Laughs.] But anyway, yeah we’re very committed to making a new release that is even better than the third one, which we’re pretty happy with. All things considered. We can rest easy knowing that we made a really solid album. Or at least I can. Are you guys sleeping all right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: This next album is–like I said, these guys are my favorite band and this next album is just so, so good. I don’t even know what to say. I’m excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: There’s no album yet, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: This year. Maybe not. I hope so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: I feel like one of the reasons why people who like it really like it is because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we’ve always been honest with ourselves and I think that maybe it’s not going to be popular, but it’s our truth and the truth is undeniable.&lt;/span&gt; So, when you’re honest with the way you need to express it, then somebody somewhere out there who’s gets it is going to get it. So, I feel like we can always be proud of what we’ve done because we’ve always been doing it honestly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We never did anything we didn’t want to do to get more people into the band. Ever. Everything was based on curiosity, exploration, innocence.&lt;/span&gt; None of us are innocent, but you know what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I also feel like what I like so much about what we’ve found is that it’s a mix between chaos and beauty. I think that that’s the whole universe. Maybe that’s what weird music is. It’s not just beautiful, it’s not just chaotic, but it’s the blend.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, I totally agree with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: It kind of captures you in all of your facets. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I would love to explore that chaos and order. That’s been a major theme going on the last few months in the philosophy I’ve been reading, but we don’t really have time for that. [Laughs.] So for anyone who’s new to you guys, what’s the best way to find out about you, find out more, and what’s the best way to support you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We’re on Facebook, Instagram, and all the recorded music is available to check out on Bandcamp and all of the other streaming services. Spotify, Google Play Music, Apple Music, Amazon. I believe it’s available. A friend of ours has a joke that you should have a t-shirt that says sorry I missed your gig. And there’s another t-shirt that says, “My music is highly available.” Anyway, Facebook is probably–between Facebook and Instagram is probably the best way to keep in touch as far as that goes. But, I’ve always said this to anybody who’s been interested in the band. Shoot us an email! It’s the band’s name at gmail.com [infinien@gmail.com].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, we like hearing from people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We like people reaching out to us. It’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: It’s a core group of people right now, so it’s very community-esque. Don’t feel like we’re on an ivory tower. We love hearing from fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah and if you go to Bandcamp, you can find our whole collection. You can get our CDs, t-shirts, there’s some merch, a biography, and some stuff. If you want to see us, YouTube. We’re building our content this year, so expect more videos coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6_frjTIDeZA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: You keep mentioning “Oasis,” there is a really good capture of that song that we just released on YouTube through a company called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sun_Sessions&quot;&gt;Sun Sessions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I saw it. It’s all solar-powered. That was so cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: It is really cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Oasis” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: And then we just happened to be–it was the last hot day of last year. It was already starting to be a cold fall and then it was just this one day of abundant sunshine and it was like, “Jeez, it’s almost 80 degrees out.” It was kind of weird, so now we’re releasing in winter these sunny videos. But yeah, that’s a good capture of that. If you like that, there’s probably–a little bird told me there’s another one of those videos coming out soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, cool. Thank you guys so much for your time. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Thank you so much&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Thank you so much. I was going to say the best way to support us is what you’re doing. You’re spreading the word and you listen. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Keep making weird music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: And hit us up on Skype! [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JB: Thank you so much for having us. Infinien is a band we all believe in so dearly. We put so much energy into it and we just love so much that it is contagious. It seems to be, anyway. We just want to keep spreading it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/infinien/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/infinien/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>California Guitar Trio Plays Daydreaming By Radiohead</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cgtrio.com&quot;&gt;The California Guitar Trio&lt;/a&gt; performed a show at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mim.org&quot;&gt;Musical Instrument Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Phoenix, Arizona on February 24, 2018. Before the show, we spent about an hour talking and filmed a great interview, which should be online and available later this month. In the meantime, I wanted to release this beautiful performance of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiohead&quot;&gt;Radiohead&lt;/a&gt;’s song &lt;em&gt;Daydreaming&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our first 4K video release, too. So, hopefully you high-fidelity video fans enjoy that! It’s still new to me, but I’m happy with how it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SBW5DMA1rvU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here’s the original music video by Radiohead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TTAU7lLDZYU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/california-guitar-trio/daydreaming</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/california-guitar-trio/daydreaming</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Taurus Bulba E Mixolydian Riffage</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-this-riff&quot;&gt;Why This Riff?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most innovative guitarists to ever live. This riff from his 1996 release &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_Garden&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fire Garden&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has always impressed me since I learned it over 20 years ago. It’s artistic, fun, and caters especially to the instrument. When you actually play this lick, you can really appreciate the intricacies and the craft that went into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fire-garden/190372450&quot;&gt;Purchase Steve Vai’s Fire Garden on Apple Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-apple&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always been one of my favorite go-to riffs that I play to warm up. It’s fun, difficult, and in the key of A (E mixolydian), so it’s hard to play a wrong note since the guitar is basically built for the keys of A and E.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the instructional video for this piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kRR1UtuUlZA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soundslice-notation&quot;&gt;Soundslice Notation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/150973/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/taurus-bulba</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/taurus-bulba</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nora Germain</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nora Germain is a multi-talented powerhouse of music, energy, and inspiration. She sings, she dances, she rips it up on the violin, she writes books, and more. I first heard about Nora through &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; when he told me about her involvement in the &lt;a href=&quot;/share/tiny-orchestral-moments&quot;&gt;Tiny Orchestral Moments&lt;/a&gt; project. Steve got us in touch and we got this interview filmed in December 2017 while she was visiting Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DffgiVSWQZE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/nora-germain/nora-germain.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/nora-germain/nora-germain.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Nora Germain is a jazz violinist and singer out of LA and she is joining us to talk a little bit about her new album, called Nora, and about some of the challenges of being an artist in today’s musical climate. So, Nora, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Thank you for having me, it’s a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. So, I’m really thrilled that you could be here. I’ve talked to &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt;, a mutual friend, about you many months ago and I saw how busy you were. I thought, “Wow, it’d be really cool to talk to her, but I don’t know if the stars will ever align. So, thanks a lot. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Of course, of course. I’m very excited. &lt;a href=&quot;/shirts&quot;&gt;Everybody I know wears your t-shirt&lt;/a&gt;, so I feel like I’m part of the gang now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, well I’ll have to mail one out to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: I’d love to have one. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Nora, can you give us a brief history of your musical career and then tell us a little about your new album?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Sure, so I started playing violin when I was really small. My parents were both violinists. When I was 15, I found an interest in playing jazz, so I sort of switched from classical violin to jazz. And then two or three years ago, I realized that I really wanted to sing. I didn’t really realize I wanted to do that until kind of later on. I’d already been playing music for 20 years or whatever. So I made some jazz violin albums and then slowly started to introduce the voice into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then in the last year or so, maybe two years even after I started singing jazz, I thought, “Well, maybe I should write my own music.” So I started exploring with this last record a sort of funk and pop sound because I love that stuff so much. And right now, I’m kind of working on how to make my jazz violin sound work with the original music that I am doing kind of as one big world. So, we’ll see how it goes. This record I did, this one that just came out, is sort of my first attempt at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m a big believer that you have to actually do something to know if it works. You can’t just think about if it would hypothetically work. You have to really try it and find out.&lt;/span&gt; So I’m learning a lot about myself and all that, going through the process, but it’s been a lot of fun. So, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZuyTYmQ_BcA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us about the world of jazz violin? I saw a quote on your website that might have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Taylor_(guitarist)&quot;&gt;Martin Taylor &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I forget who it was. It said that you’re keeping the world of jazz violin alive. I didn’t know there was a “world of jazz violin.” I imagine there’s a history, it’s just not an instrument that we normally associate with jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah, well, I mean people should associate violin with jazz because the violin was a very integral part of the blues music that jazz came out of, so the violin was kind of part of it even before the saxophone, which is a much newer instrument than the violin. The violin as we know it now has been around for 400, almost 500 years. Most of the violinists, the great jazz violinists, are from the past. There are a few living today who are great, but people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Nance&quot;&gt;Ray Nance &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuff_Smith&quot;&gt;Stuff Smith &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who played in a lot of the big bands, they were very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P_lrTmLknNA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then there was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Venuti&quot;&gt;Joe Venuti &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_South&quot;&gt;Eddie South &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who were one of the inspirations to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Django_Reinhardt&quot;&gt;Django Reinhardt &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St%C3%A9phane_Grappelli&quot;&gt;Stéphane Grappelli &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who of course were &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quintette_du_Hot_Club_de_France&quot;&gt;the first European all-string band &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And that, obviously, changed the world as well. Stéphane Grappelli is probably my favorite of all of them. But, there are a lot! Throughout history you find a lot of them. Most of them were American, but once Stéphane Grappelli and Django Reinhardt became famous, then this wave of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gypsy_jazz&quot;&gt;Gypsy Jazz &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came around and then you see a lot of all-string jazz bands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, especially this year and last year, I’ve seen there’s been a huge renaissance of that for some reason, which is very exciting. The violin in jazz was a lot more popular in the last century, but now because of this gypsy jazz renaissance, it’s becoming more popular and there are quite a few young people around the world who play jazz violin. But I don’t see that many violinists these days using what I use in the band, which is piano, bass, drums, and guitar for more of that kind of traditional American sound rather than the gypsy sound, which usually doesn’t have piano or drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, there’s definitely a world for it and I hope that I can continue to bring it more into the forefront of music rather than kind of a niche thing because I really do think, just like any other jazz instrument, it should be something that everybody can hear once in their life. But, yeah, there is a world for it, it’s just a little bit in the background right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve spoken to several out-of-the-box classical musicians and people who were trained with a classical background that ended up in the world of improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s not normally something that’s taught on classical instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: No, it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What was your background in moving from–I would assume you learned classically first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah, I did. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you get into improvisation and jazz, specifically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MpsLWI2vLHY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: There are a lot of ways to improvise on string instruments. There’s a lot of improvisation on American fiddle music and Celtic music. A lot of those fiddle tunes have a lot of–you sort of learn the tune and then you kind of make it your own and sort of pass it around a group of people. That was one of the first ideas I had about improvisation, was learning a lot of different styles of fiddle music and kind of making up my own fiddle tunes that were loosely based on the ones that I knew before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But then the jazz thing came around when I heard Stéphane Grappelli. I really remember the moment, it really changed my life.&lt;/span&gt; I heard it and it was a funny thing. I heard it and I felt like I already knew how to do it even though I didn’t know how to do it, but I heard it and I thought, “Oh yeah, I can do that.” Even though it took me many years to actually do it. [Laughs.] But, yeah, string instruments are not usually used to improvise, which is a shame because we see–to take another example, dancers, there’s all different types of dancers. There’s ballet dancers, modern dancers, tap dancers, flamenco dancers. And if you grow up as a ballerina, you might not have the kind of swag that a tap dancer has, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think it’s all about taking different things in and figuring out what speaks to you because if it speaks to you, you can probably do it.&lt;/span&gt; That’s what I’ve found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HfwouH794jI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I watched a video of you playing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy_Emmanuel&quot;&gt;Tommy Emmanuel &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He’s one of my heroes. I attended one of his master classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Oh yeah, he’s great. I love him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But, I think I saw in one of the comments that you guys hadn’t even rehearsed the songs you performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: No. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I heard so many influences, particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_O%27Connor&quot;&gt;Mark O’Connor &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in your improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I was just floored at your ability to play over these changes, especially–I mean, obviously, the song and Tommy’s an incredible musician himself, but to see you two just getting up and playing–do you attribute that to your bluegrass study or is it just something that you started doing when you were young and it’s natural to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, obviously, when you play with somebody who’s so great and you feel like you can click like that, you don’t really have to think about what you’re doing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s like saying, “How do you go to a restaurant with your best friend and not get into an argument?” Well, you just sit down and you have a great time.&lt;/span&gt; There is no argument. It’s a very effortless thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The things that do take effort are, obviously, being able to play at fast tempos. You have to work on that. You have to keep yourself pretty loose. Practicing songs in all of the different keys so that if somebody says, “Let’s play this” in a different key than you’re used to and you’re in front of a thousand people, you don’t panic. You can just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stage presence is something I work on, making the audience feel like I care that they are there and not just taking them for granted. And really playing so that they can enjoy themselves, not so that I can enjoy that they’re enjoying me. There definitely are skills that are part of that, I think, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I feel like the less you think, the easier it is.&lt;/span&gt; I really–you have to think about it when you practice and you have to think about it when you’re researching things. If you go to school, you have to think about it then, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when you’re in the moment of actually doing it, you have to let it all go otherwise you’re not really there.&lt;/span&gt; You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You won’t be able to use all this background information that you’re consciousness kind of has. It’s not really words. It’s kind of like feelings. I don’t know exactly how to explain it. What I’m trying to say is that if you just let yourself be natural, there is all sorts of help that you already have to making whatever you’re trying to do great without overthinking it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, the knowledge is already there. You’re just losing any of the firewalls that stand between you and connecting with the music at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, right. I’m not saying that I could have done that the same way when I was 10 years old. I’ve been practicing for a long time. Obviously, it’s not just automatic, but once you have the skill down, if you just let your mind go quiet and just enjoy it, it’ll always be much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I couldn’t believe how fast you guys were playing. Not just performing, but playing off of each other and spur-of-the-moment decisions… As a musician myself, I saw what you were doing and I thought, “Oh my goodness, they’re at a whole other level of communication.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well yeah! That’s what I’m saying. If you stop thinking about it, you can actually communicate really quickly between people. Like if you watch any of the great performers. If you watch the Rat Pack or anybody in any genre, you always see this kind of instantaneous thing and you realize people are not really communicating using regular communication techniques of human life. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Tommy and I are not going to talk about what we’re going to do. I don’t have to look at him for him to know what he needs to do. You just kind of let it run free. It takes a little bit of telekinesis, maybe, but I think that humans do already possess a bit of telekinesis.&lt;/span&gt; I think it’s possible. Maybe not in the, you know, conspiracy sense where I could think of an object and you would tell me what the object is. But certainly in a way that if two people have a vision in mind and they don’t really think about much else, that vision will probably come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you said you’re trying to put some ideas together in the context of who you are and what you’re capable of doing and this new album is an expression of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah, right. I’m definitely trying to do something new. Always something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the things that you feel are “new” about this record and who you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s so easy for people to say, “Oh, I’ve seen you do ‘this,’ therefore you’re this one thing.”&lt;/span&gt; “Nora, you’re a great jazz violinist, so why would you ever try another style?” I just think life is short and you don’t want to save anything for the next go-around because you’re not sure if you’re going to get one. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, you might as well try everything that you love right now even if it comes out a little bit messy in the beginning.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People might say, “Oh, you needed more time in the studio,” or, “You should have re-recorded that vocal,” or, “Your videos are not the greatest thing I’ve ever seen.” That’s fine and I’m fine to take criticism because at least I have experiments that I’m doing. You know? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’d much rather find out by doing something and releasing it, find out what I like about it, what I don’t like, what I can do better, what I might do again, what I might not do again, and then change accordingly or not change accordingly, rather than not test anything out and just never sing and never dance and never write anything and never make any music videos. I just think it’s so much better to experiment, even if sometimes you have to learn some hard lessons. But God, why shy away from that?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Done is better than perfect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: I think so. Maybe at this stage. I’m not sure if I’m going to keep going–you don’t want to experiment in the same way when you’re young as when you’re older because hopefully when you’re older you’ve gotten a lot of that stuff out of the way. But, I’m 26. I’m on the young side of life. I have an opportunity to do something, maybe, that hasn’t exactly been done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Who says that you can’t have a show when you sing a pop song and then you play a lovely ballad on the violin? Or, whatever! Who says that you have to do any one thing? So, I guess I’m just trying to figure out how to put it all together, but definitely don’t want to have any passion that I don’t test out. That would be–to me, that would be a big mistake because you always want to try anything that speaks to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: In the spirit of youth and experimentation, one of the things that drew me to you recently was a Facebook comment thread [laughs].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Oh, God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I don’t normally get into these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: You ought not to. You ought not to, that’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, but you had addressed some of the challenges of being an artist in today’s world of streaming and financial ruin or whatever where I think older people have a sense of, “This is how the industry used to be and now it’s not this anymore.” As a young up-and-comer in the music industry, can you talk a little about your beliefs and some of the spirit of these kinds of discussions? What you see and where you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, one thing about being a millennial is you have nothing to compare this disastrous non-industry to, so that’s very comfortable in a sense because I can’t sit around and say, “Oh, back in the 70s” or “back in the 80s things were so great” because I wasn’t alive then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The idea of making money off of people buying your records, making thousands and thousands of dollars off of that, even as a small artist, that to me sounds kind of crazy. Who’s going to buy them?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of these discussions, generally there’s a few different sides of it. There’s usually some kind of a pessimist who says, “It’s all over and there’s no point in anything anymore.” And then there’s somebody who’s usually very ignorant who says, “Oh, but I support artists because I stream their music and hopefully they see some kind of revenue from that.” And then you see some kind of a tech person who says, “Oh, it’s just the kinks. It’ll all get worked out. There’ll be a future with different types of revenue streams.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then you find somebody who takes things into their own hands and says, “Well fuck the whole industry. I’ve got my Patreon and I’ll be fine.” And then maybe you find somebody who’s still kind of clinging on to what once was and thinks they can get a major record deal and, for better or worse, they can kind of make it work. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m kind of all of those people wrapped into one, I guess, because I do believe that we’re in kind of a dire situation, but I also believe that we don’t know what is going to happen with the music industry five or ten or a hundred years from now.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are ways that we purchase and consume music that nobody could conceive of a while back, so obviously there are going to be new ways that come up that people haven’t thought of yet. But yeah, I’m trying to figure it out. I don’t think that anybody really has a total answer for you, even somebody who would say, “Oh yeah, I know what’s going to happen,” or, “I know the best way to make a living as an artist.” They’re probably just lying to you because I think that every artist has their own possibilities for making money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Again, you just have to try stuff. You really can’t just sit on your couch thinking, “Oh, maybe I could try this. Maybe I could do that. Maybe I can sell 500 records doing this. Or maybe…”&lt;/span&gt; You really have to try, so that’s kind of the route that I take. I just try what seems appealing to me and I learn from doing it. I’ve done a couple of crowd-funding campaigns that were really successful and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/noragermainlovesyou&quot;&gt;I’m thinking of going over to Patreon next &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-patreon&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I play with other people and I do recording sessions and things. It’s a hodge-podge, but we’re in a transition so you’ve gotta try stuff if you want to make it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4zH9Zca1vRM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so I see you forming a lot of one-offs with a broad variety of artists. You’ve recorded with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knower_(band)&quot;&gt;Knower &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and you’ve performed with Tommy Emmanuel and Martin Taylor. Kind of two ends of pretty different spectrums, you know? How are you reaching out to these people and connecting with them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, with Louis [Cole] and Genevieve [Artadi], I used to live with them so I’ve recorded on a few different projects for Louis and he used to play drums with my group sometimes. Genevieve would sing with my group now and again and I’m in a few of their music videos as well, so we were just roommates that were trying to help each other out whenever we could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But in general, one thing I really believe in in my life is if you get in touch with people, some of the time they will respond. I mean, a lot of people don’t even believe that is true. I think of a list of people I want to work with and I write to them and tell them I want to work with them on something. I’ll ask if I can be a guest on their show or if they want to have me on their record. Some of the time it does happen and it’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I think you just have to reach out to people and be honest and try to see in your mind what you want to do with them before you ask them. It would be great for me to work with Elton John, for example, but I haven’t really thought about–I guess now I could. I haven’t thought about exactly what he and I would do together, so I would probably have it in my mind, like when I did a show, Postmodern Jukebox, last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There was a video we did that got some pretty good views. When they reached out to me to be in the video, they had an idea. They had a song they wanted to do, they knew how they wanted the violin to be featured. Once you reach out to somebody, you want to kind of envision it so that if they get back to you and say, “Well, sure, that sounds cool. What do you want to do?” You’re not thinking, “Well, uh…” You want to have something in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If people reach out to me and say they want to work with me, I’d definitely consider it because we’re artists. We want to create stuff. We want to have fun. And it’s great to share audiences.&lt;/span&gt; It’s great when my audience will discover somebody new or somebody else, discover me, whatever. That’s kind of what it’s all about. I like to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Speaking of collaborations, you worked with Steve Ball and lots of the crafty guitar crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Recently on &lt;a href=&quot;/share/tiny-orchestral-moments-2017&quot;&gt;Tiny Orchestral Moments&lt;/a&gt; projects. How’d you get connected to them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Okay, so that happened through my brother. My brother was involved with those projects and he’s been a crafty for a long time and he’s known Steve for a long time. They were in Los Angeles working on a different project, happened to be my birthday actually, and Carl [Germain] was in LA and he said, “Well, I can’t really hang out with you, but why don’t you come to this rehearsal and hang out and listen?” And I said, “Okay, great!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vcXo3owlGpY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I came and I had my violin because I always have my violin and Steve and Paul Richards from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Guitar_Trio&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who I’ve also worked with, they invited me to play on this tune called Blockhead. I think there’s a video of it somewhere, but–so I just jumped in. I didn’t know what I was doing. It’s like twenty-five guitar players and me, you know? But Steve thought it was cool and fun and wacky and whatever, so I think he was kind of interested in breaking out of the traditional guitar craft modalities and sort of getting into something a little bit more out-of-the-box, inviting other types of instruments to play along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So he decided to do this Tiny Orchestral Moments thing. We’ve done two projects with that. I’ve been a part of both of them and I’ve made some amazing friends. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/julie-slick&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt; has been on two of them, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Petra_Haden&quot;&gt;Petra Haden &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was on one of them, who’s an amazing violinist, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigel_Gavin&quot;&gt;Nigel Gavin &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who’s a long-time crafty and an amazing kind of world music musician. My brother and I have gotten closer doing it and I got to record with California Guitar Trio on their last album because of this collaboration. It’s been a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I never would have considered that I would do something like this, necessarily, but music is an amazing thing because you can’t really be hurt by it. There’s nobody’s life that is at stake when you try something new. You just jump in and see how it goes. Most of the time, it’s a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MogTq30DMYU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One thing I really appreciate about your music is there’s a recurring theme of being yourself, expressing yourself, being true to yourself. Can you talk a little about that and where that motivation is coming from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, I think I was a victim of repressing a lot of my own creative passions for a long time. [Laughs.] And I only realized that kind of recently. A couple years ago. I grew up singing and dancing and playing piano and I–oh my God, I did so many different types of dance. I was a really creative person, really creative kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Violin was always something I took very seriously, but I had a lot of other talents. I was in musicals and I did all sorts of stuff. And then when high school came around I discovered jazz, I thought, “I want to be the best in the world at this thing and I want to bring this thing back. I want to hold the torch up. I want people to love jazz violin.” And that became a very deep focus for me for about ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In high school and then at both of the colleges that I went to, I really focused on that. And also because I didn’t really have any jazz violin teachers except for one briefly–I took lessons with the late John Blake Jr. who’s an amazing player, but that was only for one semester. So basically for nine and a half years, I was on my own. I didn’t really have any jazz violin teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I guess because I had to study so hard and I had to figure so much stuff out, I didn’t really sing or dance or write anything because I just wanted to be good at this one thing. It’s like hyper-focused. And I’m very grateful for that because I love the way I sound now and I really am proud of how far I’ve come with that. It was not easy. But anyway, a couple years ago I thought, “You know, there’s this whole side of me that I kind of left in the dark.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, being yourself, expressing yourself, is really about remembering who you were when you were a kid, who you were before you cared about if people were going to subscribe to your stupid YouTube channel and all that stuff&lt;/span&gt;, which matters. It definitely matters, but you’re not going to live a rich life if you’re blocking out… “Oh I can’t do this, I can’t do that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not who you are that holds you back, it’s who you think you’re not that holds you back.&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs.] So, it can be messy. I’m not saying it’s easy to incorporate all of your interests. And maybe some of your interests just are hobbies. I’m not saying that everything you love in life has to be part of your commercial product, but I definitely think if there’s a part of you that you kind of left when you were a kid, if there’s a skill that you had or something that really gave you a lot of joy, you don’t have to start from scratch. You just have to remember how to do it again because you did know how to do it before. If that makes any sense…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZPAmDULCVrU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I’m just trying to not let anything go. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I just want to be myself and all of my favorite performers are people who do lots of different things.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Gaga&quot;&gt;Lady Gaga &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; comes to mind. She’s done so much different art, but it’s all very authentic because it all really comes from her. She can sit down at the piano and that’s one mood and she can light herself on fire or whatever she’s doing and then make a record with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Bennett&quot;&gt;Tony Bennett &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then be on stage with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica&quot;&gt;Metallica &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s all available to you. You know? You don’t have to close yourself off. So that’s kind of the place I’m at now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That is awesome. That’s ultimately what this Make Weird Music website is about. I get a lot of people reaching out just sending me some of the most outlandish music you’ve ever heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Sure. Sure, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: While I appreciate that about the word “weird,” mostly I want people to be connecting with who they are because we’re all unique and weird in our own way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes we are. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, yeah, I completely resonate with that and I’m really appreciative that there are artists like you who not only are virtuosic and incredible at what they do, but see that the picture’s not completely dry yet. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s still plenty of time to keep working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, right. And also just letting go of the fact of the idea that it has to be perfect the first time you try it. You know? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I just feel the things you create don’t have to be masterpieces the first time you create them.&lt;/span&gt; I guess there’s a whole school of thought about “Should you release something that’s an experiment? Or should you not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People can go back and forth about that. You know, “you should only release the stuff that’s absolute perfection” or “you should release everything and the chips will fall where they may” and then there’s everywhere in between. But if you’re going to try something new or try something that you used to know, but you’ve left it and now you want to bring it back, you can see the total person and not just an adult version of yourself. It’s okay for it to be a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m not saying this album that I did is my full and total potential, but definitely it’s a new thing and it’s a step in a direction that I’ve never taken before. That definitely makes me proud, so there you go! [Laughs.] I’m proud of my mistakes!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. All right, so where can people find out more about you and your music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Right, okay, so I have a website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://noragermain.com&quot;&gt;noragermain.com &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-external-link-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And I’m on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/nora_germain/&quot;&gt;instagram &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/noragermainmusic/&quot;&gt;Facebook &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-facebook&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and everything. But my website is kind of the hub for everything. I’ve got my videos and biography and some links to other stuff, so definitely go to my website. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Cool. Thank you so much for taking some time out of my day to talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Of course, I’m so happy to be included in your community and I’m thrilled. I consider it a badge of honor that you think I’m weird enough. I love it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs.] Well, I don’t think anyone would listen to the music and go, “That’s really weird,” but I think it’s what you’re doing, the way you’re doing it, it’s just another definition of “weird.” You’re being true to who you are and I think it’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes, well thank you and thank you for being true to who you are by doing all of this. You’re doing an amazing thing. People should remember that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you. Sweet. That’s very kind of you. All right, thank you so much. It was really great spending time with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NG: You too!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/nora-germain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/nora-germain/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aspirations by Gentle Giant feat. Keneally, West, Green, Mortimore</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;aspirations&quot;&gt;Aspirations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of my favorite Gentle Giant songs and I was incredibly honored to be asked to join such tremendous musicians on stage for this performance. Never in my wildest dreams did I think I’d have an opportunity like this. Gary Green was a guitar hero for me growing up, and to look over to make eye contact while performing music with him is just indescribable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qNHidpbISNo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was performed live in October 2017 in Albuquerque, New Mexico for the 2017 &lt;a href=&quot;https://gorgg.org&quot;&gt;GORGG&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/gorgg-2017/aspirations</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/gorgg-2017/aspirations</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jan Zehrfeld Guitar Clinic</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;concert-trailer&quot;&gt;CONCERT TRAILER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DP2bb2Yu_Oc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incredible &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Jan Zehrfeld&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; will be offering a guitar clinic at our HQ (my living room). He’ll be covering fretboard navigation; 4-note chord voicings for 6-, 7-, and 8-string guitar players; and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nvite.com/JanZehrfeld&quot;&gt;Purchase tickets for the guitar clinic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-ticket-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Proceeds will go directly toward reimbursing our airfare and hotel costs for Jan.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-thanks&quot;&gt;SPECIAL THANKS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to our awesome sponsors Ed at &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mad Hatter Guitar Products&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fas fa-external-link-square-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Bobby at &lt;a href=&quot;http://guitaranswerguy.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Guitar Answer Guy&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fas fa-external-link-square-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks also to the &lt;a href=&quot;/support&quot;&gt;generous donations we’ve received online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/jan-zehrfeld-2018-clinic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/jan-zehrfeld-2018-clinic/</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Support Make Weird Music on Patreon</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/link/mwm-on-patreon</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/link/mwm-on-patreon</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electric Gauchos</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We first highlighted &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball in October 2016&lt;/a&gt; after having discovered the kinship of our spirits and aims. Since then, Steve and I have gotten to know each other fairly well. He invited me to join him and several others for a Seattle Guitar Work Weekend in June 2017, which coincided with a &lt;a href=&quot;/share/king-crimson-concert-2017&quot;&gt;King Crimson Friends and Family concert&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/david-singleton&quot;&gt;an interview with KC’s tour manager, David Singleton&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide&quot;&gt;an interview with virtuoso guitarist Alex Anthony Faide&lt;/a&gt;. It was a productive weekend, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve is as prolific as he is kind and generous. He’s one of the hardest-working people I know. One of his many, many musical projects is a group called Electric Gauchos. One of Electric Gauchos’ releases is a 9-CD box set featuring tons of improvised and composed music in studio and live recordings. It’s a lot to digest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we thought it’d be cool if we filmed a conversation with Alex Anthony Faide about the history and releases of the band. And here we are! Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K5IW_C5eeMw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/electric-gauchos/electric-gauchos.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/electric-gauchos/electric-gauchos.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I don’t know if you want to cover anything in particular or just want to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.electricgauchos.com&quot;&gt;Electric Gauchos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: We probably want to start by telling a little history about–maybe building on what Alex just talked about. The fact that we’ve been playing together for 23 years, 24 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: We met in Argentina? Or was it Grossderschau?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: No no, it was Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Argentina first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: ‘95.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: 1995. I was down working with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; spinoff group called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sBJED4MMWgg&quot;&gt;Los Gauchos Alemanes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which–what the hell does that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sBJED4MMWgg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Los Gauchos Alemanes. Gaucho is the Argentinian cowboy and alemanes is the Spanish denomination for German people. I think the first name that came out was Les Gauchos Allemandes [French].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Aah, the French.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Right, the French version. And Los Gauchos Alemanes were a bunch of German immigrants south of Argentina, like 1880-something. Last century. So, Argentine people would call, “Ah! El gaucho aleman! El gaucho aleman gringo.” So, Los Gauchos Alemanes were this pack of–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Dogs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Insane people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Very, very old people, also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Why were they old?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Well, they’re from the 1800s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool, so what happened? This group spun off out of the Argentina group in the mid-90s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Actually it spun out of initially the original early days of Guitar Craft. In 1992, everyone was essentially sent home to do application and assimilation of what we’d learned for the last seven years and so, Martin Schwutke from the very early days of Guitar Craft went off to Germany and bought a house in Grossderschau and a bunch of us went there to work and continue playing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The original Gauchos Alemanes was formed there with Hernan Nunez, Fernando Kabusacki, and Martin Schwutke. I visited a couple of summers in a row and some Argentinians came up to visit as well. It was clear that Argentina was going to become a next center of gravity for guitar work. So, I started commuting down to Argentina and went down to a level one course there in a place called Gandara, which is outside of Buenos Aires somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Yes, like a few miles south into the pampa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3SVPtmy8ziA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: And so, the Gauchos–we took &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discogs.com/Los-Gauchos-Alemanes-Little-Beast/release/2934111&quot;&gt;our feeble repertoire &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; into Argentina and met some incredible players who then changed the expectation and the level of our playing. Some collaborations began and we met and hit it off musically. We did a little spin-off after Los Gauchos Alemanes, playing for a couple years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I really wanted to play with a drummer. This music we were writing and all the stuff we were doing, to me, was missing a rhythmic element that–I was really hungry to play with a drummer. So Fernando Kabusacki had been playing with a well-known Argentinian drummer named Fernando Samalea, so we got together with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kabusacki.com.ar&quot;&gt;Fernando Kabusacki &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/mistermartynumber9&quot;&gt;Martin Schwutke &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/samaleaoficial/&quot;&gt;Fernando Samalea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and I think we went into a studio for a few days and wrote some…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: We went first to Mendoza and we went right into the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Ah yeah, Mendoza. We did some writing and maybe a show or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Yeah, two shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: At &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/pages/Estudio-De-Danza-Contempor%25C3%25A1nea-Luc%25C3%25ADa-y-Valentina-Fusari/1965087300183691&quot;&gt;Valentina’s dance studio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Some repertoire emerged and we recorded some stuff in Argentina and then a subset came to Seattle and we recorded and we did a live show in Seattle called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=whCDjnlD82Q&quot;&gt;Globmobalooza &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 1997 at the Broadway Performance Hall with the California Guitar Trio, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Gunn&quot;&gt;Trey Gunn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and Tony Geballe. We recorded that and then smushed together a CD that looks like this that includes live tracks from Buenos Aires and from Seattle. A famous show at the Bauen Hotel where I think the encore was a version of &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Wasn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/whCDjnlD82Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: A scary version of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Scarier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Well, they’re all scary, as you know, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: We were also scared ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Yeah, we were scared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Everyone was scared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: So we have a history going back to 1997, but last year I went back to Buenos Aires twice and we did a show at–what is the arts center called?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JTvyinFGJ7w&amp;amp;list=PLvGIL9EhBiNchBEByedwjSbXqbYdfEBy_&quot;&gt;Usina del Arte &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JTvyinFGJ7w?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Usina del Arte. We did a big show backed by 30-something acoustic guitars as well and we did an Electric Gauchos show with Fernando Kabusacki, Fernando Samalea on drums, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/nathy.cabrera.7&quot;&gt;Nathy Cabrera &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–can’t pronounce her last name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Cabrera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Cabrera on bass, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bZpQj7Z3YiU&quot;&gt;Horacio Pozzo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s also a member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/bigtimetrio/&quot;&gt;Big Time Trio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is another Guitar Craft spin-off band. I think of them as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cgtrio.com&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of South America. And did a big show and we actually recorded that as well and then released a CD of that show as well. It includes some odd cover songs you don’t hear very often, including a version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fCh5Vy-TGSA&quot;&gt;Inductive Resonance &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is an old League of Gentlemen piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fCh5Vy-TGSA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tough song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Heptaparaparaparapara–how do you pronounce it? There’s an old League of Gentlemen song with an esoteric title, which I’ll leave it to the reader to look up and pronounce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you want to attempt it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dD7iO5KMYrI&quot;&gt;Heptaparaparshinokh &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Pretty good! Daisy, you wanna give it a shot? [Talking to his dog, Daisy.] Close. Okay. So, we have a long history of working together, writing together, improvising, playing live, and when I was putting together a plan for this next year, I thought with a very open mind, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Who would I love to bring to Seattle to energize some of the work that’s going on here?”&lt;/span&gt; And three or four names came to mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At the top of the list was Alex, building on our long history of work and play together. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/tinyorchestralmoments/videos/1951848171699883/&quot;&gt;Martin de Aguirre &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the Big Time Trio is also here this week. We’re essentially continuing, we’re not just picking up again, but we’re continuing on the work of multiple decades. What are we missing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Don’t you have a boxed set?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Oh yeah, there is also a &lt;a href=&quot;http://steveball.com/EG&quot;&gt;9-CD box set &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; based upon some other improvised recordings we did a couple years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That was just Electric Gauchos, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Yeah. We brought–although there were a few guests as well–we brought a group to Seattle to improvise in the studio for four-and-a-half days. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Of that four-and-a-half days, essentially eight CDs worth of material came out of it and it’s ludicrous. But again, I don’t necessarily do music projects based upon what an audience needs or expects or what a label needs or expects.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I tend to follow my instincts about where the music is going. Or, what collaborations might bring if you invite two people who have some investment in their instrument into a room together. It’s like having an interesting conversation and so I’m very interested in capturing the authentic live conversations of musicians who’ve essentially given their lives to their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Alex, how would you describe the Electric Gauchos’ music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: It’s a trick question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Well, it’s instrumental guitar music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: To explore various genres?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: All the time. All day. At the same time, I would say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What is coming next for Electric Gauchos?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Well, well well well! I think my feeling is we’re just in a point where my sense, my personal egoistic sense, is that we came to a point where it will be great to throwing a writing period of time to writing a pool of ideas. Well, that’s what I see for the next, say, half year or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Alex, I’ll speak for him a little bit, but Alex has a series of pieces brewing loosely called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JW9MFQpFtsY&quot;&gt;Particles Of The Infinite &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  with a number of evolutions and we’ve done a little collaboration on a couple of them. Just a tiny amount. They’re massive and difficult and probably a little bit weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JW9MFQpFtsY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Yeah, definitely weird. [Chuckles.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: But there’s a seed of something brewing, I think, in sort of the new writing Alex has been doing. There’s no shortage of potential in the members’ writing skills, even, I would say, performance skills. I think the next period may actually be energized by having a new repertoire. There’s little seeds of that already brewing. I spoke to Fernando Kabusacki a couple weeks ago. He and Fernando Samalea and Argentinian singer/songwriter that we played with last October, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TEVEg96kOOA&amp;amp;list=PLziGqtc5FlJaEMX5uaWFyQsCJpGjBDNWv&quot;&gt;Marina Fages &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Did I pronounce that correctly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Perfect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: There’s some aspiration to bring this configuration to Seattle as well. Maybe in the next 6-12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: As a matter of practicality, if someone were to want to hear this music, purchase it, where would they go? Is it available in all the normal channels?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Generally, yeah. If you just search “Electric Gauchos” in iTunes or Spotify or CDBaby or Groove Music, most of our stuff is out there, including the 9-CD box set. Eight of the nine CDs are on most of the big services. You could also just go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://SteveBall.com/EG&quot;&gt;SteveBall.com/EG &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which has nice fairly-high-quality playable previews of the box set if you want to get a glimpse of what 81 tracks of mostly-improvised music sounds like. It’ll give you a little sense of what we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: It’s really hard to describe. In fact, is there a–is all the Particles work you’ve been doing, Alex, is that in OST or NST?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: It’s all OST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: So you’ll have to use one of Sophie’s guitars if you’re going to give a glimpse of what that stuff is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Maybe later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Maybe later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool! Anything else you want to say about Electric Gauchos?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FCOqPqlfyX0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: I just want to make sure we show off the historical photos that were taken, literally, twenty years ago. This was almost our twenty-year anniversary. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10156853691031562&amp;amp;set=t.574626561&amp;amp;type=3&amp;amp;theater&quot;&gt;This is from a photo shoot that happened at the rehearsal studio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where I used to share a space with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Rieflin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krist_Novoselic&quot;&gt;Krist Novoselic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Alex came to visit in 1997 with Martin Schwutke, one of the original Los Gauchos Alemanes members, and Ingrid Pape took this photo. You can’t quite see it, but it’s an old iconic sort of Seattle grunge rehearsal studio on Western Avenue. We haven’t changed a bit, if I actually look at the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AAF: Not at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: This feels like yesterday. And there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=1677156815662614&amp;amp;set=t.574626561&amp;amp;type=3&amp;amp;theater&quot;&gt;another picture from that same time frame taken in Mendoza, Argentina with the full Greenthumb Ensemble &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was a group that came together to write and record and play some songs. This includes–there’s a young Alex right up front, Martin de Aguirre, who’s upstairs sleeping right now, and some poor long-haired dude who looks like he just–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Came out of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Matrix&quot;&gt;The Matrix &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Exactly. And there’s Horacio Pozzo, also in the most recent Electric Gauchos and also a member of Big Time Trio with Martin de Aguirre. And Fernando Kabusacki, Schwutke, some famous people here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. Cool. Thanks a lot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Yeah. Hope to see you live somewhere soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/electric-gauchos/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/electric-gauchos/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>X-mas Death Jazz</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;creative-tour-de-force&quot;&gt;Creative Tour de Force&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt;’s new album, &lt;em&gt;X-mas Death Jazz&lt;/em&gt; is easily one of my favorite albums of 2017 and probably my favorite Panzerballett album. The musicality is extraordinary, the guest musicians are wonderful, and the complexity is more meaningful than ever. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Jan Zehrfeld&lt;/a&gt; and crew have completely outdone themselves. Again. There is no other band like this on earth. There is no other album that sounds like this. You truly need to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am beyond happy to be a mutual connection with these fantastic musicians and to have had the opportunity to film all these interviews around the world to make it happen. It’s been months in the making and it’s finally here (though, a few days later than I’d hoped, but that’s fine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview features Jan Zehrfeld (the mastermind behind Panzerballett), Jen Majura (&lt;a href=&quot;/share/jen-majura/inzenity&quot;&gt;we just interviewed her for her new album, &lt;em&gt;InZENity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which came out on the same day as &lt;em&gt;X-mas Death Jazz&lt;/em&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mattias-eklundh&quot;&gt;Mattias IA Eklundh&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;, plus a generous helping of song samples from the record to entice you. It’s four interviews plus music smashed into one 42-minute video. I really hope you enjoy it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FLlzX0DObCY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/panzerballett/x-mas-death-jazz/panzerballett-x-mas-death-jazz.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/panzerballett/x-mas-death-jazz/panzerballett-x-mas-death-jazz.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Introductory clip of &lt;em&gt;For Whom the Jingle Bells Toll&lt;/em&gt; from Panzerballett’s &lt;em&gt;X-mas Death Jazz&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I am here with Jan Zehrfeld from Panzerballett and they–well, Jan has a new album with Panzerballett. It’s a Christmas album and I thought it’d be cool for him to talk about why a Christmas album and about some of the guest artists on the album. So, why Christmas music? And what’d you do with it? [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, Christmas music–it started in 2003. I got a new computer, I started recording guitars and I started recording just for fun Christmas songs for my friends and contacts. And it was nothing special yet. It was just three voices of guitar, some Brian May-style thing and it got good responses. So I chose to do another one a year after. But then I was playing in a speed metal band at the time and I thought, “Well, what about mixing speed metal with Christmas songs?” I wrote just a 20-second thing and it was a whole lot of fun. After that, a year after again, I did something–this was &lt;em&gt;Jingle Bells&lt;/em&gt; and this was already in the Panzerballett style. It got like–it was even better–it got tradition. For 13 years, I’ve been doing these 1-minute Christmas greetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Christmas greeting examples: &lt;em&gt;Let it Snow&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;White Christmas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rudolf the Red-Nosed Reindeer&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Es Kommt Bald&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: After a couple of years, some of the prog stations started airing them and people were looking and asking me, “What’s your next Christmas song?” It was always big fun and why I chose to go on. It was because I feel that’s my actual feeling about the Christmas time. I feel not very calm and peaceful. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The message that I get from the Christmas time is a different one. It just reflects my inner world better to channel aggression&lt;/span&gt;, channel the aggression in the traffic that happens, to channel aggression in the shopping malls, and everything. Everyone needs a present. It has to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s like forced joy, forced cheer from this forced happiness.&lt;/span&gt; I don’t like it. It just makes me angry and I think it’s like–I like the contrast. The reason why I make music is to channel aggression. One of the main reasons. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And all the ingredients I use for making this music are like the absolute opposite of the ingredients that are used in Christmas music.&lt;/span&gt; I think this contrast is very exciting and fun to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’ve got some special guests on the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Who’d you find and why’d you bring them aboard?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: So, first and foremost of all, Mattias IA Eklundh from Jütebog. The crazy Swede, freak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: I sing a very strange, hedonistic pagan version of &lt;em&gt;White Christmas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer&lt;/em&gt;. To this very day, Rudolph is scaring the shit out of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Clip of &lt;em&gt;Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: Because Jan Zehrfeld is a mad-scientist, he sent me this beefy score with sort of the melody, but since he’s been to school and he learned many adult chords with numbers and stuff, the harmonies were so–can I say “fucked up?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: It was, “No no no. This is impossible.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It was one of the hardest things I’ve ever done.&lt;/span&gt; I’m trying to convince him to make a very strange video. Maybe we’ll do it naked. Because it’s really spooky. It’s not the Rudolph you’re used to. It’s really weird. Really weird. Make weird music. Well, that’s Jan Zehrfeld for you. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did you do the–did you scream “Rudolph” in the background?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Clip of &lt;em&gt;Rudolph&lt;/em&gt; screams.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: I am screaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re screaming all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: It’s kind of fun because I live in the Swedish woods, as you know, and there are not many people here. Occasional mooses and a few birds and I have my big dogs, but I have a great neighbor not super-far and he was up in the middle of the night working with his car and I was late, as I–I’m always late when it comes guest appearances. I wait until the very last minute. And he would hear me. We talked the other day. “Are you okay? Because around 1, 2-ish, I could hear you scream ‘Rudolph!’ and ‘Red-nosed!’ What was going on? Complete silence and then outburst of just insanity!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that was kind of fun. I said, “Yeah, I was working on a Christmas album with some German friends, you know. We needed that screaming, Rudolph screaming.” But it’s not every day you scream, “Red-nosed.” You know, blood is coming out of your mouth and red… I think I have the score somewhere. Give me a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: Oh yeah, yeah, so here is–do you see this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I see a little bit, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: Yeah. This is the vocal part of &lt;em&gt;Rudolph&lt;/em&gt; and [laughs] this is not kid’s stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Jan sent me some early mixes and every time I listen to &lt;em&gt;Rudolph&lt;/em&gt;, I laugh so hard just at those screams in the background. It’s so passionate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: Yes! I love Christmas music. I really do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, do you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: I adore it! I love Christmas as well. I always take December completely off and I have a little glass of fine cognac and I listen to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_Martin&quot;&gt;Dean Martin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I decorate the Christmas tree. I decorate the Christmas tree. I have a 10-year-old. He can put up the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene_Simmons&quot;&gt;Gene Simmons &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; decoration and stuff like that. My wife doesn’t touch it. It takes me forever. I light a fire in our lovely living room and I listen to Dean and I really work it, you know? I’m super-picky. It’s insane. I don’t know. There are a few things I wonder about myself: why do I like decorating the Christmas tree and why do I like playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(2016_video_game)&quot;&gt;DOOM &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; so much? It’s weird. 10 years of therapy could maybe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You are also contributing guitar, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: I am. Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: On which song?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: Both. I sing both &lt;em&gt;White Christmas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer&lt;/em&gt; and I also do some lead work. They cut all–I think there are three solos in White Christmas. For the video, they wanted to make it “commercial,” so they took that out, but on the album, there’s a lot of weedly-weedly. And again, it’s over adult chords, so I had to get my shit together. Every time you play with Panzerballett, you have to take a deep breath and read music and–”ARGH! What is this? What’s this harmony?” And so on. I love them. I think they’re really really really wonderful. They are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spike_Jones&quot;&gt;Spike Jones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of this century, in a way. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s musical murder.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. And Jen said it was some of the hardest music she’s ever tried to record. I actually spent some time with Jan this summer and he was having a hard time playing through it, so that was actually comforting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: I saw the video. I saw the video that you edited together. I laughed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dNE8DIRk7TA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: I laughed to tears because he’s–again, he’s a mad professor. He’s just hilarious. Everything he says, even if he doesn’t mean to be super-funny, he’s just very very funny. You know? So, I love those outtakes. It really made my day. It was such a funny video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. So, what are some of your favorite moments of what you recorded on this and what do you think people are going to get out of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: Oh, that’s a tricky question. I think they will like it. When I did &lt;em&gt;White Christmas,&lt;/em&gt; that was the first one I recorded the vocals…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[White Christmas clip]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;IA: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I tried to be funny. It was not funny. I tried to overdo it. And then I said, “Well, I actually like this music. I like Christmas music. Sing it in the most honest way you can.”&lt;/span&gt; I really tried to be a heavy metal crooner kind of guy and then it clicked. Then it worked. So, it’s funny stuff, but it’s also dead serious in many ways. You do not kid around. “Where is 1?” I tried to find the “da.” It’s really, really hard so I slapped my &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konnakol&quot;&gt;Indian Konnakol &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to say, “Where am I in this fucking music?” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You have to do it and you have to play it like you mean it and then it becomes funny.&lt;/span&gt; Don’t joke around because then it’s turning out stupid, I think. I love doing it. I was always late and I sent it off to Jan and said, “I don’t know if this is just utter crap or if it’s good.” He loved it. He’s such a gentle guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GvKFCGqdNeM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Who’s already been a guest on &lt;em&gt;Tank Goodness&lt;/em&gt; and I’ve been in touch with him since 2010 when he once wrote me on MySpace that they were touring with &lt;a href=&quot;kipedia.org/wiki/Freak_Kitchen&quot;&gt;Freak Kitchen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;they had to stop the touring bus because they had to laugh about a Panzerballett song&lt;/span&gt;, what was happening in there. So, yeah, we met at &lt;a href=&quot;kipedia.org/wiki/Musikmesse_Frankfurt&quot;&gt;Musikmesse &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and we got friends and said, “Let’s do something together.” Then we started exchanging ideas and writing together. So I thought, “Well, Mattias would be really great to have on this Christmas album again.” He even does two songs with his awesome guitar soloing. It’s just the right thing. He–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And his vocals. He sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, his vocals. Mattias told me he loves Christmas and not everyone does that. I cannot say I love it or I hate it, I just have my feelings about the Christmas time. The idea of Christmas, of course, is great, but it’s just hard to make it as it should be, actually. I requested some other guests who declined because they said, well, they hate Christmas. I guess they just didn’t listen to the music because if you hate Christmas, it’s also an album for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The anti-Christmas Christmas album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right. So, Mattias–we have Mattias. And then we have Jen Majura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B3i6bcFhVXI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, yeah, you play on and sing–wait, you sing on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I sing on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah. It happened after I asked Jan to contribute to my album. He was like, “Oh yeah, let’s do this together. I’ll do a solo for your album,” and “I’ll do some vocals for your album.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You have an awesome voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re a great singer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It was a lot of fun, absolutely. I think it [laughs] &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s been the most insane experience I’ve ever had in a studio.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Because if you work with a guy like Jan from Panzerballett–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes [laughs].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It’s kind of scary, to be honest. It’s scary because I consider him to be a genius in music and I have–not only is he a good friend, but he’s just so good in what he’s doing that I felt like, “Oh, will I survive this?” So, I asked him for a printed sheet so I could actually just read what’s going on because, of course, you can listen to it and try to reproduce it but with that amount of information, I was kind of like, “Give me a printed sheet so I can read notes.” Then I looked at the notes and I was like, “Good Lord! It’s like 11/16 followed by 13/8,” and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I was like, “Oh shit! How am I going to do this?”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I did a take and his comment–he was quiet. And I said, “Jan? Jan?” And his comment was, “Well, could you do the second triplet in the 16th again, a little bit more staccato?” And I was like, “Dammit, I’m so happy I just made it through the whole thing. Okay, let’s do it again and do it again.” It was really fun. It was fun to work with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s funny. He had that &lt;em&gt;Typewriter II&lt;/em&gt; cover thing a long time ago and I did a cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HRdk3HoknWk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I saw it. I saw it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It’s awesome! I saw it. I told you, I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you! So, I did this cover and I was like–I was really happy about it, and then I saw the winners of the contest and I was like, “Oh yeah. German precision.” Jan is like–I’m very loose, I played my thing, but I realized watching the winners, I was like, “I see why they won!” It’s a very tight cover and Jan is very precise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yes, especially when it comes to timing, note lengths… It’s good. That’s why he’s able to keep that band tied together because he’s got that special ear for tightness and timing. It’s been interesting working with him, definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I mean, what a privilege too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I was honored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m sure it took you up a couple notches in what you need to do perform it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah. I just had ants in my pants, to be honest, when I came there. I was like, “Ooohhhh” [nervous noises]. It turned out to be fun. We did it a couple of times and I had my issues and then he went to me and said, “Oh could you try this a little bit more of ‘that’ and a little bit more [screams].” And I said, “Okay. Whatever you want.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so what were some of the challenges outside of, obviously, the timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: The timing was a big–like, the major challenge. The timing. Then–well, he was also when it came to the scored notes and stuff, I suggested, “Maybe we could do this a little bit–like, an octave higher so it won’t get in the way of the main vocals,” because I had just learned in the studio that Mattias was going to sing on that one. I didn’t know that. He just sent me the track and his demo version and I was like, “Okay, that’s cool.” And then when I came to the studio to record, he was like, “Yeah, Mattias is going to sing the main vocals.” “Really?! That is awesome! Us three together on one song. I love that!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! I love it too. It’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: He was really cool when it came to talking about the arrangement. Of course, not the major arrangement, but sometimes there were words or phrases that would get in the way with the main vocals of Mattias, so I kind of suggested, “Could we do this an octave higher?” Or, he was kind of inspired and went to me like, “Hey could you try this and do a second line?” We changed some words a little bit. It was very cool working together. I really had a good time. It was interesting to see how Jan was working. I learned a lot that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And there’s a lot of stacking of what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: No not at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs.] How many vocal parts did you sing at one time? Three?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I think the most–it sounds massive, but it’s the max of three different lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s really complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah, but that is the way Jan wrote the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: So, it sort of starts odd against the main vocals and in the end, it merges together and ends up in one. That is just a phenomenal way of writing in a timing-wise thing. If you take a look at it, how he thinks about it, how he starts completely different until the whole thing merges together and ends up on the 1. That is really–it was beautiful to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you get connected with him?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/W2XzllrmXyk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I expected you to ask that question. I have no clue.  I thought about it earlier today, but I don’t know. I think I was at the [Freak Guitar camp] in Sweden with Mattias and I think we talked about Jan and then I saw your interview of Mattias when he–I love what he said there. He was like, “Jan is exploring the depths of madness.” I loved that so much, so I think I just wrote him on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, so it’s recent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah, it’s like two years? Two or three years? Something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Wow. I thought you were old friends or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: No, we really became close friends since then. It’s nice. We’re in steady contact and everything is cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, yeah, because he speaks very highly of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Thank you Jan. I know you’re going to see this. [Blows a kiss.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. So, anything else about the recording experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: After I finished recording &lt;em&gt;White Christmas&lt;/em&gt;, I went to have a break and a coffee. I came back to the studio and I remember Jan was in there singing, “We Wish You a Merry Christmas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Oh yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;[Clip of &lt;em&gt;We Wish You a Merry Christmas&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Es Kommt Bald&lt;/em&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: And he was yelling, too! He was like, “AAAGH! I can’t do this! It’s too hard!” And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love when people write music, like musicians write and are challenging themselves to get it out what they hear inside of their ears and inside of their mind.&lt;/span&gt; So, Jan apparently wrote something that drove him nuts as well and he was like, “Jen! Come here and sing that! I can’t!” I was like, “Okay!” So I tried it and I was suffering too because it was just so hard to sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, that’s funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It was fun. We really had a great, great, great day in the studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What about the rest of the album? I know you’ve heard some songs. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It’s craziness. It’s like exploring the depths of madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I think it’s a beautiful idea to put that Christmas album out there finally. I know it’s been on his mind for quite some time and it’s a great idea. The final result is technically, arrange-wise and musically, from my understanding of music, beautiful. I really like the style of music, the style of Panzerballett in general. They started with the quintuplets and then turned into–well, where are we now? &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/tuplets&quot;&gt;Seven-tuplets or something&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/91zrIPUJRtg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, they’re starting with nines now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Are we at nine now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think he said there’s sevens and possibly some nines on this Christmas album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah, sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For those twirling their mustache listening to the record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: She’s a fan of this wacky music and odd music also. She loves it. She’s singing along with Mattias on a song, on &lt;em&gt;White Christmas&lt;/em&gt; actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/l7EYqXkoWts?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: She does an awesome job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I didn’t even know she was singing. She just one day played something to me and… “Who’s singing?!” “Okay, that’s me doing some background vocals.” And I thought, “Wow, okay. This could be a great fit. Male and female voice.” Mattias and Jen together is like something I thought I could imagine well and fits well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah. And then we have &lt;a href=&quot;kipedia.org/wiki/Steffen_Kummerer&quot;&gt;Steffen Kummerer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;kipedia.org/wiki/Obscura_(band)&quot;&gt;Obscura &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s singing on &lt;em&gt;Let It Snow&lt;/em&gt;. We needed some real death metal stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Clip of Steffen’s singing on Let It Snow.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Sebastian [Lanser], he’s playing drums for Obscura as well. So I thought, “Well, let’s use this connection for making it even more evil. To express maximum evil with death metal vocals.” And the album is called &lt;em&gt;X-mas Death Jazz&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;The death jazz, that’s kind of a running gag. When we started as a band, someone was like–we played a lot of jazz clubs and some of the people who didn’t know us and just walked inside the club, “Hey, Panzerballett. What style of music are you playing?” “Uh, well, we are playing death jazz.” Not death metal. I thought, “This is a nice thing. Christmas death jazz is the right title for this album.” And Steffen brings the death part. And on the same song, we have &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;, who’s a tremendous awesome musician. When looking for someone, a singer to do this, I was asking myself, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Who could possibly ‘get’ the rhythm and wouldn’t get lost in all the rhythmic terror that we’re doing?”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Good description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;JZ: Some unusual rhythms going on there and I couldn’t ask just a regular rock or metal singer to do this. Of course, it’s set to be musician’s music, so it would have to be someone who’s really used to intricate rhythms. I’ve known you as a guitar player before. I just knew from two YouTube videos that you’re actually doing singing as well. So, one I think you played with Zappa and you’re younger than now wearing a hat, I think. And then the “daa doo dak,” something like this. Very fast. And the other one is a video where you play something in the rain, but you played double as fast, which was slowed down again. It was a track a couple of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah, &lt;em&gt;I’m Raining Here Inside&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Sug4hC3Ysb0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah. You, fortunately, provided such comprehensive materials to work with for the recording. He had instruments playing exactly what the vocal was needing to do. Rhythmically and pitch-wise, so I had the option of listening to these melodies, which is identifiable as the melody from Let It Snow. I love that song, by the way. I love your arrangement, but I’ve always enjoyed the song &lt;em&gt;Let It Snow&lt;/em&gt;, and I have a real weakness for Christmas music. I’m a total Christmas geek, but I also like the idea of taking these traditional songs and messing with them almost beyond recognition. But, it’s still identifiably the song even though rhythmically it’s going all over the place. This particular track travels through about 18 stylistic variations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Clip of Mike singing on &lt;em&gt;Let It Snow&lt;/em&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: So it’s great. I was able to hear the melodies that he needed me to sing, both in the context of these crazy rhythms and also could make all of that go away because you provided stems so I could just listen to the vocal over the click. So, at that point, or I should say I listened to the vocal melody over the click because it was keyboards playing the vocal melodies that you sent me. So I could just listen to a keyboard playing whatever I needed to sing as it related to the click. That made it very easy because all I had to do was relate it to something very steady and not be distracted by the [rhythmic noises].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HECxB67qBvM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;And it’s like, “Okay, so it’s not a question of how do I sing these quintuplets over this rock groove and make it lock in,” it’s just, “All I have to do is sing it against the click and sing exactly what the keyboard is playing, then bring back all the instrumentation and make sure it lined up with what you were hoping to do.” It was the same way with the harmonies, especially in that &lt;a href=&quot;kipedia.org/wiki/The_Andrews_Sisters&quot;&gt;Andrews Sisters &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; section where it’s extremely dense four-part harmony. If there were four of me, in reality, and we were all trying to sing that stuff perfectly, it would be a struggle because it’s four voices seemingly singing a whole tone or a half tone apart in some sections. But, you break it down to one track at a time and just sing exactly what you had the keyboard singing or playing, and then listen to them all together and make sure that the phrasing all lines up nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was experimenting with different recording situations. I had friends who had studios and stuff because I don’t have home recording right now. So, I was going to different places and the first time I tried it out, I sang that Andrews Sisters section an octave too low, which was extremely dense and then he kindly said, “It sounds very good, but this one section [laughs] should be an octave higher.” I was like, “Okay, that makes sense to me now.” Then I went to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doubletimerecordingstudio.com/&quot;&gt;Double Time &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was fun to record. That was the studio where I recorded &lt;em&gt;Boil That Dust Speck&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sluggo!&lt;/em&gt; and various projects. I haven’t worked with &lt;a href=&quot;kipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Forrest&quot;&gt;Jeff Forrest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the engineer there, for quite some time. I worked with him on &lt;a href=&quot;kipedia.org/wiki/Jamie_Kime&quot;&gt;Jamie Kime &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s solo record. That’s the last time I worked with Jeff, but I haven’t done any singing with him in a long time. So it was fun to go back there and do vocal tracks there. Kind of nostalgic. It came together pretty quickly. It took me about 2 hours to record all the stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/r7VqwdMWDXs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Jeff really enjoyed it and he’s listening to your arrangement and it’s incredibly intricate and beautifully played and all your stuff is brilliant. And he’s like, “Who is this guy?!” It was fun to introduce you to him via this track. I was like, “Oh I’m going to sing on this Christmas song.” I didn’t tell him what was going on. He was like, “Holy shit! What is this? This is amazing!” I’m very happy to be a part of the track. It’s super high quality and I suspect that the whole album is going to be that way. I’m jazzed to hear the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah! That’s great. I have a question about–for myself, when I arranged it and learned it, at first I’m arranging and then I can learn it and then it takes me some time to really get to nail it down, but the hardest part was this quintuplet part. I think the first version I sent you was with a quintuplet click, but then I remember how I thought the first time when I did the pre-production back in 2012 how I recorded it back then and then I used, actually, the other click, the triplet click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Which first just as well to the part, but is way easier to perform to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Easier to feel. It’s funkier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right! Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: It’s not as clinical. Yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I was able to sort of get in the character of your intention with that different click.&lt;/span&gt; When we recorded, I had both of your clicks, so I had them both lined up and I found that there were some sections–I couldn’t tell you precisely which–some sections where it was easier to perform to one click and other sections where it was easier to perform to the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: And then of course having the actual instrumental tracks as reference as well. But, it was very satisfying, especially when I finally executed the Andrews Sisters harmonies correctly and listened to them against–just a capella and just against the click and then with everything in–it’s such a fun arrangement. It’s really good. I think people are going to get a huge kick out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Your voice sounded so good on that recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I’m glad to hear that because I tried various approaches and I found that the best thing to do was just try to sing it as straight as I could. There’s a couple of moments that are attitudinal, but for the most part, I just wanted to execute this as cleanly as possible and get the point across without trying to play a character. I did consider doing the death growls at the end, but I thought it would be better to hand that off to a specialist. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right. Right. I wasn’t sure in the beginning, but this last part, “Is this Mike’s thing? I think maybe, maybe not.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: I think that’s the right call. Orchestrationally, I think it makes more sense just in terms of the sound of the thing to have somebody who really knows what they’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What I loved about your vocal performance on that song, it’s clearly enthusiastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: Oh yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You sound half your age, too. You sound like you’re 20 years old on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s interesting and delightful because–and I think some of that might have to do with the setting because I was working again with Jeff, with whom I worked on &lt;em&gt;Hat&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dust Speck&lt;/em&gt; 25 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: There is something I think that happened that was a little bit of a time tunnel that brought me back to who I was when I did that stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s what I thought. It was so reminiscent of your &lt;em&gt;Sluggo!&lt;/em&gt; vocals. Your new stuff, I love all of it, but it’s clearly been an evolution. When I heard that, I thought, “Wow, I haven’t heard New Mike like that in quite some time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MK: That’s real interesting to hear because I didn’t dare breathe a word of that out loud, but I felt the same way when I heard it back. I said, “I sound more like the way I did in the 90s.” So that was real interesting. So, thanks for bringing that out. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I’m very happy to have him on this album. And then we have someone maybe not everyone knows because he’s mostly in Bavaria. He’s singing in the region of Regensburg and Landshut and Bavaria, but he’s a great singer. I was looking for a singer for this German song &lt;em&gt;Leise rieselt der Schnee&lt;/em&gt;. Actually I had trouble finding singers. I first thought, “Maybe some celebrity or something.” And everyone declined because they thought it’s something they cannot sing or don’t want to sing it or it takes too long to learn or they just don’t get it. And I thought, “Well, I didn’t know anyone,” so I asked the producer, “Do you know any singer? We need next week we need something.” He said, “Oh yeah, here’s a friend. He’s a great singer. He lives kind of in the next village.” And this was Martin Strasser. He sang really awesome on it. I was just looking for awesome singing. Unfortunately, I didn’t know him before, but there he is and does a great job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. Definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Martin Strasser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool. So, when does the album come out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I think it’s the 24th of November. I’m not 100% sure about the date. It will be November for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: End of November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: End of November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Cool. Awesome. And where can people buy the album when it comes out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: The best thing they could do is to go to the website of Panzerballett, panzerballett.de, and order the album there. It’s the best thing they could do. Or, maybe even better, go to a show and we’re basically playing only Germany. Maybe Switzerland, but only Germany. The very, very best thing they could do is come to the show and buy the album there. The second best thing is go to the website. And then there is plenty of other possibilities to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. And I want to say if you’re this far in the video. You gotta buy this album. It is so freaking good. Seriously. It’s incredible. It’s a work of art. I enjoy Christmas like Mattias and I enjoy this album. So, it’s an album for everyone. People who hate Christmas. People who love Christmas. People who get stressed out by Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: And for our fans: I think the whole band, we’ve talked already about it. Probably it’s the best album we’ve–best Panzerballett album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s the best sounding album, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: As well, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Thanks a lot, Jan. It’s awesome. Can’t wait for this album to come out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Thanks, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/panzerballett/x-mas-death-jazz</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/panzerballett/x-mas-death-jazz</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>InZENity</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-jen-majura&quot;&gt;About Jen Majura&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime in 2015, I got an instagram notification that a guitarist named Jen Majura was following Make Weird Music. I looked at her profile and saw she was kind of a big deal guitarist for a major rock act, Evanescence. It’s always a little surreal when professional musicians find my content without any prodding from me. She kept liking my posts and actually paid attention to what I was doing with MWM, so I finally asked, “Are you actually Jen Majura or a marketing person that runs her accounts?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said she was the real Jen Majura and mentioned she’d found MWM via the Steve Vai and Mattias Eklundh interviews. We started chatting and became friends. We met in person at NAMM in 2016 and had a great time together. We stayed in touch ever since and she ended up coming to Phoenix in October 2017 for an Evanescence show. We thought it’d be a great opportunity to do an interview for her upcoming solo album, &lt;em&gt;InZENity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we are! I hope you enjoy this video interview. It was a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B3i6bcFhVXI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/jen-majura/inzenity/jen-majura-inzenity.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/jen-majura/inzenity/jen-majura-inzenity.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Let’s get you blabbering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jen Majura: [Sings] Let’s get you blabbering. Whoo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s how you start an interview right there. Jen Majura is the guitarist for Evanescence and a very, very great person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Aww. Thank you so much for having me, Anthony. [Crying.] Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is how you start an interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: This is beautiful. I feel so appreciated. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, Jen, you have a new album. A new solo album. Your second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yes sir. My second solo album, InZENity, will be released on the 24th of November this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The same date as Panzerballett’s Christmas album, the death [jazz] Christmas album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: And we have three people on my album the same three people are on the Panzerballett album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Are you sharing who’s on your album yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Well, yeah, it’s public. Everybody knows it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I thought you had some surprise guests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: No no no no. It’s over. The surprises are over. [Laughs.] Christmas is over. But, Christmas is coming with Panzerballett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s right. And you! Driving the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I am blessed with, first of all, good friends. And I’m blessed with good friends that are outstanding talented musicians as well. So, I don’t see it as some sort of “Oh, I want to get some name-dropping on my album. I need some big names to…” I don’t see it that way. It’s more like: all those guitar players that I asked to join my album with a guest appearance, a guest solo, are friends. And I feel humbled and grateful that they all said “yes” to my request. It’s like this product, this CD, this piece of music being me and friends, I like that. It’s just beautiful. We have Alex Skolnick of Testament, he’s playing one solo. We have Jeff Waters of Annihilator  and Mattias IA Eklundh of the Swedish band Freak Kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Can you tell us what you did on Jen’s album, InZENity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mattias Eklundh: I think it was a guest solo. A weird guest solo, as usual. I’m really good at ruining stuff in a split second. I realize, “Ah, bloody hell.” I do this while some of my heavy metal friends want me to do a typical guest solo. They say, “You can do some typical stuff. Show us some sweeping, and swooping, and finish with a harmonic.” And then I play all the wrong notes because I want to create some tension. They say, “No no no, we want the right notes. White keys of the piano, man. Ivory keys. Don’t leave the church modes. Don’t go jazz or Indian style.” I don’t remember what I play. It’s done in very little time. I just improvise and then, “Ah, bloody hell. This was okay and then I’ll do a punch-in and that’s it.” I’m always done in five minutes, but I think it turned out okie dokie. So I’m looking forward to hearing it as well. She’s a good girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: It’s a killer solo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;ME: Oh it is? Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: It’s amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;ME: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Yeah, you did a great job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;ME: Okay. Thank you very much. I have no clue. I don’t remember the song. I don’t remember anything. [Laughs.] You do it and you move on. I am constantly running downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: My dearest sweethearts. And Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett. So, Mattias, Jan, and me were going to be on my album as well as on the Panzerballett album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That is so cool. So tell us about the album. How many songs and…?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It’s InZENity . It’s 12 songs? Or is it 11? Or 12?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s 12. There’s 11 with the drummer and then the acoustic one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Exactly. There was so much going on within those 10 days being locked in the studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It was just 10 days? Oh, that’s right, because you recorded all the demos and then went to the studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Exactly. I did the whole thing. The drummer, he recorded the whole record plus one song, which I didn’t even plan to have him on. He literally recorded 11 songs within 27 hours, including night sleep, showering, eating, breaks, talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: 27 hours! I was blown away by his performance. It was just…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay. What’s his name?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Felix Lehrmann.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Felix Lehrmann.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: He’s a German. Pretty-well-booked studio drummer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And he just came in and nailed it, huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I asked him. I sent a text message one day. I was like, “Hey. Did you wanna?” Answer: “Yes, when?” I said, “From [mumble] to [mumble].” “Okay. Sign me up.” I’m like, “Okay, that was easy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Wow, that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah. I never worked with him before, but I was blown away by his performance. He came up with ideas that literally left the sound engineer laughing and crying at the same time. Lying on the floor because we couldn’t believe what he came up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, you didn’t have drum parts written for him?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I did have demo drums. But, I’m terrible with programming drums. I’m not good at this, so I told him, “Please, play drums, not the Casio-kind of bullshit I did on that one.” So, he took a lot of what I did, just did it cool. He played it rad. What I made sounded shitty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, the drums are top-notch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It was really, really awesome. I decided this time to change my attitude a little bit because when I did my first solo record, I tried to find a way to combine the way I want to sound and the way people need me to sound so I can be sold with that CD. You know what I mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Putting that thing out there to have it air-playable and stuff. Of course, I learned that never works. So I decided for this one to really do what I want to do. No one can tell me how to write songs, what I can do and what I cannot do. So, of course, this album turned out to be really InZENity . The whole philosophy about the entire piece is–it’s why the album cover and the artwork, everything is in black and white. It’s about the–I heard the joke a gazillion times, “Why didn’t you call it ‘InJenity?’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Groans.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I didn’t call it “Injenity” because: world, listen. It’s InZENity because you find your inner peace, your inner zen, as soon as you accept and acknowledge all those opposites inside of each of us, like black and white. You have mellow and happy, fast and slow, and all those different opposites together give you that inner calmness. That’s my InZENity that I found in this album because the opposites are not only in the black and white artwork, it’s in the songs that I picked to record, it’s in each song. I tried to be very dynamic. A lot of songs nowadays lose dynamic, so I really wanted to keep the verses so smooth and sweet and then go, like, “Oh my God. Here’s a big chorus that changed the entire song!” and then go back to the very sweet verse. So, it’s the whole philosophy in everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, and I noticed listening to it last night, there are huge parts. The album just sounds huge, like in InZENity . Layered vocals and the drums are just, you know, beating your face in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I heard some good comments. Some friends of mine–Schmier is a singer of a German thrash metal band called Destruction. He said, “Damn Jen. This sounds like Extreme meets System of a Down.” I was like, “Well, that’s not too bad. I can live with that.” And then we had Alex Skolnick, who was like, when I sent him the track for recording, he was like, “Man, it’s like Faith No More on acid.” This is awesome! So, I paid attention to great dynamics and I like to sing. I like big vocal arrangements. I’m a big fan of King’s X and Extreme. I love great vocal arrangements, so when I decided to record, I was like, “Yeah, I wanna have that. I don’t want to have that major vocal line on top and then something cloudy beneath to support the main vocals.” I was like, “No. I want that all out there.” Just like back in the day, Queen or something. So, I’m really happy with how the vocals turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, the title track, as I told you before we were filming–I can’t get it out of my head. And now I just hear three or four layers of your vocals screaming “InZENity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I feel sorry for you. God. [Sings.] Voices in your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, well, you don’t run a site called Make Weird Music if you don’t have problems like that. But yeah, it’s like a very rich, dense, layered album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And it’s much more authentic, as you said, than the first album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I learned when I started to show my music to colleagues, I learned the biggest compliment you could get–I didn’t know that, but I learned it–is when people go like, “Oh, this sounds like this or that band. This is like rock. This is like prog.” They always put you into that little corner and a lot of them ended up telling me, “This is just Jen.” And I learned that this makes me so proud. I mean, what can be a bigger compliment than somebody telling you, “Your album sounds exactly like you?!” I was so happy when I first heard that and kept going. People kept telling me, “It sounds like Jen.” Maybe I created a new style of music. Maybe there will be bands recording and they’re like, “This is the Jen stuff.” [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I think that’s a good idea. I’m going to record an album in the style of Jen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Awesome. Gotcha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What did you learn about yourself making the record?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I learned that I can laugh so hard. I’ve never been laughing more while recording on this piece because we were so–usually, I’m very prepared. I’m German. I like to be prepared, so, “Oh, I’m going to the studio. I’m prepared. Here are my sheets. Here are my demos.” Now this time, on the other hand, I had no time to be prepared. I had my demo recordings and I had a week in Fort Worth with Evanescence recording. I came back, had the photo shoot the day after I was back to Germany, and then I went to the studio. So, I was really nervous because I felt insecure about, “Will that all happen now?” Because some of the songs were even considered to be on my first album. I haven’t been playing that since six years, a long time. I was a little bit afraid of being unprepared, but what I learned was things came out that were so spontaneous. Sometimes I inhaled for singing and he pushed the record button and I didn’t know what I was singing until I started singing and not even then, and it turned out to be beautiful. We came up with such beautiful melodies and ad-libs and stuff and that was really surprising. It made me feel good about myself as a creative musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And what about as a guitarist? What did you learn about yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I write weird stuff. Compared to–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s why we’re here, Jen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Compared to–I’m a big fan of bands where you–in the first place, of course, where you can hear the crazy work on the guitar, like Freak Kitchen and Panzerballett. Then on the other hand, I like bands that appear to be so smooth, easy-going and as soon as you try to play, you go, “What the heck is going on there?” as soon as you dig deeper into their music. So, what I learned about my music is I’m that kind of musician. So, I write, apparently, something and as soon as I dig deeper into it, it’s like, “What the heck was I thinking? Writing it like this?” So, we had some fun moments. [Laughs.] But all in all, I’m not trying to put difficult prog riffs out there. That should never be technique or a style should never be your approach or your inspiration for being creative and doing music. The inspiration should always be the song, the feeling, the moment. Whatever inspires you. It should be the creative process of getting to the song and the musical work, or the contribution by any instrument, should always be because the song demands it, not because you want to show off on your instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us about your creative approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: My creative approach. Oh, it can be–there are so many different spots in life where you can feel inspired and creative. It can be a line in a movie, it can be a story that happened to a friend. So I usually really, when I’m working on songs, I mostly am inspired by a feeling. And I learned about myself: I can’t write music when I’m happy. I don’t know why. It’s like I’m not happy with the music that I write when I’m happy. What? Does that make any sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you know Markus Reuter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Markus Reuter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He’s this touch guitarist in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: What is a touch guitarist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s this instrument he designed. It’s like a Chapman Stick, but it’s a different take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: With how many strings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s 8 or 10, but he intentionally find the stuff he doesn’t like and explore that because he..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: You have done a video. I’ve seen it. Okay, yeah, of course I’ve seen it! I’m your biggest fan!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I can’t believe this. That’s so cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I remember. Yeah, I remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So he said if we like what we hear, then we’re familiar with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: That’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So do you have–you think about taking an album of all the stuff you don’t like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Oh good Lord. Oh God. Oh God. No, but–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Have Markus produce it for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I have that approach from time to time when I do my short “Jen Majura plays videos.” That is just for fun. It started out for fun and it still is. So when I find the time, I do that “Jen Majura” stuff and I always try to pick something that is challenging. And it’s just a minute of a song and I did a Panzerballett, tons of Freak Kitchen songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve seen a lot of your Freak Kitchen songs. And Steve Vai. You’ve done some stuff from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Steve Vai was horrible. And “Oblivion” from The Winery Dogs was horrible, too. From “Oblivion,” I think there’s even a making-of where I’m like, “THIS IS UNPLAYABLE.” I spent, literally, 10 days–no pause, no break, no eating, no peeing. Ten. It was like…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Richie [Kotzen] is a beast. He’s a beast on the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah, I know. And he’s a singer as well. Like, [sighs]. When somebody gave talent away, Richie was definitely screaming twice, like “Vocals here!” “I’ll take one!” “Guitar?” “Double! To go!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, well you’re not slouch on either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yeah, I think I’m happy and I was glad that I can work on my vocals for my album because with Evanescence, I’m doing a lot of background vocals, which are–the background vocalist is there to support the main voice. So, of course, I can’t sing the way I would sing. That would just like–Amy [Lee] would turn around and go, “WHAT? What the heck is she doing?” So I really enjoyed the work, especially in InZENity. I mean, you’ve listened to it. It’s from classical [sings] to death growls and hip hop elements. It’s just so vibrant and vivid. The whole singing process on that album. I really enjoyed singing this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you write on the guitar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s where you start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yes. Guitar or–where I live in Germany, in every room I have a piece of paper and a pen, so whenever there is an idea, I can always write it down because, like I said, inspiration can come from everywhere. Once I watched a movie, Machete Kills. It’s like an action movie, it was just in the background. And then that actor comes up and the girl says, “Oh Machete, you’re just a walking shit magnet.” I was like, “Dude! Walking shit magnet! I can write a song about this called Walking Shit Magnet!” So, I need paper to be creative whenever I feel inspired. So, that is–What was the question again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes. [Laughs.] Do you do much recording on your own? Do you sit in front of a computer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Yes. I have everything at home, a microphone and computer, recording program, and I like to work and create alone, to be honest, because I like working with other people as well, but it always ends up being not what you first had in mind, which can be a beautiful thing. But if you’re stubborn as I am, it can be distracting, so on my record, I had two songs with a co-writer and all the rest was just written by me. So I like to close all doors and windows, don’t leave home, order in, stay there and work for hours and hours until you put layer over layer over layer for your songs and they grow and you see, “Okay, I’ll take away a little bit here and add a little bit more there” and then they become this beautiful dynamic thing that you created. And that’s just a beautiful process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us the difference–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I sound so wise. This is horrible. I sound like an 800-year-old person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, you sound like a 600-year-old person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Okay, 600 sounds better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us the difference between Jen Majura guitarist for Evanescence and Jen Majura solo artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Does that fluffy thing distract you? Is it good? I love it. So, me in Evanescence, you know–it’s a gig you might get once in your life when you’re really lucky. It’s a great, great world I was allowed to dive into, but to be honest, as a guitar player, what I’m playing in Evanescence is not as challenging, like some stuff that I played before. But that is mainly because, like I said, I want to play guitar that supports the song. I’m not the the–because a lot people ask me, “Are you going to play the songs different now in your style?” I’m like, “Hell no. Somebody wrote that song. Show respect to that somebody who wrote that song.” Because the way that it’s been written is perfect the way it is. So why would I change it? So it’s not a sort of creative process in Evanescence right now for me when it comes to playing guitar. We’ll see about that in the future, but for right now, I’m literally having Troy show me what to play. And of course, I try to keep my sound and my style, but it’s not that I’m changing anything So it’s a whole different ball game when you get to play what’s just coming out of you. It’s like, “Okay, here’s me and a guitar. Let’s do something.” It’s a different approach than, “Okay, show me what to play.” So you can’t really compare it to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For someone that has never listened to your music, if they have an expectation of it sounding like Evanescence, what would you say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: There are a lot of catchy chorus parts. It’s more up–it’s not speed metal, but upspeed tempo songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hard rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Exactly. It’s hard rock style and Evanescence is a lot of very–they have a dark history, but the songs are beautiful and dark, but not as upspeed tempo like my music, maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you write upbeat songs while you’re feeling sad?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Not sad. Pissed off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, okay. Do they cheer you up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: No, I’m the best to write when I’m really pissed off about something. So, I just get everything out and then it’s good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you make sure you capture that idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Well, most of the time. Sometimes, if it’s just a feeling, you don’t write the lyrics. If something happens that pisses you off, you don’t necessarily write about the situation. It’s a feeling that inspires and it inspires your tone as well because I play different when–let’s say I’m tired and jetlagged. I would never have the same tone and approach and playing like when I’m angry. Or sad. Sad comes pretty much to jetlag than tired, but it’s a different approach you play in. So, I don’t know necessarily. I would not write about the situation, why I’m–maybe sometimes. But sometimes I have the riff and then I go, like, “Hmm, I should write a song about Walking Shit Magnet,” for example. There is no feeling for “Walking Shit Magnet,” but it sounds awesome. I mean, Walking Shit Magnet is not on the record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, it’s not. Yeah, it didn’t sound familiar, but–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: What did you think about Chuck Norris?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think that’s a fun song. It’s just fun. I listened to it when I was cleaning the studio and I had the audio on and I heard you sing, “Chuck.” I’m like, “Chuck? Is that what she’s saying?” And then you were like, “Chuck Norris!” I’m like, “What? Yeah, there’s literally a song about Chuck Norris.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I always try to–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s fun. Your whole album is just fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: The world–exactly–the world is very serious these days. There are a lot of serious things going on and threatening things and I always try to make people smile with whatever I do. Either it’s an Instagram post or a little story or music or whatever I do, I always keep that little smirk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s actually what I love about what you publish. Your videos and your interviews, the four questions with your friends–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Did I tell you the four questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve seen them, but I can’t recall them right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: You can’t… No no no no no, I’ve never put them out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh no, yeah, you’re just holding–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I text them to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No you didn’t. You didn’t tell me them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I won’t tell them NOW. I’m not going to spoil all my secrets in here. My latest four-question interview partner was Guthrie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s right, Guthrie Govan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JM: He was like, “Oh man, these questions are pretty heavy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Guthrie Govan: Wow, these are all questions that are really hard!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, well, that’s what’s so fun about what you do. Your videos always have humor and a lightness and you’re clearly having fun, but there are times where you’re clearly playing as hard as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: THIS IS UNPLAYABLE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s right! Yeah! From “This is unplayable” to you have clearly worked through and you’re shredding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: I hate the term “shredding.” Did I tell you? You shred cheese. You don’t shred a guitar. Seriously. And the same thing is like “melting faces.” Why would people melt? Think about it. Melting faces?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I like that term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. Mike Keneally has a sticker that says, “Mike Keneally ripped my head off.” [Laughs.] It’s just this stick figure with his head detached and Xs for eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Wait a minute, that is cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That is cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: But if it said, “Mike Keneally melted my face,” it would be totally not cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Huh. Mike, if you’re listening, don’t go that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Happy to be on an album with you, Mike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that’s cool. Okay, let’s wrap up. Your album comes out November 24, 2017. Where can people get it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Everywhere. Go to the grocery store. Go to your neighbors’. Everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s in the next issue of Vogue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: It’s going to be everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool! Thank you so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: You’re so welcome. Thanks for having me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m really excited to see this album come out. Cool! InZENity. November 24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JM: Woop woop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Jen Majura.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/jen-majura/inzenity</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/jen-majura/inzenity</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
