<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 18:26:47 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 18:26:47 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Western Culture by Henry Cow</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tGDyCCQzCmw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;worst-album-ever&quot;&gt;Worst album ever?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to jam screwdrivers into my ears the first time I listened to Henry Cow’s album Western Culture. I remember hearing the first 10 seconds, then my jaw dropping and my eyes bulging out of my face. It was the worst music I’d ever heard. But like a good road rage video on YouTube, I couldn’t turn it off. This was a different kind of “music” and I just didn’t understand it. My gut told me there was more going on than I could appreciate but my ears told me to turn it off immediately, as my wife continues to do every time she hears Henry Cow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only exposure to the band was through their song “Nirvana for Mice,” which is fairly accessible and melodic. I knew they were a weird band and that their mascot was a knitted sock on the cover of several of their records. What I didn’t know is that they were out of their minds, fiercely rebellious, and deep, deep into music theory. My good friend Jake, who has a music degree, explained a bit of what Henry Cow was doing and that knowledge was the key to unlocking my true appreciation for this album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western Culture contains two pieces of music with several movements. The first piece, History and Prospects, is a brutal beating of various atonal motifs ending with a hypnotic and nauseating dirge. The second piece, Day by Day, is more like Chinese water torture complemented by one of the most incredible piano solos I’ve ever heard. I’ve listened to this solo several times and I legitimately cannot figure out how a human played it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This album was a jaw-dropper for me in three ways: 1. Because it has the most courageous opening minute of any album I’ve ever heard. 2. Because learning how to listen to this album permanently changed the way I listen to music. 3. It helped me to realize that sometimes music isn’t “good” or “bad,” but something I understand or something I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve never heard Henry Cow before, I recommend reading the very thorough Wikipedia page about their history and their approach to music. It’s enlightening, encouraging, and thought-provoking. They were a group of women and men with skin in the game. They did everything they could to avoid routine music performance. They changed how they approached their instruments. They kicked members out in the middle of touring just to shake things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, this album is very listenable to me now. I actually really love it. A lot of it is singable if you can pick out the different motifs. If you’ve never heard it, take 40 minutes and listen with a very open mind. If you’ve heard it and hated it, ask a friend with a music degree to help you hear what you aren’t hearing. It’s not an easy album and it will enrich your life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/henry-cow/western-culture</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/henry-cow/western-culture</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>O Holy Night in 5/4 by Anthony Garone</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OZOT7gVohwQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love weird music and I love &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; Christmas music, but most of it is just garbage. Uninteresting, “happy,” bland music that’s too much about commercial interests. In my mind, the story of Christmas has been wayyy over-glossed and has almost nothing to do with a baby being born 2,000 years ago in the middle east in a barn in the desert. So, I like to rearrange Christmas songs to reflect my view of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy “O Holy Night” as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/o-holy-night-feat-jon-lang-sarah-garone-rob-m%C3%BCller/948367454?i=948367461&quot;&gt;digital download on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-itunes&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife is singing on this one and is the “star” of the show, but the instrumentation turned out so much better than I hoped when I wrote and released this arrangement in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sarah Garone: Lead vocals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rob Müller: Drums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jon Lang: Piano (not in the video)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nathan Richard: Synth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anthony Garone: Else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/o-holy-night</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/o-holy-night</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sara Groves</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-artist-after-the-generative-life&quot;&gt;An Artist After the Generative Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sara Groves is one of the only contemporary Christian music artists I enjoy. My wife turned me on to her music in 2005 when she brought home Sara’s album “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Add_to_the_Beauty&quot;&gt;Add to the Beauty&lt;/a&gt;.” I remember thinking, “This is good music.” (My wife’s taste in music has only &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; overlap with mine.) After hearing it around the house a couple of times, I started getting some of the songs in my head. Then I brought the CD in my car and heard Sara sing a line from Peter Gabriel’s &lt;em&gt;Come Talk to Me&lt;/em&gt; and I was like, “Okay, I’m in.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is one of the most passionate artists I’ve ever met and she’s given her whole life to music and justice. She is unlike most any artist I’ve met in that her heart and her money go outward to her community and to those in need. She and her husband, Troy Groves, purchased a 100-year-old church and use it as a community arts center. It’s a fantastic space with a wonderful atmosphere in St. Paul, Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife listens to a lot of contemporary Christian artists, but Sara is a clear standout. Her music is very enjoyable, very well recorded, well-produced, and her lyrics are penetrating. She’s one of the few artists I’ve actually listened to for her lyrics. I think growing up with shred guitar music and Yes lyrics desensitized me to lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, we’ve listened to Sara over the years and have very much enjoyed her work. We contributed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pledgemusic.com/projects/saragroves&quot;&gt;Sara’s PledgeMusic campaign&lt;/a&gt; and got to spend a day with her in May 2018. And we’re bringing her to Arizona for a concert in January 2019, which is especially exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pXn6CvFgp_0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/sara-groves/sara-groves.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/sara-groves/sara-groves.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sara Groves is a musician and artist based in Minneapolis, Minnesota and she recently had a Kickstarter campaign for a new record of hers called Abide With Me, which I have here. My wife and I participated in that Kickstarter campaign and as part of the campaign, we were lucky enough to get to spend a day with Sara in Minneapolis and that was… early May, I believe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, May 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I spoke to Sara about her music a little bit and asked her if she would have a conversation for the website. She was the first to say, “Well, my music isn’t really weird.” And, yes, that is relatively true, but the perspective I heard from her as an artist and a musician that day really was eye-opening and a bit mind-blowing at times and covered some pretty deep topics that I really wanted to have her share with us in this format. So, Sara thank you so much for joining. I really appreciate you taking the time to join.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Thank you, my pleasure. Good to see you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You too. Can you give a little bit of background as to who you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: I’ve been doing this for about 20 years. I was a teacher before I did music and taught high school for a few years and then went into music full time. I’ve been on the road, a touring musician for 20 years. When you think about that, there’s all these sort of–even when I thought about it at the beginning, either you’re doing this or you’re not doing anything. All in there, there are just a million little places for live music and for people that do music for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s just been an adventure. I have a very wonderfully-committed group of listeners that have followed me, so that makes it really possible for me to still be at it this far in. I’ve made 13 albums in that time and I do tend to play in the faith community, but my music is really about the whole of life. I am reflecting on everything. The whole of life. Singer/Songwriter. I play the piano, write at the piano. My band consists usually of a 3-piece, which is bass, piano, drums, and my bass player also plays pedal steel. So that’s a crowd-pleaser and it’s just a beautiful thing. It’s pretty stripped down. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The lyric is definitely the point of what we’re doing, but the music is important as well.&lt;/span&gt; I’ve been at that for all this time and am just grateful. I still go out and do about–I was full time on the road for 17 years and then about 3 or 4 years ago, I pulled back and do about 30-40 dates per year now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ir5RhjnSRF0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. And your albums have quite a diverse mix of music. Most recently, this new album, “Abide With Me,” is very sparse. It’s a very “simple” record, I suppose, because it’s mostly voice and piano, whereas other albums like “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Add_to_the_Beauty&quot;&gt;Add to the Beauty&lt;/a&gt;” and “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tell_Me_What_You_Know&quot;&gt;Tell Me What You Know&lt;/a&gt;” are much more highly produced, a lot more instrumentation. So, can you talk a little bit about the evolution of your music and you as an artist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: I’ve always been pretty open to and highly influenced by the producer that I’m working with because I’m not a producer. I’ve not ventured into that realm. So, I’ve worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Peacock&quot;&gt;Charlie Peacock&lt;/a&gt;, he’s grammy award winning in every decade he’s been making music. And incredibly creative. One of the most creative people I know. He worked with me on “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Other_Side_of_Something&quot;&gt;The Other Side of Something&lt;/a&gt;” and wanted to do kind of a singer/songwriter record with “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fireflies_and_Songs&quot;&gt;Fireflies and Songs&lt;/a&gt;.” So, that was really reflecting–when I collaborate with someone, I’m very much open to their vision and the band that I’m playing with. I think each of those albums you’re hearing a little bit of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, I think that when I first came out, the space that I was occupying and the people that were promoting music, I was in the middle of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contemporary_Christian_music&quot;&gt;Christian Contemporary Music&lt;/a&gt; (CCM Music). That has a whole sound and genre of its own. The first song that I had on radio did really well and it was a very natural fit. It did well, but I wasn’t having to do anything different. It just happened to fit right where they were needing, but after that the conversation became very difficult. I was having to do some gymnastics to try to meet what I thought they wanted and that kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, with the second album, I had a record of really personal, very relationship-oriented songs and there was sort of a conversation about, “There’s not really anything that we could play here that would be on a station where their mission is safe for the whole family, encouraging, uplifting.” So they asked if I would do–”Well, could you add something?” So I added this song to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Right_Here&quot;&gt;All Right Here&lt;/a&gt;” and I always just felt like it was a bummer to me because it felt so different from what I was actually feeling, like I was supposed to be doing in the space I was inhabiting at the time. So after that, I just said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Look, I’ll make a record and if you find something you like, then great. And if you don’t, then I’m okay with that.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was working with a label that was very generous with me. I was the first artist to sign and I’ve been with them for the duration. They’ve given me a lot of space to be on my own and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it hasn’t always meant success in the sense of more listenership, but I feel like the listeners that I have trust me.&lt;/span&gt; I remember at one point, Charlie talking to me about the label was saying around the record “The Other Side of Something” like, “You really have one shot left at being in the Christian music scene.” And Charlie came to me and said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“You’re more of a mom-and-pop shop than you are a Walmart, and if you were to do something that’s kind of Walmart-y, then the people that trust you might not trust you anymore. So, stick to what you feel is what you’re supposed to be doing. The stuff you’re supposed to be putting into the world.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jaW43MlC3hI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that was one of the best conversations I ever had. I was able to go to our label president and say, “I’m a mom-and-pop store, not a Walmart.” And even on an economic level, on every level he was able to understand that and he said, “Oh, okay. Let’s treat it as such, then. Let’s find your people, your ears, and just keep meeting them there.” So that was good. That was pretty early on, that was in ‘03. I really felt free to experiment. The record, “Tell Me What You Know,” is huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown_Bannister&quot;&gt;Brown Bannister&lt;/a&gt; on “Add to the Beauty” and he’s produced tons of music. “Add to the Beauty” was a real heart album and then with “Tell Me What You Know,” I was talking about social justice things, which at that time in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelicalism&quot;&gt;evangelical church&lt;/a&gt; we weren’t addressing as much. I wanted to make a really “right where you live” full-on pop album, but around themes of social justice. I had a song based on “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/When_the_Saints_Go_Marching_In&quot;&gt;When the Saints go Marching In&lt;/a&gt;” and some others that were just a big pop record. But that was kind of on purpose. We were doing something with that. I think “Add to the Beauty.” “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floodplain_(Sara_Groves_album)&quot;&gt;Floodplain&lt;/a&gt;,” “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conversations_(Sara_Groves_album)&quot;&gt;Conversations&lt;/a&gt;” are kind of the quintessential Sara Groves albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Gabriel&quot;&gt;Peter Gabriel&lt;/a&gt;, I love an epic song. I love something really vibey that can get a little wooly. I’m not averse to that. I’m not totally just acoustic and stripped down. I wouldn’t say that that’s me when I’m being myself. There’s an emotive epic feel to what I like, so that tends to be what I gravitate to. Abide With Me was produced by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnmarknelson.com/&quot;&gt;John Mark Nelson&lt;/a&gt; and he’s a young artist in his early 20s and he is very minimalist. He took that approach to that record. You’ve been to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arthousenorth.com/&quot;&gt;Art House&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Paul,_Minnesota&quot;&gt;St. Paul&lt;/a&gt;. My husband and I own a 100-year-old church where we recorded that record and John Mark said, “I want this album to sound like this room looks.” It’s very warm, lots of warm wood, resonant. That was the goal of that album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes, “stripped down” is a much better word than “simple.” It was not coming to me when I described “Abide With Me.” But it’s funny, last night to prepare for the interview, I listened to “Add to the Beauty” and “Tell Me What You Know,” and those albums are very close to me largely because of the Peter Gabriel vibe going on. And even when you sing parts of “Come Talk To Me” on the reprise at the end. But then on my iTunes it went through to “The Other Side of Something,” and I was like, “What’s this record? It’s really aggressive.” There’s totally &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiona_Apple&quot;&gt;Fiona Apple&lt;/a&gt; elements, there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beatles&quot;&gt;Beatles&lt;/a&gt; elements, it’s a very diverse album, as are “Add To the Beauty” and “Tell Me What You Know.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: “The Other Side of Something” is Charlie Peacock. You hear him in that record and again, I love those collaborations. You definitely hear the Sara Groves come through. Obviously, that’s always what it is. But Charlie came back to me–his daughter was a big fan and he said (I don’t like the word “fan,” but she’s a listener) and so she said she wanted an album where I was just a kind of a girl and her piano. So Charlie came back and said, “If I ever get a chance to do another record with you. I would do it differently.” He felt like it was his playground with “The Other Side of Something.” He was kind of playing and having fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But with “Fireflies and Songs,” he was more, “Okay, what are you doing when you’re amplified? When you’re at your best?” So those two records really show the difference of the approach of that collaboration. “Other Side of Something” was a blank check to Charlie. Songs like “The Boxer,” his whole world is from a jazz background and very improvisational. We had the band improvising for probably an hour and they’d play for probably 10-15 minutes and he’d say, “All right, everyone change what you’re doing,” and then they’d play again for another 15 minutes and then he’d say, “All right, whatever you’re doing, don’t do that again.” They’d play again and then he sort of takes all these scenes that they had created because they get into a whole picture and he chopped those up and put those back to back, so in that song, in “The Boxer,” you’re moving in and out of these jazz scenes. I loved that! I loved that whole experience. I’m just on the mic in the corner making stuff up. So, that was a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, very cool stuff. You mentioned the element of social justice in your music. That term, “social justice,” nowadays seems to be taking on its own life with “social justice warriors.” But I know that you are talking about something different than young people fighting their university, the patriarchy, that kind of thing. Can you talk a little about what social justice means in the context that you’re using it and how your music plays into your activism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah. Well, I’ll have to go to a place to talk about it from the vantage point of my faith because I grew up in church. In my late 20s, I was having a faith crisis. What I was feeling was that I was going and doing all this work to groom and groom and groom my own personal faith. My own understanding of myself, my own understanding of God, and I was doing all this sort of work and I felt all dressed up and nowhere to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;To what end do we gather every week? I believe in that, I believe in the blessed community, I believe in the flawed qualities, that we come together, that it’s important to do that. But in attempting to reflect what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatitudes&quot;&gt;the beatitudes&lt;/a&gt; are talking about, what Jesus was trying to do and say in the world, if I’m really going to follow that, I felt like what we were doing on a Sunday morning wasn’t really reflective wholly of what he was purporting we should be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I started looking around for people that were doing that and I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Justice_Mission&quot;&gt;International Justice Mission&lt;/a&gt;. They’re the largest anti-slavery, anti-trafficking organization in the world. They’re truly an international organization. They have offices all over the world and are led by the best and brightest in India and Africa and Philippines and all over southeast Asia. I started hearing these stories of rescue and of people that were being enslaved for generations and now they were going through after-care programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Lt_WpluguwE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s a story in India of a woman enslaved and then ran for city council. She’s now sitting on the city council of her community and ran against the man that is supported by her previous owner. There’s a survivor-led movement. There are more slaves today than there ever have been in the history of the world. There’s a survivor-led movement that’s happening that’s just unbelievable.&lt;/span&gt; So when I started seeing these men and women of faith who, because of their faith, were going into very difficult places. The best and brightest lawyers in India were signing up and I want to advocate for the poor. I want to be on the side of–I think that’s where Jesus said he would be. “I’ll be here with those that are oppressed, with those that are poor.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I started hearing these stories and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;my first response was, “I need to do something different than be a songwriter. I need to be a nurse or an after-care worker or a lawyer. I need to do something more tangible.”&lt;/span&gt; And that’s when Charlie sat me down and told me about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cellist_of_Sarajevo&quot;&gt;cellist of Sarajevo&lt;/a&gt; and said, “You know there was a guy during the Bosnian war who played his cello in the middle of a recently-bombed out area and a lot of people say what he did, the attention that he drew, this protest of beauty in the middle of all this chaos, it drew attention to the region and really hastened the end of the war.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Basically, art matters, and songs matter&lt;/span&gt;, and he was encouraging me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Write music about what you’re seeing!” I had met a survivor of trafficking. We became good friends. Her life and her resilience and her faith were so compelling to me. The record “Tell Me What You Know,” every single song in some way reflects her.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was writing about her, I was writing about the work of International Justice Mission, and now my husband works for them. He’s been there 4 years and it’s kind of an integral part of our life. To me, it is the expression of faith. My grandfather, for 40 years, he went down to the local prison in our town and met with a group of men twice a week. I have a history of people engaging just to enter suffering that’s not your own. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;To me, that’s what I mean when I say “social justice.” I mean: justice is what love looks like in public. And I think as Christ-followers, we have to think about that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One of the most compelling things that I realized about you through the St. Paul experience was how much you’ve given your life through your music and using your music towards this new–after-that experience. This activism. A lot of people, if they have money in music, they will just continue investing in that, they’ll build a studio, they’ll grow their careers, or something like that. You have built a community center, you use this money to change really horrible situations in the world, and your music is developing awareness and a form of activism. Can you share a little bit about the story where your lyrics may have crossed a line for your label? You shared something about that with “there’s a girl in the room.” I just thought it was so fascinating about the context where your music is normally released versus the experience that you have as a faith-based artist for a faith-based label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: It was “When the Saints,” a song based on “When the Saints.” I had written the original with a bridge that basically talked about “I think of Harriet Tubman, I think of all these people that have gone before me.” There’s a lyric, “I see a…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It builds and basically ends with a picture of a girl on the brothel floor, I see a man with a passion come and kicking down that door. That was one of the stories I had seen. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svay_Pak&quot;&gt;Svay Pak&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippines&quot;&gt;Philippines&lt;/a&gt; was a sex tourism site. It was a place where if you were a pedophile, you could go and you knew you would be unhindered. The brothels were in cahoots with the police, so there was no protection. These children were being trafficked in the open, basically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was one of IJM’s first jobs. They went there and they just began collecting undercover investigation materials and documenting all who was there. The youngest was as young as 5 years old and they brought all this information to a man in power who wanted to do the right thing. So they started something and began a work there that led to eventually the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_%26_Melinda_Gates_Foundation&quot;&gt;Bill Gates Foundation&lt;/a&gt; doing a study, an external study of their work in the Philippines. In Sebu, Philippines and in other places, they saw as much as 87% reduction of the trafficking of children in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Their work is just amazing and it works. It’s creating a barrier that’s basically telling these guys that think, “I can just do whatever I want.” You can’t do that with impunity. You will go to jail. It creates a buffer, a hedge of protection around these children. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wanted to write about that guy. I knew who the head investigator was. I’d seen footage of him kicking down the door of the brothel to get these girls.&lt;/span&gt; So I’d written and talked about the brothel and all that. When I went to go record the song, they really liked the song, but felt like maybe there was a different approach to the bridge just to fit more with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had written this whole other bridge and it was more going back to historically-Biblical figures and moving then further through history. We had tracked the whole thing, we recorded the whole thing. My husband was out with a friend and he was talking about how much it bothered him. It kind of lost its original–the whole point of the song, we wrote it because of this girl we had met and because of the stories we were hearing. So, I was 8 months, maybe 9 months pregnant and Troy comes home and was like, “We have to re-cut that bridge.” We called the producer. The record is done. It’s finished, and I think even mixed at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LxT_RqPt660?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was very last-minute, but Brown was producing that record and he called the studio in Minneapolis and we got in and I re-sang the entire bridge. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the sense was that talking about brothels in India and brothels in Southeast Asia is not safe for the whole family. For me, it just felt like that can’t be my goal, that can’t be what I’m prioritizing over telling the truth about what I’m seeing.&lt;/span&gt; We decided to go with the original lyric that I had written and that made sense. The song has gone out and had much of more an impact because of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The song was chosen by iTunes to be the “discovery download for that month,” so back then–they don’t do the same things exactly now, but back then they used to pick–and you couldn’t buy it. A label couldn’t in any way coerce how this was happening, but iTunes would pick and they would move through different genres. Maybe once or twice a year, they would pick a Christian song. It was the discovery download of the week, so they picked that song to be the discovery download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This was before the album was released and we had friends who had been working on a project to bring down this certain really insidious brothel and they had tried several times. I think they were on their seventh try to have the police come and raid this. Every time they went, someone had tipped them off so the girls were hidden or gone. So, a friend of mine emailed them and said, “Sara Groves has written you a song, “and it was uploaded that night at midnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;On iTunes, the album wasn’t even available yet, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;but where they were gathered in south Asia, they gathered around their little computer, listened to the song, and then went and conducted this raid with the police and were successful and ended up capturing and freeing all these girls.&lt;/span&gt; And I just thought that was such a neat moment for me, that the music–I had written it for them, to advocate for them to get their story out and here they were gathered around these tiny speakers really finding encouragement from the song. The director of that office wrote me later and said, “We rescued that girl. We all gathered around the computer and then went out and did it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: So for me, yeah, that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;that lyric was right and telling the truth about what I was trying to say. That was really important. It might seem like a small thing to push back about, but it was important to me. That’s always the balance that you’re trying to figure out and market your music and being true to yourself and all of those things.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s just an incredible testimony to so many things, particularly the power of music and music as art and that art is important. With that being said, why don’t you tell us a little about Art House North, what it is, why you started it, and what you’re doing with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, so I came over here because my house isn’t very quiet this morning. My husband and I own a 100-year-old church and right behind you is actually the album cover of Abide With Me and that’s a picture of 1906, that’s a picture of the building being built and the first congregation are having their first service out in the street there in front of the building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, so that’s the art house being built. So we bought it in 2011 and we really modeled it–so Charlie Peacock has just been a mentor and friend for many years. Watching his and his wife’s life, they were influenced by a lot of different people–&lt;a href=&quot;http://labri.org/&quot;&gt;L’Abrie&lt;/a&gt; and that kind of idea of having a place to gather, be able to ask questions. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In Nashville, I found a lot of places where you could get information about how to run your business, but a place where you could actually talk about what it means to be a person of faith in the world, what does it look like? What does it look like to tear down the sacred and secular divide and just be yourself? Be wholly integrated and just be doing what you’re doing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I used to talk to Charlie about not writing about the filter, but writing about what you see through the filter. That’s the kind of Christian artist I wanted to be, that I wasn’t always writing about the Christianity itself. Maybe those songs are valuable, I’m not diminishing that, but for me &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I felt really called to the integrated life. If it matters, it matters at every level and it matters everywhere I go and in every part of myself, so I wanted the music to reflect that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we watched them have this community in Nashville. They started Art House in Nashville and they bought a 100-year-old church and they actually lived in their church and had a studio there and that’s where we produced “The Other Side of Something” and “Fireflies and Songs.” We would gather there with them with other people to hear about–I learned about IJM at Art House and just talking about what kind of person you want to be in the world, what it looks like to be a person of faith, and to use that wisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, Troy and I in 2011 bought this place and we don’t have a good elevator speech because all kinds of things happen here. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The tagline is “Creative community for the common good.”&lt;/span&gt; We have two parts of Art House. We have community partnerships where people have come around us. We have a theater company that the couple that runs it lives a block away from us. Our kids are all in school together. They’re just amazing. They write original plays and they do them here, probably about three per year. And then we have, Troy and I, our Art House programming. That is all kinds of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We have afterschool music lessons for kids that kind of resemble School of Rock. We do a square dance every year. We have all kinds of things around the arts. Our neighbor is a banjo player and he came to us and said, “Nothing brings a neighborhood together like a square dance.” So we started that tradition 4 or 5 years ago. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And then Troy and I host events where we’re talking about different topics. Our format is “Artists Respond.” Artists respond to tragedy, artists respond to creation care, artists respond to gun violence, artists respond to whatever the topic is. Immigration…. So we call up 3-5 artists to respond to a topic and instead of having a panel or talking heads, that kind of thing, we let people just express through their art how they’ve experienced that topic.&lt;/span&gt; And then the discussion ends up being a lot richer and a lot more nuanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think we’ve lost nuance, we’ve completely lost nuance. It’s just almost impossible to actually reason together. So we found that through the arts you can do that a little bit better. Someone says, “I wrote this song because I was compelled by what I saw.” And also it’s often coming from a place of lament instead of anger. You tend to find that, I think, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when we invite artists that they are able to share their lament about whatever they see that’s incongruent in the world&lt;/span&gt;, if that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3y8JSNknIzE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Totally. That reminds me of a video you have on your website. I think it’s called “Extravagance” where you talk about how an artist can see what he or she does as extravagant or wasteful. Could you elaborate on that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, so another person I listen to a lot is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Makoto_Fujimura&quot;&gt;Makoto Fujimura&lt;/a&gt;. He’s a visual artist. He used to be in New York City. He was there when 9/11 occurred and was kind of part of a vital artist’s movement around 9/11 to bring spaces of healing to New York. He’s written a lot about that. He wrote a book called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Refractions-Journey-Faith-Art-Culture/dp/1600063012&quot;&gt;Refractions&lt;/a&gt;” and he’s written a book called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0830845038/ref=dbs_a_def_rwt_bibl_vppi_i0&quot;&gt;Culture Care&lt;/a&gt;.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He just puts forth the idea that culture is not a war to be won, but it is a garden to be cultivated.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The difference between a combative stance or a blaming stance where you stand around–I think about that cellist in the middle of that bomb crater in Sarajevo. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s easy to stand around the bomb crater and talk about the bomb crater and how it got there and who’s to blame for it and its dimensions and how deep it is and what a loss it is. It’s something different to crawl in there yourself and start creating something beautiful and to have this protest of beauty in the middle of chaos.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Both Makota Fujimura and Charlie Peacock have shown me what they call the “generative life.” That is the life that crawls into that space and says, “What would I build here? What would I put here? Even if it’s going to be bombed out again. Even if the war doesn’t stop. Even if the chaos doesn’t stop. What generative thing would I put here?” And so that was from a blog he had written about, I believe, the war in Iraq. He had written about this little girl that, in running back to save a flower, she saw a flower and she had been struck by a bullet. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Everyone said, “What a waste,” and yet Mako was saying in this gesture, he saw this child identifying with something beautiful in the middle of total chaos and that action was a very valiant effort to save something beautiful on her part.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He talks about how the arts can feel–we can feel as contemplatives, sometimes, the time it takes to contemplate, the materials we’re using, all those things can feel extravagant and wasteful. When we’re in these sort of utilitarian and pragmatically-driven spaces. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He says utility and pragmatism have infected every institution we know and he said maybe primarily the church where we equate “useful” with “good.” That began a dialogue in my own heart. “Oh wow, what do we do with useless people? How do we think about that? What do we do with the parts of ourselves that feel useless and lacking?”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At the time, I had been going through some depression and was having a very hard time being productive. My productivity levels were down the drain. So what value was I at that point if I wasn’t producing? So I began thinking differently about my life. “Okay, I’m having a hard time these days getting out of bed. I’m genuinely moving more slowly. So what is the value? I think there’s something here for me to learn and to listen to.” My body was telling me something. My everything was trying to get my attention. That record, “Floodplain,” was really looking at those ideas of extravagance and wasteful. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;To me, the Mississippi River is the dream of God.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e_bukdxhBKo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was looking one day at the city of St. Paul on the bluff and I thought, “The city is the dream of man. It’s amazing what we can build. What we can do. It’s incredible .You look at a city and it’s mind-blowing what we can do. We work together and we accomplish and we strive and we make these cities.” But then there’s the river running by the city. This is an invitation. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is kind of if you want to know how God is different from us. We could not make the Mississippi River. It is other. It’s so other than us.&lt;/span&gt; It’s other than what we would do and it’s an invitation to this extravagant kind of Huck Finn rest. “Come on, get on a raft. Let’s go sit a while and ponder.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Those things can feel like, “Oh what a waste of time.” And yet, I think the arts are necessary to push back against that pragmatic, useful constant dream of man that kind of whirs around us. I think it’s important. I actually think once a week we should get away and enter into this space really intentionally, into this dream of God. Obviously, I want to be participating in the dream of God and what I call the “kingdom imagination” at all times of the week. But that record “Floodplain” ended up being about my journey with depression, but finding value in pushing against that pragmatic space and entering into those extravagant and wasteful “I’m gonna do something totally lavish.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s amazing. I’ve spoken with the artist Steve Vai. He’s a guitarist that also thinks at this level. We were talking about what he calls “the movie projector metaphor” where we often think our life is what’s happening as the film crosses the movie projector, but we’re really the light. We have the opportunity to choose to be what’s on the film or to be the light. It reminds me a lot of what you’re talking about with this “filter.” You’re wearing these glasses and you have this worldview that applies to whatever it is that you’re seeing and experiencing. So can you talk a little more about how you’ve discovered as an artist what your filters are and how to move beyond that? The world wants you to have their filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, yeah. That’s a good question. I think that–I love that projector [metaphor]. That’s going to stay with me. I try to be a student of people I admire, so if I find somebody and they’re just intriguing to me–we’ve just lost &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene_H._Peterson&quot;&gt;Eugene Peterson&lt;/a&gt;, a pastor of profound gift. I was lucky enough to have met him and his books have shaped me for years. I’ve tried to read “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Long-Obedience-Same-Direction-Discipleship/dp/0830822577&quot;&gt;A Long Obedience in the Same Direction&lt;/a&gt;” once a year. But people like Eugene Peterson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Brueggemann&quot;&gt;Walter Brueggemann&lt;/a&gt;–and my dad was very much this way, too. He was always encouraging me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Kind of what I said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you can get stuck thinking so much about the filter and defining it constantly that you kind of forget to actually do the thing. Talking about the thing and doing the thing are two very separate things.&lt;/span&gt; I see for me, the word “Christian” has come to mean a lot of things. It evokes a lot of feelings in people, especially right now, but to me, at the base level, it’s being an imitator of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ra3lh0DCIDY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;To me, Jesus is–so, every man says in his heart, all throughout history, “If I were God, if I were God, if I were God, if I were God…” And then the story, as the story goes, this is God himself coming and he had every right to just roar, to just completely level, to be God. And he is God, as it says in Philippians, he didn’t consider equality with God something to be used to his advantage, but instead thought of others more highly than himself. That was what God did when he came. Even if you don’t believe that that story is real, that’s compelling. That’s very compelling to me. We’re used to “power over” always, people pushing and it’s like this is the story of the apple. It’s “I want that,” forcefully taking and possessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we know what that looks like. We see that play out in history a bazillion times, in seriously every heart. Even my dog has said, “If I were God.” Every single one of us says it. And here’s this story about God himself coming and purporting, “I am God,“ and then doing something so completely different and humble and not “power over,” but in service. So I think that what I want to be doing is sort of integrated. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madeleine_L%27Engle&quot;&gt;Madeleine L’Engle&lt;/a&gt; said there is no such thing as sacred and secular art. There’s only good and bad art.&lt;/span&gt; And I love that because I think, “Okay, I want to be putting beautiful and good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think when I do that, I’m participating in the divine nature and so I want to put those things into the world**, but I always want to be thinking about embodiment. Not just what’s happening “here” in a sort of philosophical or theological level, but then always asking the question of “what does that look like when I’m in a fight with my husband?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u15Ew-SIz6A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I wrote a song called “Roll to the Middle” when we had literally had the most massive fight. The full-blown, all bets were off and we were unloading 100% and he was leaving town, going overseas for three weeks. I thought, “He can’t leave like this. I know the right thing to do, I just don’t feel at all even remotely like reconciling at this point, but he can’t leave the country with us in this place.” So I went to the piano just in search of anything. A song of reconciliation. That song ended up being beautifully so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I played it for him. It came out in a matter of 10 minutes and half an hour later, “Can I play you something? It’s so weird, I know.” But I played that song and it’s like, no matter how my pride resists, no matter how that wall feels true, no matter how I can’t basically make you respond this equally, I can’t make you also apologize, but I’m going to lean into you. I’m going to not let you go like this. So that song ended up being a part of our reconciliation, so always looking at “what does this actually look like in human terms in what we’re actually doing here?” Not just having a faith that is for the hereafter, but very much, I think that is what Jesus says more than anything. The kingdom of God is near, it’s actually among you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I listened to that song last night and was pretty astounded at the honesty and how much I could relate. Everybody in a relationship has to go through something like that. You can choose to let it ruin you or you can use it as an opportunity to learn about yourself and the relationship you’re in. So, hearing that in a musical context was very moving and powerful. Again, it’s just a testimony to how when I listen to your music, how much power there is in your art. I don’t normally listen to lyrics, I grew up playing guitar. Shredding. So, when I listen to music, I’m mostly listening to the music, but you have a way of using the word and the lyric to really get through. The music is a context that you use to allow the word to move forward. So, that’s another thing I really admire about you and your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re welcome. Can you talk a little bit about patronage? That was a topic that we discussed, you discussed more broadly at the St. Paul experience, you and I spoke a little bit individually about, and it’s really impacted your recent career. So, talk a little bit about patronage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Well, I have to thank you because you encouraged me to take a step. Troy had been already on board for probably–since it started. He got early wind of what Patreon specifically was doing, but that conversation with you–Troy said, “Of course, one other person says…” He’s been telling me for so long and then he says, “One other strange person…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m finally that person. I’m always in Troy’s position, but now I’m on the other side. Cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah! But I think the coin maybe somehow dropped when we were talking and I thought, “You know, I need to move forward with this.” What I say about music, and there’s a lot to this obviously, this is a whole big conversation. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the music scene has changed so much and the way I describe our own lives is we were working one field for a yield and then we were working two fields for that yield and then ten fields and then it became unsustainable because of streaming.&lt;/span&gt; We’ve lived through many disruptive technologies, we’ve seen the move from cassettes to CDs and then CDs to streaming. And then even downloads then to full-on streaming, just where everything is basically free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ud5XLIOBLys?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I remember a few years ago asking our label, “So what happens on…” We were doing all this pre-release stuff to try to sell the record early and we basically–Dan Michaels had said, “You have about a month to sell your record before it comes out to the people that really want to hear it.” And I said, “What happens now because release day used to be such a big deal?” It was such a huge day and then the next month was the big month. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So I said, “What happens on release day?” And he said, “Oh that’s the day your album is free.”&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs.] And I was, “Oh my word!” I hadn’t really fully processed that yet that, oh, that’s what happens. That’s the day your record is available for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think that liminality is good for the arts. I think that it forces creativity and we’re in a space where we have to think differently and traditionally, the arts were always supported by patronage. Someone wanted &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Joyce&quot;&gt;James Joyce&lt;/a&gt; to write, so they supported him, put him up in an apartment and paid for his meals and all that so that he could write. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent_van_Gogh&quot;&gt;Vincent Van Gogh&lt;/a&gt; even was constantly having to write home for more money, but he had patronage from his brother and different people to do what he was doing. That long defeat that he walked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, there’s a short little window from the 1940s til our present in 1995 where we were able to sell a CD and kind of have this exchange, but that window has closed and we moved into a different time. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think a lot of artists are looking back to the sort of history of the arts. The arts have always required endowment.&lt;/span&gt; Troy always says, “Look at your portfolio, your support. You’ve got these stocks, you’ve got these things, are you supporting the arts?” Maybe you’re supporting public radio or something. If you’re enjoying something are you supporting it? With Patreon, you and I had talked about that, but that’s basically created a tool for artists to be able to connect with their listeners in a very direct way and create and hopefully bring value to that relationship. Deepen that relationship so that you’re bringing more exclusive content to the people that really care about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can’t support every person you listen to with streaming music, but I think you can consider what 3-5 artists do I listen to a lot. How am I actually engaging in the marketplace with them? Am I buying a t-shirt? Am I going to a show?&lt;/span&gt; To think about that, if I’m really participating and if someone’s music is really resonating with me and informing the way I think about the world, am I then somehow participating in the making of that music? I think that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patreon&quot;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt;’s created an amazing tool to let–not everyone’s going to love my music, but there are people who’ve been listening for a long time. You had so, I think, given me permission. I think I felt–it’s kind of hard. It’s a hard paradigm shift to go, “Am I asking for some sort of hand-out?” Because you’re actually again having to put value on what you do as a vocational thing. I think in the arts that can be a struggle anyway. You’re always kind of like, “Is this valuable?” [Laughs.] So, yeah, thanks for the encouragement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re very welcome. And how has the response been?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: It’s been amazing. We’ve been up for about two and a half weeks and I have 130-140 supporters at this time. It’s just a game-changer. I had posted just for Patreon listeners a little song that Ruby and I wrote. It’s a prayer that we kind of sing, not every night, but often for all the people that would be displaced on any given night. We know there are millions of people who have been driven from their homes because of violence or whatever. Thinking about the refugee, thinking about those mothers that are on the road, carrying their whole lives on their back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I just wanted a prayer, something that Ruby and I could sing or say that would just be something we would repeat and remind us of the refugee at any given time. So I wrote this song, “Jesus See the Traveler.” I posted that for our Patreon folks and I posted just a clip of it to my Instagram. Not the full song, but the response was really overwhelming. People were asking, “Where can I get this song? Can I get the whole thing?” So I’ve already booked a studio and players and we’re going to track that song, Ruby and I are going to track it in the first week of November, and then that will go out into the world. Then I’ll be able to tell my Patreon supporters, “You did this! Literally. That would have just languished in my song notebook because I wouldn’t have the resources to put together an album.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gY-3LtJtPIE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m basically on an 18-month to 2-year cycle because I’m paying for those albums. I pay to make them. It’s a huge investment.&lt;/span&gt; So, that’s a difference. I’m dreaming every single day like, “Oh I can do that. I can actually record that song.” And that’s something I used to be able to do, but just in the last ten years, how am I going to fund that? How am I going to get that to happen? So it just really is–I cried the first week [laughs] because I told Troy, “I don’t think I really appreciated the impact of not being paid vocationally for a while.” And then to have people come and affirm that again and say, “Yeah we’d like you to do this for a living.” You know? Even though I know that that’s my role in the world, it was very affirming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s very difficult to understand that separation of “this is what I’m called to do” and “this is how the world makes it happen.” You don’t want your identity to be tainted or poisoned by the way an industry might work, but I’m really glad you did it and there really are hundreds more people who want to give you money. They’re just waiting to give you their money, you know? It’s like, just get the word out and they can offer even a dollar a month. It’s like buying a CD a year, but it goes directly to the artist. So, I think it’s a very powerful thing and I’m really glad that it’s working out for you. So, congratulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Thank you. We kind of tied it in where we’re merging what I’m doing–it used to be kind of like “here’s Sara’s music” or “the touring entity” and then “here’s Art House” but we’re really seeing the two working together now. The Art House is the umbrella. The Patreon is also going towards everything we’re doing in our lives, that creative community for the common good. The music is a big part of that. Obviously it’s coming out of here. I write here at this piano and this is where that begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qavipq-IgkM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s also powerful, at least for me–I only have a handful of patrons. I don’t push the Patreon thing very much, but just knowing that there are people who want me to be doing this and they’re sacrificing their own money and their time (because they had to earn the money), it encourages me to keep going and to release things and to make it interesting for them. I don’t know if you’ve experienced that as well, but it sounds like you’re starting to. It’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, the ideas–I have this long–I’ve been ruminating on this idea for a long time to go back and meet with people that I’ve worked with in the past, like Charlie and Don and Lori Chaffer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterdeep_(band)&quot;&gt;Waterdeep&lt;/a&gt; and these other bands that I’ve worked with, and to do sort of a vlog of us writing together. Basically where we get together and write a song. I’ve lined up two of those already in January. So in January, I’ll be going down with a couple friends who do film and they’ll be basically capturing us writing music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m just excited about the possibilities. I have no idea what the song–what will we write? What will we create? I think just letting people into the process more, too, is a lot of fun. It used to be like you squirreled away and you did your work and brought it out. It’s a fun idea that–I love the author &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austin_Kleon&quot;&gt;Austin Kleon&lt;/a&gt;. He says he’s an artist that writes or a writer that draws. I can’t remember, but he does these kinds of doodle things and he curates a newsletter about creative writing once a month, I think. It’s very life-giving to me. I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But Austin, he wrote the book “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Steal-Like-Artist-Things-Creative/dp/0761169253&quot;&gt;Steal Like an Artist&lt;/a&gt;” based on the idea that we’re all just taking all the pieces that inform us and creating something new with that. Anyway, I’ve just been so inspired with this. I could actually dream about–have ideas and put things into the world now, where before, “That’s a really cool idea, but it’s cost prohibitive,” or, “That just doesn’t work.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I have worked with this label, but it has always been a marketing and distribution deal. Troy and I have funded our own album making from the beginning. It’s like buying a car every year, you know?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yep, definitely. Awesome. This has been a great conversation and I really appreciate you taking the time. So many great insights and I know that people come to these interviews with artists because they’re people like you who live it out and you are really a gifted artist and I’m very happy that we could have this conversation. So thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Me too. Thank you, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How can people learn more about you and start to discover your work and those kinds of things? How do you recommend? And best support you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Well, Patreon. I have a new Patreon. [Laughs.] What do you call it? An account?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Page? I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SG: Page? Page. But if you’re not ready for that, there’s music out there. SaraGroves.com, there’s no ‘h’ on Sara and then ArtHouse.com as well. Sorry, ArtHouseNorth.com. Those are the places that explain what we’re doing. Anywhere there’s music, you can find my music. Yeah, I recommend “Add to the Beauty” and “Floodplain” if you’re wanting an introduction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/sara-groves</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/sara-groves</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nik Bärtsch Solo Piano Show</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nik Bärtsch is a world-renowned Swiss composer and pianist. He’s released several albums on ECM Records as well as on his own record label, Ronin Rhythm Records. His music is deep, layered, and hypnotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We brought Nik to &lt;a href=&quot;http://stilwellpianos.com&quot;&gt;Stilwell Pianos&lt;/a&gt; in Mesa, AZ on October 18, 2018 for a special solo piano concert. The footage on this page is from that evening. We are honored and proud to release it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modul_14&quot;&gt;Modul_14&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy this incredible encore performance of &lt;em&gt;Modul_14&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/30peP3O3aMI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/nik-baertsch</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/nik-baertsch</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>California Guitar Trio at the MIM</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;toccata-and-fugue&quot;&gt;Toccata and Fugue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The California Guitar Trio is renowned for their ability to do “circulations,” where they pass notes from one player to another. Their use of circulations is on full display in this amazing three-guitar arrangement of J. S. &lt;em&gt;Bach’s Toccata and Fugue&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AZ_dfQaGZSE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weird-fishes&quot;&gt;Weird Fishes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the California Guitar Trio and the Montreal Guitar Trio performing Radiohead’s &lt;em&gt;Weird Fishes&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a beautiful arrangement with an emotional vocal performance from Glenn Lévesque.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZBt7nn8762c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shining-road&quot;&gt;Shining Road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the California Guitar Trio performing “Shining Road,” a beautiful piece by guitarist Fabio Mittino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iFJ4zxVaZ1Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/california-guitar-trio</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/california-guitar-trio</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>percuss.io</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;percussion-education-technology&quot;&gt;Percussion Education Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Carraway and George Torres III are the brains behind the amazing viral music video site, &lt;a href=&quot;https://percuss.io&quot;&gt;percuss.io&lt;/a&gt;. They are creative geniuses who’ve incorporated &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;Soundslice&lt;/a&gt; into videos of extremely complex musicianship. Their most popular videos have had several million views on Facebook and Instagram. They’re bringing amazing music and complex performance to the forefront of social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mOMLRMfIYf0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uYldcW_0Hig?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;podcast-audio&quot;&gt;Podcast Audio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/percuss.io/percuss-io.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/percuss.io/percuss-io.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Eric Carraway and George Torres III are the masterminds behind an awesome web technology platform called percuss.io. What brings us together is our common love for Soundslice. You may remember that &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;I interviewed Adrian Holovaty, the founder of Soundslice, back in February 2016&lt;/a&gt; and that kind of got things started behind the scenes for the both of us. We just recently started messaging because I’ve been coming across their viral videos that have millions and millions of views and they’re really technical, really awesome videos that I never would have expected to blow up the way that they did, but I did notice that they’ve been using Soundslice for some time, so I reached out. And it turns out our relationship goes a little longer than my faulty brain had remembered. So, Eric and George, thank you so much for joining me today. I’m really excited to share about percuss.io.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Well thank you for having us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: We’re really glad to be here. Actually, how we met, how it initially goes back is your website, I came across it when I was doing research on Soundslice and noticed that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MakeWeirdMusic&quot;&gt;your website is open sourced and it’s on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. I’m a web developer, so I was able to go through it and I think what I did was added a favicon (the little icon up at the top of the browser window). Yeah, it was cool! I got to do a pull request and we kind of hit it off that way and then coincidentally, we touched base about a week ago. Yeah, we’re really excited to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. Yeah, so can you tell the world a little bit about yourselves and what brought you guys together to start this website?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, dude. That’s a cool story! So, I’m the content and community manager for percuss.io and I know Eric from our music background. I recently had moved down to San Antonio and he was telling me about this project that he was starting up and how it’s been his passion project and he was really trying to get it off the ground and make it live and make it a real, living, breathing thing. When he was telling me about it, it sounded like it was going to take off and I was totally about it. So he kind of recruited me in and I was sold ever since and that’s how I started with Eric. Eric can go further as far as how he actually created this brainchild of percuss.io.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah, so my background… I’m a musician and a web developer. Web development is my second career. My first career was as a high school band director here in Texas. I taught music in the public school for about eight years and always had this second passion, which was programming. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I decided to make an industry change from full-time music teaching to web development, but I knew that I always wanted to eventually do work that combined those two passions: technology, programming, development with music.&lt;/span&gt; Specifically, music education. percuss.io–I actually bought the domain back in 2014, not exactly sure what it would be at the time. It was initially a place for portfolio projects. It eventually grew to be a brand and now an online percussion education platform and, specifically, all the stuff we do on social media, which has probably gotten the most attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, can you tell a little about that story where your videos just completely exploded unexpectedly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: The first viral video–so, the first video to do over a million views was your friend Terry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JIpSakQIV84?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/lettersbyterry/&quot;&gt;Terry Jarrell&lt;/a&gt;. It was this super-unconventional combination of literally &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JIpSakQIV84&quot;&gt;onion powder in a container and chili powder in a container and it was this weird kind of shaker thing.&lt;/a&gt; It was a minute long, but, again like you said, it was unexpected. We posted it because we thought it was fun and that it would be cool and, sure enough, within 72 hours, we had over a million views. We were like, “Well, I guess this is what the people want.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: And we use Soundslice for that. So, she’s doing 16ths in the right hand and a 3:2 clave with some treches, the spices. It’s condiment shaker things. But yeah, we transcribed it all, notated it all, sync it with Soundslice, and it just really got attention because it was weird and it was a bit nerdy at the same time because we went through the trouble of doing a transcription. From there, we had lots of people reaching out on our social media channels and a lot of collaborations then–because we had that one initial piece of viral content, that gave us a lot more opportunities because people reached out to the page, said, “I’d love to do something similar with videos that I have if you’re willing to transcribe it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s cool that you used the word “nerdy” because what you’re doing is very nerdy. I mean, you’re taking extremely complex–not in every video, but in many cases, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konnakol&quot;&gt;konnakol&lt;/a&gt; videos that you feature, lots of time signatures, very intricate groupings of notes, and I had never even–I’d seen some of the videos where somebody’s replicating the spoken music (or the sung music) on quad drums. You know? That’s very technical and each drum being lit up. I was like, “Wow. That’s someone who appreciates really complex music and somebody who’s spent a lot of time with Soundslice. This takes a lot of very nerdy work to make it happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah. And you would think that because it is so–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s brainy and it’s kind of a niche thing. We never would have expected such a large audience.&lt;/span&gt; So, I think some of that is shock and awe. People are seeing something for the first time that they’ve never seen before. It’s curiosity and it’s educational, too. If we can do something that brings those things together, makes people really curious, inspired, but at the same time, teaches them something, that’s kind of the goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell me about some of the feedback you’ve gotten from people who you kind of blew their minds, this was a new discovery for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Wow. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think showing people konnakol for the first time has been really rewarding.&lt;/span&gt; It’s something that’s a tradition. It’s an Indian musical tradition of vocal percussion that has been around for millennia, for thousands of years, but its mass appeal and exposure here in the West is something that I think is very recent. One of the first people to reach out since that first viral video was a gentleman named &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/bcmanju/&quot;&gt;Manjunath&lt;/a&gt;. He sent us a video and was like, “I’d love to do something together.” I asked him, “I would love to do a notation sync video of this, but is there any chance you could provide some notation? This is very complex.” I wasn’t about to go down the path of starting to transcribe it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There was a breakdown there because that musical tradition is entirely oral.&lt;/span&gt; It’s learned by ear, it’s passed down from a guru, from teacher to student through just memorization. It’s not written out, so that was an opportunity to do something where I was like, “Oh, okay. So if we can find a way to put this into western music notation, it helps those of us who are maybe not familiar with the very complex mathematically-based rhythmic patterns.” It’s a way for us if we are better at reading music notation to have a deeper understanding of it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I began a transcription that took months to get across the finish line, but once we did, it blew up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah. Immediate payoff for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[NOTE: Here is where I begin a mini-interview with Manjunath BC, the maker of several konnakol videos that have gone viral via percuss.io.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I wanted to hear a little bit from you about how it has impacted you, what they are doing has impacted you personally and professionally with respect to music and what you think they’re doing bringing konnakol to broad audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: Yeah, just to go a little bit to get into the history–it was me because I went to their page and just looked into what they were doing. It was like exactly one year ago last September and I just sent them a message, like, “Hey guys, I am doing stuff. Would you be interested to transcribe what I do? Because I don’t know whatever you try to transcribe from my videos, I would say it’s correct because I don’t understand what you do. It looks very interesting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I always thought the things that I was doing was more fascinating for people who could read staff notation and percuss.io–I never saw a staff notation that was scrolling with the video. It was the first time I saw it and I was like, “Oh my God. Holy shit. This is really cool.” I just told him, “Why don’t you just do one of my videos?” And he said, “Okay, send me over.” Of course you know, Eric is the one whom I was talking to. And I just sent him a random thing. And the first-ever video that they did of mine hit 6.5 million views. It was like, “Really?!” What is that? You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: I’ve never seen a million views in my videos. Of course, there were a lot of hundreds of thousands, but million–the first time. My God. And of course, a lot of people started approaching me for classes and then I guess I could come over and do stuff with them. Yeah, percuss.io has impacted a lot on what I do and also I’ve now started thinking of how I can just give it to them. What kind of material? There are a lot of videos which I do thinking of them in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you feel that they have expanded your options in terms of “I have new ideas of how this could be notated?” Or, “I might do something…” I saw the fibonacci sequence video and I thought, “That’s amazing!” There’s never been music notated quite like that. So, are you thinking out of the box now and open to new options? Are you providing them with those kinds of crazy ideas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: Well, I just throw a bunch of things to them and then they just pick it up. Whichever they find interesting, you know? But certainly, they’re doing a harder job than I’m doing because I just put a video camera there and I do my stuff and then get it done within, like, 10 minutes. But the things that they do takes weeks sometimes because the fibonacci thing, I think it took more than two weeks for them to do it. It’s not easy to do. I’ve never seen something like that in my life, this kind of spiral notation. Then I went and saw there were a lot of spiral [images] but it was not used for musical notation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then now, of course, I am thinking recently, like two days ago, I did a video with [a girl?]. I’m kind of overambitious now trying to send them whatever I do, which I shouldn’t do now. It’s not good because they should also do other stuff, not just do konnakol konnakol, you know? I see there are a lot of konnakol videos now in percuss.io. But, it’s good in a way. It’s very clearly notated so people can understand what’s going on rhythmically. At the same time, I have to be very careful, but they’ve been doing an amazing job. I’m really impressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Since it’s an oral tradition (what you’re doing), are there people that see anything that you’re doing in a negative light in terms of you’re formalizing this, it’s not supposed to be this way? Or has everyone been very supportive?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: To be honest with you, I don’t care. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s the best answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: The more I care, the less creative I’ll get. So, I just let my imagination go wild and then there are a lot of really bad stuff that’s on my page, it’s really uninteresting. Really no taste. Nothing. But I just keep trying, you know? And then that makes–maybe for the first time, if they’re traditional, they think maybe it’s all bullshit, rubbish. But once everyone starts to think–it’s normal when your own people don’t recognize you and somebody from the outside recognizes you, then they start valuing more. I think that’s what has happened with a lot of people. I would say I have got a lot of friends and fans in India, too, so they have all been just positive about what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Though I say, “I don’t care,” of course because there are a small number of people who always don’t like what you do. It’s with everyone. Even the biggest of the biggest. They have that, so who am I? I’m the smallest little drop in the ocean. But still, there are a lot of people who–more than people who dislike what I do, I think there are magnanimously more people who like what I do. I would say people are turning around back again towards me, so it’s a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s fantastic. And what would you say to anyone who is inspired by what you do, but they don’t quite know how to get further into it? It looked like you were running some training sessions. Do you have a video series or anything like that people can learn from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: Yeah, there are a lot of things in the pipeline I’m really thinking of, but it’s not just what I do. I just keep a phone on the window and do a video. It cannot be so easy, you know? So you need to do more of the physical work than the mental work. Whatever I have been doing all these days has been just my mental work and purely depending on how far my creative talent ability can go. This one requires more technical side of people, so I need to get a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And one last question. How much do you have to practice to do something like the fibonacci sequence? Counting to 21 doing all the complicated stuff that you’re doing, whether you’re subdividing or not, that had to have taken months of preparation, in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: Well, that particular video maybe took about 3-4 days for me to prepare, but I think the whole musical system is such–the music system that I’m coming from is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnatic_music&quot;&gt;carnatic music&lt;/a&gt;. It’s South Indian classical music, so it already has most of the ingredients that trains our mind to understand how to approach different things. Especially to understand anything that’s going on with me, carnatic rhythms are really one of the best tools for a musician to have. I would say, I keep preparing all the time. Mentally. But a particular thing I’m trying to prepare, I’m trying to tell a story or something like that. Especially that fibonacci video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It came from my father. I was 12 years old when he talked to me about fibonacci, but I didn’t understand anything. Then a few friends of mine from–especially one particular friend from Italy–explained to me what was a fibonacci series. And then my father was dying and then I was watching Discovery Channel and then that day, some fibonacci thing was going on. So, I was like, “I should show it to my father.” So I prepared a little thing and then I went and tried to show it to him, but the same afternoon, he passed away without even listening to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh my goodness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: So, yeah. It was for him. Not even for Facebook or anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: And then one week after he passed away, I thought maybe I should prepare it better and then just put it on Facebook. And percuss.io picked it up and edited it so now you see it’s become a huge thing. There is some truth in it because my father is inside that composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, I’m very sorry for the loss of your father, but what a tribute to him and what an amazing thing to come out of that event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BC: Thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[NOTE: Back to the interview with Eric and George.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely. The most recent one that I saw was–it’s funny, I’d seen that video outside of your Soundslice notation and there’s a young woman and an older guy who are singing together on the steps on this awesome YouTube channel. I can’t remember the name of the channel. Do you know it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iurhjlBum0o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7NdODNgLYVKKs6a6VCKHQQ&quot;&gt;MadRasana&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes! What an awesome, awesome channel. But, this woman, she’s hitting her hand on her thigh in quarter notes and it kind of gives you a sense of what’s happening, but then you realize, “Oh, she’s going into 7 and then she’s going into 5 and what she’s singing is almost completely separate.” There’s that real independence going on, and then they come back together, and then you hear the two singers doing it in unison. When I watched that video, I thought, “Oh my goodness, this is really, really rich music.” And then to see your transcription knowing that this stuff is orally passed on, I can’t even imagine the effort that you had to go through to make this happen. Thank goodness you have a music education background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Well, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amiroosman.com/&quot;&gt;Amir [Oosman]&lt;/a&gt; actually–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Dude, he’s the real unsung hero on that project. You can go into more detail, but the actual quad player, the work that he put in to actually making that happen is, I would say, almost unprecedented for something like that because it’s so unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, it’s amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: So, he learned it to do a cover video and this was before we combined our transcription. We had known each other through Instagram and I’d seen his work and he’d seen mine and our stuff, we knew we wanted to work together at one point and I remember he posted something on his Instagram feed. Maybe he’d finished up a project and was looking to start a new project and was like, “What sort of cover videos should I do next?” And I commented immediately in the thread and was like, “Konnakol. You need to go check out konnakol.” And I think a week later, he posted his first konnakol and quads video. He learned it within the span–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Within a week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Within the span on a week. And when I went to him afterward, I was like, “You transcribed all this before you played it, right?” He was like, “No.” He memorized it! He memorized it and the video is not edited and choppy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: It’s not spliced at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: It’s done in one take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/86T5171_zkU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Over four minutes in konnakol and quads in one take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: It is accurate. It’s rhythmically together. His background is similar to ours. He’s been through the college music situation, teaching music, doing drum core, we’ve got shared &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drum_Corps_International&quot;&gt;DCI drum corps&lt;/a&gt; history… All of that stuff is taught on paper and to be able to learn that much music in this totally different style–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, totally. I mean, unconventional to us here in the US. Just incredible. Truly a feat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: So he was able to provide a transcription of his part. The syllable transcription–there’s a pianist composer based in Paris that I was able to track down that had done a transcription of the syllables. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/s%C3%A9bastien-gaxie/202160031?ign-gact=3&amp;amp;ls=1&quot;&gt;Sebastian Gaxie&lt;/a&gt;, I think is his name. I reached out to him. I had already gotten the ball rolling with Amir, so I was able to bring those things together, get them into Soundslice, added our component of the light-up drums. The red and blue for the right and left hands. Did that video and it, again, went viral. We actually were able to publish a really clean–in addition to the Soundslice video–a really clean PDF transcription as well. Was able to get professional manuscript preparation done by another friend of ours, Bill. It’s cool to bring people together for these collaborative projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jA_3g8zgMf0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely. Now, can you talk a little about the success of the site and the fact that you have blown up. What have been some of the growth needs, the challenges, the exciting parts? I wanna hear the ups and downs of something growing to the size of what you’ve gotten. You’re on a great trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah! Do you remember any specific numbers, like specifically from Facebook? Views, followers…?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Oh yeah. I mean, we weren’t even in five figures yet. Probably February of 2017, I think, is when we hit 1,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Followers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, followers on Facebook. That was a kind of cool thing. I wouldn’t say there was really traction quite yet. It was slowly getting there, little by little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah, so one of the challenges has been: for what began as a side project, a passion project, is that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;progress is not linear. Not by any means. It comes in fits and starts.&lt;/span&gt; There’s moments of mad inspiration and productivity and being able to do tons of transcription videos. And on my end, development work, website stuff behind the scenes. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And then there can be long stretches of the opposite where things are–it doesn’t feel like the product is making a lot of progress.&lt;/span&gt; But, I think zooming out far enough, we’re able to see progress. Continue to stay motivated and maintain that feeling of momentum for the project, that’s been a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, I think that’s the best way to think about it. Once you have that momentum, actually being able to continue to sustain it over that long period of time instead of getting a viral video and then plateauing for a little bit, and then, “Okay, yeah, we got another spike.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And then something else takes interest in the community.&lt;/span&gt; So, just understanding the ebbs and flow of that entire process. Being on a social platform and understanding that this percuss.io is kind of new to our drumming community as well as from the social standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And do you have some sort of a paid learning platform? How do you generate any money from what you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Generating money. Yes. So, that’s been a challenge, right?&lt;/span&gt; Because the majority, the vast majority–we have nearly 80,000 followers on the Facebook page and what percentage of those people will go to the actual website? Percuss.io and sign up to use this percussion education platform, which right now and for a while has been in this kind of beta stage, preview stage. We are launching a Version 2 of that very soon. Right now, it’s been largely everything’s kind of free. It’s been largely a passion project, but it’s something that we do want to do more of and my goal is to be able to do this within a few years, hopefully, full-time. That’s been a challenge. Where my skills are in the technical side of things and the music side of things, knowing about how to do a business plan–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: And how to do marketing, and stuff like that. That’s just a challenge because I don’t know as much about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: To kind of add on to that, a lot of this came from a shared vision of: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we want people to go and experience what this is, to have it educational because there are so many areas not just in Texas, but all over, where they don’t have that extra lesson teacher.&lt;/span&gt; They don’t have that specific instructor to give you that attention that you need in the classroom or individually. So we started by making this free to the masses because that’s genuinely what we wanted to do and that was a huge part of Eric starting this in the first place. How do we get these resources accessible to literally anybody? Pull out a phone, boom, you’re done. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I hear you. I know some of those challenges having my own passion project and hoping it reaches people. It’s a tough time right now because content marketing is been this great strategy, but there’s so much saturation in it now that it’s hard to rise above. So, that’s what I think is amazing about what you guys have done with your videos. You seem to have a way to rise above what everyone else is doing in a fairly frequent way. So, kudos to you. That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: I appreciate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So can you tell me about this Hyperdrive illuminated vibraphone project that you have going on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Lnul3DwS_bc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah! It’s awesome! Okay, so this duo by the name of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCY_27qWGeEM1OAA9Ebqv_CA&quot;&gt;Team Islas&lt;/a&gt; is two people. It’s a married couple living out in Plano, which is in the Dallas area. Patricia and Islas, as well as Doug Bush. Patricia is the vibraphone player and Doug does all the drums and percussion part of it. The inspiration of this whole thing, when they first released their album back in 2008, was that they wanted to eradicate the stereotypes of keyboard percussion. To make it into this musical platform that is intellectual, yet accessible, for everybody to enjoy and to listen to. Specifically, with this project, the Hyperdrive project, it’s this new album that they’re now created that’s going to be released pretty soon in the future and–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: It’s a concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: It’s definitely a concept album with the overarching idea that it’s a dystopian future and it’s about a girl and her vibraphone saving the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: It’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, they make it awesome. The sounds that are incorporated are incredible. Go check out the YouTube video if you haven’t yet. It’s on the page and it’s really awesome. It’s truly a combination between the vibraphone–there’s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wernick.net/&quot;&gt;xylosynth&lt;/a&gt; and a bass guitar with drums in the back. The entire thing, this four-minute piece, is pretty incredible. But yeah, what makes that unique, what stood out to us whenever communications started back on Instagram, it was one ‘like’ to the other ‘like’ and it was like, “Hey, this is actually really cool.” And the perspective of the vibraphone being a birds-eye view was so key to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Not only did they have this awesome music that’s never been done before–or just in a completely different light–but to add that perspective is pretty unique considering it’s keyboard percussion. Most of the videos you’ve seen of a keyboardist playing is usually a front view in front of the keyboard or at some kind of angle. So, yeah, I think that gave us a really cool opportunity to, again, add the light-up keys to the vibraphone because it was such an incredible video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KTGJyNgFTRI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah. So keyboard percussion–the marimba, vibraphone, xylophone–it’s a very visual instrument. We talk about the guitar being a “shape” instrument. In a similar way, keyboard percussion is a “shape” instrument and you rely a lot in the learning music and memorization on what things “look like” on the keyboard. The technology that we’ve developed to light up the bars as the performer plays, from a first-person point of view video, like a birds-eye video with a camera mounted above the keyboard instrument, it makes it way more educational.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Students who–maybe we’ve got all-state audition etudes or different pieces of marimba literature, we’ve been able to shoot these videos from that perspective, add the overlays, and then put it into Soundslice so that it can be slowed down to a practice tempo, looped small sections at a time, and, importantly, click anywhere in the sheet music to see that part of the video. So, it’s combining all of those technologies to make something that we feel is educational.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s really amazing. I’m sure you, as a former band instructor-turned-programmer, have had to go through a lot of challenges in learning how to do this. Can you talk about–can you get somewhat technical in your approach on this and the approaches that didn’t work or what you had to go through to get to where it did work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah! So, it’s been for a long time, I’ve wanted to figure out how to do these kind of animations. It began years ago with paper flashcard-style things of the keyboard instrument–the vibraphone. I would learn chord voicing with flashcards of pictures of the keyboard instrument and filling in the notes that would be played. You can do a kind of stop-motion animation with something like that. From there, I found out some different presentation technologies that can trigger different images with MIDI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then in about 2007 or so, I switched over to the Mac ecosystem and learned about the IAC bus, which is a way to share a MIDI connection between different pieces of software. So if I’m driving MIDI with Sibelius or driving MIDI with Pro Tools or even GarageBand, I can run that into VJ software that responds to MIDI, or at least for a long time there was a tool called Quartz Composer, which is a node-based visual programming language. So, wiring together different things–if you’ve used MaxMSP or those sorts of node-based tools… It’s a way of wiring up a MIDI connection, the MIDI and the audio are synchronized, and then the visual overlays are done via MIDI. There’s recordings that happen from there and then overlays happen in post-production with video editing tools and kind of a green screen effect. It’s lots and lots–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That sounds like a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Lots and lots of pieces wired together and some of it’s really just hacky and not glamorous, but it works!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s how most code is. As a software development manager for the last 10 or 12 years, I can attest. It’s a norm. So, what I think is really great is that you’ve got Eric who’s doing a lot of technical work and George who’s doing the community work and I’m just making an assumption there based on what I’ve heard. I’ve found in my own work and in speaking to a lot of musicians, that community manager role is so key, but we don’t know how to do it, how to find someone who knows how to do it, and how to keep people engaged. So George, would you mind talking a bit about community engagement, what that means for musicians or music-related content? Particularly, using social media so that musicians might be able to glean some useful information to promote what they’re trying to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah sure! Absolutely. I think this goes back to when we first started back in February. We were kind of determining “how do we want to split up this thing between us two as far as whenever somebody sends us something, what do we want to do with that?” I think what’s really cool is that even though I have that title, we still share a lot of the same responsibilities as far as reaching out to people or posting something on Facebook or on the Instagram. Getting it so that way it looks great on those platforms, but I think it’s about finding those relationships from people that you know in all different kinds of aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;With me personally, yes I do this thing at percuss.io, but I’m still teaching all over the state and Eric’s background, when he was a music educator, he has almost a different generation of people that he can also reach out to or that he can create videos to target in that sense. And so, I think in my opinion, in that community role, finding those relationships and being able to expose them to what this is and to just stay in contact with those people and being able to continue to work on those projects I think is key. Obviously, Eric has played a big part in that as well. I definitely don’t take credit for just that single role. It’s all team-based a majority of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that’s really cool. Go ahead, Eric. Please.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Oh, it’s a really good point that it’s very relationship-driven. Sure there’s a lot of great technical stuff going on under the hood. The music is awesome, but of the music, of the technology, and of the relationships we’ve been able to build with people, and the people that we’ve met across the world–I include you in that group–the people that we’ve met from collaborating and doing different projects together, that’s been the most rewarding part. To make those friends, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, it’s incredibly challenging. I have a small fraction of your audience and I think, “How do you keep up?” I have 40 or 50 unread messages. I look at it, it’s overwhelming, and for a site that’s your size, the fact that you’re able to keep up with people is amazing. So, my hat is off to you. It’s amazing. [Laughs.] Can you talk about the future plans for the site? You mentioned a “version 2.” What does that mean? What are you guys looking at for the rest of 2018?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah! It’s really exciting. Currently we’re doing quite literally a retreat summit right now and blocking out this weekend of time to just focus on percuss.io. In the immediate future, we have this version 2 coming out of the site. There’s kind of two things that are coming out of it. We’ll have an official marketing site just for percuss.io so that people can actually have a very concise and very appealing way of seeing how percuss.io works and what people can do to get their content on our platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;On the opposite side of that, we’re going to have a learn.percuss.io where we can have people go over to actually use it as an educational resource for us. That’s the most exciting thing right now that’s happening in our immediate future. Eric can talk about the future plans as far as content that we’re looking to do and collaborations with organizations and artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah, the marching percussion part of what we do, that’s a large part of our audience. There’s a lot of people that we connect through. That’s how we’re connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: We were in a DCI organization called The Cavaliers. Although our ages are 11 years apart–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: 11 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: We weren’t in it at the same time, but that’s kind of how we grew up and our musical background. That marching percussion community, we’re doing more work with that. In that community, the audition process is a process of getting a PDF packet of exercises and etudes and excerpts and it’s not great. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re looking to disrupt that by using Soundslice and using our platform so that students who are auditioning for groups have better access to tools, recordings, videos, breakdown videos synchronized with music notation through using Soundslice. And all in one place.&lt;/span&gt; So, we’re looking to do that through the drum corps and the WGI indoor drumline audition processes. We’re looking to do some stuff with the Texas all-state band audition materials. So those are two projects that we’re on the horizon for percussion education and what we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s fantastic. And for anyone who doesn’t know about DCI, it is some of the most extreme musicianship you could imagine at the ages of people that are performing it. My friend Jim Reiske came from The Phantom Regimen. He’s always sending me videos and I look at these videos and I know professional musicians who could not do this. These kids are way overboard. Like Frank Zappa-level vibraphone players and not only are they playing, but they’re walking around and moving and all the choreography is just unbelievable. The DCI stuff is just mind-blowing. Every year, it seems to be advancing and advancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Oh definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AXOSQd7pxXk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Showing what the capabilities are of young people with instruments and time to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s going to be really cool to see how you contribute to that furthering of human capability at that level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, that’s definitely the goal. I think that would be a big milestone for us. Being able to actually have that resource for a drum corps organization or for a WGI organization. Definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, absolutely. Oh, I missed a project here that is the notes. This one with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Kass&quot;&gt;Rich Kass&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tigran_Hamasyan&quot;&gt;Tigran Himasayan&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know how to say the names. I’ve read them online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/E_lPE7kn834?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But, amazing musicians!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah, we’re familiar with the problem of name pronunciation. That’s for sure. As percuss.io, we run into all the time, people aren’t sure how to pronounce our names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: “Percuss IO.” “Percussyo.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: “Percuss dot IO.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: “Percusho?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah, that’s another one. Our name comes from being at the intersection of percussion and technology and “.io” is a top-level domain like “.com” or “.org” that’s frequently used in the tech industry. But if you’re not in the tech industry, it doesn’t really land. People might think we’re “percussIO.com.” So, Tigran Hamasyan, which I think–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: And Rich Kass. So, Rich is a drummer that we’ve collaborated with on a number of projects. He’s just exceptional at polyrhythms and really complex time signature changes. Just feats of coordination between all four limbs on the drumset. Been able to do stuff that has ostinatos on his feet–or, ostinati with his feet. And different melodic things going on in his hands. It’s unconventional drumming. So, this most recent project is a cover he did of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pVN36Ou4BUU&quot;&gt;Tigran’s “What the Waves Brought.”&lt;/a&gt; It’s piano with beatbox and Rich transcribed all of that and made a drumset part for it. So, we worked together to get that into Soundslice and did our process of doing our notation synchronization recordings. We released it on our social media channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6ZvrFW7tsfw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Windows is telling me important updates are pending. Thank you very much, Windows. Sorry for that interruption. That’s really cool and yeah, they are incredible players. Rich on the drums and Tigran on the piano. Are there going to be more projects with those guys?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Hopefully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: If they’re willing, absolutely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Speaking of monster drummers that are outside the box, have you worked with Terry Bozzio at all on any of the visual stuff? Does he know about your platform?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: No, I don’t think so. We really admire his work. I’m just inspired by him as somebody who’s been able to use the drumset as a solo instrument through using melody and harmony and coordination and several parts going on at the same time. So as opposed to the drumset being in a traditional role as a complementary thing or just timekeeping, Terry Bozzio as a solo drumset performer with actual compositions, that’s–if we could transcribe one of his videos and do a–yeah, that would…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Actually last night, I was listening to the video that you had, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/terry-bozzio/&quot;&gt;that phone interview that you had with him&lt;/a&gt; a few years back. What I took away from it was just the perspective that he has when he’s actually playing and how it’s just a sense of calmness. It’s at such a high level for him and everything around him–it’s just different. You know? Being able to have him outside looking in is like, “Whoa, this thing is incredible. It’s crazy.” But to him, it’s not like that at all. It’s quite the opposite and I thought that was a very interesting perspective that he has because that’s something I would have never thought about him as he’s actually playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right! Well, thanks for checking that out. [Laughs.] Awesome. So for people who want to find out more about your site, who want to check out your videos, how do you want to instruct them to find out more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Yeah, so probably three things. One are our social media platforms. Our &lt;a href=&quot;http://instagram.com/percuss.io&quot;&gt;instagram is just percuss.io&lt;/a&gt;. On &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/percussiosoftware/&quot;&gt;facebook, it’s percussiosoftware&lt;/a&gt;. So, connect with us on social media. Like, share, follow. That helps just get exposure and then, we have a lot of content on Soundslice Channels, which is a relatively new feature of Soundslice. It’s community-driven where people can share their work. So we are the premier percussion content creator on that platform. So connect with us there, and check out Soundslice while you’re at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then thirdly, our website. It’s just &lt;a href=&quot;https://percuss.io&quot;&gt;percuss.io&lt;/a&gt;. There, within the next couple weeks, we’ll have the new marketing site up that has a clear explanation of who we are and what we do and how to work together. And we also have the learning platform as well where you can sign up with your email address and have access to every project we’ve ever done. We embed the Soundslice videos there and have them catalogued and organized by categories you can search. So, both of those things. Updated versions are rolling out soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Very cool. I really want to thank you guys for not only being here, but for doing what you do. The internet is such a powerful platform, obviously, but it seems sometimes to be commandeered by business interests. To see what you guys are doing, bringing real technical music education to the forefront and introducing people to new music, to me that really is such a special thing. So I’m really glad you’re doing what you’re doing. Thank you for doing that and thank you for keeping on keeping on, because there are days where I feel like giving up and you guys are doing it right. I’m sure you face those times too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: Yeah, for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So yeah, thank you again. And I look forward to seeing what you end up doing in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;EC: Thank you! Thanks for having us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;GT: It’s been a real pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gear/percuss-io</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gear/percuss-io</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Divine Abstract by Charlie Cawood</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/18CdEleFkNk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/charlie-cawood/the-divine-abstract/the-divine-abstract.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/charlie-cawood/the-divine-abstract/the-divine-abstract.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charlie Cawood’s &lt;em&gt;The Divine Abstract&lt;/em&gt; is a work of art. It is immensely and entirely beautiful, full of wonderful rhythmic and melodic content. It brings together Eastern and Western music in a cohesive way. There’s no MIDI, there’s no sampling, there’s only one keyboard part. Every instrument is performed by a real human being, carefully selected by Charlie based on their ability on specific instruments. It’s the kind of album you can listen to while meditating, while working, or while doing nothing else but listening. For every purpose, I’ve found it offers great joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy “The Divine Abstract” as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://charliecawood.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;digital download on Bandcamp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-bandcamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s just a few bucks and is worth every penny. Check it out!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I’ve listened to this album, the more indescribably beautiful it becomes. The melodies linger and are easy to sing, but there’s so much interesting supporting material for discerning listeners. It’s well-recorded, well-mixed, and just fun. It’s an adventurous piece of music and I’m glad to have it in my collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview is particularly insightful. Not only does Charlie have a deep grasp on the history of the dozens of instruments featured on the record, but he understands their purpose, their texture, their timbre, their roles in an ensemble. He shares with us the path he’s taken to get here, including a deep look at his depression and anxiety, which has been extremely challenging for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cover a lot of ground in this conversation and I hope you enjoy it as much as I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Charlie Cawood is a multi-instrumentalist from London who is a member of the band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knifeworld&quot;&gt;Knifeworld &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and has released a solo album called The Divine Abstract. Charlie, thank you so much for joining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Real pleasure, Anthony. Thanks for having me on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, no problem. So, tell us a little about yourself and tell us about your album, The Divine Abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Well, I’ve been playing music since I was about 11. I just started getting into playing guitar, studying classical guitar and electric guitar at the same time. Listening to mainly rock music, I suppose, and then very gradually started getting into Indian classical music, some Spanish music, and sort of wanted to get an active involvement in these types of music. So I started studying sitar when I was about 13 years old and continued from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WzXVxOT8an0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Later on, got into other Asian music. Japanese music, Chinese music, and then started picking things up along the way. Then, eventually went on to studying seriously at the London Center for Contemporary music and later, SOAS, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOAS,_University_of_London&quot;&gt;School of Oriental and African Studies &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in London. I was studying at the same time Western popular music, jazz, classical, rock, blues, all the stuff you learn in music college, but at the same time had this real serious interest in other types of music and wanted to have some kind of active participation in it. So I learned about Balinese gamelan when I was at SOAS and then straight away when I graduated, started going to sessions and learning about it and playing. I’ve been doing that for six years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I also was lucky enough when I was studying to be taught things like orchestration and arrangement and all of these more elaborate things that you don’t get taught in many places. And then gradually started getting interested in other music. Lots of contemporary classical music, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Reich&quot;&gt;Steve Reich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igor_Stravinsky&quot;&gt;Igor Stravinsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, practically minimalist and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivier_Messiaen&quot;&gt;Messiaen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all. I was kind of influenced by lots of different types of music from everywhere. Originally the music I was listening to on the rock side of things was fairly ordinary. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron_Maiden&quot;&gt;Iron Maiden &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;s and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bad_Religion&quot;&gt;Bad Religion &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;s and stuff like that. Still into it, but then in my late teens, started hearing things more like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis&quot;&gt;Miles Davis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardiacs&quot;&gt;Cardiacs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were a particular revelatory experience for me. And I got to see their last-ever London show back in 2007, which was quite a moment of epiphany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The Divine Abstract–I didn’t know it was going to be an album until half of it was already written because it was part of that process of becoming immersed in other types of music. Having interest in all sorts of different types of music. I didn’t really see any sort of disconnection between them. And so I was writing pieces that had some elements of Indian classical music and had an element of contemporary classical and I was trying to get Chinese elements in there and this sort of cyclicity of Balinese gamelan. And then, about halfway through writing all the pieces, I realized, “Actually, these have got a sort of shape to them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The album didn’t really–I didn’t think of it as being an album until half the pieces were written and all written for different reasons. Some were written while studying, some of them were informal commissions from people. Actually, one of them was written–“Garden of the Mind,” which is in the middle of the album–it was written for an ensemble in the [United] States who never ended up playing it because it was too difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then, I think it was actually Kavus [Torabi] from Knifeworld that heard a demo of that and said, “Well, this sounds like a thing. You should put it out when it’s done.” And then, that was the point where I realized, “Oh actually all along I’ve been writing this–it’s got a kind of shape to it. There’s a kind of arc running through these pieces.” So I started writing stuff that would become the later part of the album, things like “The 32nd Path.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I always knew it was going to be this quite ambitious effort that’s going to necessitate lots of different instruments. It was going to draw upon lots of different things. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wasn’t quite sure for a long time how well these tunes would actually sit together as an album. Would it really work?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I turned freelance about seven years ago and started playing in all kinds of different projects and working as a full-time musician and teaching and all of that stuff. So I was playing in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knifeworld&quot;&gt;Knifeworld &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from about 2012 and working with them quite extensively and also working in other bands like &lt;a href=&quot;https://tonochrome.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Tonochrome &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-bandcamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; started around that time. I was playing in an art rock band called &lt;a href=&quot;https://spiritwo.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Spiritwo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-bandcamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which had Bob Leith from Cardiacs on drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I was playing all these different things and being fairly young and in this state of working on lots of things at once, it’s always your own project that gets put to the side. I always knew it was going to be quite a difficult thing to orchestrate and finish off. I did actually start rehearsing bits of it and making tentative recordings about four years ago. I had made a concerted effort to try and get the thing done, but then I started getting into a state of depression more and more. That’s when that period started, around then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also around that time I started touring with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medi%C3%A6val_B%C3%A6bes&quot;&gt;Mediaeval Baebes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who I was a multi-instrumentalist for. And so, again, it was another thing that I put on the back burner for a while because I was working on so much. Then, it was around late 2016, I had that fairly low period, which I’ll talk about a bit more later. I just knew that this had to be done, so I started finishing off and orchestrating the last two or three tunes on the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y2MQbUTmvFo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I got in contact with my friend Amir Shoat, who’s a really good engineer and producer who I worked with before in London. I got together with him with all the demos and everything that had been recorded so far and, “Okay, well this is the thing.” With his advice and help and support, I was able to think of how to approach this because I knew it would necessitate loads of different instrumentalists and I knew it was going to be quite difficult music to put together and edit and mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The original demos didn’t really sound that cohesive as a thing. They sort of sat and it sounded like these could have come from different places. That was one thing we had to be careful of: making sure that they all sounded like they all flowed and they all sounded like from one place. The remaining few months I managed to call up loads of musician friends who’d be up for playing on it and contributing. In that time of me being a freelancer in London, I’d been lucky enough to meet all these different people who ended up on the record. Some of them I didn’t know when I first started writing it, so it’s almost as if it needed that time to gestate and slowly develop because some of the musicians who made the most important contributions on the album, I didn’t meet until a couple years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It just seemed right to have them on there and it all worked out for the best, really. The whole thing of doing it, because it was quite an intense period having to record everything and then do all the editing myself, it was the two of us mixing it. It was quite intense, but it felt like I was doing the right thing. I was finally focused on what I should be focusing on. It was such a relief to finally have it done, because the very last tune on the album–most of the tunes are fairly sequential but it’s almost in a sort of consecutive order from when they were written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The first tune on the album is the earliest one and the very last tune on the album I didn’t finish writing until about a year ago. It was this sort of big seven-year arc that covered the whole writing process, which happens to play out in 45 minutes. It’s like it covers quite an expanse of life, as it were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s actually something I really love about the album. It is such a rich and layered album with so many different textures and sounds. Can you talk a little about the instrumentation? How many different instruments are on the album and how many of them do you play yourself? For people who may not know who you are, you are a bit of an enthusiast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah. In terms of what I played personally on the album, I didn’t necessarily want myself to be the focus instrumentally, so obviously I’m playing acoustic guitar and classical guitar and bass, but a lot of the melodic focus is taken up by the instruments I orchestrated for, like the woodwinds and the strings and pitch percussion and pianos and Chinese instruments and things. Mainly because I like music that’s texturally rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve been a guitar player since I was 11 and I’ve been through the whole period of wanting to hear lots of guitar music, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there was a point where I wanted to hear music which had lots of different textures in it&lt;/span&gt;, lots of different sounds and instrumentation. Not necessarily needing the guitar to be a focal point and that’s what I wanted to get in my own music as well. I wanted to have all these guitar parts that are kind of the skeleton of the tune. The tunes were written on guitar and then later orchestrated, but I didn’t necessarily want it to be the focus all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I played all the guitar parts and I also played sitar, Indian sitar on the very first track. On several of the other pieces, I play Chinese pipa, which is this sort of pear-shaped lute thing that you see behind me there. Apart from that, I didn’t want to shoehorn in any of the other instruments I play onto the album. There’s a lot to choose from, but I didn’t necessarily want to try to get them all on there. It’d be sort of unnecessary and sort of inappropriate to do that. So that’s why there are twenty other musicians on the album. I couldn’t tell you how many instruments there are in total, but there’s a fair amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LdygoJ0kZCY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: A few dozen, probably? [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Probably yeah, because seven of those instruments are doubled up. Lucie Treacher, who plays on “The 32nd Path,” she layered all the gamelan instruments that are on there. There’s about 8-10 different gamelan instruments on there that she did in the course of one day. We just multi-tracked them and I’d take them all and edit them later. There’s all kinds of things on there. It’s kind of what I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One of the things that I love about these instruments is sometimes it’s even hard to tell if it’s a vocal part or a woodwind, if it’s a human-created sound. Sometimes it sounds like keyboards, but I’m pretty sure you don’t have any keyboards on the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Only piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, but no synthesizers or electronic instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: There’s some Mini Moog on one track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: On “The 32nd Path” and the piano and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celesta&quot;&gt;celesta &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Samples, but they’re still samples of an acoustic instrument, so there’s no synth pads or anything like that and there’s no midi at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah so can you talk a little about the challenges of even engineering a record where–I wouldn’t know where to put a microphone on half of the instruments that you’re recording. So, what was that experience like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Neither would I, so that’s why I was so lucky to have my friend Amir working with me because he’s a real genius for recording acoustic sounds. He’s involved in lots of electro-acoustic music and experimental music and he does live sound, but he’s got this incredibly meticulous approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We’d have instrumentalists come in and sit with their instrument and he’d get them to play and sort of stalk around them finding the sweet spot where, “Okay, this is where we’re going to put a mic.” And then, “Maybe we’ll just have one mic in a very sweet location.” Some of them we might double up. He knows exactly what sort of microphones to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Working with an engineer like that who, with that kind of attention to detail, almost obsessive attention to detail when recording acoustic sounds, otherwise it wouldn’t have been possible and it wouldn’t have sounded as rich as it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s interesting what you said about how some of the melodic instruments almost sound like vocals because even though it’s fairly strange music and it’s very dense music, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wanted all along for it to have a very strong melodic focus.&lt;/span&gt; I like melody. Also I wanted this music to be able to tell its own narrative without the need for lyrics or voice. I think it’s totally possible to do that over the course of the album just using instrumental music. I love vocal music, but I find it more universal in a way. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It gets to a deeper state, I think, on certain instrumental music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But in terms of how I approached the recording of many of the instruments, it’d often be through collaboration. I’d get them to do a few takes of just playing the part straight. It’s all orchestrated, so it all exists in notation they’re reading. So once we’re happy with the part, I’d then get them to phrase it however they want. A really good example of that is on “Garden of the Mind.” There’s some brilliant clarinet playing by my friend Nicki Maher, who I used to play with in a band called Opaz [Ensemble], which was a sort of Turkish gypsy band with elements of Arabic and Kurdish and other things. I used to play in a band with her doing that kind of repertoire and she also plays G clarinet, which is much deeper–she doesn’t play it on the album, but it informs her phrasing doing all these melismas and quarter tones. It’s very colorful, decorative playing. It’s really expressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I recorded her just doing the part straight just to have it safe and then just said, “Okay, now play it however you want it. Just make it sound Turkish or play it the way you would play it.” And then she played all these brilliant–it’s the same notes, but she played it in her way. It’s like, every time I listen to that tune, it’s like, “Okay, there’s Nicki.” It’s just her characteristic and the other instruments I chose specifically for their richness in color. Say, on the three tracks that comprise the “Earth Dragon” set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a Chinese instrument called an erhu, which is a two-string spike fiddle. It’s a really simple instrument, but what it can do is it can sound incredibly emotional and expressive because of all these different ornaments that it can do. Again, that was another instrument I was really lucky to get because there are barely any professional players of that in London. At least, not many who would be able to play stuff that’s rhythmically challenging and elaborate as those tunes are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gmBYdPECGkw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I managed to find this player, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wang_Xiao&quot;&gt;Wang Xiao &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who played on the album. I basically told her, “These are the notes, but do what you want with it. Make it sound like your instrument.” Just in a couple of takes straight and it sounded like, “Finally, this is the first time I’ve heard in this seven years since I originally composed the piece, it’s the first time I’ve heard that part the way I imagined it by an actual erhu player playing it with all that kind of phrasing and delicacy of ornamentation and color and everything.” It was wonderful. Yeah, so that was a big part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Having Amir be able to record acoustic instruments so well was essential. The other thing was trying to make it all balance as well. That was the challenge for later on: editing it all and trying to make all the instruments sit together because they’re all recorded individually. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s no ensemble playing on the album, even though it sounds like it.&lt;/span&gt; There’s a lot of hours of editing and comping and mixing to make it sound approachable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Having Amir there as my other pair of ears, he would say, “Okay, this doesn’t make any sense here. I’m not quite sure what this part is meant to do.” And so he’d always be–if it made sense to him, then I know it’s working. If everything’s balanced correctly and not sounding too dense, kind of like obscuring everything. Because it’s so densely orchestrated music, it could easily sound like a mess. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Having him there and make sense of it all was essential, really.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I have to say it is a real work of art. It is not just a simple album. I don’t have ears attuned to all the various dialects of music particularly across Asia or a lot of where your influences seem to come, but to my western ear, I just thought about–between my western ears and my own sensibilities as a person who makes music, just thinking you had to learn all about these instruments. You had to learn how they sound and how they function. You had to learn how to orchestrate music to use those instruments and make an arrangement–you had to notate it so that you could have 20 different people playing on it. I mean, what an extraordinary work of art. It’s not like normal classical music where you can just hire this ensemble. I mean, you’re pulling influences from so many different areas, even if you went to India, or went to China, or Japan, or something, you wouldn’t be able to find the ensemble to play it. It’s such a homogenization of musical culture and sounds. So, it’s a real work of art and just the level of understanding that–and the journey you must have taken to be able to put it together–to me, is astounding. So, thank you for doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Thank you. That really means a lot. In terms of understanding about all these instruments, it’s just years of being a listener as well. When I was a teenager, I’d just be buying albums of Chinese music and Arabic music and Indian music and just listening and by ear being able to understand how these instruments work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was lucky enough to be taught orchestration as part of my music degree and I was really lucky because, in the place where I went (London Center of Contemporary Music), there were teachers there who could teach all these principles of orchestration and arrangement and things and that was totally necessary. And also, later on when I was at SOAS, even though it is oriental music and I was also doing some courses in Indian and Middle Eastern and everything, there was a little composition module there that I was doing and the fellow who taught that module (his name is Alexander Knapp) encouraged us to just write stuff to take some of these influences and do something that’s yours. He’d listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He’s a brilliant classical musician as well as knowing about Jewish music and Middle Eastern music and other things. So he’d hear this and say, “Yeah, this is really interesting and I really like it. Just do more.” It was that kind of environment in which I was able to finally coagulate all these ideas and realize that, “Yeah, this is a possible thing.” The instrumentation changes throughout the album as well. Each piece has a different orchestration, so if it were to be played by an ensemble, it’d have to be completely reorchestrated and reimagined for it to really work throughout a whole–which is part of the reason it’s not been played live yet. It’d just be… “How?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: That too, yeah. A guy can pull favors but there’s a limit to that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The thing about it being a work of art is kind of intentional&lt;/span&gt; because gradually, as I was coming to understand more about music and the reasons why I’m drawn to certain types of music (as well as other forms of media, like books or comics or graphic novels or films or whatever), &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I started to see them all as sharing certain ideals and intentions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vw1Sv04YQS4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For example, a big influence on me as a creative person is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Moore&quot;&gt;Alan Moore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the comic book writer who wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watchmen&quot;&gt;Watchmen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/V_for_Vendetta_(film)&quot;&gt;V for Vendetta &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, all this stuff. Just seeing him in interviews talking about art as being this catalyst for personal change and how as an artist &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s your responsibility to change the consciousness of the person that you’re communicating with.&lt;/span&gt; It’s totally possible. It literally becomes a form of magic to create something which then has a transportative or transformative effect on another person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Like this series here was what catalyzed all these ideas. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Promethea&quot;&gt;Promethea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it’s this really beautiful psychedelic comic book. It’s kind of like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wonder_Woman&quot;&gt;Wonder Woman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-ish superheroine character, but then it’s really an excuse for him to talk about these esoteric ideas. It’s really quite–[picks up a comic book] let’s find an appropriately psychedelic section. It’s got all this psychedelic art and the whole point of it is the imagination as a shared space that we can tap into as creative people and then we can draw from that and use that language to communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Reading about that made me examine what I want to do as a musician and why I like the music I do&lt;/span&gt;, or at least a lot of it. Those are the things which connect lots of different types of music that you wouldn’t necessarily draw together. It’s a cliche, but it’s why people in the 60s were drawn towards Indian classical music because it is very much a kind of devotional music, it’s a spiritual music that’s intended to transcend ordinary consciousness. It’s the same with the jazz I listen to, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Coltrane&quot;&gt;Alice Coltrane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&quot;&gt;John Coltrane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and Miles Davis, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pharoah_Sanders&quot;&gt;Pharoah Sanders &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, all these people. You start seeing all these connections and then also looking into things like dreams, the unconscious, and how our minds work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Artists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Lynch&quot;&gt;David Lynch &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for instance. There’s a big–the new stuff I’m writing, there’s a big influence, not necessarily musically but creatively, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_Peaks&quot;&gt;Twin Peaks &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a TV show that a lot of people know, but at its heart it’s about the relationship between the material world and the immaterial world where things exist and things that don’t exist and how the things that don’t exist can have a very serious, very real effect on the things that do exist. Thinking about mythology and symbolism and how art and music can represent certain things and induce certain states. That was all stuff I was thinking about all the way through the writing of the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are references all the way along to things and people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Blake&quot;&gt;William Blake &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There are several tunes which even the titles, like “The Earth’s Answer” and “Fearful Symmetry,” directly taken from William Blake. In fact &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the title of the album itself is a kind of compound of two of Blake’s ideas: the divine image and the human abstract.&lt;/span&gt; So, it’s a combination of those two ideas. He’s another character that recurs in my thinking about what I’m trying to do in terms of things I create because he had these, throughout the time, sort of visionary and unusual ideas about his own Christianity. He reversed a lot of the religious iconography at the time in order to communicate these quite visionary ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Similar things I can investigate in other cultures, like–I’ve got a few things here. So, William Blake’s “Songs of Innocence and the Experience,” that’s where those titles are taken from. And then the one that really had an effect on me was “The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.” Sort of this glare on that. And reading that was–but then reading things like this, which is “The Secret of the Golden Flower,” which I came across a few years ago and it’s like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daoist_meditation&quot;&gt;Daoist meditation &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; manual, but it’s all about, through meditation and through certain practices, you can ascend to higher states of consciousness. You can sort of become a new person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v3hQXQ5_zCM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also things like Joseph Campbell’s writing about mythology, like the hero’s journey. That played a big part in shaping the album, the track listing of the album. Where it begins and the arc in which it goes and where it ends. Like the last track, “Apotheosis,” the title comes from his ideas about the hero’s journey, how you’re taken out from your ordinary existence and you’re forced through all these trials and situations that change you into a new person. You take on all these new abilities and new powers, as it were, and then you overcome the parts of yourself that you want to get rid of. So you become a new thing at the end of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are little symbols and messages like that written into certain parts of the album that probably not many people have picked up on yet. I know they’re there. Like, the very last chord you hear, the cyclic thing you hear at the end of the last tune is largely in C lydian and it goes around that for a good couple of minutes. Across that, you hear the woodwinds do all these different melodies that go across each other and all happening at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Those are all themes from across the album I’ve taken out and they all exist in this shared space. They’ve kind of transcended their own time and exist in this shared moment. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And then right at the end of that, it resolves and modulates up a whole step to D lydian, which is where the album starts.&lt;/span&gt; The very first chord you hear is in a D lydian. I wanted it to be a bit more obvious, like with maybe the tune from the beginning coming back at the end, but it just didn’t seem to work, so it’s kind of there in a very subtle way, but probably not in a way that it’d be really noticeable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. That’s a really cool way of introducing all the cyclic aspects of life and these stories that you’ve brought in. Even in the artwork, it’s very–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: I couldn’t be happier with the artwork. That was a very late development on the album because the original image I wanted to use, I didn’t have access to because the artist wasn’t available. I had that as a planned image for quite a while and then it turned out that that wasn’t going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, it just so happens that through Knifeworld and going to these more proggy gigs around London, I knew &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Buckingham&quot;&gt;Mark Buckingham &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who’s a big, big fan of unusual music. He also happens to be an artist for Marvel and DC comics. He’s worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil_Gaiman&quot;&gt;Neil Gaiman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all these things. Brilliant artist. He was the artist on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fables_(comics)&quot;&gt;Fables &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a well-known fantasy comic that ran for quite some time. It was really popular. I got to know him at gigs and we’d chat about comics and music and things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He said at one gig, “Well, let me know if you ever need anything.” At the time, I still had this other image in mind for the cover. I said, “Okay, maybe next time.” Maybe I could ask him some other time. But it turned out that the original plan fell through and I just sent him a really panicked message saying, “I know you’re busy, but can you do something.” He said, “I’m busy but I’ll…” Yeah, the first pencil sketch, I had to make some changes to it, which felt pretty weird telling this really amazing comic artist. “Well, maybe we can make some changes.” It felt kind of odd. But then the second sketch was perfect and that’s pretty much what you see on the cover. He turned it into a really beautiful black and white, sort of art deco ink drawing and it was colored in later on with some adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I couldn’t be happier with it because he really listened through the album a few times and looked at all the song titles and made a lot of effort to integrate all those ideas into the mandala on the cover. It’s got elements from all the different tracks on there. It’s one of those real fortuitous things because I wasn’t planning that until quite late. It was about two months before it came out. Less than two months before it came out when we actually had the artwork. It was right at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/p5jt_8Tzu7s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is the music idiomatic to the performers and their instruments or did they have to spend time trying to understand what you were after?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Everything was orchestrated, so no one came up with their own parts, necessarily. Some of them made alterations to certain things, maybe in the piano parts. Certain voicings needed to be more pianistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I mean, because you’re blending different types of music, you might have had someone on the erhu playing something that might have been more of an Arabic type melody or something like that. Did you run into any of those kinds of situations or did you really just place the instrument where it was most appropriate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Oh yeah, definitely. I wrote for the instruments, so I made sure that the tunes that, say, the erhu played were the sort of thing you would imagine in who might play. It wasn’t taking it too far from its original context. In that way, it can play in its own way. It can be played and add their own.. It’s not something that’s unfamiliar. The only things that were unusual were the counting and–in the tunes, there’s all kinds of odd time signatures and hemiola and all kinds of stuff going on. That’s the thing that makes it not melodically that complex, but the rhythmic placement of it is quite unusual and definitely not the sort of thing you would encounter if you were a professional erhu player, unless you’re doing really “out there” contemporary music. Most of the time, it’s not really a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right. So I have some simpler questions that are more about being a musician. Doesn’t mean the answers are simple, though. [Laughs.] First of all, how many instruments do you play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: I kind of lose count. I think it’s about 15 at varying levels. There are some that I’ve been playing for a long time and some I’ve just picked up and learned on the spot, put on records and things. It’s about 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And how many do you own?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Uhh… [Thinking.] Somewhere around that. Fifteen, maybe. I’ve got two electric guitars, the Les Paul and the Jazzmaster. A classical guitar, acoustic guitar, a sitar, the oud, the saz, acoustic bass, electric bass, I’ve got a Fender 6 that’s on there. There are some that are borrowed, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hammered_dulcimer&quot;&gt;hammered dulcimer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that I use–not on the album, but it’s all over the Mediaeval Baebes album. It’s been used on a couple of things. That’s borrowed. And a couple of the other things are, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zither&quot;&gt;zither &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I borrowed. There’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harp&quot;&gt;lap harp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I borrowed for the Mediaeval Baebes album that is borrowed. Other than that, I lose count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs.] Okay, and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Too much mental occupancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you talk a little bit about the instruments in the room with you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Oh yeah, sure. I’ll introduce you to a few of them. The newest one I have, which I’m really excited about is this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What is that called?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: This is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsugaru-jamisen&quot;&gt;tsugaru shamisen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a Japanese, three-stringed lute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That looks like the instrument that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kongar-ol_Ondar&quot;&gt;Kongar-Ol [Ondar] &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I think his name is. He plays with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9la_Fleck&quot;&gt;Béla Fleck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and he does the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuvan_throat_singing&quot;&gt;Tuvan throat singing &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Oh right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It looks like that’s the same instrument that he plays. A two- or three-stringed thing that he just strums and plays some simple chords on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MgN_xIHqLUA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Might not be the same one, but the shamisen came from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanxian&quot;&gt;sanxien &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a Chinese instrument. It traveled over to Japan a couple hundred years ago. It’s slightly different. It’s got a sort of snakeskin body. There are other central Asian instruments that the sanxien is related to. Basically, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silk_Road&quot;&gt;Silk Road &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is where a lot of these instruments traveled. There are probably relatives in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuva&quot;&gt;Tuva &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongolia&quot;&gt;Mongolia &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and various places. The shamisen came into being when the sanxien moved over to Japan via &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Okinawa_Island&quot;&gt;Okinawa &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it fell into the hands of musicians who played the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biwa&quot;&gt;biwa &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is another Japanese lute instrument, which is played with this massive plectrum. I don’t play that yet, but at some point. So that’s why the shamisen is played with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is that flat?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah, it’s called a bachi. Originally, the skin was snakeskin and it changed to dogskin. This is synthetic. I’m a vegetarian, so that’s kind of preferred. The instrument itself is used in all kinds of forms. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabuki&quot;&gt;Kabuki theater &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, storytelling, chamber ensemble music, but tsugaru shamisen happened around the late 19th century. So, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edo_period&quot;&gt;edo period &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of Japan and mainly played by destitute blind musicians. It’s almost kind of a blues music. The style is a lot more aggressive and it fell out of favor for a long time and then over the course of the 20th century, people started becoming more interested in it. It’s really a cold, brash style. You hold your plectrum like this and your plectrum travels through the string and into the body, like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Ah, I can’t see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Can you hear that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Uh-huh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah, you’re gonna hear that. It’s quite loud. It’s got this kind of percussive effect. It’s become really popular with young people in Japan over the past couple of decades. It’s become fused with other types of music. These two players called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoshida_Brothers&quot;&gt;Yoshida Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who are kind of rock stars in Japan. They’re a duo playing this. I first saw it when I was about 16. There was a concert in London of the best player of this instrument, a guy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shinichi_Kinoshita&quot;&gt;Shinichi Kinoshita &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it was amazing. I’d never heard any Japanese music before. It was totally my introduction to a lot of East Asian music. It was just wonderful. The traditional pieces were great and he played his own compositions. It was a real life-changing concert. I wanted to learn it, but there was no one playing it in London at that time, so that sort of fell by the wayside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then a few years ago, this fellow moved to London called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hibikishamisen.com/&quot;&gt;Hibiki Ichikawa &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who is the only professional player in the UK, currently. He was actually on the soundtrack of this film called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kubo_and_the_Two_Strings&quot;&gt;Kubo and the Two Strings &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which came out a couple of years ago. It was a stop-motion animated film. He’s on the soundtrack of that. We actually did a gig together a few years ago and I thought, “Okay, I can get some lessons from him sometime.” Only recently, I’ve thought, “Okay, I need to do this.” I’m teaching him Western music theory and he’s teaching me shamisen. It’s three strings, fretless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SxsbKlKkCJg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you give a very brief sample of what you might play on that instrument?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah, sure. Remember, I’ve only been playing this for about a month. [Plays shamisen.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: It’s all that kind of stuff. It’s great. It’s really fun to get to grips with because you’ve got this wide vibrato and the sliding and it’s very improvisational, which is unusual for Japanese music. So, there’s that. I’m looking forward to learn more of that. In terms of stuff that’s on the album, there’s this and this is the pipa that I mentioned earlier. This is Chinese. This is actually related to the biwa, which is the Japanese lute. The biwa came from this and it dates back to the 8th century. It’s got a long history and it’s old, hundreds and hundreds of years. It’s got four strings. There’s your decoration on the thing there. And you’ve got a dragon carved on the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh wow, what a beautiful instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah, it’s all rosewood, which is lovely. What’s unusual about it, it’s played vertically, like this. You can see all the frets are raised off the body, like that. It’s played vertically and the fingerstyle technique is really weird. Your nails are going into the string like this. It’s the opposite of fingerstyle guitars. So it’s–[plays the pipa]. That’s your basic sort of sound. There’s also the really characteristic technique. The instrument uses a really fast five-finger &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tremolo&quot;&gt;tremolo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which starts with the index finger all going into the sort of strings like this. So it’s all five fingers. [Plays the pipa.] The reason why the frets are so high is because the instrument uses all sorts of bends and decorative techniques. It’s really versatile because of all the different sounds you can get from the instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: It’s lovely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s around your fingers on your left hand?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Oh this is for the shamisen, actually. This is the fingerguard for the neck of the shamisen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Ah. To protect it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah because you’re gliding along the neck all the time. This is just to help reduce friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And protect your skin, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: That too. The shamisen strings are this yellowish color because they’re dyed with turmeric. Notice these tiny blood stains starting to appear on the strings. It’s because I’ve been working hard enough. So, that’s great. The pipa is really useful for–I’ve been able to use it in all kinds of situations. I actually played this a few years ago in a performance of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Glass&quot;&gt;Philip Glass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; opera called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sound_of_a_Voice&quot;&gt;Sound of a Voice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a chamber opera based on Japanese ghost stories. They use this instrument because it’s tuned to a chromatic scale. It’s got very wide range, quite diverse tonally. So it’s pipa, flute, cello, and percussion with two voices. I was asked to play in that because I was a professional player of the instrument, which is unusual in this country, and I can read all the notation. It can be used in all kinds of situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7SBZrEHSbSE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. And that other instrument?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Oh, and this one here, that’s the massive one. That’s called a &lt;strong&gt;daruan&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruan&quot;&gt;ruan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a family of Chinese stringed instruments that’s actually older than the pipa. It kind of disappeared for centuries and wasn’t reconstituted until the 20th century where it was redesigned and turned into sections, like a string sections. I also play the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zhongruan&quot;&gt;zhongruan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is the tenor one. There are smaller ones, but this is the one I thought I’d show you, because this one is the massive bass one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Ah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: It’s really fun. I started playing this a few years ago and my teacher–I was transcribing a tune for acoustic guitar. A piece for this instrument because it’s in D A D A. Makes a deep sound. I transcribed it for guitar and she said, “Why don’t you just play on the actual thing?” And she just handed me this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: The performance of that was a week later. I had a week to get to grips with it and perform the piece of bass. It’s really unlike a lot of other Chinese instruments. It’s got this deep quality. [Plays the daruan.] So it’s got that real boomy, slightly brutal quality to it, which is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s funny. When it’s on the stand, it looks maybe as wide as an acoustic guitar, but then when it’s in front of your body, it looks like it’s bigger than your torso.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: It’s a perspective thing. It’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s very cool. All right, so, how do you make a living? London is one of the most expensive cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: It really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: In the world. And you live there, and you play all of these strange instruments, playing pretty much not-mainstream music. So how does that work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Well, I have played mainstream music before, but I don’t talk about that as much. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Making a living as a musician in London is practically impossible&lt;/span&gt;. It’s a really difficult thing and a lot of people either have to give up or just stop. Most of all, they have to bolster their income with other professions. Someone might just have a full-time job, maybe, or they might just–I know pretty well-known musicians who, during the day, will do painting and decorating work and then make weird music with the rest of their time. It’s pretty normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6DbJQhu_YGk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m lucky because I don’t have a family to look after. I don’t have children or anything, so that’s something that a lot of my friends have to deal with. I’ve been quite lucky with the breadth of experience I’ve had in terms of studying classical music and playing classical guitar and learning theory and things, being able to read, has been quite an important thing. The ability to read music well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of it’s teaching as well. I’ve been a guitar teacher for just over a decade, which has its own rewards and frustrations. It can be brilliant as well. I’ve got one student at the moment who’s about 11 years old and he’s just passed his grade 3 classical exam. All he wants to talk about when I get to his class is the anime series he’s watching. “Don’t start because I will talk to you about this.” It can be really fun, but I also–teaching evening courses and even though all the instruments I play might not necessarily be used for mainstream music, very few people are playing them on any sort of professional level, so I have the advantage of being “the guy that people can come” if they need someone like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Hence why I was asked to join Mediaeval Baebes. Kavus was the previous instrumentalist and then when he joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gong_(band)&quot;&gt;Gong &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he didn’t really have the time anymore, so he asked me to join. It seemed like a logical thing because I play all these things. So then you can get session work doing that. Things like the Philip Glass opera. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m pretty much one of two or three people who could have done that&lt;/span&gt; because the combination of playing the instrument well enough and being able to read pages and pages of classical notation is quite a niche skill. So I’m able to get by with that thing. Also just being competent enough to play bass and guitar in any situation that might be useful, though I have gone through periods of doing other things as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was actually on TV once. It was on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_Morning_(TV_programme)&quot;&gt;This Morning &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a real mainstream breakfast show. I was playing bass for a country duo, these two twin sisters. The only reason I got the gig was because I was friends with their manager and he saw a picture of me on Facebook playing bass and a hat on the stage with Knifeworld. He was like, “Oh yeah, looks really good. Bass and a hat. Fancy some television work?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: “Bring the hat!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah. I didn’t wear it on TV. It was too much for TV. And that was a thing I got to do once and was paid to do it by the manager and we signed a release form to use their image. Then ITV sent me a check a couple of weeks later for the same amount, so the occasional weird things like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So that’s a big hodge-podge of gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Oh totally. Just real corporate things where you’ll be playing in the corner and no one in the room is listening. Those are often the best paying gigs you’ll ever do. But, then that facilitates everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You do get by and you have a place in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: More or less, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you’re doing it, so that’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah, there are certain–it’s that thing of having to work constantly. It’s never quite settled so I always have to be active, but it’s just being lucky enough to know lots of people in London and being able to exist in all these different worlds in London and know the guys in the weird, funny music. The proggy scene and knowing people who do traditional ethnic stuff and–it’s just sort of putting yourself out there. If people know you and they like you and you do good enough work, on time, and are reliable, that counts for a lot. Some strange things have come along as a result. Bands paying me to go with them to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antwerp&quot;&gt;Antwerp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to shoot music videos because they like the ideas I did on their record. It’s just strange things like that. It’s a hodge-podge. It’s fairly scattered and variegated, but it’s just the way things are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8PX5KKQqN-c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s what it takes. Okay, and then–I do have to get back to work, but I do want to talk about–you have talked about the stress, anxiety, and depression around finishing The Divine Abstract, at least on Facebook. And this morning, I believe it was this morning, you posted something about returning to that era. Working through certain things in your newest composition work. Can you talk about that era, what led to it, and how you’re working through it now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah, so I came to terms with the fact that I suffer from depression about four years ago, four and a half years ago. Around then, around 2014. Before that, I’d probably gone through periods of anxiety before. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I knew I had friends with depression, but I could never quite relate to it. It never seemed like something that could happen to me.&lt;/span&gt; It was always like this other thing. And then finally I had to be honest with myself and say, “This is what I’m going through.” It’s a combination of things: general existential crisis and, who knows, maybe a certain amount of psychological stuff from the past, perhaps. A combination of things. The stresses of being a freelance musician in London and the crises you go through with that. Relationships and things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you get discouraged about your music as well? “Not enough people care about it” or “Why am I doing this weird, esoteric things?” Does that get to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Oh, of course. All the time. I think that’s quite common amongst people who do what we do. It’s the thing you have to live with.&lt;/span&gt; Maybe what you do will appeal to a certain number of people and might not necessarily have much value outside of this sphere that you operate in. It’s a shared thing amongst friends of mine and people I work with. The main thing was being open and honest about it. It got to the point where I just had to start talking about it with friends and be open about it on social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What happens then is that you start being contacted by people who you didn’t know were going through the same thing. They’ll tell you privately and it creates this deep connection with other people, I’ve found, being open this way. Maybe what was happening before was I was trying to be guarded. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You start realizing that the version of yourself that you present to other people is often just that. It’s a construction.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What happens with depression is that the illusion is then dissipated. You don’t have that image of yourself anymore. It kind of destroys that image of yourself because you realize that it’s possible for you to be brought down to such a level. It can happen to you. You start assessing all different things about your personality and how it manifests in relationships or day-to-day things or in life in general. So it’s this thing you have to face. You have to go through it. You have to face these things. Often quite uncomfortable things about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s a long period of being honest and open with the people around me and therapy and trying to create and trying to keep myself busy with music as well and remain active. And yet, it’s a real liminal state, this real transitory thing where after all you almost start seeing it as a positive because the person you become when you have to deal with all these things is so much better than the one that existed when you first started going through it. More open, more empathetic, more able to express emotions and things like that in language with other people. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That can only help your creative work as well because if you’re closed off emotionally in your everyday life or you try and hide certain things about yourself then that’s only going to come out in what you write, I think.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then I also had this relationship with the music I was writing, the music that ended up becoming The Divine Abstract. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It almost became a way of writing myself out of these states, so it’s not necessary that I be depressed and write depressing music because it’s a means of wallowing in it. It’s almost a means of escaping it.&lt;/span&gt; You’re trying to create an ideal state for myself, like a world in which I could exist that brought me back to not necessarily normality, but beyond that, above that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Trying to aim for the best aspects of myself. I think you can do that with music.&lt;/span&gt; When I was talking earlier about things like magic, it’s just manipulating symbols and sounds to create these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FmrIZzmYc_A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It informed my approach to harmony as well, in terms of harmonic shifts. It’s what you’ve changed in harmony, about what they’re doing. You can create these changes in color and these changes of mood and these changes of mental state through the manipulation of harmony. You can create agitated, manic states through the manipulation of rhythm through hemiola or time signatures or polyrhythms. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can create musical depictions of these kinds of states.&lt;/span&gt; It’s kind of what I approach with the music on the album, it became this liminal thing. This thing that you pass through to become a new person, as it were, a new entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The music I’m writing currently, which is going to be the next album, is similar but different to the music on The Divine Abstract. It was all written in the space of about two months in terms of the original demos. At first it was this manic period and that broke, and then it became a real depression, like a really bad period of depression. It was that same period of depression that led me to finally be honest with myself and then make the music that’s on the album. But I’ll finish the music that’s on the album that’s just come out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So the process of working on this music now, a year and a half later, to a certain extent takes you back to that time, to that period. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It reminds you of the space that you’re in, but it would feel creatively dishonest if I didn’t do that, if I didn’t face it and then go through the cathartic process of turning that into something, which is that alchemical process of turning a leaden consciousness into a golden one.&lt;/span&gt; Taking these negative states and then channeling into something that is positive, that not necessarily sounds like it’s coming from a place of depression because I wouldn’t necessarily want it to sound like it did, but has come through it and has expressed these states and created something from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well thank you so much for sharing all of that. That’s very insightful and vulnerable, so I appreciate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Thanks, yeah. It’s wonderful to talk to you about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you. So, finally, for people who want to learn more about you and your music, what do you suggest they do and how can they best support you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2ZEq1RIyqKw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: The album is on Bandcamp, &lt;a href=&quot;https://charliecawood.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;charliecawood.bandcamp.com &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-bandcamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.com/charliecawoodmusic&quot;&gt;also on Facebook &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-facebook&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I’ve got the musician page on Facebook, which I use to update about exclusively musical things. I do &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/charliecawood&quot;&gt;Twitter &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-twitter&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/charliecawood&quot;&gt;Instagram &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Cawood&quot;&gt;the wikipedia page &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; now, which is a real fun thing to have. That’s actually fairly well sourced and it’s pretty much accurate, so there is that. Working on a website currently, that’s something that’s going to happen. Other things that are happening soon is new Knifeworld at some point. There will be the follow-up to the current album that I’m currently working on, which is going to come out hopefully in a year’s time, maybe a bit more than a year’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The last part of this year, there’s the new Mediaeval Baebes album, which I co-arranged and played about twelve albums on it. It’s a compendium of nursery rhymes and children’s songs, done in this partially beautiful and partially horrifically discordant way. For what’s essentially a pop-classical project, it’s probably one of the most avant garde things I’ve ever worked on. It’s brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a new band that’s going to come into existence online soon called Lost Crowns. There’s an album in production with that. That’s almost like a supergroup of our little group of musicians in London. I’m on bass and the music is written by a fellow called Richard Larcombe, who’s one half of this really brilliant band called Stars in Battledress with his brother James. Josh [Perl] from Knifeworld on keyboards, Rhodri Marsden from Prescott on keyboards. It’s this real collection of far-out musicians. And the music is totally psychedelic and singular and strange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m really looking forward to people hearing that one because it doesn’t really sound like anything else. It sounds like the sort of music for Stars in Battledress, but done with a full band. So there’s all sorts of stuff happening in the next year. New Matrix in Spirit, which is a sort of Balinese gamelan mixed with electronica and psychedelia and other stuff. That’s on the go as well, so that will hopefully be coming out next year. There’s all kinds of things. I tend to update everything on my social medias and my Facebooks and that kind of thing. There’s that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, cool. Thank you so much for joining us. I do want to say there are two Charlie Cawoods, same spelling…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes, extremely different music. So if you do search for Charlie Cawood, make sure you’re getting this guy and not the singer/songwriter acoustic guitar player. If you want to listen to that, go for it, but that’s not this Charlie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Yeah, it’s pretty much diametrically opposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, pretty diametrically…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: It’s a fair distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’ll know when you’re listening to this Charlie Cawood when you hear all the instrumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: You might prefer the other one. Oh this is really good! This is much better than that instrumental stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Although, anyone who’s gotten this far in this video is probably interested in what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Or experiencing slight cognitive dissonance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Charlie, thank you again so much. I really appreciate you spending the time with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CC: Thank you. Real pleasure talking to you finally.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/charlie-cawood/the-divine-abstract</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/charlie-cawood/the-divine-abstract</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mats/Morgan Live with Norrlandsoperan Symphony Orchestra</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b51700LPExs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mats/Morgan is an experimental jazz/rock duo from Umea, Sweden featuring Mats Oberg on keyboards and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/morgan-agren&quot;&gt;Morgan Agren&lt;/a&gt; on drums. Their latest release is a concert they filmed and performed in 2017 with the Norrlandsoperan Symphony Orchestra conducted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://tomtrapp.net&quot;&gt;Tom Trapp &lt;i class=&quot;far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Umea. The concert was a major achievement for the group as it’s something &lt;a href=&quot;/share/morgan-agren/morgchestra&quot;&gt;we’d talked to Morgan about&lt;/a&gt; in December 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy “Live with the Norrlandsoperan Symphony Orchestra” &lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.morganagren.com/butik/cd/matsmorgan/mats-morgan-live-with-norrlandsoperan-symphony-orchestra/&quot;&gt;on Morgan Agren’s onine store &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new release comes with three discs: a DVD video of the performance, a CD containing the audio from the concert (same as the DVD), and Morgan’s previously-released &lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of the Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt;. It’s very well packaged and affordably priced considering all of the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have one thing to say about this collection: &lt;strong&gt;It is perfect&lt;/strong&gt;. Seriously, the video is excellent, lots of fun to watch, well-edited, well-colored, and more. The audio is fantastic. There’s not a boring song to skip. It’s just wonderful, unique, complex, and musical. It is &lt;em&gt;so musical&lt;/em&gt;. I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morgan released this album as part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/804823372/morgan-agren-mats-oberg-cds-dvds-urgent-hearing-tr&quot;&gt;a kickstarter to raise funds for his best friend Mats &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-kickstarter&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who was born blind and is now having trouble with his hearing. The original goal of the crowdfunding was around $15,000 USD and the fans contributed more than $47,000 USD altogether! Incredible! This will make a big difference for Mats/Morgan and allow Mats to see one of the best doctors in the world for his hearing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altogether, if you’re a fan of this website, you have to buy this release. It’s emblematic of the kind of thing we hope to promote on the site: an adventurous, artistic, creative pursuit of music.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/mats-morgan/live-with-norrlandsoperan-symphony-orchestra</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/mats-morgan/live-with-norrlandsoperan-symphony-orchestra</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evil Genius and Studio Opening</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;studio-grand-opening-concert&quot;&gt;Studio Grand Opening Concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who follow our activities closely, you’ll know from social media that I’ve been building a new video studio in my backyard to accommodate all the MWM work, as well as making a space for doing my day job remotely. It’s been an exhausting (and sometimes fun) project, but it’s finally “done.” Well, it’s done enough to be usable. And to commemorate the grand opening of the studio, I invited the band &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/evil-genius&quot;&gt;Evil Genius&lt;/a&gt; out to my house and they performed a show! Super cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UEa2NuhAZA8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s one of the songs I requested, called &lt;em&gt;Colonel Karl Marx and Keenan McCardell&lt;/em&gt; from their excellent new album &lt;a href=&quot;https://evilgeniustrio.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Experiments on Human Subjects&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-bandcamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and until I do a final video about the studio, here’s a little about the project while I was working on it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tby3TJGg5xc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asterisk&quot;&gt;Asterisk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another track written by drummer Mike Lockwood called &lt;em&gt;Asterisk&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/PNsTYtHgMfc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/evil-genius</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/evil-genius</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Animal Lover by The Residents</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hc3BSjGR2kc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/the-residents/animal-lover.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/the-residents/animal-lover.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;animal-lover&quot;&gt;Animal Lover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first video in a series called “Jaw Droppers” where I’ll feature albums that have literally made me lose track of time until I suddenly realize I’ve been sitting slack-jawed while listening for 20 minutes or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first album I want to feature is “Animal Lover” by The Residents. This album has had a profound impact on me. It is absolutely not for the light-hearted listener. It’s like listening to your worst nightmare. This is not an exaggeration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy “Animal Lover” as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/animal-lover/1204944563&quot;&gt;digital download on iTunes&lt;/a&gt;. Check it out!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I distinctly remember being at my desk at work and listening to an online stream of the album back when it came out in 2004. I had just gotten out of a meeting that ended at around 2PM and I started listening. About 40 minutes later, I awoke from a trance. The music and its absolute strangeness completely captivated me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It starts with a song called “On the Way to Oklahoma” that describes a man who becomes a cat, falls in love with a tiger, and then eats a dog. The vocals are highly digitized, harmonized, and oddly melodic. This song was so stunning that I decided to have a music listening party with several friends just so I could play it for them. My friends jokingly referenced the lyrics for years after that night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next song, “Olive and Gray” is truly terrifying. It seems to be about a man who indecently exposes himself and then gets stoned to death. It is an incredible piece of music, too. Very complex, lots of dreamy instrumentation, tons of dissonance, and a cacophonous choir. This is one of the scariest songs I’ve ever heard. It literally makes me tear up in fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guitarist Nolan Cook absolutely shines on this record. Molly Harvey’s vocals are haunting. The orchestration is beautifully arranged and performed. It’s a very musical and melodic album with almost-timeless production qualities. The recording quality is top-notch, too, which isn’t a standard feature on all Residents albums. But make no mistake, each song is like an assault on one or more of the senses. It’s truly bizarre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/homer-flynn&quot;&gt;Watch our interview with Homer Flynn&lt;/a&gt; of the Cryptic Corporation, the Residents’ personal and business managers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s not forget the artwork! It’s definitely not safe for work and it’s barely safe for private consumption. The lyric booklet in this 2-disc special edition is just gorgeous, although it’s definitely a product of its time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this to say that it’s one of my favorite albums of all time and definitely my favorite Residents album. It holds a special place in my life for reasons I probably don’t even want to think about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/the-residents/animal-lover</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/the-residents/animal-lover</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
