<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 09:42:30 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 09:42:30 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture, Ep. 6</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-6-fracture-is-impossible-to-play&quot;&gt;Episode 6: Fracture is Impossible to Play&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgmlive.com/diaries/Robert%20Fripp/RF_diary_2016_Nov_30&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp wrote in his online diary&lt;/a&gt; that “Fracture is impossible to play.” What on earth could that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fracture/id978457922?i=978458012&quot;&gt;Purchase King Crimson’s &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.nexternal.com/dgm/starless-and-bible-black-c228.aspx&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Robert Fripp’s website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3oZf_zn1iFE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-failure-to-fracture&quot;&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a video series I’ve put together about all the things that have stood in the way of my successfully playing the song &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; despite years and years of study, practice, writing, and making videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-list&quot;&gt;Episode List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Episode 0: Introduction&lt;/a&gt; (includes notation/tablature)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/stress&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Tension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/picks&quot;&gt;Episode 2: Picking Picks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/inefficient-picking&quot;&gt;Episode 3: Inefficient Picking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/overzealous-precision&quot;&gt;Episode 4: Overzealous Precision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide&quot;&gt;Episode 5: Alex Anthony Faide Interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/impossible&quot;&gt;Episode 6: Fracture is Impossible to Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-transcript&quot;&gt;Video Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the 6th episode of Failure to Fracture, a series that highlights my now-20-year struggle to play the hardest song I’ve ever encountered: “Fracture” by King Crimson. Robert Fripp, the composer and guitarist on the track, writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgmlive.com/diaries/Robert%20Fripp/RF_diary_2016_Nov_30&quot;&gt;“Fracture is impossible to play.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, no wonder! I guess I’ve spent the last 20 years of my life unnecessarily angering my wife with metronome ticks and non-stop atonal picking. 20 years staring at my hands in mirrors and on camera trying to identify minuscule extraneous movements to eliminate. 20 years losing hope in myself as a guitarist. I could have used this insight 20 years ago, Robert! But maybe there’s more to this story. Let’s see what else he writes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“it took a year to bring my practising up to speed, as it were; and four months directly and specifically on Fracture. my Wife had quite enough after a few weeks, so i had to lock the door to the Cellar; where i practice.” [Sounds familiar…]
“to keep Fracture-fit takes 80% of my time and attention. which is too much. and it’s almost improper that a man of 70 should be doing the high-wire every night;
when there’s a younger generation who might take it on!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean when Robert claims “Fracture is impossible?” Clearly it’s “possible” because he has recorded it on more than one occasion and I’ve even seen him perform it. In fact there are recent live recordings of Fracture on King Crimson’s live Vienna and Mexico City releases. So, what’s he talking about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a collection of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgmlive.com/in-depth/guitar-craft-aphorisms&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft aphorisms&lt;/a&gt; that shed some light on this topic. If you’re like me and don’t know what an aphorism is, here’s a definition. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphorism&quot;&gt;According to Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, an aphorism is ”a concise, terse, laconic, and/or memorable expression of a general truth or principle often passed down via tradition. Aphorisms are distinct from axioms. Aphorisms generally originate from experience and custom, whereas axioms are self-evident truths and therefore require no additional proof.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, these expressions may only mean something to those who’ve pursued serious study in the ways of Guitar Craft. I do not include myself in this group because my formal study is quite limited. My mostly-self-guided practice gives me a little bit more insight. But because I’ve failed so expertly (and for so long) at playing Fracture, I have attained enough knowledge to allow me some understanding of the aphorisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guitar Craft aphorisms state:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Begin with the possible and move gradually towards the impossible.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Desperate doesn’t mean hopeless. Hopeless doesn’t mean impossible. Impossible doesn’t mean unnecessary.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Efficiency: as little as possible and as much as is necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;One measure of possible and impossible is the probable.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If we are able to describe the characteristics of the level to which we aspire, our aspiration becomes possible.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It is not possible for the musician to play music. But, it is possible for the musician to be played by music.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Perfection is impossible. But I may choose to serve perfection.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sometimes the impossible is necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The artist is a bridge between the possible, the impossible and the actual.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The greater the seeming imperfection, the greater the possible transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The necessary is possible. The optional is expensive. The arbitrary is unlikely.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We are asked to work honourably: honourably = what is possible + 10%; too hard = 1. Two steps beyond hard, rather than one. 2. When determination becomes “grim determination”. 3. When we lose a sense of ourselves.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We do what is possible and allow space for the impossible to enter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this to say, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Fracture is impossible in the same way climbing Mount Everest is impossible or eating the 72 ounce steak in two hours is impossible.&lt;/span&gt; Fracture is an etude. An athletic feat. I find it fun, engaging, meditative, meaningful, challenging, torturous, and worthwhile all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P7R38s9x0Jo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand the distinction between impossible and possible. If I believe Fracture is truly impossible, I will fail miserably. This is true for anything difficult. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If I believe Fracture is incrementally possible, I will have a different aim. I always have the choice between torture and joy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Ball shared the following story about his first college math teacher, who said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“If a problem is too hard, no one will take it on. If a problem is too easy, no one will take it on.” Aspiring to learn and play Fracture is a ‘too hard’ problem that only one with confidence, determination and willingness to sacrifice all that is required can master the speed, precision, agility, mobility, tone and endurance required.&lt;/span&gt; Steve’s story doesn’t leave room for ignorant people like me who don’t know what they’re getting themselves into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view toward the impossibility of Fracture has shifted over the years. In my youth, I was driven by ego and a misguided sense of personal value. Either Fracture was impossible to play or I was a failure as a guitarist. Now I know better and am driven by a means of knowing myself, discovering subtle flaws, and relating my hands to an instrument through the action of playing music. My 20-year effort toward playing Fracture is a measure of my available will to master the piece. It was just this week that I identified inefficiencies in my picking. I am still learning every time I pick up the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So yes, Fracture is impossible. This is by design. And it’s designed as a horrendously steep mountain that may only be scaled via persistent, focused, daily climbing, one small step at a time. The point is not to get to the top of the mountain because it rises into the clouds. The point is to keep moving up the mountain in small steps each day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those looking to understand more about this, there’s is a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fripp.com/frippvt/robert-frippvt-live/&quot;&gt;virtual training program available via Robert’s sister’s website, Fripp.com&lt;/a&gt;. Look for the Robert Fripp virtual training program. You can learn more about craft, mastery, and discipline on your own time directly from speeches by Robert. Let us know in the comments if you check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also suggest watching the documentary “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jiro_Dreams_of_Sushi&quot;&gt;Jiro Dreams of Sushi&lt;/a&gt;” for analogous lessons in this journey to Fracture. I’ve watched the film several times and have taken many notes while watching. It’s an amazing film about mastery, repetition, and awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to thank the many people who’ve emailed and commented about this series. I can’t believe how many people are climbing this mountain with me around the world and have been paying attention to my efforts all these years. There’s plenty more to this series, so stay tuned. Leave a comment or send an email if you have ideas for the next episode.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/impossible</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/impossible</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Six Demon Bag by Man Man</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FS61hOaUILM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creatively-uninhibited-with-white-war-paint-all-over&quot;&gt;Creatively Uninhibited with White War Paint All Over&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend Rosemary was always on the cutting edge of new music. She frequently exposed me to stuff that I never would have heard of, like Kings of Convenience, American Football, Of Montreal, Badly Drawn Boy, and lots of other bands. One day in 2006 she sent me an mp3 of a song called “Engrish Bwudd” by a band called Man Man and I was completely stunned within the first few seconds of listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wurEDf8z9tc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was from an album called “Six Demon Bag” and it was like a wonderful, actually-enjoyable blend of Captain Beefheart, Tom Waits, Squirrel Nut Zippers, and circus music. I loved everything about it. The carnival-esque feel, the very-multi-layered vocals, the bouncy minor keys, the nonsensical lyrics, the strange percussion, and especially the live roomy sound of the record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole album was a treat to my ears and unlike anything I’d ever heard before. Truly unique, fun, and musical, which is a rare combination. Every single song on this album is great and seriously so fun to listen to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The band members had the greatest pseudonyms, too. The singer goes Honus Honus. The drummer is Pow Pow. The bassist is Sergei Sogay. Others include Blanco, Les Mizzle, G. Clinton Killingsworth, and San Bañon Pisto. Anyway, I caught them on tour and they were mind-blowing. It was a huge band, probably like 7 people, with a mountain of gear and the whole band wore all-white tennis clothing with white war paint on their faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dfmKW4BSw5w?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I saw them three times, each time in a successively larger venue with successively larger groups of hipster teenagers “dancing” rambunctiously right in front of the stage. Man Man always put on an excellent show, but the crowds spoiled it for me and I stopped going to see them. I’m just a cranky old man, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After buying “Six Demon Bag,” I bought their first album, “The Man in a Blue Turban with a Face.” It was also excellent, real creative but with less sophisticated songwriting. Then their third album, Rabbit Habbits came out, which is seriously entirely excellent. Great, great songwriting and totally uninhibited. Another excellent album that probably would have dropped my jaw just as quickly as Six Demon Bag did. The song “Harpoon Fever (Queequeg’s Playhouse)” is a real brain-twister. Probably my favorite on the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z2rilJ-Wlr4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following albums never really grabbed me, but I think it’s time to give them another chance. They actually released some new music in late 2018 and performed a few shows. Hopefully this is a sign of things to come! If you’re a fan of Man Man, let me know what I’m missing. If you check them out because of this video, let us know your thoughts in the video comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nJop3yCsEU8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/man-man/six-demon-bag</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/man-man/six-demon-bag</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Devin Townsend on Creativity</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-interviews&quot;&gt;Other Interviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Looking for the interview segment about Devin’s 2019 release, &lt;em&gt;Empath&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/devin-townsend/empath&quot;&gt;Here it is!&lt;/a&gt; Or the interview segment about his new signature acoustic guitar, Steve Vai, X-JAMM, and more? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/devin-townsend/guitar-vai-x-jamm&quot;&gt;Here it is!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KEOmke-9dgg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/devin-townsend/creativity.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/devin-townsend/creativity.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Devin Townsend is an artist based in Vancouver, British Columbia in Canada and I am really honored to be here because you are the most requested person to be interviewed on the site and it’s so cool to finally be with you after listening to your music for probably 20 years. So thanks a lot for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Thanks man, it’s nice to be here. I appreciate being invited onto this, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I appreciate it. So, for people who might be new to you, can you give a brief introduction to yourself and the kind of music you produce?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Sure. My name’s Devin Townsend. I’m a 46-year-old Canadian musician. I guess my bread and butter has been hard rock and progressive heavy metal. I’ve got maybe about 30 records now through certain bands. I had Strapping Young Lad when I was younger, which was really heavy, and Devin Townsend Project had a whole gaggle of solo records of different styles and aesthetics. I’ve worked with a lot of people. My first thing was with Steve Vai in 1993 and I’ve worked with a lot of people since then. I’ve done a lot of productions for bands in varying degrees of success and I’ve toured and played for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Everywhere, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Pretty much. Some places more than others. But it’s been a long and confusing career and I am happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. So, even on your website you talk about how you have HevyDevy Records because you “make weird music.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you needed a place to release it. Those are your exact words. Can you talk a little about what makes you feel like your music is unique or different and why you might need a vehicle for you to release it on your own?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: The record label started inadvertently as I couldn’t convince the labels at the time that what I was doing was viable commercially, for one, but also for the level of capital I would need to pull off. So, because the Steve Vai record had done well in Japan, Sony Japan suggested that if I just incorporate a name of whatever the name was, it dubiously ended up being HevyDevy Records, then they would license the work. That’s how it started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I put together Strapping Young Lad and that ended up on the label Century Media, if I could make any claim to business acumen, it was that I insisted that the only thing they had rights to was Strapping. Then, everything else that I did, whether or not it was ambient or country or rock or orchestral—anything., I would have the rights to do that on HevyDevy records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Why do I think it’s weird? I don’t think it’s weird, I just think I’m told it’s weird, so I just preface most conversations with preemptively telling people that “you may not dig this” or “people are typically confused about this” or what have you. But I think for me, it’s musically I don’t think about what I do, I guess. I’ve never really thought about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I go by what I’m compelled to do and those compulsions tend to be very vision-based and super specific. So, I’ll do things because that year seems to have certain aesthetics that play into it, like I’m interested in green and I’m interested in this particular font. I’m interested in this particular sound and this frequency and a particular guitar sound, which leads me to another guitar pickup and then by the end of the year, all of these subliminal clues tend to triangulate to the point where there’s a really specific vibe that a name typically happens in the formative stages of those clues coming together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;By the end, I’m like, “Oh, I guess it’s Ki.” “Oh, I guess it’s Ziltoid.” “Oh, I guess it’s Empath.” And I’m sometimes like, “Oh that’s weird.” But I knew it had to be that way, I know it has to sound that way, but I’d be first in line to suggest that it’s strange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One of the main reasons I wanted to talk to you is because of this book. You wrote a book on creativity. Can you give a little background on the book?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I think part of the process that I have been working towards my own ability to actualize ideas is: how do you refine your creative spirit to the point where what your intention is is unclouded by any of the crap that you’ve put into your body or you ingest with media or other people’s music or whatever? That requires a lot of exploration, whether or not that means I’m a vegetarian. I’m a vegetarian for years and I’m like, “Well, why am I a vegetarian? Eat meat and figure it out.” Then I eat meat and it makes me feel the way that it did and then I’m vegetarian again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But it’s like I think that on a creative level a lot of what prevents me from being just a pure channel to what it is emotionally I’m trying to represent is my sense of self or my insecurities or my ego or whatever. I think that writing the book ultimately was an extension of being afraid of giving things away, whether or not it’s my guitar sound or my production process or what it is that I—what my reasons are personally, spiritually, whatever. I think I held on to those things for a long time because my insecurity is like, “Well, if other people know how I do what I do, then they’re going to be able to do it and I’m going to be out of a job and I’ll go broke and and…” Whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I think a couple years ago when the suggestion to come up with the book on creativity came up around, there was a part of me that felt that if I was really forthcoming with the process, then there’s a certain part of the burden of protecting that, that you can forget it all. Like, “Here’s my guitar sounds.” “Here’s how I produce my vocals.” “Here’s how I do it all.” And then through it, I think what I recognized is that what makes what I do unique is the same thing that would make what you do unique or what you do unique or what anybody does unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s got very little to do with your process and more to do with how that process interprets your trip, which no one else is going to be able to articulate. So more people that have it, the better music I think ultimately will become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There are a few interesting themes in your book. One I want to talk about is you talk quite a bit about the subconscious and you’re kind of discovering something that’s already there. And you almost make it sound like “it just happened to me. I didn’t make it. This is already there.” And even the terminology you use is often work-related in terms of perhaps an archaeological dig or you’re massaging something. I was curious if you think—why are there so many references to old things? What are you digging up? What are you excavating? What are you trying to bring to light? Is that stuff that’s been there your whole life? Did it already exist? Where are you coming from with that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Well that has nothing to do with me. I think it has nothing to do with any artist. I’m often critical in the sense of artists who claim that the work that they do is anything other than just trying to do an accurate version of the manpower to honor the source than it has anything to do with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As a person, I think I’m lost and simple. So, I can only hope that the moments that I’ve had in my life of spiritual significance—no religion, but spiritual significance—are such where I’m like, “Well, that’s the only thing that I want to represent. That’s the only thing I want to sing about. That’s the only thing I want to get right.” But it’s not that my version of that is, by any stretch of the imagination, “the version” of it. It’s just middle class white Canadian male named Devin. You have a glimpse of these things, as we all do, artistically and we’re like, “Oh, that. Well, through my filter and through my biases and my fears and my hangups and the fact that I liked Judas Priest when I was a kid, or Enya, or any of these things,” it’s that that comes through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And it is ancient. That’s primordial and I think that improvisation and artists who strive to represent these things with reverence, you have to be proactive in calling yourself out on your own bullshit. I think that for me, my reasons for doing that are not because if I do that, I’ll become more successful or I’ll become famous or what have you, it’s just that it seems like the source and those sorts of fundamental human experiences are worthy of that sort of self analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you feel like you just trip over it? You trip over it and it just happens to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Holy crap, yeah. Not only that, but I don’t understand it until I’m on it, so I often fear it, which is super counter-productive to the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What specifically do you fear?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I fear that I’m not capable of handling it. Right? I feel like unless I keep my attention rooted in something that’s fundamentally productive and fundamentally helpful, as opposed to destructive, then it’s going to be skewed and it’s going to be colored by my own ego in a way that misrepresents something that is larger than us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I struggle with insecurity because I don’t know what I’m doing and I don’t claim to be particularly adept at any aspect of what I do. The things that I like in life, you know like my family and I like food and I like sex. You know, the fundamental parts of life are all that I really feel that I can enjoy and there is a passion that is just so rooted in fear that the process becomes, “Okay well face your fears” on some level. If it’s vegetarianism or if it’s sex or if it’s peering into the void or if it’s any of these things, it’s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In the past, I had experimented with a lack of accountability with writing as part of the process of trying to actualize my own connection to creativity. I thought, “Well, maybe that’s an avenue to explore.” So this record, “Alien,” and “Infinity” and these things were all based in me going, “Well, I don’t care how people perceive this.” But then through that is a real sense of, “Well, it’s all connected.” Like, everybody’s interconnectedness is part and parcel of how you approach this. Your awareness of where your throw extends will ultimately affect how ably you are to articulate this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I struggle with it because it’s such a compulsion. It’s not like, “Oh I’ve got a good idea. I’ll write a record like this.” It’s just all signs start pointing to certain things, like Empath, this new project. Years ago, I was like, “Okay, well it’s got something to do with covers of those old new age things with the whales underneath and the universe up on the top and the font is something like Star Trek.” You know what I mean? It’s like all these things, the pieces start to fall into place and then by the end of it, I think I’ve recognized in the past by going down avenues that were in hindsight rooted in arrogance or selfishness that I thought that led me to that place, which was horrible for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t want to represent that. It’s much to the chagrin who had something invested in that. Like people in bands that I was with, we were just on the cusp of success or what have you. The last band, The Devin Townsend Project, I was so afraid of the dark that is part of being human that I refused to acknowledge that it was a big part of what balances my creativity. As a result, that band started getting this reputation of being like, “Oh it’s a positive thing.” Then people would come to me like I had answers to some degree, like, “Oh, you know what to—“ You know? “Because you’re saying it, everything’s going to be okay.” I’m like, “But it isn’t!” You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then all of a sudden, I started looking down the trajectory of what that would become because the next stage for DTP was more success and more success. I’m like, “My God, I’m going to end up representing something that I’m not qualified to represent. I don’t have the fucking answers. Not even slightly.” And not only that, there seems to be very clearly a market for not only telling people, “Fuck the world” because to be able to rationalize that with a cool logo, there’s a lot of people that are willing to pay for that because it removes that need to say, “No, don’t fuck the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And conversely, saying “Everything’s going to be fine.” There’s a huge market for that because everything’s not, clearly, okay. People want that sort of reassurance and to have it as a slogan on a shirt, all these things, and so I started recognizing, I’m like, “Well again, your fear is preventing you from representing your truth. Your truth. Not the truth. Your truth. My truth is somewhere in the middle, as it should be. My truth is: everything’s clearly not alright, but I firmly believe that if you’re willing to work and recognize that even though there’s darkness everywhere, it’s up to us to find the joy in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Even with the awareness of that, not blocking out the awareness that it is fundamentally chaos, with a certain type of internal discipline I think you can transmute that into something that is healthy and enjoyable. I’d like to be a step in the latter as opposed to the other. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There are themes in the book, and we were discussing before filming, this notion of via negativa where you are cutting away at things instead of building something up. You use via negativa in a few ways. When you are talking about things not working out in the world, are you using your art to chip away at that? Or are you using art to shine a light on that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Certainly not intentionally. That’s where sometimes I feel like the imposter syndrome on some level because if you get it right, or at least I feel if I get it right artistically, in hindsight it looks intentional. But it wasn’t. It was all based in just staring into the darkness. Take these things that present themselves purely as an interest and then just have them not irritate me anymore. When I have a piece of music come into my head, it’s finished when it doesn’t bug me. It’s not that it’s—when I start a piece of music, it’s not like the intention of this is going to be for this and that and this is how it’s going to help and this is how it’s going to—it’s got nothing to do with that and I think that’s why I spend so much time being self-deprecating as well because I’ll have these ideas that seem to be of a lot of depth and importance to me and my trip, yet I don’t understand them until they’re done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you give an example of something you didn’t understand until it was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: All of it. All of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Something a little more tangible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah. Empath. It’s taken me a year and a half to write it and I consciously went into writing heavy music again for this one, but juxtaposed by very mellow music. It’s the first time I’ve done it in one place. The fear of doing that for fear of people interpreting that or the ups and downs of it, psychologically being disturbing to people was such that I couldn’t trust that my intentions for it were not self-destructive. You know? On some level I was trying to sabotage myself because of the self-loathing or whatever that on some—because I don’t feel like… It’s not like I’m not in control of it, but because of the peripherals are so close, I don’t see it as it’s going. I was like, “Oh my God, what am I doing? What am I doing? What am I doing? This is terrible. This is terrible. This is terrible. It’s great. It’s great. It’s great. This is terrible. It’s terrible. It’s terrible.” But then once it was done and I listened to it, I’m like, “Oh it’s beautiful!” Like your intentions all along were to represent that life is not one thing. Life is all these things. And the last piece of music from the record, the last line is, “If you can’t shine for you, please shine for me.” It’s like, through the storm of the record, what was kind of guiding my hand like an infant was this sense that if you really want to contribute to music, to other people, other people’s art and other people’s frames of mind in a very destructive time, you can’t be oblivious to the fear. You can’t block it out under the assumption that it will simply go away. You have to face it. So by the end of the record, when I finally concluded that I was able to listen to it and say, “This is a positive statement.” It’s a very uneasy time and therefore, as somebody who’s empathetic to what’s going on just in his immediate environment, let alone the media and all the shit we’re bombarded with, of course it’s going to come out like that. Of course it’s going to come out like that. Unless you’re being dishonest, of course it’s going to come out like that. And your fear of other people interpreting it in the wrong way is based on the fact that you’re not a terrible person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s interesting how you view—it seems like you live with this juxtaposition of order and chaos. An album is essentially order. The recording is ordered, everyone’s recorded, the mix is perfect, the master is perfect, but you’re pointing and saying, “There’s still the chaos.” You’re saying, “I don’t know what happens, I don’t know why this happens.” But you have a 5-step guide to creativity, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I think the 5-step guide is based on very pragmatic, almost parental, advice because any advice that I have to people to—“wield” sounds too pompous, but to “handle” this type of process, is like—you know, “Don’t do drugs and stay in school!” You know? It’s really a lot more about when these moments of darkness and existential trauma comes into your life, it’s about practicing real fundamental parts of being a decent person so that your heart is bigger than your fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you feel that you’ve worked through a lot of this with your art? Do you feel like you’re a much healthier person of who you were, or do you feel like you have different issues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Different issues! I want to be healthy, for sure. I think that I’ve made a lot of inroads in my personal life where I couldn’t have gone into very self-destructive. For example, drugs are a very tender subject because a lot of the times the inspiration you get from cannabis or alcohol or LSD or ayahuasca or any of these things are such that it’s really enticing because you think on some level it removes fear and you’re able to just produce. However there’s a certain aspect of that that it feels like you’re taking it out of the bank. You know? You make a withdrawal that allows you to get a riff or something like this, but you pay for it in a psychological type of chaos that I think disallows you from being able to handle the ramifications of what it is that you’re producing. So, it’s a very fine line. I think that extends to coffee and exercise and all these things, but you’ve gotta live too. It’s not like you can be a monk in this world. If you’ve got kids and if you’ve got a job and you’ve got phones and you’ve got—you’re recycling, yet you’re drinking out of plastic bottles. All these things. I think what that comes down to in the same way, maybe some artistic avenues can lead you to dark places, I think the idea you’ve withdrawn everything from and being completely like, “I’m a pure vessel,” is also a type of hangup and I think what you’ve really got to do is foster some sort of sense of self-love that is rooted in, “Just give me a fucking break, man. Eat a piece of chocolate, dude.” You know what I mean? I think that that ultimately plays into the book as well because what works for one person is not going to work for everybody else. There’s some people I know that can do drugs all the time. Or drink alcohol. Or do any number of things that may not work for other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It may not be working for them, either. You just think it does watching them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Maybe, but I think that maybe it predisposes that there’s “one way.” I’m not sure that I subscribe to that. I think that there’s one way ultimately, but I think that there’s very much the idea that everybody has a certain level of evolution and then, for example, I could remove everything from my life. I can become a monk and I can do all these things that seem to be enticing. I just don’t know if I’m spiritually evolved enough for that to not be a waste of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: After seeing some of your performances, I’m not sure you’d be authentic to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: That’s just it! The whole purpose of the guide to creativity, if there is such a thing, is that you’ve gotta figure out who you are and what your parameters are and then honor that, but don’t lie to yourself about it. Sometimes the best thing that you may be able to do for yourself is have a glass of wine and watch Netflix for two days. You know? Maybe it isn’t. Maybe for somebody else, that would be super destructive. But I’m pretty far from enlightenment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You say the first step is to figure out who you are. Would you say that these things you’re describing about yourself is what you’ve figured out about who you are or are they kind of something else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I’ve figured them out only because I’ve been so afraid of life. In trying to not be perpetually immobilized by fear, these things have kind of revealed themselves to me as opposed to any sort of benevolent, like, “I think that my role in life is to…” I’m shit scared all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is the music a vehicle to process that? Or is it a way of blocking it out for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Music started as a loophole for me because we were raised in an environment where overt displays of emotion were viewed as distasteful, I think. I think that the downfall of that within my family is there’s a lot of people who have not a very highly evolved empathic, but moderate. And I’m in that category, so you can’t feel the need to understand emotions or to represent emotions with such primal ferocity without a loophole for it to come out if you’re in an environment where it’s not cultivated or else you’re going to go fucking crazy. For me, because music—I’ve always been, I guess synesthesic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The neuroscientist would know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I mean, numbers and colors and shapes and sounds and emotions are really connected, right? As a result of that, it could have been music, it could have been art. It didn’t really matter. Music was just a loophole. Because I was in a musical family, I could represent those sort of repressed things in a way that wasn’t going to get me in trouble and then when I found that it became a convenient place for me to put it, everything kind of got hardwired to that. And so now as I find myself, and this one could argue that I’m learning these lessons that I’ve imposed on myself are helping, or I’m just getting older. But music and its importance to me in terms of my identity is much less than it was. So now I find that, for example on Empath, a lot of the theme ended up again at the end being recognized as: what you’re trying to do is let these things come and not let them define you. Let them bubble to the surface and then let them go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Which is something you cover in the book where you say, “Don’t spiritualize or idolize the idea. Just commoditize it and record it, have a system for storing it, and you’ll get back to it later.” It’s not like, “Oh crap, if I don’t work on this, my life will fall apart.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: So if I can add a caveat to that: if you want to. I think as soon as you say you don’t or one method is or “this is how you do it,” I think it verges on the same problem I have with religion where it predisposes that whoever’s telling you these things knows. I will be the first to say, “I don’t know and what I thought I knew tends to morph from year to year.” When I was experimenting with eating meat again, I had all these people in my life that were hardcore vegan and they were hyper-critical of me. I was like, “Yeah, but I don’t know. I’ve been vegetarian for so long, I don’t even know why I’m vegetarian. I just need to know.” It was like, “Well you can’t.” I’m like, “But why? It just seems stupid.” And I mean, the truth is somewhere in the middle for me. I realize that by allowing myself the lack of judgment that goes into saying, “If you choose to try something, that makes you a terrible person. You’re going to hell.” Or whatever it is. I find that’s been really helpful creatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This book is kind of all about that, like this notion of everyone has their own truth and popular society may not be interested in yours. But if pleasure and artistic expression is the goal, you’re going to have to get over that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah. Yeah. I think it really comes down to: just be honest with yourself and it doesn’t matter if what you want is something that isn’t “right” to want. Maybe all you want to do is make a ton of money, but if that’s what’s going to make you happy, then you’d be foolish not to pursue that because maybe somewhere along the line you’ll find that in the path of that is what you needed to know. It’s like, “Oh, that isn’t going to make me happy. But I didn’t know it was not going to make me happy until I went there.” I think that it’s like Bart Simpson testing the electric muffin. He’s like, “Ow. Ow. Ow. Ow.” I feel like to a certain extent, my process is like “I just need to try it to know.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well now that you’re a millionaire, you know if that money isn’t that important to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I’m a “thousandaire.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right on. Me too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I mean, I think money is a pain in the ass. I would love to have enough money to never have to say “no” to the guacamole, as they say. I know a bunch of people who have millions of people and they just seem like they have so many problems. I feel like I’ve got, in a lot of ways, more than I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I heard a great saying the other day. It’s a Chinese proverb/adage type thing. “No food, one problem. Lots of food, many problems.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: That makes sense. That makes sense. But I think, again, I think where the problems come there is thinking, “Well that’s what you have to do, then. So I’m going to get rid of everything and I’m going to get a white cloak and I’m going to tell my family that I’m the Buddha and I’m going to go off and…” But if you’re not spiritually in that place, all you’re doing is fucking yourself and everybody else that you care about. I think that’s a really important thing because during Infinity, I went down that path where I was like, “I’m going to get rid of everything and I’m going to go be a monk.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is that why you’re naked on the cover?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Totally. But it’s like, “But I’m not evolved enough for that.” It’s like I’m kind of stuck in the western view of what spirituality is to the point where I think there’s a way that you do it. You know? If I got more than one guitar, then I’m spiritually unevolved and I find that a lot of my problems with spiritualism or religion, but spiritualism in general, is people thinking that–for example, I know a lot of people who are vegetarian because that’s what spiritual people do. But then I know a lot of people that seem really spiritually evolved that eat meat. You know? So when you feel like you just have to have the uniform for what’s going to–you’re going to transcend the birth and death cycle, you’re going to go to heaven, whatever it is. You think, “Well as long as I’ve got these things, I say ‘namaste’ a lot and I do a lot of yoga and I still talk shit about my buddies when they’re not around.” I think ultimately, it’s like, “Man you’re wasting your time. Just figure out what you want to do. Burn around in a race car and eat ribs. If this is your one time around, then maybe that’s what you should be doing.” As opposed to just being frustrated with everything. Now, I think the other side of the coin now is the further down you go, certain things just don’t make sense anymore. Like for me, I love meat, but after a while it’s like, “Well that just doesn’t make sense for a number of reasons.” But I needed to know that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I like Robert Fripp’s way. He has a couple of ways of thinking about this. First he says that Tai Chi shows the perfect form exists and it’s your job to align with that form. Whatever that form is, may be different for different people, but we need to build the discipline to be able to take that form. And then he calls King Crimson “a way of doing things.” And I always thought, “That is so irritating. What does that mean?” But just like you’re saying, it’s like, “This is how I process what I need to do. This is my way of doing things.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I thought you were going to say, “Just like what you’re saying is irritating.” [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, can we move on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah, I’ll choke now. No, I get it, man. I think it’s like–I like my friends, I like my family, I don’t claim to know a lot, I like laughing, I like eating. I don’t know. I don’t know. And I know less every day. So I think that the creative thing frightens me just because I clearly do know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: And that’s the thing where there’s a disconnect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You can’t not know after 30 years of it, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DT: This is the problem! So because of the real disconnect between chaos and order that even exists within my creative mind, I constantly feel ill at ease about what I do and that prevents me from improvising in the way that I hope to one day. You know? I think that once I can make–and I think it comes down to insecurity. I spent so many years going, “Oh I’m an idiot. I don’t know.” You internalize that to the point where you clearly do know and it’s like, “Oh no I don’t.” [Inaudible.] “I don’t know.” Right? But maybe this whole mid-life thing, I mean 46 is pretty late to still be battling with this shit, but whatcha gonna do?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/devin-townsend</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/devin-townsend</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Devin Townsend</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-interviews&quot;&gt;Other Interviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Looking for the interview segment about Devin’s 2019 release, &lt;em&gt;Empath&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/devin-townsend/empath&quot;&gt;Here it is!&lt;/a&gt; Or the interview segment about his book on creativity? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/devin-townsend/creativity&quot;&gt;Here it is!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qa&quot;&gt;Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the final 15 minutes of our interview with Devin Townsend. We talk about a variety of things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His new Prestige signature acoustic guitar prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His Framus Stormbender signature electric guitar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Questions from MWM commenters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New and future work with Steve Vai&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vKZsU6RFLhU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/devin-townsend/guitar-vai-x-jamm.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/devin-townsend/guitar-vai-x-jamm.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I want to talk about this instrument briefly, too, because you just got it yesterday and it’s just gorgeous. What is this? Can you hold it up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Sure, so this is the prototype of this signature acoustic guitar that I’m working on with this Vancouver company, Prestige. I’ve got a very close relationships with the companies that I work with and I’m very loyal to the brands. Same thing that keeps me married for so long. I know what I want and then once I get it, that’s what I want. I don’t want to go look for something else. I’m good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One and done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: One and done. I started with Peavey and I had an idea for a guitar, but we couldn’t pull it off together for financial and just the logistics. Peavey is a company that has to sell things at a certain price point. We couldn’t produce it for what I wanted. So I went to Framus and they said, “We’ll do exactly what you want and you can take all the time you need.” So I came up with this guitar with them called the Storm Bender, which is exactly the guitar that I want. I got to design the body, I got to design the pickups, I got to design…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is new? The Storm Bender?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I’ve been working on it for three years, but it was released last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, I thought so. All right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I took it on tour for two years and then refined it. Little things. Like, this cut here is bugging me, the pickup selector needs to be here as opposed to there, the tilt of the neck–because I want it to be a maple top with mahogany and I want it to be a set neck, but I want the cutaway to feel like a thru, but I want it to sound like a set, I want it to be thicker, I want it to be heavier, and when I lay it on the ground, I want the headstock to not touch the ground because I’m gonna step on it. You know what I mean? And they did it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All the things you design a guitar for. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: The reason it is is it’s like, unless I can get it exactly like that, I’ll just use a guitar that is currently being produced. Some people are saying, “Okay, well, you’re doing a signature guitar so you can make money.” However, the Framus guitar, the list price on those are like 10 grand, so no one’s going to fucking buy it. So I made it because that’s what I want. I had talked to other companies and it was like, “Well if you do it cheaper, if you do it this way, then you’ll make money.” But I was like, “Yeah, but I want the guitar.” You know what I mean? [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re not born for this industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: No I’m not, but luckily my relationships with these people are such that I get what I need. And so I talked to Hans-Peter [Wilfer] at Framus and I was like, “There’s a Vancouver company called Prestige who I met in an elevator at NAMM and they’re just down the street from me and I’d like to do a signature acoustic with them.” I know that Framus does acoustics, but they’re willing to do the same way that you did the Storm Bender. They’re willing to do exactly what I want for an acoustic guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So this guitar here, long story long, is the prototype of it. Don’t have a name for it yet and this isn’t, obviously, exactly right yet, but I’m doing a bunch of acoustic touring this year to sort of not only get out there again, but also use it as an opportunity to do Q&amp;amp;As and sort of talk about the process so that when I do start touring again in November, it’s prefaced. So what I did with this was I wanted a certain thing, like I wanted a folk music type of guitar, like Gordon Lightfoot and all these sorts of things that I grew up with, which is a dreadnought shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But little things, like I like the dreadnought shape, but I do like to play up high and so I wanted a cutaway and I wanted the tourified top, which is baked so basically it removed a lot of the moisture and speeds up the aging process. I wanted the ebony fretboard, I wanted these certain type of tuners, and there’s now this guitar. Even as I’m playing it, there’s a few things about it that immediately I know we’re going to change, but they as well have now given me a year. Just like, “Okay, take it on tour and don’t hold back. Tell us exactly what you mean.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m thinking first off I’d like this cut a little more, I’d like this heel to not be as pointy, I might want to change the radius from a 14 to a 12, but it allows me by the end of it to have the acoustic guitar. It’s not at that point, “Well I’ll go into my selection of acoustic guitars and take the one that’s best for the song.” It’s like, “No. That one.” Because my reasons for efficiency in what my instruments are is because the process requires me to move super fucking quick, so I don’t want to think about whether or not this is going to work. It’s gotta be right, it’s gotta be in tune. The Evertune, that’s perfect for me because it’s like I’m always in tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This guitar is beautiful. It sounds great. It feels great. I love the texture on the top, too. Like, the feel, the smell, everything. I just loved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: And it’s indicative of my Vancouver-ness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: With the maple leaves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah that’s a little thing. We were talking about this. When they release the actual guitar, each one of them–we had this kind of a cool idea. They’re going to have a little tab that sticks up out of the sound hole that I’m going to do a letter, so each one of them is going to have its own letter. So when you pull it, it’ll be like, “Okay, well that’s this one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Your little love note to that guitar itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah. But I think it’s important, too, because the relationship to an instrument is where the songs are. I worked with ESP, I worked with Peavey, both of which were really great and generous companies to me. But what their objectives were were a lot more based in the commercial side of things where, “If we do it like this, we can make a decent instrument and we can make money.” But for me, I’m like, “I don’t need a lot of money. I just need my place, I need my kid to go to school, and I need the tools for me to do my job. I don’t want more tools than what I need. I don’t want more plugins than what I need. I just want the fastest way for me to do my thing so I can go on vacation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that’s awesome. Thanks for sharing that. I want to say thank you for playing at the concert at NAMM. I’m a sponsor of the concert with Julie and Rodney Cord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Oh they’re really nice people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: They’re great people it means a lot to all of us who have worked on or in some way contributed to this show. So I appreciate you doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Absolutely. I hope people come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s going to be awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: It’s the first–well, I guess the second now because I’ve got the CBC thing, but the first opportunity I’ll have to sort of represent this new phase of my life-slash-career by just doing acoustic on stage with the Fractal [Axe FX II]. I think like attracts like ultimately. Again, I think that’s why intention’s so important because I think you gotta know whether you’re full of shit and it’s really easy, at least for me, to convince myself that I’m not when I actually am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s how we go through every single day, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Right! I’m like, “Oh that’s what I meant! That’s totally what I should be doing!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I should be making more, I should be doing more, I should be weighing less…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: That’s the thing. Just even to finish off that statement. When we were talking about the difference between being a monk and being a father in western Canada, you may have to sacrifice some of your spiritual aspirations just for the fact that you live here. This is what your curriculum is. This is where you’re at. It’s like, I’m not just going to ditch the family because, “Well this way I’ll be able to ascend spiritually.” I’m like, “Get out of here. I’ve got a kid and I’ve got fucking braces,” and your wife’s like, “What happened to the fucking banana boy over there?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And everyone hates you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I’m okay with that! [Laughs.] But, I think it’s like you commit to something and you’ve gotta see it through in the most–you know, find a compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: That’s what I’m hoping to do with my creative versus my paranoid mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ll be looking for you at NAMM with a banana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Haha, Peter caught me twice with a banana…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I saw you with a banana at NAMM a couple years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Really?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, we walked right by each other. It was pretty funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Maybe I’ve got such a…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s a thing! It’s a meme!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: [Inaudible.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, I’ve got some quick questions before you go. Who are your favorite female artists?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Musically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Whatever. A lot of the music that we discuss on the site is male-dominant. Metal, very male dominant. So I want to hear–actually this question comes from someone who submitted the question. So, we want to hear your favorite female artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I don’t know if I think about it like that. I mean–sexism is so dumb. It’s like–I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: We can cut it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: It’s all right. I think it’s a good question. I listen to this ambient artist, Meg Bowles, all last year. I know nothing about her, but I assume because her name is Meg, she’s a female. I struggle with male artists in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you listen to much? Are you listening to anything now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: It’s all ambient music. I don’t know what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The guy falling asleep on the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Just [makes a note]. But I don’t know who does it or what the name of it is. I just put on Spotify ambient stuff and just–you know I’m looking for watercolors in the background rather than something that pulls me in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right. Very interesting. Do you have a most surprising song of your own?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: That I’ve written?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That you’ve written. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I don’t think anything that I’ve written surprises me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Will there be an Ocean Machine 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I doubt it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, you mentioned Vai is playing on this new record, too. Someone wanted to know what’s next with you and [Steve] Vai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Steve contacted me. Okay, going back in time, I did vocals on his last record on that last song and he really enjoyed that. So I suggested, because he doesn’t really jam, and I do but not as much as I should. I said, “Oh we should just try writing something. I’ve got a ton of riffs. I’ll send you a riff that I’m not totally married to. You do something to it and send it back. I’ll do something to it and send it back. And we’ll kind of do a chain mail.” And we ended up writing a song called Star Chasm that is a good start. It’s really interesting, but admittedly it sounds like two people who are tag-teaming in terms of writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And that’s on Empath?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: No it was going to be, but I think it deserves to be something that we pursue together. So we’ve discussed writing together, however long that may take. Five years, ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: It’s a good start. And then I sent him–This last song on Empath is called Singularity and it’s 22 minutes long and it’s not nearly as full of shit as that sounds. Actually I think I can say this and I don’t know how it came up, but he asked to hear it, so I sent it to him and he was really taken by it and asked to do a solo on it. It was originally going to be Vernon Reid, who I had met, who’s really a cool guy, but we just couldn’t seem to make that happen. It’s a complicated solo at the end that I was just too lazy or whatever and figuring out what could make it work. Steve offered to do it and he did and he put a brilliant solo at the end of it. I’ve known this guy for thirty years and every now and then I’m like, “Oh Steve Vai’s on my record.” It’s still really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. He has an effect. It’s him more than us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I think the name, too. I just remember being so taken by him as a teen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Same here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: It’s still that. But, yeah, he did a great solo on it. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When we talk on the phone, I get butterflies in the stomach, like when I call him or see his name on the phone, I’m like, “Hahhhhh.” [Laughs.] And it’s like, “Oh yeah, I’ve known this guy for twenty-some years.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah, I think it’s interesting how we’ve all grown together in a lot of ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: He’d be the first to admit that he’s grown in a lot of ways too. He remains one of the most generous people that I’ve worked with in this industry. He’s done more for me than anybody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I might even say the same about him for myself. He changed my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah, me too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So the album comes out when?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: March 27.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thanks so much for taking the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Thank you, man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: You’re more than welcome, man. Thank you for the interview. It’s been a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Let’s go get some lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah! Where we going to eat?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/devin-townsend/guitar-vai-x-jamm</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/devin-townsend/guitar-vai-x-jamm</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Devin Townsend</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-interviews&quot;&gt;Other Interviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Looking for the interview segment about Devin’s creativity book? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/devin-townsend/creativity&quot;&gt;Here it is!&lt;/a&gt; Or the interview segment about his new signature acoustic guitar, Steve Vai, X-JAMM, and more? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/devin-townsend/guitar-vai-x-jamm&quot;&gt;Here it is!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chaos-and-order&quot;&gt;Chaos and Order&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devin Townsend is a bit of a conundrum. After 30 albums and decades of producing music, he still says he doesn’t know what he’s doing. He’s written a book on creativity, which is the impetus for this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview is broken into a few segments. The first one we’re releasing is about his new album, &lt;em&gt;Empath&lt;/em&gt;, which will be released on March 29, 2019. I had the distinct honor and privilege of driving around in Devin’s car for about an hour and listening to nearly the whole thing, discussing with him the highs and lows of the record, themes and stories, and more. It was an unforgettable experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/059_URRoZ9U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/devin-townsend/empath.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/devin-townsend/empath.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’ve said some pretty superlative things on Twitter about Empath, but then you’ve also taken it back. “Well it’s just an album, it’s just music, it’s just…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Both sides of me having a conversation. Okay, well what do I feel about Empath? I feel that–what I feel about it I don’t want to say. I feel like it’s brilliant. I feel like it’s–I feel like it represents me taking my life apart, laying it out, analyzing it, and letting it go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Let me tell you what Mike Keneally said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Because I emailed him and he said, “Devin is a unique creator in my experience.” This is not to embarrass you, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: No that’s all right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: “The speed with which he works and the totality of his vision and the uniqueness of the results, he is a genius in my estimation. Empath is a truly amazing record and one of the most rewarding projects I’ve ever been involved in.” Morgan [Agren] told me it was an incredible project. The people in it see the genius and I think that’s worth repeating, even if you don’t want to say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: I mean, when you tell me these things about these people, my first thought is of them as people and how much I like them. I think my favorite thing about both Mike and Morgan is that I forget that they play music. And that when we have hang time, it’s nice. I think my biggest problem with it is I don’t like being the focus of that because I feel that all I’m doing is trying to honor something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, when they say these things about the record or when people say these things about the record, my hope is that people ultimately know that it’s not me, it’s the process. And the process is perfect, but I’m not perfect and the record’s not perfect. But what we’re trying to achieve is something that is perfect and maybe that’s why art exists because it’ll never be perfect. There’s always things to write about, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I work super fast, but I also feel that’s because when you’re listening for it, it’s an immense amount of information and unless you’re focused, you’re going to miss it. So it’s just about your process has to be super fast and super efficient and you have to exercise and you have to meditate and you have to do these things because otherwise I think you end up internalizing it that this is you, as opposed to the collective unconscious where you’re just dipping your ladle into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Again, I think the intention is you’re dipping your ladle into it because you think it’s beautiful and you think that ultimately it can help. And I really appreciate that Mike says that and I really appreciate that Morgan says these things, but I’m super uncomfortable with it. It’s not that I don’t have an ego, because clearly my ego is enormous, but it’s just–when I sent the record out to the label, they used all these superlatives about it and I just didn’t know what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was just like, “I don’t want to respond. I don’t want to hear it.” At first, I was just like, “Oh I hope they like it. I hope they like it.” But then when they really liked it, I was like, “Oh my God, I don’t want to think about it.” So, clearly just by this interview you can see that my hangups as a dude are what makes the whole thing such a Gong Show, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well that’s why we’re here and I’m not so-and-so from X magazine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Well that’s it! I appreciate that as well because what I was always afraid of was it was going to get popular and I was going to become a representative for this sort of thing that I don’t understand. I try and surround myself with people that understand and respect me and respect the process and, you know, want to watch Rick and Morty with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In that way, I can do this. I can totally function. If there’s not a huge amount of importance placed on it. Sometimes I’ll have people listen to the stuff and they feel something about it is over the top and I’m just like, “Oh my God, I don’t want to be here for that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What I think is interesting is we were talking beforehand about Morgan. You just needed to let him do his thing. Why don’t you tell that story?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Well, because of the music I tend to be privy to, if I could put it that way, is a very specific vision, like super singular in a lot of ways, there’s room in there for someone’s color to make it unique. But, within that there’s fundamentals to the song. Maybe 60-75% of the song that has to be a certain way. It’s like, “That hit has to be there or else that won’t work. And this here has to go like this or else that won’t work.” But past that, what you do with the cymbals, what you do with the fills, all you. But those 60-75% of things are really complicated a lot of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So with Morgan, because I spent a lot of time with Morgan, we’ve done a lot of playing, we did the Casualties of Cool project, I get along with his family, and we have a good social thing, I asked him to do it because he’s Morgan. He’s an amazing drummer and a beautiful person, I wanted that energy. But he hasn’t had to learn music since probably Zappa or Fred [Thordendal] or any of these things that he had done, so he was turning himself inside out trying to learn this stuff. He’s sending me texts like, “Man, I’ve been working on this for hours and I’ve got four bars. It just doesn’t sink in.” Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He’s not a chart kind of guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: No! But when you let him be Morgan, there’s no one as good. So, I watched him and he’s like, “I really wanted to do this right,” and everything. He’s playing it and I’m thinking, “Man, what you’re doing doesn’t sound like Morgan to me. It sounds like you with a leash on.” So I was like, “Oh my God, the deadline for this record is coming up and there’s so much to learn and I can’t leave this to chance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I said to him, “Let’s do a Skype call.” And I said, “Well what if I got two other drummers? One guy who does death metal who’s the best I can find for the CD. He’s a good dude. And one guy does progressive heavy metal. He’s willing to chart it and play it exactly with the cymbals any way we want.” And Morgan’s like, “Thank God. Sounds great.” And I said, “Okay, but I still want you on there, so let’s figure out how to do that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I gave it some thought and every drummer had a different process that on the documentary I think it’s easier to hear that there. But with Morgan, at least, when he showed up, what I did was I took each song that I wanted him to do–So maybe he had four or five songs and then parts. Like the first song is Anup [Sastry] and then Sam [Paulicelli] and then Morgan and then Sam and then Anup and it’s all Frankenstein’d together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So what I did with all Morgan’s parts was I took the song and I took each riff that I wanted him to do and he was like, “Do you want me to learn it ahead of time?” And I was like, “Well actually, no. I don’t want you to learn anything. Nothing at all.” And he showed up kind of confused like, “Well what do you want me to play?” I had taken each song and taken each riff and then I looped each riff for 20 minutes in this massive long section and I just sat in front of him and, without telling him what the riff was, I had an iPad and I put on the iPad a picture of what I wanted to achieve. If you look up YouTube, there’s four-hour sunsets…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s where you taped it to his kick drum, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah. I said, “This is what it’s supposed to feel like.” And I just asked Nali, I said, “Press record.” And then usually three or four minutes in, Morgan was playing phenomenal things. And I was like, “Okay, next riff.” And then I just chopped it up and then put it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: And it was great because at the end of it, he’s playing things that not only no one else would think of, but he wouldn’t remember if we had to do that for a week of rehearsals. It helps I got his first take of it and his crazy little embellishments. We had a great time. It was super easy and I didn’t have to work, which is awesome because I like getting it right, but I don’t like working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Even at the recording, Mike who loves working–I had written all these crazy little guitar things that I played once and then I forgot because I was like, “Oh that’s too hard. I don’t want to play that shit.” But Mike would say, “Well what is that part?” And I was like, “I don’t know.” He’s like, “Well let me figure it out!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then Mike would figure it out and he’d learn these riffs and then I’d be like, “Well the idea is for the bass player to do that.” And he’d say, “Well okay, maybe you can come in here while the bass player’s learning.” And I was like, “That sounds terrible.” I was like, “Why don’t you–because you learned that bit–why don’t you show him how to play it?” And he was all about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So he ended up taking Nathan [Navarro] and showing him all these parts, and the whole time, Anup, Sam, both those guys learned those guys learned their parts. I had Anup come over to Vancouver and I showed him exactly. And Sam, I gave him all the MIDI so that he knew it exactly. So the whole recording, Anup and Sam were in there with the engineers and they were so intent on getting it right that I knew that the parts were good and I didn’t have to do that. And Mark and Mike were so conscientious about getting these super intricate parts, like, exactly that he went to go with an engineer and he’d sit and I watched TV for two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was great! Because when I came in, everybody was so dedicated to getting it right and I had told them ahead of time, “This is what it is. Here’s a demo. The demos are super-specific. These are the notes. This is exactly how I want it to sound.” But I don’t want to do that. It’s really difficult. [Laughs.] You know what I mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What brought Mike in? Had you worked with Mike before?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: He called me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This was just a–off the cuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: He called me a couple years ago. He’s like, “I’m not doing anything. We’ve never met. We should try and do something together.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s what’s so great about Mike. I love that guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Yeah! Yeah! Same. He came to Vancouver and we wrote a bunch of crazy shit that arguably doesn’t have a lot of place anywhere, which is separate from all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh! It’s not on the record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: No, it’s like eight songs of just, like, explosive creative wank. You know what I mean? It’s like, a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: They sell pills for that. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: Oh God. When are we gonna endorse ‘em? You know what I mean? ECW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Explosive Creative Wank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: It’s a good name for a band, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You should make that happen. I could see that happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DT: ECW? Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/devin-townsend/empath</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/devin-townsend/empath</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Western Culture by Henry Cow</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tGDyCCQzCmw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;worst-album-ever&quot;&gt;Worst album ever?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to jam screwdrivers into my ears the first time I listened to Henry Cow’s album Western Culture. I remember hearing the first 10 seconds, then my jaw dropping and my eyes bulging out of my face. It was the worst music I’d ever heard. But like a good road rage video on YouTube, I couldn’t turn it off. This was a different kind of “music” and I just didn’t understand it. My gut told me there was more going on than I could appreciate but my ears told me to turn it off immediately, as my wife continues to do every time she hears Henry Cow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only exposure to the band was through their song “Nirvana for Mice,” which is fairly accessible and melodic. I knew they were a weird band and that their mascot was a knitted sock on the cover of several of their records. What I didn’t know is that they were out of their minds, fiercely rebellious, and deep, deep into music theory. My good friend Jake, who has a music degree, explained a bit of what Henry Cow was doing and that knowledge was the key to unlocking my true appreciation for this album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western Culture contains two pieces of music with several movements. The first piece, History and Prospects, is a brutal beating of various atonal motifs ending with a hypnotic and nauseating dirge. The second piece, Day by Day, is more like Chinese water torture complemented by one of the most incredible piano solos I’ve ever heard. I’ve listened to this solo several times and I legitimately cannot figure out how a human played it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This album was a jaw-dropper for me in three ways: 1. Because it has the most courageous opening minute of any album I’ve ever heard. 2. Because learning how to listen to this album permanently changed the way I listen to music. 3. It helped me to realize that sometimes music isn’t “good” or “bad,” but something I understand or something I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve never heard Henry Cow before, I recommend reading the very thorough Wikipedia page about their history and their approach to music. It’s enlightening, encouraging, and thought-provoking. They were a group of women and men with skin in the game. They did everything they could to avoid routine music performance. They changed how they approached their instruments. They kicked members out in the middle of touring just to shake things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, this album is very listenable to me now. I actually really love it. A lot of it is singable if you can pick out the different motifs. If you’ve never heard it, take 40 minutes and listen with a very open mind. If you’ve heard it and hated it, ask a friend with a music degree to help you hear what you aren’t hearing. It’s not an easy album and it will enrich your life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/henry-cow/western-culture</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/henry-cow/western-culture</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>O Holy Night in 5/4 by Anthony Garone</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OZOT7gVohwQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love weird music and I love &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; Christmas music, but most of it is just garbage. Uninteresting, “happy,” bland music that’s too much about commercial interests. In my mind, the story of Christmas has been wayyy over-glossed and has almost nothing to do with a baby being born 2,000 years ago in the middle east in a barn in the desert. So, I like to rearrange Christmas songs to reflect my view of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy “O Holy Night” as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/o-holy-night-feat-jon-lang-sarah-garone-rob-m%C3%BCller/948367454?i=948367461&quot;&gt;digital download on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fab fa-itunes&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife is singing on this one and is the “star” of the show, but the instrumentation turned out so much better than I hoped when I wrote and released this arrangement in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sarah Garone: Lead vocals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rob Müller: Drums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jon Lang: Piano (not in the video)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nathan Richard: Synth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anthony Garone: Else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/o-holy-night</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/o-holy-night</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sara Groves</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-artist-after-the-generative-life&quot;&gt;An Artist After the Generative Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sara Groves is one of the only contemporary Christian music artists I enjoy. My wife turned me on to her music in 2005 when she brought home Sara’s album “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Add_to_the_Beauty&quot;&gt;Add to the Beauty&lt;/a&gt;.” I remember thinking, “This is good music.” (My wife’s taste in music has only &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; overlap with mine.) After hearing it around the house a couple of times, I started getting some of the songs in my head. Then I brought the CD in my car and heard Sara sing a line from Peter Gabriel’s &lt;em&gt;Come Talk to Me&lt;/em&gt; and I was like, “Okay, I’m in.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is one of the most passionate artists I’ve ever met and she’s given her whole life to music and justice. She is unlike most any artist I’ve met in that her heart and her money go outward to her community and to those in need. She and her husband, Troy Groves, purchased a 100-year-old church and use it as a community arts center. It’s a fantastic space with a wonderful atmosphere in St. Paul, Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife listens to a lot of contemporary Christian artists, but Sara is a clear standout. Her music is very enjoyable, very well recorded, well-produced, and her lyrics are penetrating. She’s one of the few artists I’ve actually listened to for her lyrics. I think growing up with shred guitar music and Yes lyrics desensitized me to lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, we’ve listened to Sara over the years and have very much enjoyed her work. We contributed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pledgemusic.com/projects/saragroves&quot;&gt;Sara’s PledgeMusic campaign&lt;/a&gt; and got to spend a day with her in May 2018. And we’re bringing her to Arizona for a concert in January 2019, which is especially exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pXn6CvFgp_0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/sara-groves/sara-groves.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/sara-groves/sara-groves.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sara Groves is a musician and artist based in Minneapolis, Minnesota and she recently had a Kickstarter campaign for a new record of hers called Abide With Me, which I have here. My wife and I participated in that Kickstarter campaign and as part of the campaign, we were lucky enough to get to spend a day with Sara in Minneapolis and that was… early May, I believe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, May 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I spoke to Sara about her music a little bit and asked her if she would have a conversation for the website. She was the first to say, “Well, my music isn’t really weird.” And, yes, that is relatively true, but the perspective I heard from her as an artist and a musician that day really was eye-opening and a bit mind-blowing at times and covered some pretty deep topics that I really wanted to have her share with us in this format. So, Sara thank you so much for joining. I really appreciate you taking the time to join.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Thank you, my pleasure. Good to see you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You too. Can you give a little bit of background as to who you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: I’ve been doing this for about 20 years. I was a teacher before I did music and taught high school for a few years and then went into music full time. I’ve been on the road, a touring musician for 20 years. When you think about that, there’s all these sort of–even when I thought about it at the beginning, either you’re doing this or you’re not doing anything. All in there, there are just a million little places for live music and for people that do music for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s just been an adventure. I have a very wonderfully-committed group of listeners that have followed me, so that makes it really possible for me to still be at it this far in. I’ve made 13 albums in that time and I do tend to play in the faith community, but my music is really about the whole of life. I am reflecting on everything. The whole of life. Singer/Songwriter. I play the piano, write at the piano. My band consists usually of a 3-piece, which is bass, piano, drums, and my bass player also plays pedal steel. So that’s a crowd-pleaser and it’s just a beautiful thing. It’s pretty stripped down. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The lyric is definitely the point of what we’re doing, but the music is important as well.&lt;/span&gt; I’ve been at that for all this time and am just grateful. I still go out and do about–I was full time on the road for 17 years and then about 3 or 4 years ago, I pulled back and do about 30-40 dates per year now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ir5RhjnSRF0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. And your albums have quite a diverse mix of music. Most recently, this new album, “Abide With Me,” is very sparse. It’s a very “simple” record, I suppose, because it’s mostly voice and piano, whereas other albums like “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Add_to_the_Beauty&quot;&gt;Add to the Beauty&lt;/a&gt;” and “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tell_Me_What_You_Know&quot;&gt;Tell Me What You Know&lt;/a&gt;” are much more highly produced, a lot more instrumentation. So, can you talk a little bit about the evolution of your music and you as an artist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: I’ve always been pretty open to and highly influenced by the producer that I’m working with because I’m not a producer. I’ve not ventured into that realm. So, I’ve worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Peacock&quot;&gt;Charlie Peacock&lt;/a&gt;, he’s grammy award winning in every decade he’s been making music. And incredibly creative. One of the most creative people I know. He worked with me on “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Other_Side_of_Something&quot;&gt;The Other Side of Something&lt;/a&gt;” and wanted to do kind of a singer/songwriter record with “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fireflies_and_Songs&quot;&gt;Fireflies and Songs&lt;/a&gt;.” So, that was really reflecting–when I collaborate with someone, I’m very much open to their vision and the band that I’m playing with. I think each of those albums you’re hearing a little bit of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, I think that when I first came out, the space that I was occupying and the people that were promoting music, I was in the middle of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contemporary_Christian_music&quot;&gt;Christian Contemporary Music&lt;/a&gt; (CCM Music). That has a whole sound and genre of its own. The first song that I had on radio did really well and it was a very natural fit. It did well, but I wasn’t having to do anything different. It just happened to fit right where they were needing, but after that the conversation became very difficult. I was having to do some gymnastics to try to meet what I thought they wanted and that kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, with the second album, I had a record of really personal, very relationship-oriented songs and there was sort of a conversation about, “There’s not really anything that we could play here that would be on a station where their mission is safe for the whole family, encouraging, uplifting.” So they asked if I would do–”Well, could you add something?” So I added this song to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Right_Here&quot;&gt;All Right Here&lt;/a&gt;” and I always just felt like it was a bummer to me because it felt so different from what I was actually feeling, like I was supposed to be doing in the space I was inhabiting at the time. So after that, I just said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Look, I’ll make a record and if you find something you like, then great. And if you don’t, then I’m okay with that.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was working with a label that was very generous with me. I was the first artist to sign and I’ve been with them for the duration. They’ve given me a lot of space to be on my own and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it hasn’t always meant success in the sense of more listenership, but I feel like the listeners that I have trust me.&lt;/span&gt; I remember at one point, Charlie talking to me about the label was saying around the record “The Other Side of Something” like, “You really have one shot left at being in the Christian music scene.” And Charlie came to me and said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“You’re more of a mom-and-pop shop than you are a Walmart, and if you were to do something that’s kind of Walmart-y, then the people that trust you might not trust you anymore. So, stick to what you feel is what you’re supposed to be doing. The stuff you’re supposed to be putting into the world.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jaW43MlC3hI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that was one of the best conversations I ever had. I was able to go to our label president and say, “I’m a mom-and-pop store, not a Walmart.” And even on an economic level, on every level he was able to understand that and he said, “Oh, okay. Let’s treat it as such, then. Let’s find your people, your ears, and just keep meeting them there.” So that was good. That was pretty early on, that was in ‘03. I really felt free to experiment. The record, “Tell Me What You Know,” is huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown_Bannister&quot;&gt;Brown Bannister&lt;/a&gt; on “Add to the Beauty” and he’s produced tons of music. “Add to the Beauty” was a real heart album and then with “Tell Me What You Know,” I was talking about social justice things, which at that time in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelicalism&quot;&gt;evangelical church&lt;/a&gt; we weren’t addressing as much. I wanted to make a really “right where you live” full-on pop album, but around themes of social justice. I had a song based on “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/When_the_Saints_Go_Marching_In&quot;&gt;When the Saints go Marching In&lt;/a&gt;” and some others that were just a big pop record. But that was kind of on purpose. We were doing something with that. I think “Add to the Beauty.” “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floodplain_(Sara_Groves_album)&quot;&gt;Floodplain&lt;/a&gt;,” “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conversations_(Sara_Groves_album)&quot;&gt;Conversations&lt;/a&gt;” are kind of the quintessential Sara Groves albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Gabriel&quot;&gt;Peter Gabriel&lt;/a&gt;, I love an epic song. I love something really vibey that can get a little wooly. I’m not averse to that. I’m not totally just acoustic and stripped down. I wouldn’t say that that’s me when I’m being myself. There’s an emotive epic feel to what I like, so that tends to be what I gravitate to. Abide With Me was produced by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnmarknelson.com/&quot;&gt;John Mark Nelson&lt;/a&gt; and he’s a young artist in his early 20s and he is very minimalist. He took that approach to that record. You’ve been to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arthousenorth.com/&quot;&gt;Art House&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Paul,_Minnesota&quot;&gt;St. Paul&lt;/a&gt;. My husband and I own a 100-year-old church where we recorded that record and John Mark said, “I want this album to sound like this room looks.” It’s very warm, lots of warm wood, resonant. That was the goal of that album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes, “stripped down” is a much better word than “simple.” It was not coming to me when I described “Abide With Me.” But it’s funny, last night to prepare for the interview, I listened to “Add to the Beauty” and “Tell Me What You Know,” and those albums are very close to me largely because of the Peter Gabriel vibe going on. And even when you sing parts of “Come Talk To Me” on the reprise at the end. But then on my iTunes it went through to “The Other Side of Something,” and I was like, “What’s this record? It’s really aggressive.” There’s totally &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiona_Apple&quot;&gt;Fiona Apple&lt;/a&gt; elements, there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beatles&quot;&gt;Beatles&lt;/a&gt; elements, it’s a very diverse album, as are “Add To the Beauty” and “Tell Me What You Know.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: “The Other Side of Something” is Charlie Peacock. You hear him in that record and again, I love those collaborations. You definitely hear the Sara Groves come through. Obviously, that’s always what it is. But Charlie came back to me–his daughter was a big fan and he said (I don’t like the word “fan,” but she’s a listener) and so she said she wanted an album where I was just a kind of a girl and her piano. So Charlie came back and said, “If I ever get a chance to do another record with you. I would do it differently.” He felt like it was his playground with “The Other Side of Something.” He was kind of playing and having fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But with “Fireflies and Songs,” he was more, “Okay, what are you doing when you’re amplified? When you’re at your best?” So those two records really show the difference of the approach of that collaboration. “Other Side of Something” was a blank check to Charlie. Songs like “The Boxer,” his whole world is from a jazz background and very improvisational. We had the band improvising for probably an hour and they’d play for probably 10-15 minutes and he’d say, “All right, everyone change what you’re doing,” and then they’d play again for another 15 minutes and then he’d say, “All right, whatever you’re doing, don’t do that again.” They’d play again and then he sort of takes all these scenes that they had created because they get into a whole picture and he chopped those up and put those back to back, so in that song, in “The Boxer,” you’re moving in and out of these jazz scenes. I loved that! I loved that whole experience. I’m just on the mic in the corner making stuff up. So, that was a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, very cool stuff. You mentioned the element of social justice in your music. That term, “social justice,” nowadays seems to be taking on its own life with “social justice warriors.” But I know that you are talking about something different than young people fighting their university, the patriarchy, that kind of thing. Can you talk a little about what social justice means in the context that you’re using it and how your music plays into your activism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah. Well, I’ll have to go to a place to talk about it from the vantage point of my faith because I grew up in church. In my late 20s, I was having a faith crisis. What I was feeling was that I was going and doing all this work to groom and groom and groom my own personal faith. My own understanding of myself, my own understanding of God, and I was doing all this sort of work and I felt all dressed up and nowhere to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;To what end do we gather every week? I believe in that, I believe in the blessed community, I believe in the flawed qualities, that we come together, that it’s important to do that. But in attempting to reflect what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatitudes&quot;&gt;the beatitudes&lt;/a&gt; are talking about, what Jesus was trying to do and say in the world, if I’m really going to follow that, I felt like what we were doing on a Sunday morning wasn’t really reflective wholly of what he was purporting we should be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I started looking around for people that were doing that and I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Justice_Mission&quot;&gt;International Justice Mission&lt;/a&gt;. They’re the largest anti-slavery, anti-trafficking organization in the world. They’re truly an international organization. They have offices all over the world and are led by the best and brightest in India and Africa and Philippines and all over southeast Asia. I started hearing these stories of rescue and of people that were being enslaved for generations and now they were going through after-care programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Lt_WpluguwE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s a story in India of a woman enslaved and then ran for city council. She’s now sitting on the city council of her community and ran against the man that is supported by her previous owner. There’s a survivor-led movement. There are more slaves today than there ever have been in the history of the world. There’s a survivor-led movement that’s happening that’s just unbelievable.&lt;/span&gt; So when I started seeing these men and women of faith who, because of their faith, were going into very difficult places. The best and brightest lawyers in India were signing up and I want to advocate for the poor. I want to be on the side of–I think that’s where Jesus said he would be. “I’ll be here with those that are oppressed, with those that are poor.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I started hearing these stories and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;my first response was, “I need to do something different than be a songwriter. I need to be a nurse or an after-care worker or a lawyer. I need to do something more tangible.”&lt;/span&gt; And that’s when Charlie sat me down and told me about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cellist_of_Sarajevo&quot;&gt;cellist of Sarajevo&lt;/a&gt; and said, “You know there was a guy during the Bosnian war who played his cello in the middle of a recently-bombed out area and a lot of people say what he did, the attention that he drew, this protest of beauty in the middle of all this chaos, it drew attention to the region and really hastened the end of the war.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Basically, art matters, and songs matter&lt;/span&gt;, and he was encouraging me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Write music about what you’re seeing!” I had met a survivor of trafficking. We became good friends. Her life and her resilience and her faith were so compelling to me. The record “Tell Me What You Know,” every single song in some way reflects her.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was writing about her, I was writing about the work of International Justice Mission, and now my husband works for them. He’s been there 4 years and it’s kind of an integral part of our life. To me, it is the expression of faith. My grandfather, for 40 years, he went down to the local prison in our town and met with a group of men twice a week. I have a history of people engaging just to enter suffering that’s not your own. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;To me, that’s what I mean when I say “social justice.” I mean: justice is what love looks like in public. And I think as Christ-followers, we have to think about that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One of the most compelling things that I realized about you through the St. Paul experience was how much you’ve given your life through your music and using your music towards this new–after-that experience. This activism. A lot of people, if they have money in music, they will just continue investing in that, they’ll build a studio, they’ll grow their careers, or something like that. You have built a community center, you use this money to change really horrible situations in the world, and your music is developing awareness and a form of activism. Can you share a little bit about the story where your lyrics may have crossed a line for your label? You shared something about that with “there’s a girl in the room.” I just thought it was so fascinating about the context where your music is normally released versus the experience that you have as a faith-based artist for a faith-based label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: It was “When the Saints,” a song based on “When the Saints.” I had written the original with a bridge that basically talked about “I think of Harriet Tubman, I think of all these people that have gone before me.” There’s a lyric, “I see a…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It builds and basically ends with a picture of a girl on the brothel floor, I see a man with a passion come and kicking down that door. That was one of the stories I had seen. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svay_Pak&quot;&gt;Svay Pak&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippines&quot;&gt;Philippines&lt;/a&gt; was a sex tourism site. It was a place where if you were a pedophile, you could go and you knew you would be unhindered. The brothels were in cahoots with the police, so there was no protection. These children were being trafficked in the open, basically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was one of IJM’s first jobs. They went there and they just began collecting undercover investigation materials and documenting all who was there. The youngest was as young as 5 years old and they brought all this information to a man in power who wanted to do the right thing. So they started something and began a work there that led to eventually the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_%26_Melinda_Gates_Foundation&quot;&gt;Bill Gates Foundation&lt;/a&gt; doing a study, an external study of their work in the Philippines. In Sebu, Philippines and in other places, they saw as much as 87% reduction of the trafficking of children in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Their work is just amazing and it works. It’s creating a barrier that’s basically telling these guys that think, “I can just do whatever I want.” You can’t do that with impunity. You will go to jail. It creates a buffer, a hedge of protection around these children. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wanted to write about that guy. I knew who the head investigator was. I’d seen footage of him kicking down the door of the brothel to get these girls.&lt;/span&gt; So I’d written and talked about the brothel and all that. When I went to go record the song, they really liked the song, but felt like maybe there was a different approach to the bridge just to fit more with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had written this whole other bridge and it was more going back to historically-Biblical figures and moving then further through history. We had tracked the whole thing, we recorded the whole thing. My husband was out with a friend and he was talking about how much it bothered him. It kind of lost its original–the whole point of the song, we wrote it because of this girl we had met and because of the stories we were hearing. So, I was 8 months, maybe 9 months pregnant and Troy comes home and was like, “We have to re-cut that bridge.” We called the producer. The record is done. It’s finished, and I think even mixed at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LxT_RqPt660?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was very last-minute, but Brown was producing that record and he called the studio in Minneapolis and we got in and I re-sang the entire bridge. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the sense was that talking about brothels in India and brothels in Southeast Asia is not safe for the whole family. For me, it just felt like that can’t be my goal, that can’t be what I’m prioritizing over telling the truth about what I’m seeing.&lt;/span&gt; We decided to go with the original lyric that I had written and that made sense. The song has gone out and had much of more an impact because of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The song was chosen by iTunes to be the “discovery download for that month,” so back then–they don’t do the same things exactly now, but back then they used to pick–and you couldn’t buy it. A label couldn’t in any way coerce how this was happening, but iTunes would pick and they would move through different genres. Maybe once or twice a year, they would pick a Christian song. It was the discovery download of the week, so they picked that song to be the discovery download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This was before the album was released and we had friends who had been working on a project to bring down this certain really insidious brothel and they had tried several times. I think they were on their seventh try to have the police come and raid this. Every time they went, someone had tipped them off so the girls were hidden or gone. So, a friend of mine emailed them and said, “Sara Groves has written you a song, “and it was uploaded that night at midnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;On iTunes, the album wasn’t even available yet, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;but where they were gathered in south Asia, they gathered around their little computer, listened to the song, and then went and conducted this raid with the police and were successful and ended up capturing and freeing all these girls.&lt;/span&gt; And I just thought that was such a neat moment for me, that the music–I had written it for them, to advocate for them to get their story out and here they were gathered around these tiny speakers really finding encouragement from the song. The director of that office wrote me later and said, “We rescued that girl. We all gathered around the computer and then went out and did it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: So for me, yeah, that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;that lyric was right and telling the truth about what I was trying to say. That was really important. It might seem like a small thing to push back about, but it was important to me. That’s always the balance that you’re trying to figure out and market your music and being true to yourself and all of those things.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think it’s just an incredible testimony to so many things, particularly the power of music and music as art and that art is important. With that being said, why don’t you tell us a little about Art House North, what it is, why you started it, and what you’re doing with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, so I came over here because my house isn’t very quiet this morning. My husband and I own a 100-year-old church and right behind you is actually the album cover of Abide With Me and that’s a picture of 1906, that’s a picture of the building being built and the first congregation are having their first service out in the street there in front of the building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, so that’s the art house being built. So we bought it in 2011 and we really modeled it–so Charlie Peacock has just been a mentor and friend for many years. Watching his and his wife’s life, they were influenced by a lot of different people–&lt;a href=&quot;http://labri.org/&quot;&gt;L’Abrie&lt;/a&gt; and that kind of idea of having a place to gather, be able to ask questions. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In Nashville, I found a lot of places where you could get information about how to run your business, but a place where you could actually talk about what it means to be a person of faith in the world, what does it look like? What does it look like to tear down the sacred and secular divide and just be yourself? Be wholly integrated and just be doing what you’re doing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I used to talk to Charlie about not writing about the filter, but writing about what you see through the filter. That’s the kind of Christian artist I wanted to be, that I wasn’t always writing about the Christianity itself. Maybe those songs are valuable, I’m not diminishing that, but for me &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I felt really called to the integrated life. If it matters, it matters at every level and it matters everywhere I go and in every part of myself, so I wanted the music to reflect that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we watched them have this community in Nashville. They started Art House in Nashville and they bought a 100-year-old church and they actually lived in their church and had a studio there and that’s where we produced “The Other Side of Something” and “Fireflies and Songs.” We would gather there with them with other people to hear about–I learned about IJM at Art House and just talking about what kind of person you want to be in the world, what it looks like to be a person of faith, and to use that wisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, Troy and I in 2011 bought this place and we don’t have a good elevator speech because all kinds of things happen here. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The tagline is “Creative community for the common good.”&lt;/span&gt; We have two parts of Art House. We have community partnerships where people have come around us. We have a theater company that the couple that runs it lives a block away from us. Our kids are all in school together. They’re just amazing. They write original plays and they do them here, probably about three per year. And then we have, Troy and I, our Art House programming. That is all kinds of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We have afterschool music lessons for kids that kind of resemble School of Rock. We do a square dance every year. We have all kinds of things around the arts. Our neighbor is a banjo player and he came to us and said, “Nothing brings a neighborhood together like a square dance.” So we started that tradition 4 or 5 years ago. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And then Troy and I host events where we’re talking about different topics. Our format is “Artists Respond.” Artists respond to tragedy, artists respond to creation care, artists respond to gun violence, artists respond to whatever the topic is. Immigration…. So we call up 3-5 artists to respond to a topic and instead of having a panel or talking heads, that kind of thing, we let people just express through their art how they’ve experienced that topic.&lt;/span&gt; And then the discussion ends up being a lot richer and a lot more nuanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think we’ve lost nuance, we’ve completely lost nuance. It’s just almost impossible to actually reason together. So we found that through the arts you can do that a little bit better. Someone says, “I wrote this song because I was compelled by what I saw.” And also it’s often coming from a place of lament instead of anger. You tend to find that, I think, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when we invite artists that they are able to share their lament about whatever they see that’s incongruent in the world&lt;/span&gt;, if that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3y8JSNknIzE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Totally. That reminds me of a video you have on your website. I think it’s called “Extravagance” where you talk about how an artist can see what he or she does as extravagant or wasteful. Could you elaborate on that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, so another person I listen to a lot is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Makoto_Fujimura&quot;&gt;Makoto Fujimura&lt;/a&gt;. He’s a visual artist. He used to be in New York City. He was there when 9/11 occurred and was kind of part of a vital artist’s movement around 9/11 to bring spaces of healing to New York. He’s written a lot about that. He wrote a book called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Refractions-Journey-Faith-Art-Culture/dp/1600063012&quot;&gt;Refractions&lt;/a&gt;” and he’s written a book called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0830845038/ref=dbs_a_def_rwt_bibl_vppi_i0&quot;&gt;Culture Care&lt;/a&gt;.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He just puts forth the idea that culture is not a war to be won, but it is a garden to be cultivated.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The difference between a combative stance or a blaming stance where you stand around–I think about that cellist in the middle of that bomb crater in Sarajevo. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s easy to stand around the bomb crater and talk about the bomb crater and how it got there and who’s to blame for it and its dimensions and how deep it is and what a loss it is. It’s something different to crawl in there yourself and start creating something beautiful and to have this protest of beauty in the middle of chaos.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Both Makota Fujimura and Charlie Peacock have shown me what they call the “generative life.” That is the life that crawls into that space and says, “What would I build here? What would I put here? Even if it’s going to be bombed out again. Even if the war doesn’t stop. Even if the chaos doesn’t stop. What generative thing would I put here?” And so that was from a blog he had written about, I believe, the war in Iraq. He had written about this little girl that, in running back to save a flower, she saw a flower and she had been struck by a bullet. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Everyone said, “What a waste,” and yet Mako was saying in this gesture, he saw this child identifying with something beautiful in the middle of total chaos and that action was a very valiant effort to save something beautiful on her part.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He talks about how the arts can feel–we can feel as contemplatives, sometimes, the time it takes to contemplate, the materials we’re using, all those things can feel extravagant and wasteful. When we’re in these sort of utilitarian and pragmatically-driven spaces. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He says utility and pragmatism have infected every institution we know and he said maybe primarily the church where we equate “useful” with “good.” That began a dialogue in my own heart. “Oh wow, what do we do with useless people? How do we think about that? What do we do with the parts of ourselves that feel useless and lacking?”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At the time, I had been going through some depression and was having a very hard time being productive. My productivity levels were down the drain. So what value was I at that point if I wasn’t producing? So I began thinking differently about my life. “Okay, I’m having a hard time these days getting out of bed. I’m genuinely moving more slowly. So what is the value? I think there’s something here for me to learn and to listen to.” My body was telling me something. My everything was trying to get my attention. That record, “Floodplain,” was really looking at those ideas of extravagance and wasteful. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;To me, the Mississippi River is the dream of God.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e_bukdxhBKo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was looking one day at the city of St. Paul on the bluff and I thought, “The city is the dream of man. It’s amazing what we can build. What we can do. It’s incredible .You look at a city and it’s mind-blowing what we can do. We work together and we accomplish and we strive and we make these cities.” But then there’s the river running by the city. This is an invitation. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is kind of if you want to know how God is different from us. We could not make the Mississippi River. It is other. It’s so other than us.&lt;/span&gt; It’s other than what we would do and it’s an invitation to this extravagant kind of Huck Finn rest. “Come on, get on a raft. Let’s go sit a while and ponder.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Those things can feel like, “Oh what a waste of time.” And yet, I think the arts are necessary to push back against that pragmatic, useful constant dream of man that kind of whirs around us. I think it’s important. I actually think once a week we should get away and enter into this space really intentionally, into this dream of God. Obviously, I want to be participating in the dream of God and what I call the “kingdom imagination” at all times of the week. But that record “Floodplain” ended up being about my journey with depression, but finding value in pushing against that pragmatic space and entering into those extravagant and wasteful “I’m gonna do something totally lavish.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s amazing. I’ve spoken with the artist Steve Vai. He’s a guitarist that also thinks at this level. We were talking about what he calls “the movie projector metaphor” where we often think our life is what’s happening as the film crosses the movie projector, but we’re really the light. We have the opportunity to choose to be what’s on the film or to be the light. It reminds me a lot of what you’re talking about with this “filter.” You’re wearing these glasses and you have this worldview that applies to whatever it is that you’re seeing and experiencing. So can you talk a little more about how you’ve discovered as an artist what your filters are and how to move beyond that? The world wants you to have their filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, yeah. That’s a good question. I think that–I love that projector [metaphor]. That’s going to stay with me. I try to be a student of people I admire, so if I find somebody and they’re just intriguing to me–we’ve just lost &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene_H._Peterson&quot;&gt;Eugene Peterson&lt;/a&gt;, a pastor of profound gift. I was lucky enough to have met him and his books have shaped me for years. I’ve tried to read “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Long-Obedience-Same-Direction-Discipleship/dp/0830822577&quot;&gt;A Long Obedience in the Same Direction&lt;/a&gt;” once a year. But people like Eugene Peterson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Brueggemann&quot;&gt;Walter Brueggemann&lt;/a&gt;–and my dad was very much this way, too. He was always encouraging me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Kind of what I said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you can get stuck thinking so much about the filter and defining it constantly that you kind of forget to actually do the thing. Talking about the thing and doing the thing are two very separate things.&lt;/span&gt; I see for me, the word “Christian” has come to mean a lot of things. It evokes a lot of feelings in people, especially right now, but to me, at the base level, it’s being an imitator of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ra3lh0DCIDY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;To me, Jesus is–so, every man says in his heart, all throughout history, “If I were God, if I were God, if I were God, if I were God…” And then the story, as the story goes, this is God himself coming and he had every right to just roar, to just completely level, to be God. And he is God, as it says in Philippians, he didn’t consider equality with God something to be used to his advantage, but instead thought of others more highly than himself. That was what God did when he came. Even if you don’t believe that that story is real, that’s compelling. That’s very compelling to me. We’re used to “power over” always, people pushing and it’s like this is the story of the apple. It’s “I want that,” forcefully taking and possessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we know what that looks like. We see that play out in history a bazillion times, in seriously every heart. Even my dog has said, “If I were God.” Every single one of us says it. And here’s this story about God himself coming and purporting, “I am God,“ and then doing something so completely different and humble and not “power over,” but in service. So I think that what I want to be doing is sort of integrated. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madeleine_L%27Engle&quot;&gt;Madeleine L’Engle&lt;/a&gt; said there is no such thing as sacred and secular art. There’s only good and bad art.&lt;/span&gt; And I love that because I think, “Okay, I want to be putting beautiful and good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think when I do that, I’m participating in the divine nature and so I want to put those things into the world**, but I always want to be thinking about embodiment. Not just what’s happening “here” in a sort of philosophical or theological level, but then always asking the question of “what does that look like when I’m in a fight with my husband?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u15Ew-SIz6A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I wrote a song called “Roll to the Middle” when we had literally had the most massive fight. The full-blown, all bets were off and we were unloading 100% and he was leaving town, going overseas for three weeks. I thought, “He can’t leave like this. I know the right thing to do, I just don’t feel at all even remotely like reconciling at this point, but he can’t leave the country with us in this place.” So I went to the piano just in search of anything. A song of reconciliation. That song ended up being beautifully so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I played it for him. It came out in a matter of 10 minutes and half an hour later, “Can I play you something? It’s so weird, I know.” But I played that song and it’s like, no matter how my pride resists, no matter how that wall feels true, no matter how I can’t basically make you respond this equally, I can’t make you also apologize, but I’m going to lean into you. I’m going to not let you go like this. So that song ended up being a part of our reconciliation, so always looking at “what does this actually look like in human terms in what we’re actually doing here?” Not just having a faith that is for the hereafter, but very much, I think that is what Jesus says more than anything. The kingdom of God is near, it’s actually among you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I listened to that song last night and was pretty astounded at the honesty and how much I could relate. Everybody in a relationship has to go through something like that. You can choose to let it ruin you or you can use it as an opportunity to learn about yourself and the relationship you’re in. So, hearing that in a musical context was very moving and powerful. Again, it’s just a testimony to how when I listen to your music, how much power there is in your art. I don’t normally listen to lyrics, I grew up playing guitar. Shredding. So, when I listen to music, I’m mostly listening to the music, but you have a way of using the word and the lyric to really get through. The music is a context that you use to allow the word to move forward. So, that’s another thing I really admire about you and your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re welcome. Can you talk a little bit about patronage? That was a topic that we discussed, you discussed more broadly at the St. Paul experience, you and I spoke a little bit individually about, and it’s really impacted your recent career. So, talk a little bit about patronage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Well, I have to thank you because you encouraged me to take a step. Troy had been already on board for probably–since it started. He got early wind of what Patreon specifically was doing, but that conversation with you–Troy said, “Of course, one other person says…” He’s been telling me for so long and then he says, “One other strange person…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m finally that person. I’m always in Troy’s position, but now I’m on the other side. Cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah! But I think the coin maybe somehow dropped when we were talking and I thought, “You know, I need to move forward with this.” What I say about music, and there’s a lot to this obviously, this is a whole big conversation. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the music scene has changed so much and the way I describe our own lives is we were working one field for a yield and then we were working two fields for that yield and then ten fields and then it became unsustainable because of streaming.&lt;/span&gt; We’ve lived through many disruptive technologies, we’ve seen the move from cassettes to CDs and then CDs to streaming. And then even downloads then to full-on streaming, just where everything is basically free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ud5XLIOBLys?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I remember a few years ago asking our label, “So what happens on…” We were doing all this pre-release stuff to try to sell the record early and we basically–Dan Michaels had said, “You have about a month to sell your record before it comes out to the people that really want to hear it.” And I said, “What happens now because release day used to be such a big deal?” It was such a huge day and then the next month was the big month. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So I said, “What happens on release day?” And he said, “Oh that’s the day your album is free.”&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs.] And I was, “Oh my word!” I hadn’t really fully processed that yet that, oh, that’s what happens. That’s the day your record is available for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think that liminality is good for the arts. I think that it forces creativity and we’re in a space where we have to think differently and traditionally, the arts were always supported by patronage. Someone wanted &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Joyce&quot;&gt;James Joyce&lt;/a&gt; to write, so they supported him, put him up in an apartment and paid for his meals and all that so that he could write. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent_van_Gogh&quot;&gt;Vincent Van Gogh&lt;/a&gt; even was constantly having to write home for more money, but he had patronage from his brother and different people to do what he was doing. That long defeat that he walked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, there’s a short little window from the 1940s til our present in 1995 where we were able to sell a CD and kind of have this exchange, but that window has closed and we moved into a different time. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think a lot of artists are looking back to the sort of history of the arts. The arts have always required endowment.&lt;/span&gt; Troy always says, “Look at your portfolio, your support. You’ve got these stocks, you’ve got these things, are you supporting the arts?” Maybe you’re supporting public radio or something. If you’re enjoying something are you supporting it? With Patreon, you and I had talked about that, but that’s basically created a tool for artists to be able to connect with their listeners in a very direct way and create and hopefully bring value to that relationship. Deepen that relationship so that you’re bringing more exclusive content to the people that really care about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can’t support every person you listen to with streaming music, but I think you can consider what 3-5 artists do I listen to a lot. How am I actually engaging in the marketplace with them? Am I buying a t-shirt? Am I going to a show?&lt;/span&gt; To think about that, if I’m really participating and if someone’s music is really resonating with me and informing the way I think about the world, am I then somehow participating in the making of that music? I think that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patreon&quot;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt;’s created an amazing tool to let–not everyone’s going to love my music, but there are people who’ve been listening for a long time. You had so, I think, given me permission. I think I felt–it’s kind of hard. It’s a hard paradigm shift to go, “Am I asking for some sort of hand-out?” Because you’re actually again having to put value on what you do as a vocational thing. I think in the arts that can be a struggle anyway. You’re always kind of like, “Is this valuable?” [Laughs.] So, yeah, thanks for the encouragement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re very welcome. And how has the response been?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: It’s been amazing. We’ve been up for about two and a half weeks and I have 130-140 supporters at this time. It’s just a game-changer. I had posted just for Patreon listeners a little song that Ruby and I wrote. It’s a prayer that we kind of sing, not every night, but often for all the people that would be displaced on any given night. We know there are millions of people who have been driven from their homes because of violence or whatever. Thinking about the refugee, thinking about those mothers that are on the road, carrying their whole lives on their back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I just wanted a prayer, something that Ruby and I could sing or say that would just be something we would repeat and remind us of the refugee at any given time. So I wrote this song, “Jesus See the Traveler.” I posted that for our Patreon folks and I posted just a clip of it to my Instagram. Not the full song, but the response was really overwhelming. People were asking, “Where can I get this song? Can I get the whole thing?” So I’ve already booked a studio and players and we’re going to track that song, Ruby and I are going to track it in the first week of November, and then that will go out into the world. Then I’ll be able to tell my Patreon supporters, “You did this! Literally. That would have just languished in my song notebook because I wouldn’t have the resources to put together an album.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gY-3LtJtPIE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m basically on an 18-month to 2-year cycle because I’m paying for those albums. I pay to make them. It’s a huge investment.&lt;/span&gt; So, that’s a difference. I’m dreaming every single day like, “Oh I can do that. I can actually record that song.” And that’s something I used to be able to do, but just in the last ten years, how am I going to fund that? How am I going to get that to happen? So it just really is–I cried the first week [laughs] because I told Troy, “I don’t think I really appreciated the impact of not being paid vocationally for a while.” And then to have people come and affirm that again and say, “Yeah we’d like you to do this for a living.” You know? Even though I know that that’s my role in the world, it was very affirming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s very difficult to understand that separation of “this is what I’m called to do” and “this is how the world makes it happen.” You don’t want your identity to be tainted or poisoned by the way an industry might work, but I’m really glad you did it and there really are hundreds more people who want to give you money. They’re just waiting to give you their money, you know? It’s like, just get the word out and they can offer even a dollar a month. It’s like buying a CD a year, but it goes directly to the artist. So, I think it’s a very powerful thing and I’m really glad that it’s working out for you. So, congratulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Thank you. We kind of tied it in where we’re merging what I’m doing–it used to be kind of like “here’s Sara’s music” or “the touring entity” and then “here’s Art House” but we’re really seeing the two working together now. The Art House is the umbrella. The Patreon is also going towards everything we’re doing in our lives, that creative community for the common good. The music is a big part of that. Obviously it’s coming out of here. I write here at this piano and this is where that begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qavipq-IgkM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s also powerful, at least for me–I only have a handful of patrons. I don’t push the Patreon thing very much, but just knowing that there are people who want me to be doing this and they’re sacrificing their own money and their time (because they had to earn the money), it encourages me to keep going and to release things and to make it interesting for them. I don’t know if you’ve experienced that as well, but it sounds like you’re starting to. It’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Yeah, the ideas–I have this long–I’ve been ruminating on this idea for a long time to go back and meet with people that I’ve worked with in the past, like Charlie and Don and Lori Chaffer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterdeep_(band)&quot;&gt;Waterdeep&lt;/a&gt; and these other bands that I’ve worked with, and to do sort of a vlog of us writing together. Basically where we get together and write a song. I’ve lined up two of those already in January. So in January, I’ll be going down with a couple friends who do film and they’ll be basically capturing us writing music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m just excited about the possibilities. I have no idea what the song–what will we write? What will we create? I think just letting people into the process more, too, is a lot of fun. It used to be like you squirreled away and you did your work and brought it out. It’s a fun idea that–I love the author &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austin_Kleon&quot;&gt;Austin Kleon&lt;/a&gt;. He says he’s an artist that writes or a writer that draws. I can’t remember, but he does these kinds of doodle things and he curates a newsletter about creative writing once a month, I think. It’s very life-giving to me. I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But Austin, he wrote the book “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Steal-Like-Artist-Things-Creative/dp/0761169253&quot;&gt;Steal Like an Artist&lt;/a&gt;” based on the idea that we’re all just taking all the pieces that inform us and creating something new with that. Anyway, I’ve just been so inspired with this. I could actually dream about–have ideas and put things into the world now, where before, “That’s a really cool idea, but it’s cost prohibitive,” or, “That just doesn’t work.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I have worked with this label, but it has always been a marketing and distribution deal. Troy and I have funded our own album making from the beginning. It’s like buying a car every year, you know?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yep, definitely. Awesome. This has been a great conversation and I really appreciate you taking the time. So many great insights and I know that people come to these interviews with artists because they’re people like you who live it out and you are really a gifted artist and I’m very happy that we could have this conversation. So thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Me too. Thank you, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How can people learn more about you and start to discover your work and those kinds of things? How do you recommend? And best support you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SG: Well, Patreon. I have a new Patreon. [Laughs.] What do you call it? An account?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Page? I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SG: Page? Page. But if you’re not ready for that, there’s music out there. SaraGroves.com, there’s no ‘h’ on Sara and then ArtHouse.com as well. Sorry, ArtHouseNorth.com. Those are the places that explain what we’re doing. Anywhere there’s music, you can find my music. Yeah, I recommend “Add to the Beauty” and “Floodplain” if you’re wanting an introduction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/sara-groves</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/sara-groves</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nik Bärtsch Solo Piano Show</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nik Bärtsch is a world-renowned Swiss composer and pianist. He’s released several albums on ECM Records as well as on his own record label, Ronin Rhythm Records. His music is deep, layered, and hypnotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We brought Nik to &lt;a href=&quot;http://stilwellpianos.com&quot;&gt;Stilwell Pianos&lt;/a&gt; in Mesa, AZ on October 18, 2018 for a special solo piano concert. The footage on this page is from that evening. We are honored and proud to release it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modul_14&quot;&gt;Modul_14&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy this incredible encore performance of &lt;em&gt;Modul_14&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/30peP3O3aMI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/nik-baertsch</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/nik-baertsch</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>California Guitar Trio at the MIM</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;toccata-and-fugue&quot;&gt;Toccata and Fugue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The California Guitar Trio is renowned for their ability to do “circulations,” where they pass notes from one player to another. Their use of circulations is on full display in this amazing three-guitar arrangement of J. S. &lt;em&gt;Bach’s Toccata and Fugue&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AZ_dfQaGZSE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weird-fishes&quot;&gt;Weird Fishes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the California Guitar Trio and the Montreal Guitar Trio performing Radiohead’s &lt;em&gt;Weird Fishes&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a beautiful arrangement with an emotional vocal performance from Glenn Lévesque.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZBt7nn8762c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shining-road&quot;&gt;Shining Road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the California Guitar Trio performing “Shining Road,” a beautiful piece by guitarist Fabio Mittino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iFJ4zxVaZ1Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/california-guitar-trio</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/california-guitar-trio</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
