<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>A resource for musicians to discover new artists, learn weird music techniques, listen to interviews, and share their weird music.
</description>
    <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 22:00:40 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 22:00:40 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using Content Without Attribution</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;okay-this-is-weird&quot;&gt;Okay, this is weird!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit, I never expected to write a piece of content on the site like this, but here we go. First of all, I think everyone can tell from the video content on the site that I’m a pretty laid-back guy and I’m pretty passionate about artists getting recognized first and foremost. I don’t assume everyone else is out there for the same reasons, but when it comes to the kinds of artists I like, I think they usually need all the help they can get in the current economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://drumtalktv.com/portfolio/billy-cobham/&quot;&gt;an interview with Billy Cobham &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on a site called &lt;a href=&quot;http://drumtalktv.com&quot;&gt;Drum Talk TV &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was a cool interview promoting an event coming to Mesa, AZ (where I live), so I got all excited and emailed the site asking to get together because they’re based in Phoenix. How cool, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/172173613?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/172173613&quot;&gt;Exclusive Billy Cobham Interview June 2016&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/drumtalktv&quot;&gt;Drum Talk TV&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, then I find them on Facebook and see what they’re doing. Turns out they’re uploading content produced by other people to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV&quot;&gt;their facebook page &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and getting tons of followers. I thought it was pretty anomalous that a drum channel would get such a rapid and huge following, so I started digging deeper. Turns out they’ve gotten 850,000 FB followers in 3 1/2 years! Amazing, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I look into &lt;a href=&quot;http://drumtalktv.com/video-submission-guidelines/&quot;&gt;their content submission guidelines &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and find the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please send your video via a link from a 3rd-party broadcast platform, such as YouTube or Vimeo, we can download it from there if we use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umm? So, I start looking at their FB posts and they’re usually referencing the artists, but they don’t link to artist pages and they don’t thank anyone for the content. It kinda gives the impression that they’re filming and releasing all this amazing content. But they’re not. They ARE releasing some cool content, but it’s a significant minority of what I’m seeing in their marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also found out that the guy who runs the site, Dan Shinder, runs a program called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smosmasterclass.com&quot;&gt;Social Media on Steroids &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which has pictures of Dan presenting to a group of people at NAMM about growing a business. My immediate thoughts were, “There’s a presentation to artists and companies at a major music industry event about how to use other people’s content to grow your business? You’ve got to be kidding me!” Like he says in the video: “We teach how we’ve done this without advertising and without boosting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/167967812?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;352&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/167967812&quot;&gt;Musicians: Time to Get Results!&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/drumtalktv&quot;&gt;Drum Talk TV&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no social media guru, but I work at a digital marketing company. The way his FB page is running is incongruous with the way the rest of Drum Talk TV is running. 850K FB followers, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DrumTalkTV&quot;&gt;1,200 Twitter followers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/drumtalktv&quot;&gt;no followers/likes on 278 original videos on Vimeo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (despite an interview with Mike Portnoy and his son Max!), which made me feel like artists are getting the short end of the stick while Dan Shinder and Drum Talk TV get “likes, comments, and shares” that help him sell his social marketing program. If you look at the other channels, there’s not much going on, so this clearly isn’t a comprehensive strategy built on meaningful, original content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And look at me! I’m practically advertising for him! (Any publicity is good publicity, right?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus began the following email exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;email-exchange&quot;&gt;Email exchange&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not receive Dan’s permission to post his emails in their entirety, so I’ll summarize them here instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hi Dan,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My name is Anthony and I run a website called Make Weird Music, which features creative, in-depth interviews with musicians around the world. I came across your site tonight and found out you’re in Phoenix! I’m in Mesa. It would be really cool to get together and talk about what we’re doing with these music website projects. Looks like you’ve got a full-time thing going on, but I work at a software development company and do the website in my spare time.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Anyway, if you’re interested in getting together or talking, let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Anthony&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drum Talk TV’s paraphrased response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hi Anthony,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We’re going to send your message to our CEO, Dan Shinder. We’ve grown a lot in 3 1/2 years with millions of people talking about us despite never paying for advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dan’s filming a special with Billy Cobham and will get back to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay. I didn’t ask about their growth, but whatever. Sounds cool! Dan writes back shortly offering to get together and saying he loves what I’m doing. That’s cool. Then I come across a video from their Facebook feed from a friend and look up their content submission guidelines. Here’s what I sent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hi Dan, Candi, and others on the Drum Talk TV team,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks for getting back in touch with me recently about getting together to talk about my Make Weird Music project.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve been looking through your facebook feed noticing that most of your content is not your original content and you even have a statement on your submission guidelines page that states: “Please send your video via a link from a 3rd-party broadcast platform, such as YouTube or Vimeo, we can download it from there if we use it.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As a content creator, I’m curious as to why I’m not seeing the content creators credited in your posts and why you don’t link to them so they can benefit from the hundreds of thousands of followers they’ve generated for you on your page. If you go through the trouble of re-downloading existing content and uploading it as your own, isn’t the effort to attribute the source (a basic journalistic practice) a simple, small additional thing to do?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Even the musicians performing in these videos don’t get links to their pages. If the intent is to promote these artists, why not give your followers a chance to follow the artists themselves?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I was looking forward to meeting with Dan to talk about our mutual music projects, but I find this stance on content attribution pretty discouraging and am personally concerned that my content may get repurposed by your channel without attribution.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For example, here is a post you created today: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1093114114100585/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1093114114100585/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And here is the original content creator’s video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RuOxN2lx9HA&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RuOxN2lx9HA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Is there a particular reason you don’t link to the original content creator’s facebook page? Or at least to their youtube channel? These links took me seconds to find and it’s even easier when other people send you to the 3rd party page so you can download and upload their content as your own.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And in case this might seem like a one-time occurrence, here are some other links to videos of other people’s content that have been repurposed for your own use within the past 24 hours:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Your” video, posted today: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1101211763290820/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1101211763290820/&lt;/a&gt;
Original source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WbRoQB1OAyY&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WbRoQB1OAyY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Your” video, posted yesterday: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1096576833754313/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1096576833754313/&lt;/a&gt;
Original source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hJ7lkGhfw9c&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hJ7lkGhfw9c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Your” video, posted yesterday: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1090323964379600/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/DrumTalkTV/videos/1090323964379600/&lt;/a&gt;
Original source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3rqZFh8AXgI&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3rqZFh8AXgI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The music industry is having a hard enough time surviving as it is because of software companies selling the works of artists at slices of pennies apiece. Why would someone who consults musicians and companies at NAMM be operating in this fashion? What if I were to take Dan’s original work with Billy Cobham and upload it to my channel calling it my own? Would you consider it fair use? Would it be ethical?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Going with the best assumption that there is no ill will to take other people’s content, I would love to see a change in behavior on Drum Talk TV’s channel with proper adherence to accepted journalistic ethical practices: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source_(journalism)&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source_(journalism)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have already talked to a couple friends about this and they’re unfollowing your channel immediately. This isn’t a threat, just a reality that there are people who don’t want to support companies that don’t properly attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also included a screenshot from a friend’s FB post where this person said he was unfollowing them and had always wondered why the video quality was so low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this was entirely uncalled for. I don’t know. I was super passionate/heated at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan wrote back shortly and I’m paraphrasing here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Anthony,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more here than meets the eye and I’d rather talk in person.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;20% of our Facebook content is our original content, 50% of the rest of it is sent to us and we post as is. 100% of what you see on the website is original.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We use Facebook to curate content. If we didn’t do it this way, a small piece of our existing audience would see the content and we’d be doing very little for the artists. By posting like this, we give artists significant exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;People thank us all the time for the free exposure we provide and it leads to all sorts of great opportunities for them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We are a media company and we give proper credit in our posts. Look at our numbers! The major news networks rarely credit their sources, but we do.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’m available to chat with you some time.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Our methods work in and out of the music industry, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks for your prompt response. I appreciate it and I get your perspective. You are making the most of the way the Facebook algorithm works today, which is understandable, but I cannot agree ethically to your argument. I am not a confrontational person and I don’t like going in this direction, and I can’t convince myself to do otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I would love to see this question of ethics posted on your Facebook page. Perhaps asking your 800K followers whether they agree with your submission guidelines statement of downloading 3rd party content as part of “curation” as a “News, Publishing, and Media” company. Ask some of the prominent artists you represent whether they appreciate your downloading of their content, re-publishing it without attribution (or express permission?), and share some of the answers (positive and negative) you receive.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Whatever your justification is, I can tell you that many musicians I know, as well as myself, are offended at the idea that you are doing us a favor by using our content on your page as “promotion” of our work. You know as well as I do (I work for one of the valley’s largest digital marketing firms and we run a social media analytics platform, which gives us plenty of insight into this stuff) that most people don’t follow up the way you’re describing. They largely do not copy and paste artist names (sometimes misspelled, “Liberty DeVito” [sic]) into a search field to find their pages and follow those artists. They also largely do not click links to non-Facebook websites to see all your original content.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This can be evidenced by the fact that a majority (~75%) of your 100 YouTube videos have fewer than 2000 views and the rest (save 3) also have relatively low view count and your Vimeo collection of 278 original videos (that’s a HUGE amount of work!!) has 2 followers, 3 likes, and no discernible comments. There’s no significant following on Twitter either and little promotion of your original content. I don’t say this to get into a numbers war, nor to be competitive, but it’s clear where the priorities are for you and your team when looking at your various marketing channels. And your touting of social media capabilities as a consultant is awkwardly unbalanced between these channels.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The original work you do is great, but that is hardly touted on your FB channel. I really enjoyed a couple of your interviews and that’s what attracted me to your work. You’re enthusiastic, you appreciate and love the artists, and you probably have the same purpose I do: to help and promote the work of real artists.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’m happy to meet/talk and discuss this, but you are unlikely to convince me that you’re putting equal effort into promoting the work of others when someone ELSE has to mention Row-Loff in a comment on their video repurposed on your channel and they don’t even thank you for it. Row-Loff got 8 new likes from your video with 1,250 shares, by the way. Sounds like a great opportunity was somehow missed by them!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Your audience is so large at this point, why manipulate the game anymore? Why not link directly to the artists? Or do so in a comment (which doesn’t seem to affect reach)? Or do a separate post? Or post your original content with that artist and link to THAT in the comment? You have so much great content, why not promote that? And now that you have a team, why don’t you pay for any promotion? Why tout that you’ve grown your audience to that size for free when it’s largely based on the content of others?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Lastly, do you mind if I publicly post this exchange so I can solicit the thoughts of my following across all my channels? I’d love to get their thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Anthony&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I followed up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Also, thanks for your patience. You didn’t ask for my ranting and maybe you don’t deserve a letter of it. This is a hot button item for me and I want to make sure the artists you and I BOTH love get as much opportunity as possible without anything else getting in their way. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no “argument.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-thoughts&quot;&gt;Your thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think? Am I out of line? Was I arrogant and presumptuous? Is he providing proper attribution by saying who was performing without linking the viewer anywhere or naming the author of the video?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a part of me that regrets calling him out and there’s a part of me that’s proud to stand up for artists. I looked up several of the artists Drum Talk TV mentioned in the past few days and NONE of them have seen an uptick in FB followers. Literally, one of the posts today was shared over 1,200 times and netted the content producer 8 new followers. Eight. Fewer than ten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan seems like a nice guy and I think we have a lot of overlapping tastes. It probably would have been real cool to collaborate with him, but I blew that chance. It’s never too late and I still stand behind my feelings, even though I may have acted inappropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally am not a person looking to explicitly seek feedback on MWM as it’s just something I do for the artists and my own creative satisfaction that other people seem to enjoy. Nevertheless, I’d love to get your feedback if you happened to read through my blathering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this played out, I had a sense of what Robert Fripp was so upset about over the years in which he was arguing with streaming services and record labels that hadn’t paid out royalties and were breaching distribution contracts. Sometimes it feels like the people who work the hardest can’t win. The best strategy in my mind is to have done nothing, but sometimes I can’t bite my tongue when I see something that seems so unethical from a person in my neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept thinking about him taking my &lt;a href=&quot;/concert/michael-manring&quot;&gt;Michael Manring house concert&lt;/a&gt;, downloading the 20-minute clip of Michael and Andy West playing, distributing it through some channel, and me never finding out about it. All the work I put into it. All the money we put into it. All the lighting Michael Nitro and his team put into it. Taken by a Facebook channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/2011/07/attribution_and_credit&quot;&gt;here’s an article &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that nicely describes my view on attribution. Particularly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Linking is indeed key. You get a story from somewhere else, you link to the original when you post about it. That’s the first rule of web attribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife says this happens all the time in the food blogging industry. My wife is very careful to attribute &lt;a href=&quot;http://alovelettertofood.com&quot;&gt;on her site &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but she says sees famous food bloggers use the same recipe from somewhere else and do something as simple as adding dried parsley to the top of the food, but it’s the same exact recipe she’s seen elsewhere and the recipe gets no attribution. (Unlike Drum Talk TV, however, these food bloggers don’t even mention that the recipe came from the mind of another person.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But hey, great exposure, right? All I know is I’d better be careful setting up and recording a house concert with a famous drummer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;“Exposure Bucks” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whiskeyfoxxtrot&quot;&gt;@whiskeyfoxxtrot&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cottonbureau&quot;&gt;@cottonbureau&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/nGUrgRrcOL&quot;&gt;https://t.co/nGUrgRrcOL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Frustrated dealing with this problem tonight...&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/762872620723216384&quot;&gt;August 9, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/repurposing-content</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/repurposing-content</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Morgan Agren</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/s8cqnlbH2jM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/markus-reuter.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/markus-reuter.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager, I bought a copy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zappa%27s_Universe&quot;&gt;Zappa’s Universe&lt;/a&gt; on VHS in my obsession to buy everything I could with an appearance from &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt;. I was astounded at the incredible drumming on the video. I saw Morgan’s name credited as the drummer and talked to my super-musical friend Todd in Chicago via America Online about him. He told me about Morgan’s involvement with a blind Swedish keyboard player named Mats Oberg and their duo band Mats/Morgan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the late 1990s, I’ve loosely followed Morgan’s career and became more aware when my friend &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/carl-king&quot;&gt;Carl King&lt;/a&gt; made a documentary about Morgan called &lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.carlkingdom.com/products/conundrum_dvd&quot;&gt;Morgan Agren’s Conundrum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/akOFZb4GpCY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.morganagren.com&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Morgan Agren is? Check out his website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in late June 2016, I wrote to Morgan asking if he’d ever do an interview. He got back to me within two weeks and we got things scheduled pretty quickly. He’s such a nice, down-to-earth guy and it was pretty easy to get things going. I hope you enjoy our interview! It was a real pleasure for me to talk with such a creative genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with Morgan Agren who has joined us all the way from Sweden. Morgan, thank you very much for joining us. Let’s just get started. The purpose of the site is to get people to learn about new musicians and new kinds of music. Could you introduce yourself and tell us about your musical history and tell us about why people might know who you are as a musician?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Morgan: Yeah. Thanks for calling me, by the way. I’m happy to be here. I think I heard about your site or your activities quite recently, actually, and then I found an email from you in this weird hidden folder in Facebook Messenger and, as you might know, if you’re not friends with the people you get a message from, it goes into this kind of hidden folder. Sometimes I check this folder because, who knows? And then I found you there just a few weeks after I heard some snippets from an interview you did with… Anthony Levin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, Markus Reuter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Oh, sorry! Ben Levin, I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, Ben Levin! Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yes, Ben Levin from Bent Knee. So, that’s where I noticed your Make Weird Music thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: So yeah, my name is Morgan and I am a drummer, musician, composer living in Stockholm, outside of Stockholm in Sweden. I just turned 49 and, not 50 yet but getting there. I started to play at age 4 or 5 or something on the drums and met my musical partner at age 14 and he was 10. I met Mats Oberg, who is my life-long musical partner and that’s where it started for me, I think. Before that, my father was in a Swedish so-called dance band and they were my first idols. That’s where it really started because they were a big influence on me. When I went to school, you get a pen and paper and write whatever you want and I wrote a lot about them, his band, about their tubas… So there’s hundreds of pages about my dad’s band. Obviously they were my first idols and my first time on stage was with them one day. They had me come up on stage to play when I was 7. So that was my premiere and that’s where it kind of started. What else? I started a record company in 1996 and released 15, 20 albums or something and then I moved onto a label called Cuneiform because it was too much work that didn’t have too much to do with music. You know, paperwork and all that stuff. It was a good period still because it was a good experience to make your own albums and release them and try to get them out. I released my own albums on this label, but I also released projects with other friends like my brother, Frederik [Thordendal] from Meshuggah–he did his solo album, which is probably the most, maybe not most, but when it comes to releases, that’s probably the one that’s most famous. His album Sol Niger Within. I released that in 1997 and I did some projects with Denny Walley, former guitarist from Frank Zappa and Tom Waits. And then I played with Frank [Zappa], of course. Some people know me from that. I played with Frank Zappa when I was 20 the first time and then he invited me to the US later on, a few years before he passed away. I used to be a member of a Swedish group called Flesh Quartet and, yeah, that’s a little bit on my background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I found out about you through Zappa’s Universe. I bought the VHS copy of the concert and I said, “Who’s the keyboard player and who’s that drummer?” because you guys weren’t a part of the standard Zappa touring band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And then I found out about Mats/Morgan and it’s just unbelievable music. So, can you tell us about–you mentioned a musical partner and in the interviews I’ve done so far on the site, no one’s really mentioned having a musical partner. You guys have been making music since you were kids together, so can you tell us about how that started and where it’s gone and what’s special about Mats that makes you guys so close musically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah. And the thing about that is this year we actually are going to have our 35-year anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: It’s kind of unreal how much time we actually have had together. I see it truly as a gift because–I remember when I met Mats. I was 14 and he was 10 and I knew already by then that this is such a nice meeting. I could tell from the first moment that this is–“Wow, this can really be good and this already is good.” Now, 35 years later, you can look back at what happened from another perspective. At that time, I was happy about it, of course, and I was excited and everything. But now, 35 years later, you look at these years in a more humble way or a thankful way or something because meetings like these don’t happen often. I put more value on the fact that I met him now than at the time when we played. How that happened was I received a phone call from a lady in my hometown and she–actually, this is coincidence, but I can try to–[holds up a photo of Mats, Morgan, and a woman between them] can you see this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, I can see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: The woman there in the middle–this picture was taken in 2002, maybe? This lady is actually the lady who called me that day in 1981. She called me–somebody called me–but she called me and said, “Hello, my name is blah-blahblah and I’m running a little music cafe outside Umea,” me and Mats’ hometown, “and I’m going to have this guy call you named Mats Oberg who plays piano and he’s gonna call you and play some 15-20 minutes there. I read about you in a local magazine and I just had a sense that you and he would fit together.” That’s what she told me and at this moment, I didn’t know anything about Mats. The only thing I knew was that I heard while being on vacation with my family once was that I was listening to the radio and the guy was super young that talked on the radio and played fantastic music. You know, music that never gets played on the radio and the guy–probably at the time, maybe 9–playing music on the radio. That I heard on the radio and I started to realize that maybe I heard this guy on the radio once, but other than that I didn’t know anything about him. But I got the request to come out to this place and play drums with him and so I did and I was happy to get this request. I went there and we met probably 2 hours before the concert and we were supposed to play 15-20 minutes. So we met on the venue, shook hands, and he looked like he was 7 or 8, even though he was 10, he looked really tiny. We started to discuss what we could possibly play, but it has to be covers now because we just met and we’re going to be on stage in 2 hours. So he started to ask me, “Do you know this and this and this and this band?” So he asked me, “Do you know The Beatles?” And the only song I knew by them at the time that I could possibly play without rehearsing was &lt;em&gt;Help!&lt;/em&gt; so I said, “Okay, I know &lt;em&gt;Help!&lt;/em&gt;” And then, of course, whatever I said, he knew it. That was the crazy thing. “Do you know it?” “Yes, I know it.” “Okay, do you know Stevie Wonder?” he continues. And then for some reason, I had a friend whose older brother just bought &lt;em&gt;Hotter Than July&lt;/em&gt; and when I was at his house, he played that album, so I remembered the first track, &lt;em&gt;Master Blaster&lt;/em&gt;, and I told Mats, “I know this song. This reggae type of &lt;em&gt;Master Blaster&lt;/em&gt; maybe. Do you know it?” “Yeah, I know it,” he says. Okay, so now we had two songs, so we need at least one more, so he asked me, “Do you know Frank Zappa?” and of course, &lt;em&gt;Bobby Brown&lt;/em&gt; was the only one I knew. He knew that one, too, of course, so then we had three songs and we had a short little sound check and then we went on stage and just played. Super tiny little house, like a cabin, I’d say with 10-15 people in the audience. The room would take maybe 30 people and that would be fully packed. I remember almost–I really remember clearly that I was totally amazed by the fact that–I mean, I was doing a concert, but at the same time, I was in the audience because I was also watching him play in disbelief. He was standing up with his electric grand and he played–the electric grand was almost to his chin and then he played incredibly and he sang in almost perfect–the language was good, but his mother didn’t let him sing the ugly words in &lt;em&gt;Bobby Brown&lt;/em&gt;, so he left those out, but other than that he was singing and playing in an incredible way. I remember also after the concert–both of our parents were there. My dad and his dad were there because they were driving us with our car to the venue. After, we met backstage and both our parents were really touched from having seen their kids do that together with 2 hours–almost no preparation at all. I think my dad, what I could see, was almost crying because of what he saw. Mats’ father was also really–he started to say to me, “Maybe you could do this again. We have drums in the basement and,” blah blah blah blah blah. He really wanted–he saw more possibility that Mats found a friend who liked the same music as he did. So that was basically how we met and this photograph that I showed you, this happened in 2002. This lady called me up again and I hadn’t spoken with her since 1981, but she called me and asked me, “Is this the number of Morgan Agren?” I said, “Yeah, it’s me.” “So, yes, my name is and I live here and there and I guess you remember the first time you played with Mats in that cafe.” And I go, “Yeah.” “The girl who called you there–that was me.” And I got the chills because I was wondering so many times, “Who was this lady that called me out of the blue having this idea of me and Mats getting together?” So, next time we went to our hometown, we set up a meeting with her and we went over to her house to say hello and have a cup of coffee and take some photos. So that’s the very first time and this was in November 1981. After that, me and Mats, we met if not on a weekly basis, which was the most case. Sometimes maybe it went 2 or 3 weeks, but it was quite regularly for the next 35 years, more or less. I have never been out of contact with Mats more than a few weeks since then. We have been doing a lot of other things. We play all the time, but sometimes we both play with other acts. This is not the only thing we do, but we have played all the way since then. We’ve toured all over the world and played with a lot of our teenage idols and whatever. It was a really good meeting and I’m really happy for that, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: One thing you didn’t mention is that he’s blind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yes, he’s blind. I would have been equally amazed about what he did when we did this first gig. But, the fact that he’s blind makes everything even more amazing. He’s born blind and I think that a guy like him that’s born with a thing like this–the focus in life gets only–his thing in life is music. Music and food. That’s what he enjoys. He doesn’t care about too many other things and that’s how we developed this ability. This happened very early, a long time before I met him, because I know for sure that he was listening to–when he was 2 or 3 years old, he was listening to the typical lullaby music as all the other kids at the same time as he was listening to Mahivishnu Orchestra because that he actually did when he was 3 or 4 years old. So, a little bit Miles [Davis], a little bit Mahivishnu, and a little bit of lullabies. He went back and forth between really different music and “diaper music,” if I may say so. I know some stories from his childhood that he was really–I think his parents gave him some kind of downer. He had to eat something that took his energy down because he was listening to music for, I think maybe 10 hours straight without any breaks. He got hyper and he was scratching vinyls, listening to it backwards–everything was just about sound, sound, sound, sound. I know that for instance when he was 7, he sort of forced his parents to buy the latest Earth, Wind, &amp;amp; Fire album. Otherwise, he had a stair at home and he went to the end of the stairs and stood on the edge and said, “If you don’t buy the latest album, I’ll jump.” Stuff like that because he was really–“I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want the last Earth, Wind, &amp;amp; Fire. Get it for me otherwise I jump.” Stuff like that. Really into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Wow, that’s astonishing. Did you guys study together musically? Did you study music? Any formal music education or is everything just through self-learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I would say self-learning although we went to the same high school in Stockholm, but we started so early and for me, everything I do comes from me listening to albums and just listening and being inspired. I got so much inspiration from listening to all these albums at an early age. Everything was on these albums. I didn’t really have any questions because everything was there and the “only problem” was to do it yourself. That’s something you have to develop, of course. But I think that as soon as you hear something and as soon as you really feel that “this is really what I like, this is really what I want to do, I don’t want to do that, but I want to do this,” and as soon as you know and feel that in a way, I think you’re halfway because then it’s about personality in the music and the whole spirit and everything because the music is like a mirror of yourself. So when you get this inspiration and you realize that–for instance, when I heard a few of those albums that really opened up a new universe for me was an album called &lt;em&gt;Road Games&lt;/em&gt; by Allan Holdsworth. All these chords and the harmonies, besides him being a fantastic guitarist, but the music, the compositions took me just somewhere else, where I wanted to be. This was just, “I’m home. This is really what I like.” If I hadn’t run into an album like that at age 14 or something like that, maybe 15… I don’t know. That album and many others, of course, but those albums were really important for me in not only as a musician playing drums trying to compose, but also as an individual. In a spiritual way. It was really important. Another album that I was listening to on and on was Return to Forever &lt;em&gt;Romantic Warrior&lt;/em&gt; and the first album by UK. Bill Bruford’s &lt;em&gt;One of a Kind&lt;/em&gt;, Brecker Brothers’ &lt;em&gt;Heavy Metal Bebop&lt;/em&gt;… There are many, but those albums just kept going on and on and on and on and on. When you have that, going to a school–I know that I started so early so I’m aware of the fact that it was quite easy for me to play because I started early. I don’t say that school would be useless or anything, but for me the inspiration and the energy I got from the albums was worth more than any drum book in the world or any school. The schools were good too because I met nice people and even had some good teachers that inspired me. But, yeah, so me and Mats, we don’t read music. I’m a lousy reader and Mats, obviously, is blind so he doesn’t read it. But, we just listen and learn from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How would you describe the music you two make?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Well, it’s–23:25&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/morgan-agren/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/morgan-agren/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discover MoonJune Records</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-little-about-moonjune-records&quot;&gt;A LITTLE ABOUT MoonJune Records&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I saw something musically interesting on Facebook, I’d see the name Leonardo MoonJune Pavkovic. We were already “friends” on Facebook, but had never interacted. We had enough mutual friends that it made sense and we were commenting on a lot of the same posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Months later, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/markus-reuter&quot;&gt;Markus Reuter&lt;/a&gt;’s double-CD sampler, &lt;a href=&quot;https://markus-reuter-moonjune.bandcamp.com/album/fool-of-music-compilation-free-download&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fool of Music&lt;/em&gt; was available for free &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://moonjunerecords.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;MoonJune’s BandCamp site &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to do a little research and see what that was all about. It was pretty astounding. On the MoonJune website was a collection of names I’d never seen before playing astonishing music at extremely generous prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leonardo was very friendly and fast to respond to my Facebook messages requesting an interview. In fact, he was ready to do an interview at 9AM the next morning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the video of the interview with Leonardo Pavkovic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nx_8gLAlFiQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leonardos-recommendations&quot;&gt;Leonardo’s Recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the recommendations Leonardo made from his MoonJune catalog to get you started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moonjune.com/mjr_web_2013/catalog_mjr/075_DWIKI-DHARMAWAN_So-Far-So-Close_MJR075/&quot;&gt;Dwiki Dharmawan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moonjune.com/mjr_web_2013/catalog_mjr/068_simakDialog_Live-at-Orion_MJR068/&quot;&gt;simakDialog’s &lt;em&gt;Live at Orion&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moonjune.com/mjr_web_2013/catalog_mjr/063_DEWA-BUDJANA_Surya-Namaskar_MJR063/&quot;&gt;Dewa Budjana &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll also add &lt;a href=&quot;https://markus-reuter-moonjune.bandcamp.com/album/fool-of-music-compilation-free-download&quot;&gt;Markus Reuter’s &lt;em&gt;Fool of Music&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; since it’s free and fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;And TONS of music is available for free at &lt;a href=&quot;https://moonjunerecords.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MoonJune’s BandCamp site&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with Leonardo Pavkovic from MoonJune Records based in New York City. Leonardo, thanks so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Leonardo: Hi Anthony, thank you very much for inviting me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Can you tell me who you are and what you do and give us a brief introduction to MoonJune Records?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: I’ve been running MoonJune Records and management since 2001. I am based in New York City and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I started the record label by accident with the intent to help a couple of friends.&lt;/span&gt; I really didn’t know what I was doing except that I was helping my friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then a couple of years later, because I started managing the band called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soft_Machine&quot;&gt;Soft Machine Legacy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is the continuation of Soft Works that is sort of Soft Machine but became Soft Works in 2001 with &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_Holdsworth&quot;&gt;Allan Holdsworth &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elton_Dean&quot;&gt;Elton Dean &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Hopper&quot;&gt;Hugh Hopper &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Marshall_(drummer)&quot;&gt;John Marshall &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–the band then became Soft Machine Legacy with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Etheridge&quot;&gt;John Etheridge &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; coming in the band after Allan Holdsworth, who for whatever reason wasn’t able to continue with the band. Then I started booking this band in Europe and they needed a new album because we had a great album of Soft Works with Allan, but they didn’t do anything with John Etheridge in the new band, but they just changed the name of the band from Soft Works to Soft Machine Legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FpYXWn0cVBs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then in 2005, I actually started being a label even though I started in 2001, but I believe that in 2004–after 3 years–I really decided that this is what I should do. And again, my label started with the idea just to help my friends in a couple of bands I was involved with. And that’s what I’ve done for 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So far, I have 80 releases to my label and I also do management and booking. I work with a lot of artists not necessarily on my label. I book maybe about 3 dozen artists on a non-exclusive basis all around the world, mostly in Asia, Latin America, some in Europe and USA. I do some other things, but that’s basically what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I know it’s very difficult nowadays to run a record label. Do you have a very dedicated fan base? Is it an act of love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: Yes, I have to underline something. When I started my label, my first releases were releases from bands that had a nice cult following. Two Italian progressive rock bands, &lt;a href=&quot;https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finisterre_(gruppo_musicale)&quot;&gt;Finisterre &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DFA_(Italian_rock_band)&quot;&gt;D.F.A. &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and my old friend, the legendary Elton Dean. Somehow I was able to get some decent industry success in a niche market with those albums. Then I released a tribute to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaco_Pastorius&quot;&gt;Jaco Pastorius &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; helping a friend of mine who produced that album and then I started releasing albums by Soft Machine Legacy, Elton Dean and Hugh Hopper, and Italian progressive rock legend &lt;a href=&quot;https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arti_e_Mestieri&quot;&gt;Arti &amp;amp; Mestieri &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phil_Miller&quot;&gt;Phil Miller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RkrQnE3_N_0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In the beginning with the first 15 or 16 releases, I had albums that were kind of selling. Of course we’re not talking about huge sales, we’re talking about decent sales. Then I started releasing albums of literally-unknown bands from Indonesia, Spain, Italy, Canada, Brazil, Japan, and then many things have changed in the last 10 years in the recording business, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t make a living from my label. It’s impossible.&lt;/span&gt; I make a living from other things, but I decided that I have to keep alive my label because it’s something that I like and, as I mentioned before, the label is based on music of my friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t sign artists. There is no such thing where you’d send me a demo and I’d consider it and say, “Okay, I will sign you and I’ll give you a contract.” I don’t do that. I’m a completely unusual label, and again, I only work and release albums of my friends.&lt;/span&gt; We become friends for whatever magic reason. There is music happening and we record some albums and we say, “Okay, let’s release this album.” I’m very unusual and I’m happy to be that way because it doesn’t restrict me to obey certain rules of the music business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Especially lately with &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/markus-reuter&quot;&gt;Markus Reuter&lt;/a&gt;, who became a very close friend of mine. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We have a very unusual way of promoting the music, which I started about 6 or 7 years ago offering free music through downloads and free music through downloads means reaching more people and, actually, we can make some money offering free music because people are really generous. They download it for free and making donations.&lt;/span&gt; We’re collecting more and more funds and we’re building a very solid fanbase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XqTz4M5k2FQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Of course, I have a lot of fans of Soft Machine, John Etheridge, Allan Holdsworth. These are legends. And now, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stick_Men_(prog_band)&quot;&gt;Stick Men &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m just building the niche audience. I like to interact directly with fans and my email list is about 15,000 people that I collected in the last 15 years, which is through my mail-order company and collecting emails on the live shows of Soft Machine Legacy and Allan Holdsworth and other bands and simply people signing up for my newsletter and offering those free downloads and people are sending their contributions as they’re downloading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that’s how I build my niche reach. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Of course, I have national and international distribution, but in today’s age, that really doesn’t mean anything because there are no more stores. It’s very hard, but as I said, I don’t do this for a living. I’m just doing this because I love the music and they’re my friends and we are doing this together.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, first of all, thank you so much for what you do. It’s awesome to see someone so passionate doing what you’re doing. It’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not just passion. It’s my duty.&lt;/span&gt; When my friend Elton Dean gave me a live tape of his tour with English guitar player &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Hewins&quot;&gt;Mark Hewins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2000 when he visited New York and I knew Elton since the mid 1980s. I met him in Italy and he toured Italy very often and we became friends. We were friends since 1986. When he offered me this tape and when I met a couple other Italian bands that became my fans, I said, “Okay, this is what I have to do.” They asked me for help and I said, “Okay, I’ll release these albums and I’ll see what I can do for you in the USA.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YBcSv6OhjRY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s how it started and it’s more than passion. It’s also duty to help friends. We are all helping each other. Of course, we are living in very troubled times, not just in terms of the music business, but in general. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Music is something that can unify people and make us happy and enjoy what we do. I think that’s something that will continue.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s why I am saying, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;no matter how the music business may be bad in the future, I’m the record label that will never ever fail or never go bankrupt because I don’t follow any rules that normally record labels are following. That’s why I will always exist.&lt;/span&gt; I might start releasing less albums, but I’ll be always there because of my very, very unusual way of promoting and distributing and selling this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: It’s something that I learned. It’s not something that I said 15 years ago and envisioned. I decided 15 years ago I thought it would be something else, but this is something I have learned because I believe the way of promoting independent music from now is just making partnerships with musicians. We are doing it together. Of course &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we know that from some of this music we cannot be rich, we cannot make any living. But collectively if we contribute to the cause, something will happen.&lt;/span&gt; We don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Are you a musician yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: No, I’m not a musician. My grandmother was an opera singer. She bought me a guitar when I was 10 years old and she wanted me to become a musician because she was a musician. I learned a lot of music from her, especially classical music. But after 1 or 1 1/2 years, I resisted. I was 12 years old. I thought I had some other interests. I never played an instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also, I’ve never driven a car in my life. I’m very unusual. I’ve been married 23 years and I don’t have a ring. I just feel free. Once they asked Frank Zappa what kind of music he liked, he said, “I don’t know what I like because I have my own music. I don’t have time to listen to other music.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But because I’m not a musician, it gives me complete and total freedom.&lt;/span&gt; First of all, to listen a lot to music. Musicians that are performing all over again, playing the same music every night, the same kind of music, and they’re rehearsing, and sound-checking, and performing gigs… I use that time to listen to more and more different music. And the fact that I’m a musician gives me opportunity to listen to music in a very neutral way. I’m not paying attention to technique, like if this guy is playing in this-and-that way, but just enjoying the music. For me, the music comes first and then technical abilities and everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s great. So, what are your top 3 or 5 records that you’d recommend from your label for people who are looking to expand their musical horizons?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ROg6uEaPkzI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: My upcoming record that I’m announcing today, one track, and announcing next week an album that will come out in late September, is a double album of &lt;a href=&quot;https://id.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwiki_Dharmawan&quot;&gt;Dwiki Dharmawan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an Indonesian piano player. On this double album he’s playing only acoustic piano. That’s probably one of the highlights of my label because it’s something very special. Dwiki Dharmawan is one of the nationally most well-known musicians in Indonesia and a very good friend of mine for 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We recorded this album in London last year and we are finally releasing it with some of the top musicians, my favorite musicians in the world, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Wingfield&quot;&gt;Mark Wingfield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilad_Atzmon&quot;&gt;Gilad Atzmon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamelan_jegog&quot;&gt;Gamelon Jess Jegog &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meiergroup.com/meiergroup/index.html&quot;&gt;Nicholas Meier &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That’s an upcoming release that I will promote starting today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Regarding the older catalog, I’ll also mention a couple other Indonesian artists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tohpati&quot;&gt;simakDialog &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; double live album recorded in Baltimore on the first USA tour a few years ago called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moonjune.com/mjr_web_2013/catalog_mjr/068_simakDialog_Live-at-Orion_MJR068/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Live at Orion&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s one of my favorite live albums in the past 20 years, not just on my label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X0tK3hDiA3c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Another Indonesian guitar player, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dewa_Budjana&quot;&gt;Dewa Budjana &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. His album with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vinnie_Colaiuta&quot;&gt;Vinnie Colaiuta &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy_Johnson_(bassist)&quot;&gt;Jimmy Johnson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That’s one of the highlights of my label. And then, I’ll also recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wrong_Object&quot;&gt;The Wrong Object &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; band from Belgium led by a friend of mine, Belgian guitar player &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_Delville&quot;&gt;Michel Delville &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is kind of–if you like &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt;, Soft Machine, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magma_(band)&quot;&gt;Magma &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terje_Rypdal&quot;&gt;Terje Rypdal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that’s kind of some of my favorite musicians. It’s very great experimental jazz rock. There are many albums. I have 80 albums, but I have so many albums that if I start mentioning albums, I’ll have to mention probably all 80 of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And the new Stick Men record?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: Stick Men is not really a MoonJune album. It’s kind of a MoonJune album. It’s not 100% MoonJune because it started doing something very unusual. We released it by ourselves. It only came out officially in Japan. It’s an album that we’re only selling at our shows and on BandCamp. It’s a sort of MoonJune because I’m involved with the band, I’m their exclusive booking representative. It’s almost MoonJune records, but it’s not 100% MoonJune. Of course, it’s one of my favorite live albums and it’s simply amazing, especially–it’s very special because my old friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Cross_(musician)&quot;&gt;David Cross &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A couple of these Stick Men guys will be on my label. I will be releasing the upcoming new studio album of Markus Reuter in January with members of the Swiss avant garde band, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonar_(band)&quot;&gt;Sonar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is already on a couple of albums that I’ll be releasing very soon on the new Dewa Budjana album, Indonesian guitar player. He plays upright bass and we’re having a recording session this Sunday in the Woodstock area with a Serbian guitar player on my label who lives in Barcelona, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moonjune.com/mjr_web_2013/catalog_mjr/058_DUSAN-JEVTOVIC_Am-I-Walking-Wrong_MJR058/&quot;&gt;Dusan Jevtovic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Spanish Catalan drummer &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moonjune.com/mjr_web_2013/catalog_mjr/062_XAVI-REIJA_Resolution_MJR062/&quot;&gt;Xavi Rejia &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That’s Xavi’s album with Markus Reuter as a special guest, which means that all these Stick Men musicians are gradually moving to the MoonJune area first as session musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7LtsfDjOS2w?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In the case of Markus Reuter, I’ll be releasing his new studio album, and he’s also in a collective improvisational band with English guitar player Mark Wingfield and two Israeli guys based in London, bass player &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutjazz.com/yaron-stavi-profoundly-bassist-yaron-stavi-by-sammy-stein.php&quot;&gt;Yaron Stavi &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and drummer &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asaf_Sirkis&quot;&gt;Asaf Sirkis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that album will come out in November. That’s another album that I will consider one of the highlights of my label in the last 15 years because, first of all, features some of my favorite musicians on planet Earth: Markus, Mark, Yaron Stavi, Asaf Sirkis Some of my favorite musicians. The music is just completely and totally improvised music, but it’s very melodic and very groovy and very jammy and I think it’ll blow everybody’s minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Excellent. Thank you so much for your time. I really appreciate it and I really appreciate what you do. Thank you for making Fool of Music a free download. I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: Thank you very much for inviting me. Hope to talk to you soon. I’ll see you in January, I suppose, in Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s right. For the Stick Men show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: Last time I was in Phoenix was 20 years ago. Looking forward to coming back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: January’s a great time to come. Now [August] is not a great time to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;L: Okay, thank you Anthony. Talk to you soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Bye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moonjune-records/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moonjune-records/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture, Ep. 2</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-2-round-and-sharp-picks&quot;&gt;Episode 2: Round (and Sharp) Picks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgmlive.com/diaries.htm?entry=3463&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp paid me a compliment in his online diary&lt;/a&gt; in response to videos and blog posts I’d written at that time about playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. He said, “Mr. Garone’s work on this is honourable, and has my respect.” This sentence motivated me for many years to continue pursuing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, he made a recommendation that, for some reason, took me years to understand: use a sharp pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fracture/id978457922?i=978458012&quot;&gt;Purchase King Crimson’s &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.nexternal.com/dgm/starless-and-bible-black-c228.aspx&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Robert Fripp’s website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the video to accompany this episode of &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/p3vYVtplGi8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-failure-to-fracture&quot;&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a video series I’ve put together about all the things that have stood in the way of my successfully playing the song &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; despite years and years of study, practice, writing, and making videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-list&quot;&gt;Episode List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Episode 0: Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/stress&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Tension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/picks&quot;&gt;Episode 2: Picking Picks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problems-with-round-picks&quot;&gt;The Problems with Round Picks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; with a round pick is like slicing a ripe tomato with a butterknife. (What?!) In my experience, round picks are great for all sorts of players, but for &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, they’re just not the right tool for the job. Here are my thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Round picks are more difficult to get a clear, consistent attack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They need to be nearly parallel to the string for every stroke to maximize sound&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;’s incessant string skipping makes clear tone quite difficult with a round pick&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Round picks can “slide” across strings instead of connecting me with the notes and strings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I feel like I’m not in control of my playing with round picks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are very personal reasons, but watch the video and you’ll get a sense of the tonal differences between the round and sharp picks. I play the moto perpetuo with both round and sharp picks, alternating between the two so you can get a sense of how the picks make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;picks-picks-picks&quot;&gt;Picks, Picks, Picks!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Fripp recommended use of a sharp pick, he wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The recommended pick is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guitarcraftguitars.com/picks.html&quot;&gt;a triangular Guitar Craft pick&lt;/a&gt;, of which there is a small production line, handmade in Japan by Mr. Hiroshi Iketani. If a Dunlop Tortex is the only choice, I would use the Tortex Sharp &amp;amp; consider that life was hard, cruel &amp;amp; unfair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I had no access to the triangular Guitar Craft pick at the time, I bought &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Dunlop-412P1-0-Tortex%C2%AE-Sharp-Players/dp/B000PTRJW8&quot;&gt;Dunlop Tortex Sharps&lt;/a&gt; and it made a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; difference in tone and accuracy. (I prefer the yellow .73mm ones.) Here’s what I love about them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They make your strings sound &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; brighter and more clear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick noise is severely reduced&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They’re slightly longer than a normal pick, so there’s more to grip&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduces accidental string muting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sounds much more like Fripp!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a normal pick makes it harder to play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; for the reasons I just listed. Normal picks don’t have the clear tone of a sharp pick. They’re noisy and make a lot of noise because you’re almost always rubbing the surface of the pick across a string instead of striking through a string. They’re shorter and not as grippy. Their shortness also makes it hard to let long notes ring during the “death picking” part of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. And if you’re really trying to play like Fripp and sound like him, you’re not going to have good luck with a normal pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;guitar-craft-triangular-picks&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft Triangular Picks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I attended the Guitar Circle intro course, some official india rubber Guitar Craft picks were available for purchase. It turns out there are two types of GC picks: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_rubber&quot;&gt;india rubber&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyoxymethylene&quot;&gt;delrin&lt;/a&gt;. My india rubber picks are shiny, slick, and fancier than the delrin ones. The delrin ones have a matte, fine texture and I prefer them to the india rubber ones. Guitarist &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com/index.htm&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com/words/history/PickHistory/&quot;&gt;a written history of the picks on his website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These picks are definitely, definitely awesome. Before I had any access to these picks, I bought every sharp pick I could find on the market. The only ones that even come close to the GC picks are the Tortex Sharps Fripp recommended. The biggest advantage (for me) to the triangular pick is that it doesn’t spin or move nearly as much when playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-sharp-picks&quot;&gt;Other Sharp Picks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I understand that it may be my own poor technique that leads to a spinning pick, but I can say that the triangular pick spins the least of any of the picks I’ve seen. Even as I’ve been making this series, I’ve worked pretty hard on my picking grip and have started re-evaluating other sharp picks as I’m learning to better control the pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all this work, none of the other sharp picks I have come &lt;em&gt;close&lt;/em&gt; to the Tortex Sharps or the GC picks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/DAndrea-TG355-96HV-Celluloid-Guitar/dp/B001RMDQCY&quot;&gt;D’Andrea triangle picks&lt;/a&gt; are really big. I’ve cut them down to the size of the GC picks, but one of the sides is unfinished.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Jim-Dunlop-478P-88-Tortex®-Players/dp/B00ISQCJRU&quot;&gt;White Dunlop Jazz III picks&lt;/a&gt; are the best of the rest. For GC-style picking that’s suitable for playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, these are pretty nice, though a little thick for my taste. The other Jazz III picks are just too thick for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re on the subject of picks, there are some pretty crazy picks out there. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Ibanez-0-75mm-Sand-Grip-Plectrums/dp/B004CYEPGU&quot;&gt;Ibanez makes one with a sandpaper grip&lt;/a&gt;! I ordered this crazy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.v-picks.com/product/shredder-lite/&quot;&gt;V-Pick “Shredder Lite” triangular guitar pick&lt;/a&gt; and it’s SUPER sharp, precisely made, but a little too thick for my tastes. It is nearly the same size as the GC picks and works pretty well. There’s even a woman using this technique with a different pick in the New York Guitar Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/fracture/picks</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/fracture/picks</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Markus Reuter</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/s8cqnlbH2jM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/markus-reuter.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/markus-reuter.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-thanks&quot;&gt;Special Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://lucasleemusic.com&quot;&gt;Lucas Lee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for doing the transcription of this interview! Lucas Lee’s studio albums featuring &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Mastelotto&quot;&gt;Pat Mastelotto &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stick_Men_(prog_band)&quot;&gt;Stick Men&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin&lt;/a&gt; and Markus) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://tobiasralph.com&quot;&gt;Tobias Ralph &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (The Crimson ProjeKCt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew_Power_Trio&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew Power Trio&lt;/a&gt;) are now both available at CDBaby. I love that people want to help with the work of this site. Thank you, Lucas!! &lt;a href=&quot;/support&quot;&gt;If you’d like to help out with the site, let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I attended the Guitar Circle introductory course in Mexico in February 2015, I made a lot of new friends on Facebook. Then, I started hearing a lot about this Markus Reuter guy, seeing him pop up in interesting discussions and seeing my new friends praising his music. Turns out, he’s a very, very experienced GC participant with a unique take on composition, performance, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.markusreuter.com&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Markus Reuter is? Check out his website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few hours into research, I saw that he’d basically invented a new kind of guitar called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.touchguitars.com&quot;&gt;Touch Guitar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, wrote a stunning orchestral ambient piece called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todmorden_513&quot;&gt;Todmorden 513 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; based on a combinatorial algorithm that generated all sorts of sequences and chord structures, and had a super-unique take on music as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It became immediately obvious that he was an ideal candidate for a MWM interview. Enjoy this no-holds-barred conversation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Hi this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with Markus Reuter, all the way from Berlin. Markus, thank you for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Hello.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: The site is about discovering new artists and expanding your creative horizons. You’re a very creative musician. Can you tell us about yourself and how you got to where you are today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Well, that’s a very good question. Somehow I got motivated in my very early teens to become a musician but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the word “musician” really isn’t big enough to describe what it’s about, what I’m doing. It’s more like I’m trying to find something that I want to hear.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like I have this vision inside me that I somehow feel driven to find what that vision could be in the real world. So it’s been a very, very long process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started, I think, when I was around 9 or 10 years old. Even now at almost 44 years, I feel like I’ve only just started. This feeling of always being uncomfortable where I am as an artist is part of what’s driving me. So the worlds that I’m looking for with my music are undiscovered worlds. So speaking of “weird music,” I believe that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s still a lot of uncharted territory in music, even though some people believe that everything has been said or done. I think that’s just plain stupid, to tell you the truth.&lt;/span&gt; Especially with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_music&quot;&gt;western system &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chromatic_scale&quot;&gt;12 notes of the chromatic scale &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we use, I think there’s still so much more to be said, because almost 100 years [ago], the knowledge was at a high point, really, and then disintegrated a little bit. We had the whole, let’s say, rock n’ roll, pop music thing happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think we’re at a time now where things start to fuse again. So, there’s all the knowledge of rock and the classical, combined with what used to be called punk, the DIY scene and stuff like that–experimental music. I think we’re in a post-modern time where experimental music and experiments really do not lead to new results anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/176190677&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/176190677&quot;&gt;Susanne Kessel plays: Markus Reuter &amp;quot;His last decade&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user43222763&quot;&gt;Susanne Kessel&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;what I’m trying to do is fuse, to build a bridge between old knowledge and new technologies–a new knowledge&lt;/span&gt;, you could say. But it’s really–I could go on talking about it on an abstract level or we can really speak about something specific and I can explain what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, you said you get uncomfortable and you try to dislodge yourself from that comfort. What are some of the things that help you to recognize that you are comfortable? What are some of the things you do to dislodge yourself from that comfort?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Mainly, it’s interesting because what does make me feel comfortable is if I don’t understand. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If I get the feeling that there is something that I don’t understand that makes me happy. That makes me feel comfortable. Because for me, the world is boring.&lt;/span&gt; The world is extremely boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Let’s just stick to the music, you know. I’m looking for states that make me feel uncomfortable and that means that’s the music that I haven’t heard. That’s like, for example, with my main band, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centrozoon&quot;&gt;Centrozoon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a German/Swiss project. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We have this rule that whenever we hear something we played that we don’t like, that’s what we’re going to explore.&lt;/span&gt; If we’re recording, we’re not keeping the things we like. We throw those out but we keep those that we don’t like. We put those recordings out and we treat them like the most beautiful children. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s one way of raising something new. Things that aren’t beautiful. Things that you don’t recognize right away. Things that you actually nurture and then kind of at a later point, in hindsight it becomes beautiful.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think it’s the same with a lot of music, especially with looking at the biographies of a lot of the artists that have been discovered when they’re long dead. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So it’s really about finding something that hasn’t been said. For me, that really includes that when I’m writing music or creating music, I do want to find a music in a language that no one has heard before.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You talked about vision. You sound more of like an artist using music to manifest that vision than somebody who explicitly chooses music out of a love or adoration for the craft, in a way. Can you talk about how you came to find music to create that reality of your vision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mffn1EfRMy8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: The word “vision” has nothing to do with being visual, you know? It’s not something that’s represented in the sense of vision and it isn’t even represented in the sense of hearing for me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s really about states of emotions, feelings–and even that doesn’t really cover it. It’s almost like a sixth sense kind of thing, there is something that I do want to capture.&lt;/span&gt; So really, how did I discover that music or sound is the medium? I think the answer is very simple. Sound and vibration is the ultimate medium. It’s what the world is made of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My understanding of the world, my worldview, is that everything’s a vibration. You can basically track everything down to vibration. You break it down again, but it’s all vibration. That’s why musicians or people who manipulate sound are basically–and let me just use this word carefully–are basically gods, you know, just in the sense of the word that you’re creating the materials that have been used in order to build the world.&lt;/span&gt; So that’s why music really is, for me, the most fundamental art there is. Even though other arts plug into the same thing. Music is the most basic, the most simple, the most important, I would say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you talked about how everything is a vibration and that music is a very basic fundamental thing in the world. Your ambient music and a lot of your music doesn’t seem to follow a traditional song structure in the rock or western sense of intro-verse-chorus-verse-chorus-bridge, that kind of thing. Do you feel that that’s a layer that’s been added that’s unnecessary or that you have worked through that and come to understand music differently in a way above or in parallel to that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, I mean… the idea that musical pieces should be structured into sections–or that you are repeating sections and stuff–that’s really what I call “songwriter music” where the approach is to tell a story that’s usually also told with words. So in a way, the music becomes a secondary thing. I don’t necessarily mean in quality, just in terms of the message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So yes, I have worked with those structures in several projects–things I have produced and also my own projects–and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve come to realize that there’s the tendency to edit yourself or to edit the music when you’re approaching it like a songwriter because you’re asking yourself–because you’re telling a story, it means you already know what the story is.&lt;/span&gt; That’s not my approach to music, that’s why my music is so different in its form–I don’t know which story you are telling yourself when you’re listening to the music I’m making. So I can’t be–or I try not to intervene, you know, and kind of cut things down to tell my story–but I want you to be able to hear your story. And that’s really where song structures, I think, might work for some people, because you’re still making up your own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BEBw4F5HuVI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But for me, it was just important to kind of let the music speak for itself and for me there’s no such thing as too many repetitions.&lt;/span&gt; It’s really that for me, the music itself–or let’s say because I’m basically composing conceptually. So the musical concept tells me what the structure should be, but it’s not anything that I’m superimposing as a human being in terms of, “Oh, this means that and this means that,” you know? So that’s really the reason why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I mean it’s interesting, like, for example one of my first professional groups, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europa_String_Choir&quot;&gt;Europa String Choir &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was a chamber group. There were really interesting things happening when we were writing. We were actually using the songwriter’s approach, but it was fun because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we realized sometimes you don’t even want to repeat something twice. You just want to repeat it one and a half times, or two and a half times.&lt;/span&gt; It kind of came together in a recording project in the sense that when we were recording those pieces that have these more interesting complex forms, we figured out, “Ok let’s play at 105BPM and listen back to and see what it sounds like.” “Oh no, it’s a little slow” and we’d try 106. Then we’d try 105.5 and it turned out 105.5 was the right tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So what I mean is really what was happening–or what was happening for me–is that I’m kind of raising the resolution of what I’m doing, how I’m experiencing music. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_audio_workstation&quot;&gt;DAWs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that we have that are all set to 120BPM when we open them up and a lot of music is around 120BPM.&lt;/span&gt; And that’s like–it’s sad. It’s especially clear so many people are not listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I mean, just saying, it wasn’t meant as a criticism, but as an example that technology kind of gives us this–I mean &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;technology and education that gives us this grid that we believe things should be in, and what I’ve been doing is to kind of raise the solution of that grid for myself. I still believe that a grid is nice, just like I said that we have the 12 notes that we can work with and that there’s still a lot to discover, we can still discover a lot within that grid, but we should try to subdivide more.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s so interesting. You said that you want people to hear their own story and your stories, but you also said that a lot–or &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of your music at least is released as the songs that you didn’t like, the things that made you uncomfortable. Do you believe that any of the discomfort carries to the listener? Or is it just that was your experience and you believe they’ll still find their own?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: So &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the funny thing is that what I actually said was that it makes me feel comfortable. It’s the discomfort that makes me feel comfortable because the discomfort is the sign that I’ve discovered something.&lt;/span&gt; I hope and I believe that’s what’s carrying over to the listener too, yes? I think so! There’s something that you need to latch onto as a listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Just as a human being, we’re going through this world as the most advanced pattern-recognition machine that there is ever going to be, probably. So we’re walking through this world and we’re seeing something. We’re hearing something. We’re feeling something and we latch onto that and we develop an interest in it. So for me, for example, that was actually the band &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;, which you know, but it wasn’t the music of the bad King Crimson. It was the name. My piano teacher mentioned King Crimson to me and I knew there was something there. I knew there was something behind that name that I needed to follow up on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/z_dZTUA1qNc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Only like 2 years later or so, I discovered the music and it turned out that yes, I was right. So really the pattern recognition–it really extends to, let’s just say “between the lines.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re really such amazing beings and we’re not aware of it, really.&lt;/span&gt; Like the subconscious processes so much and it kind of picks up on vibes, yeah? That’s really what I’m very interested in also with my music. Just to kind of feed the subconscious at the same time as the conscious and then I’ll try to get the people to get into this state where somehow the gates open, you know, both going inside and going outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So what people get where they get creative themselves and in a way–and this might sound, I mean it still sounds funny, but I think if there was anything–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you would ask me, “Markus what are you doing here?” I would say that I’m actually a “healer.” I don’t want to be a healer. It’s not that I’ve chosen that.&lt;/span&gt; And just the music for myself, that’s my medium. That’s my world. That’s where I feel good. That’s where I can develop. That’s also the world I can withdraw into. But for other people, I think it does the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Coming back to your question… &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Yes, it makes people feel uncomfortable and that’s a good thing. I don’t need to do things to make people feel comfortable… that’s just not the way I am. It’s not my responsibility to make you feel comfortable.&lt;/span&gt; You should feel comfortable. It’s not my responsibility, but I can create something that might inspire you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So it sounds like… I would imagine that all of this developed over time–this perspective developed as you grew up from an adolescent to adult and then also as somebody who was taking maybe some piano lessons and got formalized education elsewhere on other instruments. Is a lot of this stuff a result of dissatisfaction with standard songwriting in music techniques or is this just kind of… were you born with this intuition? Were you born with these feelings? Can you tell us about the development of this perspective?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Anthony, that’s a very deep question. It’s extremely personal and if you mean that, I can tell you. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think it’s my childhood and like the greatest musicians, the greatest artists, they had a shit childhood.&lt;/span&gt; My childhood, from my perspective from what I know now wasn’t bad. But maybe there was something. Like for example, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;as a 3 yr old I was alone in the hospital for 3 weeks. I don’t know, maybe that’s why I became a musician. That’s why I have the drive to create. Maybe they tied me down at night. I don’t know. It’s something like that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s really, really simple. I think if we–like all of us, if we look back, there’s something that drives us and it’s usually something bad, you know? I mean it’s like not a lot of people talk about this, because like especially artists and the old model with record companies, you obviously try to keep a distance, so you wouldn’t really say these things. But one of my greatest influences is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Oldfield&quot;&gt;Mike Oldfield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and he has always been very straightforward about what happened in his childhood. He started to ride out real battles when he was six years old or something. Somehow I think that this drive, and this is something that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigmund_Freud&quot;&gt;Freud &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; said we have: the drive to die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q1_VuiMYxtU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So there’s this drive to die and somehow, some of us become creators and we are all creators. It’s just a continuum. So there’s nobody in this world who’s not creating but some of us just have this need to do that. I’m just one of them.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you talked about being a creator and that possibly stemming from childhood wounds or illness or something bad and then you also said that you found yourself to be a healer for music. Are those things that tie together? Does music heal some of that wound or whatever it is that motivating you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;To be honest I’m not sure if the music is the healer. I think we are still the healers for ourselves. I guess that you can kind of, in a way, misuse music to have an excuse not to heal yourself.&lt;/span&gt; But still, I don’t really believe that anymore, but maybe 10-20 years ago I would have said that’s why we have happy music in the world… to close up our own responsibilities to heal ourselves. But that’s a little extreme. It’s not that way, but it’s food for thought, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Consuming things can always distract you and you can distract yourself by looking at the greatest paintings. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So it’s not necessarily the piece of art itself that is healing, but it provides the materials that you need to heal yourself.&lt;/span&gt; So I mean, like this whole idea of what I said earlier that people who manipulate sound are gods. I also think there is something like that there are demons, but that would be like in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_mythology&quot;&gt;Greek mythology &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think there is a lot of wisdom in the Greek mythology. The gods themselves–they fail, you know? The demons, there are very bad demons, and there are demons that are not so bad. It’s a spectrum. A spectrum of beings, where I think if we think about it, it makes a whole lot of sense. There are some people that are creating the materials with which the world is being built and there are others that are then on a different level creative, using those materials in order to build something. It’s not really like there’s really good and bad, or a yin and a yang, there are levels of materials that are being generated in this world, and music, I believe, is one of the really basic ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I’m talking about music, I’m not necessarily talking about what we consider to be music making, but also listening, you know? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The act of listening is also making music. So you could be in the wild without any musical instrument and you’d be hearing the birds and the waterfall or whatever, and it would be music to your ears.&lt;/span&gt; Just the act of listening turns it into music. So somehow that’s–in simple words, it’s kind of like one of the energizing factors in this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Now as I mentioned, this site is for helping people to discover new kinds of music and new artists. You are the first ambient artist–well actually, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/michael-manring&quot;&gt;Michael Manring&lt;/a&gt; does ambient as well. But I’d like to ask you specifically about ambient music because you obviously have a lot of deep opinions and thoughts on music and its capabilities. So can you–what turned you onto ambient music and can you describe how ambient music reaches you in a way that’s similar to or different to non-ambient music, you know–more standard radio music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aXwoo2Gzl-s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Well, first of all, I would say that for me, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;what sounds like ambient music to other people, it’s just one particular kind of contemporary music in the sense that it’s more concerned with the music than the marketing or the packaging. It’s more like classical music than pop music in that sense.&lt;/span&gt; The cool thing about ambient music is that it–even though when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Eno&quot;&gt;Brian Eno &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; coined the term, the idea was for it to be like a passive listening thing. But with modern–or I’ll just say post modern ambient music, it’s really music that people actively listen to, you know? You can do anything with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s just up to you. It’s not really printed into the music what you can do with it. So ambient music in that sense is really speaking of that: the emotional content of the music. What we’d describe as ambient music has the potential to be about a pure–or more of a pure expression of an emotion. When I say expression, I don’t mean that it’s an emotion that you as the creator have, but the emotion that the listener can kind of compose around the sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s interesting because it’s really all sort of technology that brought me into ambient music because I started using delay loops pretty early on when they became available in the mid-90s when the Oberheim Echoplex Digital Pro–that’s the device that I used to record my first album, actually. It’s kind of like a microcosm. You’re zooming into sounds. You’re zooming into harmonic structures. You’re allowed to take your time and that’s what really makes this such an amazing genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also, for personal development. I think I did it in order to practice making music. Like, the delay loops to play into it. You’re hearing back to what you just played right away and then you can add something. You learn about the spacing of the notes. You learn about the spacing in time, the spacing in the spectrum and all like that. It was really just fascinating and inspiring for me to have technology available that allowed me to compose in real-time that way. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So I still do that when I’m making ambient music. It’s always an expression. It’s like real-time composition. It’s not improvisation. It’s real-time composition and I can apply similar concepts to the composition to doing it “offline.””&lt;/span&gt; But the live composition has always been a very important factor. Really, ambient music lends itself to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What first attracted you to ambient music and did it strike you as appealing at first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Very much so. I think the first music that I would describe as “ambient music” that I heard was also was by Mike Oldfield from an album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Killing_Fields_(album)&quot;&gt;The Killing Fields &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A soundtrack album and there were just these really short ambient pieces on there. Just maybe a minute or so of really, really weird chords and those fascinated me a lot. It was just this… just the mood to have the sustained sound and you could just kind of zoom in onto the relationships of the notes with each other and it was like a whole world was opening up in just the combination of those static pitches and that’s really what was fascinating for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Bc4KWsxoBYI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Around the same time, I got into contemporary classical composers of the 20th century, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivier_Messiaen&quot;&gt;Messiaen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Bedford&quot;&gt;David Betford &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for example, who is really amazing. Those guys were always doing ambient music but what kind of set it apart and what kind of drew me in I guess was that they were always breaking the boundaries of what people considered to be consonant versus dissonant. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And really that’s where my interest always was, to teach myself to hear things. To not even fall into this category of saying, “This is dissonant and this is consonant.” I’m still kind of in the process of breaking that barrier for myself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s very relevant for an instrumentalist if you’re playing like me. I’m performing and I do not want to cringe when I play a “wrong” note and I’ve been working on that for almost 20 years and I’ve gotten very good at it. I can play any wrong note at any time. It might sound very bad to you but to me it sounds great. That was really one of the aims, I think the looping technology, the ambient music was one of the ways how I could accomplish that for myself, how I could practice that for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That kind of raises another very amateur question that I wrote down. I enjoy ambient music, but I only have been exposed to what I would say are professionals, you know? &lt;em&gt;laughs&lt;/em&gt; You, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Brian Eno, Michael Manring, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Hedges&quot;&gt;Michael Hedges &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Is there &lt;strong&gt;bad&lt;/strong&gt; ambient music? How would you know if it was bad, if there’s such a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Dude, there’s no bad music. There’s either music or it’s not music. You’re the one who defines that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Alright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Just this idea of a “guilty pleasure,” which exists in the English language, yeah? The guilty pleasure–doesn’t makes sense to me. Like, you know, whatever floats your boat. Really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s cool! You said in another interview where you found your voice at the age of 33. Can you–as somebody who has gone too far in the world of technique and instrumental noodling–can you tell me about how you found your voice and the path you kind of took? Because for me, I feel like I need to get a step away from some of that. We both did guitar craft stuff. For me it’s almost taken me too far into the technical direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Mm hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: But I wanted to hear about your side of things and how you found your voice in the path you took and the path that you’re on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: OK. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So just this concept of your personal voice, I really–I wouldn’t use those words, because it’s not my voice. It really isn’t, because I’d rather consider myself to be like an interface, ok?&lt;/span&gt; So the voice is between whatever is there to inspire and the recipient. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m part of the audience, you know. When I’m playing, I’m listening. That’s really actually maybe the wisest thing I can say or you could say to any musician: listen to what you’re playing or what you’re doing&lt;/span&gt;, right? I don’t ever question that, but probably it’s something that people just don’t do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zaF46p-Z8tU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I think that’s like &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you want to find your own voice, just listen to what you’re doing.&lt;/span&gt; I guess that’s the answer. You know, and it really connects to the question you had earlier, like with looping devices. That’s what they do, you know? You play into them and it plays back to you right away, so you’re hearing what you did and you have the opportunity to decide for yourself if you, let’s say like it, or not like it. Or even if you don’t want to use those terms, how you would describe what’s happening?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Maybe you play 3 notes, and then you realize, “Oh the second note, that was a D. The D had a little bit of a buzz on it.” Then you decide for yourself whether the buzz is something you want the next time you play the D or no, or maybe you don’t want the buzz. Or maybe the D didn’t really satisfy you, so next time you’d play an E-flat. Really that’s how we kind of find our voice, just by playing things back to ourselves and that could be like, you could sit down with the instrument, start the recorder, and just improvise, just play, just move your fingers, don’t even improvise, just move your fingers and then listen back to it, and then repeat. That’s how you can find your voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Did you overcome–you said you avoided cringing or you’re learning to avoid cringing when you’re playing a “wrong note.” Did you have to overcome fears to get to where you are, to create the music that you create, even to become a musician?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, very much so, but in a way I got lucky that my personality is like that I’m very um… well, I don’t know how to put it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Some people think that I’m arrogant. But it’s not that I’m arrogant, I just have this vision, I kind of know what is right and what is wrong&lt;/span&gt;, even if it’s in the greater context, what I consider is right is wrong, I don’t care, but &lt;strong&gt;at least I have an opinion&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m good at creating references and milestones for myself and that’s really what, at least that’s my path of developing of improving, you know. For example with the touch guitar, with a touch-style instrument. When I started out in the early 90s, people were saying, “Oh we don’t know anything about it… blah blah blah. Nobody knows how to play this instrument, blah blah blah blah blah.” And I said, “&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Ok yeah we don’t know how to play this instrument but we know what we need in order to play what we consider music. We need to be able to start a note and we need to be able to stop a note.&lt;/span&gt; We can look at the instrument and find out how to start a note and how to stop a note. That’s what we can do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s what I was always very good at, identifying what we know, or what I know, and then I could go from there. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s really one of the secrets: to not get distracted by what you don’t know but to start at a point where you feel confident that something’s right.&lt;/span&gt; Even that, if that thing is right to you is wrong in the bigger context, it’s still is something that pushes you forward, because you’re not criticizing yourself. You’re not kind of putting your hands into cuffs before you’ve even started playing a note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: This kind of approach, I’d imagine, requires a very supportive audience. And thankfully for the internet, there’s an international community that’s open to this kind of music. Do you think that you could have done what you do and make a living 20 years ago approaching music in this sense where you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I started around 20 years ago, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AQKv49exnQI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: So the answer is “yes” I think. For me, it doesn’t really matter. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t really assume there is an audience. I don’t assume that people want to hear what I’m doing. I think that’s just wrong.&lt;/span&gt; I can get excited about something that I create and then maybe somebody else gets excited about it. But he group of people that is really getting excited about it is either extremely small, which is fine, because you know, it could be one person. It could just be me, that one person. Fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not about quantity for me. It’s the quality. I believe that the whole–all the talk about music business, the new paradigm and stuff–really what it is for me is that quantity doesn’t count anymore. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s the quality of the connection with the fans of the artist. The fans are your audience. I would even call them “friends.”&lt;/span&gt; If for example, I can put out a free download and maybe there’s one guy who really likes what I do and he puts in 100 Euros for a download of an album, so these 100 Euros do not represent the value of a CD or a physical product you would press, but it represents the trust in the artist that somebody really likes it, there’s nothing you can quantify there anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s about quality and this is where things kind of start happening, like for example, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I would have to sell 100 downloads of a 1 Euro song to get 100 Euros. That’s not going to happen. It’s much more likely that there’s 1 person that’s going to give me 100 Euros, and that for me is the new paradigm.&lt;/span&gt; That’s how it should be and that’s how it always was. It’s just a little detour we’ve made with the “music business.” The music business is just one example of this Greek mythology thing with the demons and the gods, where the demons are trying to keep the gods stupid and naïve, stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So in a way that’s really like where we’re… well when I say “we,” I’m obviously talking about myself. Fortunately I’m at a different… I really don’t… I couldn’t be bothered without selling copies of something. I don’t care. It’s not what motivates, also. It’s different, I mean &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/notes/steven-wilson/steven-wilson-talks-streaming/1160792253941035&quot;&gt;I read an interview &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Wilson&quot;&gt;Steven Wilson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago, which actually was not an interview, but an advertorial. Anyway, people were discussing it online as if it was a real interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I read the same thing. &lt;em&gt;laughs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: There was one point at which Steven said that he would rather have stuff out on Spotify so people could listen to it and I think that clearly, and I’m–this is not like criticism of this person, I’m saying &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it shows what his motivation is. His motivation is that he wants people to hear what he’s doing. That’s fine. That’s something a lot of us need. That would kill the music for me. I don’t want to do that.&lt;/span&gt; It’s really interesting that the less compromise I make for project, the more successful the project… it’s totally counterintuitive, but it’s true and it’s kind of interesting because I love collaborating with people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So for example, and here’s an interesting story. My friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Boddy&quot;&gt;Ian Boddy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that I started working with in 1999, so a long time ago. Whenever we put out an album, we switched the names around so it could be Ian Boddy + Markus Reuter or the other way around. You’d assume that if you have two groups of fans intersecting, you would, I mean, or being added to each other, you would get a bigger audience. But the opposite is true. When Ian releases a solo album, he sells more, you know? And the other way around. It’s really interesting how the psychology also plays into the image that people have over certain artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DJdqd4DAy-U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also the protectiveness and preciousness about a certain artist. It’s interesting how these things go that like at some point, a name becomes the music in a way. It’s not about the music anymore. You have to like it. Because people say so, because the media says so, and I don’t have a problem with that because it’s cool and it helps and I mean I can tour with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, because the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/So_(album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;So&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Gabriel_discography&quot;&gt;Peter Gabriel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was so successful in the 80s and without all the money they spent on it, I wouldn’t be where I am!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But still, it’s just really something that you need to be aware of these days that a lot of things that you read, or most of the things that you read, are just paid-for content and paid-for opinion and it doesn’t mean anything. That’s just the way it is. Some of us–maybe we have a sense of that and understand that you would always have to read between the lines and stuff. So anyway, there’s no need for me to get into that world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You must be a great music producer. I know you produce a lot of artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Why? I would say as somebody who manages people as my full-time work, what pays me in the market, I see a man with a very strong vision, a way to articulate that, a way to use that vision and motivate other people. Even just hearing you myself here and now, I feel like, “Yeah! I need to get up and make music and quit worrying about the things I worry about! I need to put those fears behind me.” How do you bring that out in the artists you work with, especially if they see things pretty differently, or that they have an agent that doesn’t agree with your philosophies here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: It’s really a struggle, always, for me. It’s really difficult to say how it works, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;one way of describing it is that I do need to &lt;strong&gt;make&lt;/strong&gt; people deconstruct what they’re doing and then reconstruct it, and even if what they reconstruct is exactly the same thing that they had before they deconstructed it, they have more awareness of what it is.&lt;/span&gt; So for example, there was a band that I produced 6-7 years ago, where they didn’t have any transitions between the sections of the songs and we worked on all the transitions in the rehearsal room. Then for the recording, we dropped half of the transitions and went back to just to the A-B thing. But the way that those transitions felt at that point was completely different because not having a transition IS a transition, but it’s only a transition if you are aware that you haven’t considered that there could be a transition. Know what I’m saying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s about awareness, with deconstruction you’re looking at all the elements–you’re kind of assigning meaning to things, and then you put the puzzle back together. For example, if you have a puzzle of New York City, like 3000 pieces, and you just look at it–that’s New York City. But then you take all the pieces apart and you look at each one and say, “OK that’s the top of the Chrysler Building. That’s blah-blah-blah,” and then you put it back together. That’s a real piece of art then–and that’s how I produce. So the result could be exactly same thing that goes in, but it’s not the same thing. It’s completely charged up with meaning and emotion and… intention–that’s the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I would imagine that there’s a good sense of fulfillment for you as a producer, especially when you can bring that out in the art or the artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GjG5R8FzJYE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yes, but I have to say, it’s really the most frustrating job, you know? Because with some artists, it’s just so difficult to get them to really look at what they’re doing and to reevaluate what they’re doing. Even something like there’s a performance that isn’t good but it &lt;strong&gt;has&lt;/strong&gt; to be that performance because “I have to play the guitar part.” It can’t be the studio musician, it can’t be the guy who can actually play guitar. “It has to be me,” and the… again here’s a big difference. Usually I encourage them to play the stuff themselves, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if your vision as an artist goes beyond what you’re capable of, I would rather collaborate with somebody to find the best realization of that vision rather than trying to do everything myself&lt;/span&gt;, you know? There are people capable of doing that. but there are others who are not really capable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So the struggle with the artist is usually to get them to let go. When I say “let go,” it’s not to let go of an idea at all, but just to let go of an emotional attachment to a specific detail in the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: There is a phrase in writing called, “Murder your darlings.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Mm hmm. Never heard that before, but makes sense, yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, that’s so interesting. OK can I get to these burning questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Sure. The burning questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yes. Let’s see… [These are questions from Bernie Quiroga, a Markus Reuter insider] “I understand some material that you brought to the same &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stick_Men_%28prog_band%29&quot;&gt;Stick Men &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; sessions have been written first for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ProjeKct&quot;&gt;(The) Crimson ProjeKCt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but that was not released as Crimson ProjeKCt, so can you tell us a little about what happened there?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Well, that’s really inside information there. Actually that particular piece didn’t make it to the Stick Men record, so it’s still out there. It’s still in my computer waiting to be played by 6 people, and it has to involve &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because I did something very cheeky. You know, being in the inner circle of King Crimson, I got to listen to material that has never been released. So there was something that they played during a 2004 rehearsal, which was the year after the last incarnation of the band disbanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So there was one little riff that they played, this little piece, which is just really one riff, but they didn’t take it anywhere and it didn’t come out, and they didn’t like it at all. I just felt inspired to write a piece around the riff and I did it, and that was when The Crimson ProjeKCt was active and it was just the idea to have something that Adrian would like, because it was based on his riff, but I never sent it to him. He’s never heard it. Pat and Tony have heard it and loved it, but when we tried to massage it for this Stick Men album, it turned out that Adrian’s riff is defining the piece so much that we couldn’t replace it. It just didn’t work and I just didn’t want to waste a good piece, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: According to the vision, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yes, yes, exactly. So that’s that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: OK, I’ll do one more here. “Why do you feel that &lt;em&gt;Face&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.markusreuter.com/discography/tuner/&quot;&gt;Tuner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Falling for Ascension&lt;/em&gt; are two albums you won’t release, even though you’re very proud of them?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: You know, I’m in a position where I’ve dedicated my whole life into making music. That means I’m also dedicating, well not necessarily 24x7, but maybe 19x7 hours to making music.
&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You know, people call me Markus, the guy that never sleeps or something, which isn’t true. I do sleep. But when you go to work, yeah, I make music.&lt;/span&gt;So I have like maybe somebody that writes 32 emails per day. Ok, I can write 2 pieces per day, or I can record 5 hours of music each day. I don’t do that at all because that doesn’t make sense, which I’m going to explain now, but really, I just make music all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So there’s just too much material and I don’t have enough support outside of my own self to really put out music, and even the Stick Men record–even though we had an offer for the upcoming Stick Men record &lt;em&gt;Prog Noir&lt;/em&gt;, we had an offer from a label, which just–Tony didn’t like the deal at all, so we didn’t do it, which means it ends up in my hands. In “our” hands, which means my hands. I have to be the product manager. I have to be the label, and put it out out. It’s just so frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I mean, I have kind of given in and I do these things, but it means that &lt;em&gt;Face&lt;/em&gt;, for example, which is probably, I mean… it’s kind of funny to say, but I think that the best work I’ve done is not yet out there, yeah? I mean some of it is already completed and obviously a lot more is there, but I’ve just come to the point where, what I was saying before. Like other people say he wants people to hear his music and I just say, “No, I’m not going to pay the price to put these things out just for like 5 people to hear it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Because even though I said that I’m more about the quality, yes, which means that before I put something out I have to ask myself, “Do I want to invest the time, do I invest myself with putting it out?” I have to look at the quality of life I’d be giving myself. So that even before I consider the quality of the music or the quality of the interaction with a friend or fan, I have to say, “How well am I with that? Am I doing something good for myself?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At this point it’s just difficult to put out &lt;em&gt;Face&lt;/em&gt;. There’s not enough behind it to really put it out there, and &lt;em&gt;Falling for Ascension&lt;/em&gt;–I’m talking with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nik_Bärtsch&quot;&gt;Nik Bärtsch &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s a friend of mine, and his label &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.roninrhythmrecords.com&quot;&gt;Ronin Rhythm Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to put it out, but it seems like he’s also not 100% convinced of the album. I don’t know… so it’s always.. there’s always something that kind of derails these projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s great. Thank you for these very thoughtful and detailed answers. I really appreciate you going through all of this. I feel like there’s a least another hour’s conversation in here, but I have to get to a sales meeting in 20 minutes, so… &lt;em&gt;laughs&lt;/em&gt;. But thank you so much for your time. I really appreciate it, Markus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/markus-reuter/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Michael Manring Concert</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;concert-trailer&quot;&gt;CONCERT TRAILER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hB6-ZtZh-pc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m so excited about this, I don’t even know what to say! I’ll let this trailer speak for itself. In case you couldn’t tell, this concert is available for purchase via YouTube for $20. Michael gets a large share of the revenue and MWM keeps a little so we can keep making this kind of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=He96CHvohyk&quot;&gt;Purchase this concert on YouTube.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;A majority of the revenue goes to Michael.&lt;/em&gt; :)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of free footage below! Read on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-thanks&quot;&gt;SPECIAL THANKS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks so much to Ken Coffman from &lt;a href=&quot;http://stairwaypress.com/&quot;&gt;Stairway Press &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for sponsoring this concert!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks so much to &lt;a href=&quot;http://michaelnitro.com&quot;&gt;Michael Nitro &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for his lighting crew and equipment. He’s a huge reason the concert looks so great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks so much to &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt; for lending us all his gear so we could do this concert. And for helping to move furniture out of my living and dining rooms (along with another good friend, &lt;a href=&quot;http://softwareplusplus.com&quot;&gt;Cory Berg &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks so much to the 35-40 people who attended and made this such a special event, and then donated to MWM. So many wonderful people supporting the arts and fantastic and creative music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;promo-footage&quot;&gt;PROMO FOOTAGE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael and I thought it would be cool to take a chunk of the concert and offer it for free, so here’s about 18 minutes of free footage that will hopefully entice you to purchase a copy of the rest of the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BZwB7sa2o1s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the opening improv piece, Michael’s cover of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_Send_Me&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You Send Me&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in this video is my favorite part of the concert. And his performance of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dixie_Dregs&quot;&gt;Dixie Dregs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’ &lt;em&gt;What If&lt;/em&gt; with the Dregs’ own Andy West is a real treat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the early 2000s, my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://damprabbit.com&quot;&gt;Bob Mendelsohn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; posted some videos of Michael playing at NAMM and I just fell in love with Michael’s playing. I signed up for his mailing list and waited anxiously for him to come to Phoenix, AZ to perform. In 16 years, he never did! So, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/michael-manring&quot;&gt;when I interviewed him&lt;/a&gt;, I asked him if he’d ever be up for a house concert. He said he would and I resolved to find a way to fly him out and perform at my house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ualQv5bOwsM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on Saturday, April 23, 2016, I had around 40 friends come over for a private event where we all sat in awe watching Michael work his magic up close and personal. And he hung out for a while afterward signing stuff for people and taking pictures. It was a real dream come true. That and &lt;a href=&quot;http://alovelettertofood.com&quot;&gt;my wife &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; catered the whole thing, which made it delicious for the ears as well as the tummy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosting this house concert was a dream come true and Ken Coffman made it all possible financially. I am deeply indebted to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you really enjoy this concert because I have another concert planned in November with another special guest!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/concert/michael-manring/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/concert/michael-manring/</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teddy Kumpel Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-thanks&quot;&gt;SPECIAL THANKS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks so much to Julie Cord from &lt;a href=&quot;http://bluemouthpromotions.com/&quot;&gt;Blue Mouth Promotions &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for setting me up with this interview! She and her brother manage a whole bunch of great artists at BMP. Check them out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://lucasleemusic.com&quot;&gt;Lucas Lee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for doing the transcription of this interview! I love that people want to help with the work of this site. Thank you, Lucas!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hZTfDQvzNbw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/teddy-kumpel/teddy-kumpel.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/teddy-kumpel/teddy-kumpel.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d never heard of Teddy Kumpel before Julie recommended I interview him. Once I asked some Facebook friends about him, several chimed in saying they loved what he did. I spent a few hours checking out his incredible and exhaustive YouTube channel featuring his Loopestra, which (as you’ll soon find out) is a band with rotating members that perform different arrangements of songs every time Teddy books a gig. It’s incredibly creative and I can’t even imagine how challenging it must be for Teddy and his compatriots. The only experience I have with this is playing at church, where I never am playing with the same people, but the music isn’t typically challenging or terribly diverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://teddyjam.com&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Teddy Kumpel is? Check out his website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I checked out Teddy and learned more about him, I knew he’d be a great candidate for an MWM interview. Thanks so much to Teddy for letting me spend time with him during a practice day at the beginning of his 2016 tour with Joe Jackson in Scottsdale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Hi this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I am here with &lt;a href=&quot;http://teddyjam.com&quot;&gt;Teddy Kumpel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, guitarist for &lt;a href=&quot;http://joejackson.com/&quot;&gt;Joe Jackson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and man of many musical adventures.
Teddy, can you tell us about yourself, and your formation as a musician?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: My formation, yes… Okay, here it goes. I was born on Long Island, New York. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My father was a mathematician and my mom was a church organist&lt;/span&gt;. My father played &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadway_(Manhattan)&quot;&gt;Broadway &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Show_tune&quot;&gt;show tunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I was a kid, we sang and played a lot. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My mom played tons of classical music and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ragtime&quot;&gt;rags &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. She loved &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Joplin&quot;&gt;Scott Joplin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and super early jazz stuff, so I was definitely informed by that.&lt;/span&gt; I think by the time I got to be maybe in third grade, I was already playing guitar. We should start with guitar, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was already playing guitar by maybe 3? I was probably playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ukulele&quot;&gt;ukulele &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and both my parents were in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbershop_quartet&quot;&gt;barbershop quartets &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Wow! That’s pretty cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, so my sister and I would learn harmonies to the barbershop quartets and sing with my parents in the car when driving somewhere. We’d learn how to sing background harmonies at a very young age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Ukulele, barbershop quartet - that’s the early years. Let’s see… Then we move up to the 3rd grade. So, school band, playing saxophone… I didn’t grow up wealthy or anything, so my summer camp was going to summer school at the local elementary school. This was in the 70s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And my music teacher, Claire Kahn, was super cool, and since I didn’t really know if I liked the saxophone as I was into the ukulele more,
I said, “Hey, I want to try the tuba.” She was like, “Yeah, sure, try the tuba! Take that home!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;She let me take home every band instrument one summer and I tried the viola, cello, tuba, trombone… everything you can think of.&lt;/span&gt; French horn, trumpet–I just took them home and messed around with them and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that kind of informed my guitar playing because just the willingness to go in many different places and try things and make different sounds other than guitar sounds was part of my upbringing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I played in concert bands from 3rd grade until I was a senior, and I played all different instruments. I played baritone horn, tuba, trombone, saxophone… all that stuff, and then also played guitar in the jazz band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had an excellent guitar teacher when I was a kid. This guy–&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stonybrookmusic.com/richard_rabatin.html&quot;&gt;Richard Rabatin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who was a &lt;a href=&quot;http://berklee.edu&quot;&gt;Berklee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; composition major–taught me. I guess he recognized when I was like 14 when I started with him that I had a pretty good ear. So he started me on atonal sight-singing right away, which he apologizes for now. Hi Rich! [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That really opened up my ears I think at a young age and he showed me a lot of stuff that I don’t think any other teacher would have gone there with such a young kid.&lt;/span&gt; Yeah. So… There you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Did you play piano at all with your mother’s influence or anything?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: My mom was so good at piano that when I watched her play, I was like, “Um, I’ll never be able to do that. I’m sticking with guitar.” [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You obviously were passionate enough about guitar to go to Berkelee College of Music, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I didn’t go to Berkelee College of Music. I got a scholarship to go there and I decided that I’d rather go to University of Miami, so I went there and that was really great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In my freshman year there, my roommate was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.andytimmons.com/&quot;&gt;Andy Timmons &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I had a bunch of great guitar players around me: &lt;a href=&quot;http://brianmonroney.com&quot;&gt;Brian Monroney &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.du.edu/ahss/lamont/faculty-staff/faculty/abbott-mike.html&quot;&gt;Mike Abbott &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timmitchellmusic.com&quot;&gt;Tim Mitchell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://shakira.com&quot;&gt;Shakira’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; musical director. We were all in it together and started teaching each other stuff as we went along, and it was really great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What did you focus on as part of your guitar instruction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I think the first couple of years in Miami were sort of an eye opener for me, because it showed me how much Richard, my teacher in high school, showed me. I placed out of all the theory classes and I didn’t have to take any of them, but also I realized that I didn’t know a lot of things on the guitar that a lot of other people knew, so it was all about learning all your chord voicings, learning tunes, jazz tunes, and transcribing. It was the Studio Music and Jazz Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Where did you go from there, once you graduated? What were some of your early opportunities as a musician?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Well, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;while I was in college, I was playing 6 nights a week playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top_40&quot;&gt;Top 40 music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to get myself through it. So, 6 nights a week, 6 sets a night.&lt;/span&gt; That was Miami in the 80s. South Florida in the 80s. That’s the thing–you could just play and play and play. You’d join bands and make a couple dollars. And the main thing about that was that you’d be learning tunes constantly, because you had to know whatever was on the radio. And it would get your stamina up. You’d have to play so long every night that if you can’t stand on the stage for that long, if you got tired or didn’t give it your 100%… [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How long did you do that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: That was probably a good 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Brutal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You must have burned through strings. It’s humid in Miami, playing 6 nights a week too…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, true, true, true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: 6 sets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: 6 sets a night…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh my goodness…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Dance Clubs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: It started like 8 o’clock at night and ended like 2 or 3 in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Wow, and you never traveled? You just stayed in Miami doing these clubs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I was sort of like up and down the coast of Florida. I think the farthest north we went was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Palm_Beach,_Florida&quot;&gt;West Palm Beach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but we would also go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key_Largo,_Florida&quot;&gt;Key Largo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for a month. If you weren’t in school at the time you could go do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How long were you in Florida?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/H_gNrf6-5uA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: About 5 years. I took a gig with this band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rare_Silk&quot;&gt;Rare Silk &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. They were like the weird &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Manhattan_Transfer&quot;&gt;Manhattan Transfer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. They got a Grammy nomination, and they were really a creative band. I toured with them with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ric_Fierabracci&quot;&gt;Ric Fierabracci&lt;/a&gt; on bass and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.umdrums.com/2015/08/16/olbin-burgos/&quot;&gt;Olbin Burgos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who played drums for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thesoundmachine.net&quot;&gt;Miami Sound Machine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for a long time
and this amazing producer from Miami, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lester_Mendez&quot;&gt;Lester Mendez &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; playing keyboard. We were their band, and we toured for about a year, then we all quit. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Something happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I think we wanted more money and they wouldn’t give us more money, something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And when was this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: It was about 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What’s been going on, you know after that, since then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: After that, I moved to New York, and did what every young starving musician does in New York in the 80s. At least there were only a few things that you could do to make money and one of the main ones was doing club dates or weddings. So &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think between 1988 and 1998, I did about probably 750 weddings.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh my goodness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You were probably really good at wedding music by then after the Miami dance scene, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Well, Miami pop music/dance scene was sort of like what’s on the radio, and wedding was in NY are a very specific thing. You’ve got to know your &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Sinatra&quot;&gt;Frank Sinatra &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you’ve got to know a couple of standards, some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bossa_nova&quot;&gt;Bossa Novas &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antônio_Carlos_Jobim&quot;&gt;Jobim &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you’ve got to know…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Maybe there’s a set of dance music, maybe there’s a set of oldies dance music like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sly_and_the_Family_Stone&quot;&gt;Sly and the Family Stone &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So it’s very diverse and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you meet a lot of really great players when you do weddings in New York because everybody does them.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you’re not a producer, or if you’re a musician and you’re only a side man and that’s your job, then you’re gonna probably going to end up in a wedding gig at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, it’s funny &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt; was in a band called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.andywest.com/music/recordings/fwap2.html&quot;&gt;Fwap &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with a guitarist named &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joaquinmusic.com/&quot;&gt;Joaquin Levano &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in New York, and my dad recently moved back to NY. He’s been playing and he met Joaquin through the keyboard player that my dad has known for a long time, and Joaquin and Scott [keyboardist] were playing weddings in New York! So that’s just funny talking to my dad. “You know, you’ve got this guitarist named Joaquin Levano” Like, what? He played with Andy West! And my dad played and I with Andy West shortly in Arizona, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Oh yeah? Cool. Andy’s super cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah. Everyone plays weddings in New York!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So what about your own compositions like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdbaby.com/cd/teddykumpel&quot;&gt;Loopestra&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/PDnftXsCwsQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, it’s my own music. Composition-wise, started composing, and I would say when I was in high school I was writing instrumental rock tunes. Then in Miami, I started writing a lot more, branching out, writing lyrics, and putting together little productions of things on a 4-track recorder, trying to figure out how to do that. Then I had a band in the early 90s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdbaby.com/cd/nomesane&quot;&gt;Nome Sane? &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;http://tonyscherr.com/&quot;&gt;Tony Scherr &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s the bass player for &lt;a href=&quot;http://billfrisell.com&quot;&gt;Bill Frisell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.andymiddleton.com/&quot;&gt;Andy Middleton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s an amazing sax player, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.briandunnedrums.com/&quot;&gt;Brian Dunne &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who’s the drummer for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hallandoates.com/&quot;&gt;Hall and Oates &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: We had a funk band. That was pretty fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Nome Sane?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Nome Sane? &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/nome-sane/id46625193&quot;&gt;You can find that on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: It has a question mark at the end. Nome Sane, question mark. We did some touring. We played in Europe. We had a really good time and I think &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I learned a lot about being a bandleader from doing that for four strong personalities&lt;/span&gt;, trying to figure that out. It’s good and then as time went on, people kind of drifted off and we disbanded and I started writing a lot of pop songs. So I wrote a lot of pop songs with some artists who got signed and I got a publishing deal with EMI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Um.. which, you know, that and $2.50 will get you on a subway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Great, Right! Yeah. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: So &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I have a lot of experience demoing and writing pop songs and I guess that does inform my weird music making too.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah I bet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I know how to craft something into something that’s listenable but I also like weird things, so I like to marry those two things together.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Who are some of the weird influences that you’ve got?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4tKq1kc1RKk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Oh man, well weird influences–let’s see. That’s a good question. I listened to a lot of early &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rambler_%28Bill_Frisell_album%29&quot;&gt;Bill Frisell - Rambler &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That album where they had 2 brass instruments. He had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenny_Wheeler&quot;&gt;Kenny Wheeler &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on flugelhorn and he had tuba player and he had electric bass and him and the drummer so like… high and low strings and high and low brass and a drummer. I like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I listen to a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Garbarek&quot;&gt;Jan Garbarek &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He’s a Norwegian sax player who sounds like he’s playing in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fjord&quot;&gt;Fjords &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–lot of reverb and &lt;em&gt;makes sounds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I listen to a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;http://adrianbelew.net/&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zappa.com/&quot;&gt;Zappa &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of contemporary weird classical music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Like minimalist? Like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.philipglass.com/&quot;&gt;Phillip Glass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevereich.com/&quot;&gt;Steve Reich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: No, I’m more into the harmonic stuff, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erik_Satie&quot;&gt;(Erik) Satie &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parade_%28ballet%29&quot;&gt;Parade &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah. And guitar-wise, I’m into all the typical sort of influences that everybody has I guess &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimi_Hendrix&quot;&gt;Hendrix &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Beck&quot;&gt;Jeff Beck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy_Page&quot;&gt;Jimmy Page &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: &lt;em&gt;Eh.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I don’t meet many musicians who’d do that with Jimmy Page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Jimmy Page… I mean I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not like the guy who listen to Led Zeppelin and goes “Wow! I want to play all those guitar licks,” you know? But, I played them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Of course. 6 nights a week…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Well I had my band in 8th grade and we played all that stuff. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pinkfloyd.com&quot;&gt;Pink Floyd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, then later on I listen to a lot of Frisell, and a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnscofield.com/&quot;&gt;John Scofield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and that’s about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I just saw Scofield with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bradmehldau.com/&quot;&gt;Brad Mehldau &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://markguiliana.com/&quot;&gt;Mark Guiliana &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Oh Yeah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Awesome show in New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah. I love Mark. Mark has done the Loopestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z4l0QmP8cks?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s right! Yeah, I wanted to ask you about that. So the Loopestra–how did that get started? Did you first with the electronics, and get an idea, or…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Loopestra kind of came about because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wanted to have a band where I could write open ended songs that didn’t have a lot of changes and I wanted to get another guitar player who would just play rhythm and I could make weird noises over that and sing songs, but I couldn’t find anybody who would just play rhythm.&lt;/span&gt; Everybody wanted to have other roles and as great as that could have been, it wasn’t what I wanted to do. And right about that time, Boss came out with a looper. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: So I was like, “Well, sorry dude, you’re fired. I’m getting a looper!” and it turns out that worked well for me. I was able to exercise my production brain live with that, which isn’t to say that I do a lot of electronics stuff because sometimes it’s very organic and basic. Sometimes I can make it sound like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jamesbrown.com/&quot;&gt;James Brown &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes I can be totally bizarre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How did you get in touch with the roster of people you’ve played with? Is just the years of working as a musician playing gigs that you’ve built that network? Or are you seeking out these people for specific sounds or talents?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I think it started out–I wanted to have a set band when I started that, and then it’s New York city. Sometimes people can’t make $50 gigs, so I had to start mixing it up and then that became a thing. It became interesting to have a different drummer and bass player on the gig every time, because you’re making loops–and it’s not a lot of changes and there’s no rehearsal, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;so it ends up that they just had to bring their own personalities to the table and they don’t know what’s going to happen either, so it’s exciting for them. They don’t have to have any preconceived notion of what’s going to happen.&lt;/span&gt; I try to tailor what I’m doing to what I think they’re going to bring, but then sometimes they surprise me and bring in something completely different than what I thought they were going to bring, so it’s really fun for me to get to play with all these guys and mix it up with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah it seems less like music performance and more like musical communication between 3 or 4 people at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Mm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You don’t play the songs for the other guys beforehand generally unless they’ve done a gig with you before? Then they’re unfamiliar with what you’re going to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Exactly, yeah. Yeah, I think when somebody wants to know what they should check out, I say, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Just go check yourself out. Check out your personality, alone in your apartment and meditate a little bit or something. I don’t know what to tell you, pal.”&lt;/span&gt; [laughs] That’s a really New York answer, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, but as far as the people who have done this… You’re doing this on a Monday night in New York, where all musicians have a day off and people come out, so they see it and they want to be part of it. Or I think, “Oh you know those 2 guys played with blah-blah-blah together. Maybe it’d be cool if they did it ‘cause they have a thing together.” I try to keep people together that have “a thing.” Then sometimes you can’t get people to play together a lot, so you have to put people together that never play together, then they evolve into having “a thing” also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Is this live dynamic performance a response to anything in your past? Like playing through-composed music by other people for so much of your career as a paid musician, doing these wedding gigs, club gigs and that kind of thing? Were you just craving this kind of live improvisation? Or is that always been part of your musical…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Good question. I would say, I’ve been jamming like that with my mom since I was a kid, where she would play organ and I would play piano. Even though I don’t really know how to play piano, I have ears and fingers, so I can kind of find and play in between and we would have these epic half hour long jams that would just go from totally &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bizarro_World&quot;&gt;bizarro world &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–but very reactionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;She would play something, I’d answer. And she doesn’t really consider herself an improviser necessarily. She’s got great ears, but she’s a classical musician, so everything she’s drawing from is something that has been played before. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But I had no idea what that was most of the time, so I was just sort of hearing my way through it.&lt;/span&gt; And I guess, that’s always been part of my M.O.–jamming and playing extended things as it’s always been fun for me. But equally I like the set forms too, so thankfully I get to do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah! Are your sets unplanned with the Loopestra?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I don’t even think about it. I just go on stage and sort of go, “Ok, what song do I have here? Maybe I’ll sing that song.” You know? Start something and go, “Nah, I don’t want to sing that song for this. It sounds like this other song.” Because it could go either way. I have some preconceived little loopy ideas that I do for some songs, but instead  probably a third of the time, I’ll sing something else over it, just to mix it up and push the thing into an unknown territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: We didn’t actually say what the Loopestra was! We didn’t talk about it. What IS the Loopestra and how do you tell people about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The Loopestra is a band that has a rotating cast and rotating guitar parts&lt;/span&gt; [laughs] via loopers. So the way it works is, you get a couple of people playing bass and drums. You get a looper, you make a loop. The drummer goes, “Oh, I know what to play with that.” He does it and then the bass player says, “Oh I don’t really like that chord. I’m going to play something totally to wrong make it into another chord.” Hopefully he’ll do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah. I watched one of your gigs. Most of them are on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/TeddyKumpel&quot;&gt;your Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;. Or many of them… I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: It’s extensive, the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: They run screaming. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What’s amazing to me is, you’d play a loop and my ears think, “Oh I get it.” And then the drummer would come in and do something totally off the wall, like…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/paRYPRpUfVk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And it completely changes the direction of the song. Even just for 8 or 16 measures. Do you get a thrill out of that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It’s not confusing for you or anything? [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I &lt;em&gt;hope&lt;/em&gt; it’s confusing. I love it when it goes to the edge of the cliff and you really have to pay attention. It just makes you pay attention when they do that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So tell me about the edge of the cliff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Okay… well &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you’re playing a gig where you know everything that you’re going to play, you’re not on the edge of the cliff&lt;/span&gt;, which is fine ‘cause you have thing that you’re going to do and that’s a performance. It’s a different kind of edge of the cliff, let’s say, because there are subtleties that could come out in a live performance that don’t come up every time, but you kind of have to cover the bases of what the thing is, right? Like with Joe [Jackson], he’d have set parts, and then with Loopestra, since you have no idea what it’s going to be, basically, it forces you to listen, I guess, that’s the only way to… you’re all sort of holding hands and jumping off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’m assuming these other musicians also enjoy being on the edge of the cliff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Some more than the others. [laughs] Yes. Some of them have gone “Was that good? I don’t even know.” When they say that, I’m like, “That means it was good.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When you think you don’t know, that’s where you want to live for this gig.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I love that, oh man, that’s good… and what about audiences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Well… that’s an interesting point, because it can get self indulgent if a drummer, let’s say, decides that he’s going to be Mr. Odd-time-weirdo-loud-non-dynamic-guy, the ladies in the audience would not be happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;However, if the drummer decides that he’s going to be Mr. Pay-attention-to-the-room, look around, see who’s holding their ears, very dynamic, super groove oriented, sometimes a little bit spicy, weird for taste, then the ladies will hang. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0Xzm0ON4iDo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And your gigs are… I mean I watched one at the Smithtown public library. I was born in Smithtown, so it was like, “oh!”…. and my aunt  does a lot of political work there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: There you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So it was cool, but you could tell, at least, listening, there seemed to be a lot of older women in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Those older women loved it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I think partially, because of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawn_Pelton&quot;&gt;Shawn Pelton&lt;/a&gt;, the guy who’s playing drums with me… He’s good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: He’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: He’s the master at it. He knows how to make it happen. They’re eating it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And you had no bass player. It was just the two of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, yeah. I played some bass parts in that show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So what is your… has your electronics rig kind of grown into something to support the Loopestra?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, because it’s all about sort of on-the-fly access to a wide variety of sounds. I’ve cultivated, you know of, an array of probably… I don’t know, I have never counted them, but maybe there’s 40 levels of little tidbits of information there that could be turned on and off and I’m generally a one-at-a-time kind of guy. I’m not a big fan of turning on 17 different effects at the same time and seeing what happens… I’m more of a very specific and, you know, “Let’s get a delay” &lt;em&gt;makes sounds&lt;/em&gt;, “rock guitar chord on a down beat,” “let’s get another thing”… &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;and then you just build a vocabulary within the framework. So it’s… in that respect, it’s not completely improvised, because you do have you know, when you’re speaking words, you know words and they’re going to come up in sentences, right?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yep. But you’re pretty busy. I mean, when you’re playing, it’s not just the guy playing guitar. I mean, you’re turning loops on and off, you’re changing the pitch, you’re shifting the pitch of what you’re playing. What are some of the tools of your trade in the Loopestra?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: That’s the looping aspect of it, yeah. The previous thing I talked about was the sound element, where you have a variety of sound. But for the looping aspect, I have a rig set up to go through 2 diff amps in stereo, so one thing can come out in the right and one thing can come out in the left. I’m not a fan of stereo effects necessarily, where things are like ping-ponging back and forth between 2 amps. I’m more of a fan of it sounding like a record where there’s a rhythm guitar player on the right and a bass guitar player on the left. Those things can go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I have a way of turning off a whole side of information. I have a way of turning off a specific loop, so I have access to making 4 loops at a time and they can all be on both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, ok. So you’re signal routing in addition to thinking about what you’re playing, in addition to thinking about what instrument your guitar’s going to be sounding like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you’re thinking texturally, sonically, spatially…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Mm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Was that super difficult at first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I mean, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it took me about 2 years to develop the rig to the point where I liked it&lt;/span&gt;. So, yeah. When I first started out, I had a Boss looper that had a guide track in it and I would experiment with it by putting the guide track through an amp, so it was sort of like a drum machine playing all the time through this amp that the drummer could hear and it was just–that had to always be there. It was annoying. So I figured, “Ok, I have to figure out a way to have a click track,” because otherwise how are you going to stay in time with the loops?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, that’s an interesting point, because some people would say, “Well, why don’t you just have a basic rhythm loop going to the drummer’s headphones and then he could always hear that and play along with it, right?”. Is that something that somebody would say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Somebody would say that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I’ve heard that many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I believe you’re correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: So, I tried that and recorded it and listened to it and I decided that - A) I don’t always want to have the beginning of the song have rhythm guitar, sometimes I want it to be ambient.  B) When I’m in a recording session with the drummer and I’m playing funky guitar, that thing is not metronomically correct necessarily. It sounds funkier when the rhythm guitar, at least my style of it, is sort of behind the beat, or sort of messing around with the beat, or…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Kind of what &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/ben-levin&quot;&gt;Ben Levin&lt;/a&gt; was talking about where he’d find an equal amount of time and it doesn’t have to be accurate, that’s what it gives it interest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Right, exactly. So I mean if I’m playing a reggae groove… I’m going to go “&lt;em&gt;um&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;um&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;um&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt;…”. I’m going to go, ““&lt;em&gt;um&lt;/em&gt; (slight delay) &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; (shorter delay)&lt;em&gt;um&lt;/em&gt; (slight delay) &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; (shorter delay)&lt;em&gt;um&lt;/em&gt; (shorter delay) &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt;.” Like swinging a little bit, or doing something weird with it, or play a 32nd note behind just for one of them. And the drummer knows what’s going on, because he could hear the click and me doing that against the click. So he can go “Oh, I see” right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And these guys are pros. They’re not messing around. So they’re not going to hear that and go, “Oh no, what’s going on?” They’d hear it and go, “I see, Teddy’s being weird. Ok, cool.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s interesting. So do you find that, or did you find when you’re doing the rhythmic looping in the ears… was that introducing bias into your choices while you were performing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Bias in terms of…?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, you might hear something and go “Oh well, that’s what I’m hearing in my hears and just going to play to that, or was that constraining you at all, in the choices you were making…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Hearing the click?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It sounded like you had at some point kind of a rhythm or drum or something before the click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Oh THAT thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, well with that thing, it was like a beat that would always be on, so you couldn’t turn it off and you couldn’t get away from it and it sounded really gross and it wasn’t helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And it was always in 4/4?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: No. The Boss has many different time signatures that all sound equally terrible. They designed that thing for a guy who’s playing by himself at a Holiday Inn lobby who is going to play his Bossanova, you know, (sings) “I Just Called to Say I Love You” and he needs a Bossa beat and he’s going to play like a little guitar and solo over it and maybe he’ll loop some background vocals later in the song or something. So they design it for that. They didn’t design it for somebody who’s going to get weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Right. You’re exploiting the tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’m seeing a lot of people do this kind of one-man-band kind of thing and layering percussion, salt shakers, whatever, but it seems that you’re primary sticking to the guitar and your loops. Have you explored building loops in that just aren’t guitar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I used to play kazoo or sing some stuff into the looper. I like that. It can be fun. That makes the setup bigger, which in New York isn’t necessarily good. But sometimes I still do that. I really don’t have any interest in being a 1-man band at all, so my thinking was never along those lines and how to get good at that. I always wanted it to be bass player and drummer and guitar trio with the extra stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you ever, or are you inspired by any particular people doing looping?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UXyHf_SpUUI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: The most inspiring guy to me is the guy who does this most simplest and the most one-man band, which is &lt;a href=&quot;http://reggiewatts.com&quot;&gt;Reggie Watts &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He is so good. The guy–just his feel, like how he can make something quarter notes so amazing. I’m a huge fan of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’m trying to get him for this site at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: He’d be great. I know his bass player really well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh. I’ll have to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Might have to talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah! Did you ever try something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ableton.com/&quot;&gt;Abelton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is built a lot around song structure, components, pieces?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I’ve tried that and I’ve found, for me, the foot pedal thing, is more solid as a tech on a gig for me. I know a lot of people that use that live and that’s fine. But I guess something with computers and me on a stage just doesn’t work really well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It kind of makes one more thing to bring and it does open up a lot more possibilities of what you can actually do, but that doesn’t necessarily help me. I think the limitations in my rig help. I think it’s good that I can only turn off one side at a time, or, you know, it’s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I agree. Constraints are a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, so I use an &lt;a href=&quot;http://pigtronix.com/infinity/&quot;&gt;Infinity Looper &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What’s that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: That’s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://pigtronix.com&quot;&gt;Pigtronix &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; looper. It has stereo in and stereo out and it has reverse pitch, has undo, has many, many different functions I think probably all the same ones that Ableton has, except instead of the foot pedal. Then I use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tcelectronic.com/ditto-x4-looper/&quot;&gt;TC Electronic Ditto 4 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that has some kind of weird–like, you can do stutter effects &lt;em&gt;makes sounds&lt;/em&gt;. You can do tape slow down &lt;em&gt;makes sounds&lt;/em&gt; stuff. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I always like to sing the effect when I’m telling the person. Is that ok? [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah! Absolutely. That’s why we’re here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: This stems from a New York session that I got called for once, where my friend Joey called me up and goes (in New Yorker accent) “Hey Teddy, I need you to come down here. I need you to bring your guitar and need you to bring a (&lt;em&gt;makes sounds&lt;/em&gt;) phase shifter and I need you to bring a &lt;em&gt;makes sounds&lt;/em&gt; wah wah.” This is a phone message that I got… it was just the classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I know so many people that talk just like that! [laughs] That’s awesome! How did you get hooked up with Joe Jackson?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Joe Jackson sent out an email to probably 20 of his ex-bandmates, or people he knew in the music business to try to find a guitar player who could sing and was good with effects. So one of them who used to play with him, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdbaby.com/Artist/AndyEzrin&quot;&gt;Andy Ezrin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, this keyboard player guy I know from college, got the email and he sent it to me and said, “Hey, you should do this, audition for Joe!”  and I said, “Oh yeah, I love Joe!” So I sent Joe an email and 6 other people recommended me and then I got to audition for him and he was super cool and we hit it off right away! There you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: When was this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: This was last summer, about a year ago&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh wow, this was pretty recent for you. You’ve been touring with him on and off from the past year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, this is our third tour. We did a US tour in October and November and we did an European tour in the Winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you play with any other acts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Right now? No, I’m busy enough with Joe and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I mean in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Oh, yeah, sure I’ve done a lot of stuff. I mean, played with &lt;a href=&quot;http://rickieleejones.com/&quot;&gt;Rickie Lee Jones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for a month on the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That must have been fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: You know, I grew up listening to her and I think kind of learned how to sing from her. So for me, it was a really spiritual experience to be with her and sing backgrounds with her and she liked my singing. She was really nice to me about that. But then right after that she went on to do another kind of project that she had a band up in California for, so we lost touch. But, yeah, I really enjoyed playing with her. She’s great–really freaky, kind of free-spirit. I did a background vocals gig for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nin.com/&quot;&gt;Nine Inch Nails &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; once, that was pretty amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/chNPM-rUCwI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: In studio, or live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: It was MTV Music Awards 1999. So it was at the Metropolitan Opera House and it was 6 days of rehearsal for one song and it was pretty deep, man. Trent really–he’s some detailed oriented stuff. Really amazing, and to watch him work and be control in every aspect.. lights, movement on stage, every single little detail he was into. It was very eye opening. It watched the dedication and hard work he put into it. It was pretty amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Trying to think of other people I’ve played with. I do of one-off things. I did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Today_(U.S._TV_program)&quot;&gt;Today Show &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; appearance with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feist_%28singer%29&quot;&gt;Feist &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was pretty fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: My wife LOVES Feist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Feist is great. I knew her before she was famous too and she’s been fun to watch her to do her thing. She’s so great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah. We found out about her through &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kings_of_Convenience&quot;&gt;Kings of Convenience &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Do you know them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_%26_Garfunkel&quot;&gt;Simon and Garfunkel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-type out of Norway. She did several songs with them on their albums but no one knew who she was. Great voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Yeah, amazing. I did a lot of playing with this guy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Brown_(Canadian_musician)&quot;&gt;Chris Brown &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s a Canadian producer. Actually him and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kate_Fenner&quot;&gt;Kate Fenner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, his song writing partner and band mate - they were in this band called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourbon_Tabernacle_Choir&quot;&gt;Bourbon Tabernacle Choir &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the, I guess the 80s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Great name!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2g77t_CnYM8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: That band, became &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_Social_Scene&quot;&gt;Broken Social Scene &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so Chris and Kate split off as their own thing and the rest of the people kind of went on to be involved with Broken Social Scene, which is where Feist came from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Okay, interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: So it’s like a whole Canadian contingent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You mentioned that you sang with your family growing up. But then, focused primarily on guitar after that. But I’m sure, obviously that you sing and play guitar. Anything about your vocal development - is that something you’ve focused on particularly hard or is it just natural coming from your family?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Both, I think. I always sang when I was a kid. I was in the all-state choir. Chorus in high school, I was always singing. I never really sang pop songs until college, when I did those top-40 gigs. I sort of just learned by listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stevie_Wonder&quot;&gt;Stevie Wonder &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Gabriel&quot;&gt;Peter Gabriel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and Rickie Lee, kind of emulating my heroes. I used to always joke that my warm up was a hamburger and a cigarette for singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This was back in the old days. Now I think it’s just drinking a lot of water and humming a lot helps, but I don’t have any real philosophy of singing, except to… it’s sort of the same on the guitar. I’m not a… &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I studied the guitar a lot and come to realization that being yourself is the most important thing - so… doesn’t require thought to do that necessarily. It’s more like getting.. you can study a lot and get a lot of things together on the guitar, but really what you want… what I want to do is to have a direct connection between my emotions, I guess, or soul, or whatever you want to call it to the instrument. So there’s no filter between those things. Just whatever you come up with on the spot is what you’re going to do.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Tell me how you developed to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I think just doing it. I don’t know. &lt;span class=&quot;importnat&quot;&gt;I don’t think there’s any way to develop that except by–you can’t think that through. You can have that philosophy and say that’s what I’m going to do and then you do it, then realize, “Oh, it takes a lot more relaxation than sort of mind over matter kind of focus to get to that than you think it does.” You’re sort of getting into your own way, right?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Absolutely! Yeah. You study technique. You study other people’s music, but there’s no real instruction on who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you feel like that you found yourself musically a long time ago, or has that been fairly recent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I think by the early 90s, I was fairly well in myself, yeah. I’ve learned how to do that better over the years and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think playing with other people and being a side man helps me find my voice within other music, which helps me find my own voice within my music too, you know. So they all kind of go hand in hand.&lt;/span&gt; There’s no real one moment when I said, “Oh yeah, now I’m who I’m supposed to be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I know people who’ve had that and I’m always like, “Wow.” Sometimes through drugs and I’m like, “Wow, well, I’m glad I didn’t have to do THAT to get there!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, no kidding. What about relaxation? What makes you emphasize that as one of your key points?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think when your mind is focused and relaxed, you can let more of yourself through&lt;/span&gt;, you know. You’re not uptight about what’s going to happen, or pre-thinking what’s going to happen, necessarily, even if it’s set music, if it’s something that’s pre-decided or prearranged, you’ve got to be in the moment. You can’t be thinking, “Oh, here it comes! That part… oh geez! [laughs] &lt;em&gt;makes Groan noise&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: “There it went!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Brace for it! [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: The word “weird” in Make Weird Music is more about that, like finding your voice and realizing that you’re not someone else, musically - that if you’re trying to be somebody else, then you’re not being weird. Everyone’s weird. Can you tell me your take on “weird” and why we’re here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e1BiSGOOuR4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Liebman&quot;&gt;Dave Liebman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you know who that is? Saxophone player? Played with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis&quot;&gt;Miles Davis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, really amazing teacher and player. I was lucky enough to sit in on one of his saxophone clinics for Dave, because I drove my friend there and he said something that blew me away. He said that there’s 3 stages… real New York guy, (&lt;em&gt;in New York accent&lt;/em&gt;,) &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“3 stages to every musician’s career. You’ve got imitator, everybody starts out imitating - gotta do it. 2nd stage. Stylist. You became yourself within a style of music. Very good for you. 3rd stage. Innovator - nobody gets there. Couple of guys.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So like.. wow, that’s brilliant and sort of like encapsulates the whole thing, you know. I’d be happy to be myself within a style of music, whatever that style is. I guess my style is sort of incorporating a lot of styles together, which you’d like to think it makes a new style, but really it’s a bunch of things mixed together. So, it’s up to the critics to decide if it’s a new style or not, I suppose. Did I answer your question? [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Sure. Whatever [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Question shmestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I don’t even know why I’m here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, I really appreciate you taking the time to tell us all about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: I appreciate you coming all the way over here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Thanks a lot Teddy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Thanks for having me! Appreciate it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Thanks man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;T: Alright! Thanks Conan!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/teddy-kumpel/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/teddy-kumpel/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discover Phish</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-little-about-phish&quot;&gt;A LITTLE ABOUT PHISH&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phish is an improvisation-focused rock quartet formed in Burlington, Vermont and consisting of members &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Anastasio&quot;&gt;Trey Anastasio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (guitars, lead vocals), &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Gordon&quot;&gt;Mike Gordon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (bass, vocals), &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon_Fishman&quot;&gt;Jon Fishman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (drums, percussion, vacuum, vocals), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Page_McConnell&quot;&gt;Page McConnell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (keyboards, vocals). Their stylistically whimsical and genre-defying music includes hints of rock, jazz, country, progressive rock, folk, funk, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-so-weird&quot;&gt;WHAT’S SO WEIRD?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of Phish’s work makes use of the following weird music techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time Signatures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Composition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virtuosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surrealism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atonality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6TIGxcghQzY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-care&quot;&gt;WHY I CARE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 1995 my musical interests were deeply rooted in the psychedelic blues of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd&quot;&gt;Pink Floyd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the statistical density of composers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igor_Stravinsky&quot;&gt;Stravinsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ravel&quot;&gt;Ravel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Zappa&lt;/a&gt;. My ears were ever searching for interesting harmonies, complex &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyrhythm&quot;&gt;polyrhythms &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atonality&quot;&gt;atonal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consonance_and_dissonance&quot;&gt;dissonance &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; while also maintaining roots in groove oriented blues and rock. It was a crossroad in my life. I was graduating from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thrash_metal&quot;&gt;thrash &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_metal&quot;&gt;death metal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoner_rock&quot;&gt;70s stoner rock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to more sophisticated rock music stylings. Coming from a history lightly battered in classical music sensibilities, I was lucky enough to have developed a bit of an ear for the weird and unorthodox in music and was well on my way to discovering and becoming engrossed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_rock&quot;&gt;Progressive Rock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was about this time that a good friend and accomplice in music recommended I take a listen to a weird little band from Vermont called Phish. What struck me first was the name: Phish. I mean, why was it spelled that way? The first album I tucked into was called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junta_(album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Junta&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; another oddity in nomenclature. Needless to say, I was right off the bat intrigued. My intrigue heightened when I learned that they had a fan newsletter called &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.phish.net/forum/show/1303154865&quot;&gt;Doniac Schvice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which was comprised of nonsensical stories, poems, puzzles, anecdotes, instructions and surreal art provided ‘from fish to tongue.’ I haven’t even heard the music yet and I’m having fun. This should be good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening to &lt;em&gt;Junta&lt;/em&gt; was, for me, a pretty life changing experience. I had simply never heard any music like this (this was before I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatfield_and_the_North&quot;&gt;Hatfield and the North &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Health&quot;&gt;National Health &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but more on that in another discovery). It was comical, cartoonish, whimsical, dark, surreal, absurdist, atonal, harmonic, virtuosic, psychedelic and rocking all at once. Until I found (and subsequently became obsessed with) Zappa, I had never heard something so bizarrely unique in rock music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CzWqHvSkQZI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the next–well, still actually, I followed the career of this band eating up everything I could get my ears on. I got all their albums which, as it turned out, only scratched the surface of their body of work. I learned that their live shows were ever changing and that no two performances ever sounded the same as they were incredible improvisors that made a point to explore musicality at every show. Songs became ‘vehicles’ of sonic exploration and going to a Phish show typically entailed getting tickets to several concurrent shows or following the band on tour a la the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grateful_Dead&quot;&gt;Grateful Dead &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to hear all the different permutations of their songs via improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all comparisons to the Grateful Dead aside, Phish has maintained an incredible body of work that is altogether weird, beautiful, organic, dissonant, and exploratory. As far as weird music is concerned, Phish, in my opinion, should be touted up alongside Zappa, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/the-residents&quot;&gt;The Residents&lt;/a&gt;, and others as a cornerstone of the ‘genre.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-should-hear-first&quot;&gt;WHAT YOU SHOULD HEAR FIRST&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to pinpoint specific albums for different ideas because each record covers so much ground. Also, the recorded works are really only a fraction of what’s available to enjoy. So I’ll cover a few compositions that are core to the Phish experience and you can explore as you will from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a well-rounded ‘This is Phish’ experience: &lt;em&gt;Harry Hood&lt;/em&gt; off of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Live_One&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Live One&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Reba&lt;/em&gt; off of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawn_Boy&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lawn Boy&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There is also an amazing live rendition available on YouTube &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/cnJlBWjDeXA&quot;&gt;here &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/AKmIV1SY9gY&quot;&gt;here &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cnJlBWjDeXA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For completely weird, Zappa-esque outlandishness: &lt;em&gt;David Bowie&lt;/em&gt; off of &lt;em&gt;Junta&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Split Open and Melt&lt;/em&gt; off of &lt;em&gt;Lawn Boy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For compositional complexity: &lt;em&gt;All Things Reconsidered&lt;/em&gt; off of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rift_(album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rift&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Fluffhead/Fluff’s Travels&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Junta&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For balls-to-the-wall guitar rock: &lt;em&gt;Chalkdust Torture&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Picture_of_Nectar&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Picture of Nectar&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Run Like an Antelope&lt;/em&gt;, again from &lt;em&gt;Lawn Boy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For wonderful melody and songwriting: &lt;em&gt;Horn&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Rift&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Esther&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Junta&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Divided Sky&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Junta&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you’re looking for something REALLY out there, check out &lt;em&gt;Dave’s Energy Guide&lt;/em&gt; or any improvisation labeled &lt;a href=&quot;http://phish.net/song/daves-energy-guide&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;DEG&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Phish has provided so much improvised content over their career that there is a meta-labeling system to help categorize different ‘types of jams’ from their library of work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be foolish to try and pigeonhole Phish’s music into a specific label or category. They simply do too much different shit to fit into a single bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/phish/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/phish/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>33 in Buffalo</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I posted the &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai interview&lt;/a&gt;, MWM started getting a lot of attention. I got an email from Robbie while he was in Europe traveling with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/BannedFromUtopia/&quot;&gt;Banned from Utopia&lt;/a&gt; in October 2015. We ended up having a lot in common and connected via Facebook. He sent me a copy of his wonderful record and some YouTube videos and I knew we had to chat. So, we met on a rooftop in Manhattan while I was traveling for work and we made some MWM content. And here we are!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://treb-c-moon.wix.com/fullmoonfever&quot;&gt;Purchase Robbie Seahag’s &lt;em&gt;Full Moon Fever&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MK3rnPPAjQM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soundslice-notation-and-tablature&quot;&gt;Soundslice Notation and Tablature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living sheet music brought to you by &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Wanna know more? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;our interview with Soundslice co-creator, Adrian Holovaty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/46301/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/33-in-buffalo/33-in-buffalo.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/33-in-buffalo/33-in-buffalo.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-transcript&quot;&gt;Video Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Ant: This is Anthony with Make Weird Music and I’m here with Robbie Seahag Mangano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Robbie: Hi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And, Robbie, why don’t you tell us about what you’re going to show us from your album, &lt;a href=&quot;http://treb-c-moon.wix.com/fullmoonfever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Full Moon Fever&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: Okay. As you’ve requested to see about &lt;em&gt;33 in Buffalo&lt;/em&gt;… The number 33 actually has to do with the time signature of that whole riff. So it’s 10 notes, then another 10, then another 10, and then 3. So we got 33.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Is that in standard tuning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: It’s in standard tuning. A friend of mine thought it was without open strings, but that sounds a little too hard to figure out. This was actually pretty hard to figure out because of this little move right there [hiding the middle finger under the others to slide on the high e string].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Ahhh… I was trying to slide with my pinky on the B string when I was figuring it out, but the fingering was too big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: And that last note, I pick with the middle finger [on the right hand] because I’m never going to get the pick there in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Where did the song come from? What inspired it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: I play all day at home. Not all day, but there’s a guitar in a stand and the rest of them in cases all over the place. But, I pick it up and if I come across something I’ve never played before and try to get good at it. Especially if there’s a mistake. So that one came out as–maybe the notes came one at a time. And I wanted these notes instead of something easy like [plays an alternate phrase with open strings].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: And also, it has a lot to do with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Close_Encounters_of_the_Third_Kind#Soundtrack&quot;&gt;Close Encounters theme &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s also influenced by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaco_Pastorius&quot;&gt;Jaco Pastorius &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, which one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: It’s off &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaco_Pastorius_(album)&quot;&gt;his first solo record &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s the one with the harmonics. I can’t remember the name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v_kv_UjIM7Y?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It’s a girl’s name, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: No, that’s Portrait of Tracy. This ostinato thing and he has a horn going and that sounds like my thing. So that’s where I think that kind of comes from, loving those melodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Right! Those intervals. Did you intend to write something in 10 + 10 + 10 + 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: Yes. At that point, I was thinking about the number 33 a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Interesting. Why’s that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: I’m into numbers. I’m not really sure why. Percentage is an interesting thing when there’s 3 people and there’s a split-up of something and it’s 33 1/3. If you’re going to split anything up it’s that 33 thing. That 33.333333. And they say that Jesus died at 33. It’s not like they would really know, but maybe there’s this secretive 33 thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Right. The freemasons and the 33rd degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: Right! I don’t know much about it, but if you do, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And what about the next part of the song? What about that? How do you play that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: I wanted to make 100, so I added one more note. Something about 33.33333 makes me unstable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It’s unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: So when I got to the last note, it’s 99 when I do it 3 times. So when I hit this last one, it’s 100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: If you get paid by the note on this song, then you know exactly how much to charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;R: Exactly. First verse is $100. There’s overdubs on the next section [plays harmonies].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we start talking through the chords and intervals. And we wrap it up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/33-in-buffalo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/33-in-buffalo/</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zon Michael Manring Hyperbass</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;zon-michael-manring-hyperbass&quot;&gt;Zon Michael Manring Hyperbass&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager, I saw a video of Michael Manring playing a 3-octave bass with dynamic tuning capabilities and sorta became obsessed with the idea of owning one. In the late 1990s, the price was around $7,000. A brief Google search yields used ones for ~$10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/michael-manring&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Michael Manring is? Check out our interview with him! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check out our &lt;a href=&quot;/concert/michael-manring&quot;&gt;private house concert with Michael featuring Andy West&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was always a fantasy of mine to see him play live, so I flew him out to our house for a house concert (video coming soon!) in April 2016. Not only did I get to see Michael play, but I got to have his wonderful instruments in my home for a few hours! Michael was gracious enough to do an interview about the instrument before the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_9LgUKKCmDs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/hyperbass/hyperbass.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/hyperbass/hyperbass.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hey, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with Michael Manring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Michael: Hi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Uh, in my bedroom studio. So, thank you for traveling out here, Michael.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: My pleasure. Thank you for having me, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, I wanted to talk about instruments that provide a unique voice for musicians and you certainly have one of those instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I know something about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, can you tell us about the bass you have today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, this is officially known as the “Zon Michael Manring Hyperbass.” It’s a bass that Joe Zon and I designed together almost 25 years ago now and the idea was that there were a lot of different design possibilities that we wanted to try out on an instrument. We kind of decided, “Well, let’s put them all on one instrument and see what happens.” We weren’t banking on it being a success. It’s a prototype. That’s what it is; an experiment to see what would work and what didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We ended up–I was gonna say we ended up being lucky, but what happened is Joe Zon is just really good at what he does and everything works beautifully. So, the instrument really works so well as an integrated whole, but it’s kind of its own beast and it’s just been a joy for me. It’s really opened up a whole lot of possibilities that wouldn’t be there otherwise. It’s a thrill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So what makes this instrument different from a regular 4-string fretless bass?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: So, a couple things. Probably the most obvious design change in this is the fingerboard is especially long. A standard bass fingerboard ends about here [points at the 21st fret] and then there’s a standard that ends here [points at the 24th fret] and this little bit is almost an additional octave because the notes get closer together as you go up the neck. So, extending it this far gives a lot more range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;However, the idea behind this wasn’t necessarily about having more range as much as it was we couldn’t figure out why not to do it. We knew where we wanted the pickup to be and we couldn’t think of why the fingerboard should end at some point before that and so we thought, “Well, we’ll just extend the fingerboard to the pickup and see what happens.” I don’t tend to do a lot of direct playing in this last little area of the fingerboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Occasionally it’s real nice to have. But, there’s other things that happen because I have fingerboard there that have ended up being really, really exciting. There’s lots of sounds I can make on that part of the fingerboard with my picking hand, my right hand, that really have become an important part of what I do. So that’s been a really nice thing and as time goes on, I’ve been kind of working on playing in this super stratosphere. It’s really kind of nice to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;With bass, you’re always kind of running out of notes when you’re going for that extreme moment. That’s never going to happen on this instrument. There’s always more to play than I can usually manage to get to. So that’s the first thing about this. And then Joe decided to do a real deep cutaway so it’s not too hard to get up here. I have to kind of decide to go on top of the cutaway or underneath it in my fingerings that I use. And I’ll do either one depending on what kind of passage I’m playing, but it’s kind of nice to have that option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Is it the full width of the body behind the neck? Is there any sort of special shaping for your hand to reach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: There’s no bevel. It’s just a straight cut back and in instruments we’ve been doing since this one–as I said, this one was the first prototype like this–he’s been doing some different shaping with that part of the instrument to see what works. It’s a lot of fun. I don’t know if there’s a right or wrong way to do it, but it’s kind of nice to see what can be done. So, yeah, that’s kind of the first thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Another interesting thing about this instrument that’s not immediately visible is the electronics. We wanted to do some different things with the electronics on this instrument and so one of the things that’s happening is underneath this pickup cover, there’s four separate pickups, one for each string. There’s a humbucking pickup for each string. So that gives me the ability to plug each string into a different amplifier or a different channel in a mixing board and really deal with each string individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And this is something I’d been wanting to do for a long time and I just find really thrilling because it just opens up a ton of things you can do. I suppose it’s kind of obvious that you can do completely bizarre, crazy things, like put a massive amount of fuzz tone on one string and have the others clean, and that’s a lot of fun. But, often I’ll just use it kind of subtly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If I’m recording–I use it mostly when I’m recording solo bass music and so I can have, for instance, the same reverb sound across all four strings, but it can be shorter on the low strings so I can have a rich reverb that doesn’t cloud up as much. I can have different kinds of compression on each string, all kinds of EQ, and panning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I can do panning differently with the strings and that’s something that has ended up being really thrilling to me. Just the panning thing alone, the sound that it makes really is something that really impresses me. If you have sound moved across a sonic canvas of some kind, it really behaves in a different way than if it’s all coming out of one thing. So, right, so that’s the quadrophonic magnetic pickup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In addition to those four outputs, Joe built into the body ceramic pickups. There’s one up here [by the horn], one down here [on the lower horn], there’s one here [by the arm rest], and there’s one up here [in the headstock by the truss rod] in the headstock. And then the signal from those goes back here [flips over the bass]. There’s a little trim pot mixer, these little trim pots you can move with your fingernail so you can decide how much of each of those you want to have in the mix, so if you want to have just one in a separate output, you can do that. You can do different things with that where you can mix in different ways. And that comes out on a fifth output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;All these outputs work together out of a really nice multi-output jack by a company called Lemo Jack. It was a very expensive, groovy part of this instrument, using this Lemo Jack to do the multiple output. In addition to that, Joe figured out how all of those could be summed together so I could play this instrument in mono. I was so excited about these possibilities that it never really occurred to me that it’s kind of wildly impractical to have five inputs any time you want to play the instrument, so Joe built a mono output into this instrument as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;All these outputs are summed and you can still control the mix of the transducers, which is nice, and those come out a regular 1/4” output, just like any other instrument, and in fact, that’s the one I end up using most of the time just because it’s logistically so much easier. But, I love recording with the multiple output. So, that’s kind of the electronic aspect of this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then finally, probably the most bizarre thing about this instrument is that we designed it for dynamic tuning. For many years, I’d been interested in using different tunings on the bass. The bass is incredibly receptive to altered tunings and when you change the tuning, these kind of wonderful magical things happen. I just got very into this concept and realized there’s so much you can do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s so many different tunings you can do with the bass that I really wanted to keep moving beyond that and to go to the next level with it. And one of the places I wanted to go was into this area of dynamic tuning. So, not only is it about using these unusual tunings for the bass, these altered non-standard tunings on the bass, but being able to move those and change through those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I started trying to do that just by turning the tuning keys while I was playing. And that’s okay, you can kind of do a little bit with that, but I really wanted to take it a lot further than that and that was probably the biggest challenge from a design standpoint. Joe and I talked about this for a long time and talked about various systems we could do and we designed a few systems that we couldn’t afford to build. But we ended up with this system, which has really worked amazingly well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What’s happening is that here at the headstock, we are using Hipshot Extender Keys. And this is actually a relatively standard add-on device for a bass. It’s designed to be put on your low string, typically on the low E string, and the tuning key sits on a kind of plate and when I move this lever, the whole tuning key tilts, just the tension of the string causes the tuning key to tilt. You can use that to drop your E string to a D or a C or a B. Really whatever you want. You can set it up with this little set screw in the back. And so these are two right-handed Hipshots and these are two left-handed Hipshots. I have one on each string here and it allows me to change the tuning of each string individually here at the headstock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Can you play us just a few notes to show us how it works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Sure! [Plays harmonics and changes tunings.] So it’s a really nice tool to have. It really opens up a lot of possibilities. One of the things I discovered is that I really like the sound of the tunings moving. Just how it sounds when the bass moves, which is not something I expected necessarily and I often write pieces around that, just the moving of the tunings because to me it’s an appealing sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So in addition to this system, we did a system here at the bridge as well because we really wanted to do as much as we could at the time given the constraints of the technology and the amount of money we had to put into this. So, this bridge is one that Zon makes and it’s a little hard to explain. What happens is each string kind of sits on a kind of a tray and underneath the bridge, so they’re basically flat on one side and rounded on the other and these levers turn the cams. The trays, there are little set screws on the trays, and when I turn the cams, that causes the trays to move up and down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You can set what you want the tunings to be with the set screws in the bridge. The bridge is designed to do three different tunings. You have a high tuning, a medium tuning, and a low tuning, more or less whatever you want within some limits. It depends on a lot of things like the gauge of the string and the tension of the string, things like that. Even how you set up the bridge makes a difference. But it does give you some really cool possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As you move through the tunings in the bridge, you don’t have to have all the strings change, too. I usually set this bridge up, in fact, so that from the high position to the low position, the two high strings stay the same and then to the low position, dropping down all four strings. It doesn’t have to be that way, but it’s a thing I like to do with moving just two strings or all four or whatever you want to do. So, yeah, and then that moves all four strings like this. I’m moving all four strings a whole step. This is Bb, F, Bb, F and [flicks the cam on the bridge] now it’s Ab, Eb, Ab, Eb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I use these two systems in combination to–it gives me a chance to go through a whole lot of tunings [manipulates both bridge and headstock tuners.] In one piece. And I think that’s pretty much it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That is pretty incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, let’s get some footage of you playing. Let’s see if we can get this 5-output thing going. Thanks a lot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: You bet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/hyperbass</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/hyperbass</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
