<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 12:09:49 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 12:09:49 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>King Crimson Concert Thoughts</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;warning&quot;&gt;Warning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a music critic, nor am I particularly qualified to deliver musical criticism, so these are my personal thoughts on attending the King Crimson Friends &amp;amp; Family concert on June 11, 2017 in Seattle. My intention is to be positive. I have some criticism of the show at the bottom, which I didn’t include in my Facebook note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts&quot;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, I saw King Crimson perform in its new 8-headed beast configuration (3 drummers, 2 guitarists, 1 woodwind, 1 bassist, 1 keyboardist). It was an absolutely incredible concert. They performed for more than three hours across two sets of complex music proving themselves to be one of the most present, focused, energetic, and powerful configurations of the band’s 48-year history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true highlight of the evening for me was a ripping performance of Fracture, a song I never believed I would see KC perform in my lifetime. &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;I have been studying and failing to play this impossible song for almost 20 years&lt;/a&gt;. This band, with its 71-year-old founding guitarist, performed it with new life at a breakneck pace (I’m guessing 136-138 beats per minute during the grueling moto perpetuo). The performance of this song was an unforgettable life experience for me and left me stunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9ySAvqgX0Rs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arrangement included a beautiful passing of notes between &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakko_Jakszyk&quot;&gt;Jakko Jakszyk &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, incredible percussive and drum additions across the three (three!) drummers, a deeper exploration of the song’s motifs, and a new musical direction after the moto perpetuo. The performance and arrangement were so impressive, the performers received a near-immediate standing ovation. The friends and family crowd were screaming, standing in the aisles between seats, clapping above their heads, and shaking their heads in disbelief. It was the kind of performance that kicked you out of your seat and made you feel like you could run a marathon. It was overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t spoil any more of the setlist, but it is worth noting there is brand new KC music being performed and some great additions to the band’s repertoire. And the decades-old music being performed takes on a new life. Robert has said that the music is new no matter when it is being performed, which is philosophically true, but I can personally attest that this lineup brings new life to many KC “standards.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8-headed Crimson is significantly better than the 7-headed incarnation I saw in Los Angeles on September 30, 2014. They clearly have much more internal alignment and practice as a band. I remember several rough spots during that show, which was still a great show but did not make quite the impression this new KC made last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every band member contributed meaningfully to the performance. Throughout the show, I would look at someone in the band and think, “Wow, what an amazing player! I love what he’s doing tonight!” Near the end of the first set, I realized I had done that for each of the eight members. I entered the second set with complete admiration and respect for the musicians on stage, each performing at the top of their game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FhKJgqxNDD8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mel_Collins&quot;&gt;Mel Collins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was the highlight of the 2014 show for me, and he was equally impressive last night. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was shredding on the Stick and bass like I’ve never seen, even after catching &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stick_Men_(prog_band)&quot;&gt;Stick Men &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in January in Phoenix. Jakko played several extremely difficult guitar lines, offered a very solid and passionate vocal performance, and still had energy through the end of the encore. He clearly gave his all. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Riefin’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; keyboard parts were great and contributed a lot of atmosphere that rounded out the songs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeremy_Stacey&quot;&gt;Jeremy Stacey’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; drums were a beautiful complement to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Mastelotto&quot;&gt;Pat Mastelotto’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; percussive exploration and sound library. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gavin_Harrison&quot;&gt;Gavin Harrison &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was… well, Gavin Harrison–a precise master of his craft with excellent tone and clarity at every tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, of course, there’s Robert. This is a man that has had such profound impact on me and many others. In fact, I was in Seattle for a “Seattle Guitar Work Weekend” led by Steve Ball (&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-ball&quot;&gt;see our interview with Steve on MWM&lt;/a&gt;). What struck me most about Robert last night was not his playing nor his smiling throughout the show (some smiles of joy, some smiles of laughing at mistakes). What struck me most about Robert was the community he has built around the world, particularly in Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seattle Guitar Work Weekend was a wonderful event bringing together a group of guitarists (and a few non-guitarists) from across the globe to make and appreciate music together. Some of the musicians in the group have known each other and performed together for decades. These are people who connected via Robert and his Guitar Craft/Guitar Circle efforts. Steve Ball and several other Seattle-based guitarists have familial relationships through music, craft, and love. What Robert has brought together in these people is so special and so far beyond the music. I am awed and humbled to have been invited to take part in a very small way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert’s impact on these good human beings is profound. He has helped foster an adoration of silence, understanding of self, mastery of craft, and love for others through music, relationships, and study. And these achievements have changed the course of my own life and my own relationship with music and the guitar. I cannot overstate the significance of what I’ve experienced through the Guitar Circle teachings and through the relationships I’ve been privileged to have through the Guitar Circle. And I cannot overstate the impact I’ve seen in others much more experienced than I. Several of us flew thousands of miles just to participate in the Guitar Work Weekend and to attend the KC show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Robert played incredibly last night. Yes, he wrote some great music. Yes, he has assembled a cadre of expert musicians that will melt thousands of faces this year. But most importantly to me, he has selflessly given himself to music and to others in a way that’s only understood when you spend some time with his friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[NOTE for KC fans, I filmed an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Singleton&quot;&gt;David Singleton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before the show and another interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/instrofreak&quot;&gt;Alex Anthony Faide &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube-play&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the only other guitarist in the world that can play Fracture. So stay tuned on the site for more KC-related fun…]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/227L6FW30ZA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the live show in 2014, the sound was poorly mixed in Seattle. It was really the only disappointing part of the experience, but it was a clear disappointment for myself and many others. For the first half of the first set, Tony’s bass and vocals could not be heard. For most of the show, Pat’s electronic drum pad couldn’t be heard. Robert’s guitar parts were hard to hear. Jakko’s amp sounded like it was submerged in a lake and key guitar parts were indiscernible in the mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the three drummers at the front of the stage is amazing for stage setup and visual presence, but it’s pretty brutal for the audience. When all three are playing at the same time, it’s nearly impossible to hear anything else, especially when the cymbals are blaring (there are a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of cymbal crashes throughout the show). Nearly all the frequencies of the band are smothered by the drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mix got much better into the second set, but it still wasn’t great. That being said, having done some live sound, I do not envy the work of a sound crew working with three entire drumsets and unamplified instruments. It’s an incredibly difficult task, but some of the mix was difficult to excuse. Key guitar parts were too quiet or inaudible in certain songs, which made me feel like the sound engineers were unfamiliar with the music. In fact, two of my favorite/most anticipated guitar parts were nearly inaudible in the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept wondering if Robert or David had sat in the venue to listen to a song or two being performed because it was legitimately distracting. Everyone I talked to was disappointed with the sound. The show in 2014 was so, so badly mixed, but that may have been due to the fact that I sat up front. Nevertheless, I remember I couldn’t hear bass or vocals at that show, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that as they get further into the tour, the sound and mixing quality improves. Part of the risk of attending a Friends &amp;amp; Family show is you are the testing audience, but the performances all night were so strong that the sound issues stunted the potential of the performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2017 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/king-crimson-concert-2017</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/king-crimson-concert-2017</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>David Singleton</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;David Singleton is a multi-talented songwriter, producer, audio engineer, record executive, tour manager, author, and more. He is best known for his work at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgmlive.com/&quot;&gt;Discipline Global Mobile &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [DGM], the company behind &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;. David is also behind a semi-fictional persona in the music industry called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Vicar_(music_producer)&quot;&gt;The Vicar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, producing not only a very interesting album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://shop.schizoidshop.com/the-vicar---songbook-1-cd-p1324.aspx&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Songbook #1&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but a whole universe around the character including &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/graphic_novel.html&quot;&gt;graphic novels &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/novel1.html&quot;&gt;written novels &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/videoblog1.html&quot;&gt;video blog series &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s extremely creative and huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met with David during the Seattle Guitar Work Weekend in June 2017, a collaborative music effort led by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; including around 20 ex-&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft/Circle &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; participants. The work weekend culminated in a &lt;a href=&quot;/share/king-crimson-concert-2017&quot;&gt;King Crimson Friends &amp;amp; Family concert&lt;/a&gt;. David and I talked in the historic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Lang_Studios&quot;&gt;Robert Lang Studios &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about his music and what’s going on with King Crimson through 2019, making a living as a musician, digital music streaming, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy this very enlightening conversation in video and podcast formats below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com&quot;&gt;Check out The Vicar’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tnCu8N4Zmuc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/david-singleton/david-singleton.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/david-singleton/david-singleton.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have a very special guest with me today. It’s David Singleton, all the way from England. Thank you so much for joining. We met last night and had a great conversation about music. I’d love to continue that, but can you introduce yourself and talk a little about what you do for yourself and for King Crimson?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Well, I’m David and probably the main thing I do is I run DGM, which is not really a label, but the company I run with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which we started in 1993 as a way of bringing music into the world and trying to solve the always-clumsy relationship between music and commerce. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s really our core being: to try to find ways of honoring the music, bringing the music into the world, and trying to ensure that–if there is money involved–that artists get paid correctly.&lt;/span&gt; We started that in 1993 and we’re still at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We handle three artists. We formally handle King Crimson, Robert Fripp, and The Vicar. In effect, we handle King Crimson and then the personal music of Robert and me. That’s probably the best way to put it. I don’t think we’re perfect, but I think over the years, we’ve found fairly good ways of accommodating the dilemma because it isn’t simple music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Music really has to be made for the right reasons, which are artistic reasons and therefore, I think when music is driven by commerce (rather than the other way around) it often isn’t perfect.&lt;/span&gt; It’s always challenging, actually, trying to figure out how you marry the two. That roughly is what I do. My background is as a songwriter and producer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I listened to The Vicar &lt;em&gt;Storybook #1&lt;/em&gt;. I loved it. I heard lots of influences from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andy_Partridge&quot;&gt;Andy Partridge &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XTC&quot;&gt;XTC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to some &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatles&quot;&gt;The Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Can you talk a little about your musical background and your involvement with The Vicar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pmuNV7GlKsY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Okay, so The Vicar is a fascinating project. My background is a songwriter and most of the songs on that album I wrote about 20 years ago. There’s a song on there called &lt;em&gt;Twenty Two&lt;/em&gt; that I wrote when I was 22. At the time, I was trying to write songs thinking that I might play them and I never liked any of the results. So, I wrote the songs and I didn’t know how to produce them and nobody else was playing them in a way I liked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I revisited them more recently, I surprisingly discovered that the person who could actually arrange and produce the songs that 22-year-old David could write was actually me in the future. In fact, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The Vicar is a strange collaboration between a younger me and an older me&lt;/span&gt;, both parts of which are really valid. I think, generally, younger people write very good pop songs. I think there’s a simplicity and an idealism that’s harder and harder to find as you get older. In fact, if you look at most of the things that most of us sing from the arts we love, actually were written most of the time before they were 30, whereas after that you develop other skills that are just as important, particularly musical skills and production skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I love this collision between a raw thing that I wrote–a lot of it did change, but there was a raw genesis written then and you produce it. With one of two of the songs, they were very changed. I always laugh at–there’s the story of the broom when someone says, “I’ve never replaced my broom ever. All I’ve ever done is replace the head five times and the handle four times, but I’ve never replaced my broom.” To some extent, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve always said there is no such thing as a bad song. There might be a bad melody and a bad lyric and a bad arrangement, but if you just change all of those, you’ve probably got a good song.&lt;/span&gt; So some of those songs have been slightly reinvented since the 22-year-old me wrote them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hNlHVGry9Wg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did you write them with the orchestration in mind? There’s so much going on…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: “No and yes and no” is the answer. When I was younger, I couldn’t have conceived of those exact orchestrations. I wouldn’t have been good enough to write them. But, some of those songs have been done with bass drums and guitar and I thought they died. People have played on them, but they were never intended to be played like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, the big decision with The Vicar album, which I didn’t realize, was the fact that there are no drums on it. That was a conscious decision partly because I hate it when you–if you have drums on something in particular, you start by laying down a click track and it’s this mechanical thing that everybody’s playing to. I’ve always hated that. I realized that I don’t hear drums in my head. This is a fault with me, I’d like to point out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If I ran a Beatles song in my head now–I could run you &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penny_Lane&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Penny Lane&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I can hear &lt;em&gt;Penny Lane&lt;/em&gt; in my head, I could talk to you about all the instruments, and oddly enough, I wouldn’t ever mention that there are drums. That’s not true of all Beatles songs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strawberry_Fields_Forever&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strawberry Fields&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something, but most Beatles songs, I realize I hear the orchestra, I can talk to you about what the guitar’s doing, the piano’s doing, the wonderful orchestration is doing, but I don’t hear the drums in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Even in something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Come_Together&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Come Together&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: No, there are songs where the drums are such a thing. That’s one song like that. But, a lot of them, I suppose where the drums are just holding the backbeat, I sort of take it for granted, but I don’t run it in my head. I thought, “Rather than this rule of being guided by drums, let’s imagine there are no drums.” Really, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;all of the orchestrations on the album were as a result of that one decision because the moment you take the drums away, now it’s great fun.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now your string part or whatever has got to fill in for what drums would have been doing for carrying the beat. I didn’t want to have any strummed guitars or drums. There’s nothing solidly strong carrying the beat. The album was what it was because of that very simple decision. I am a huge Beatles fan, but I think a lot of the reasons people hear it, even in the songs that I don’t think are particularly Beatle-esque actually, and they say, “Oh, but it’s so Beatle-esque…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think that’s simply because there aren’t that many people who’ve done that. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor_Rigby&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eleanor Rigby&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a classic example. But there aren’t a lot of artists who’ve gone away and done things that are obviously pop songs. Andy Partridge also goes to that interesting land. Oddly enough, I wanted him to sing &lt;em&gt;The Girl with the Sunshine in Her Eyes&lt;/em&gt;. I may yet persuade him, but Andy isn’t really comfortable singing over other people’s stuff. But, we’ll see. I’m still working on him for &lt;em&gt;Songbook #2&lt;/em&gt; because it’s an obvious match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you get into production and audio engineering and mixing and all that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: In the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s not much history out there. It’s just, “This is what he does.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Okay, well, it’s odd because I’ve always done it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My background is as a musician that doesn’t like practicing.&lt;/span&gt; That’s probably where I started. I was like that in school. I used to play instruments for about a year or two and once I thought I sort of understood the instrument, I wanted to compose for it, but I wasn’t interested in being able to play it. So, I played the cello for two years, I played the french horn for a bit. I played the piano quite a bit. I played the flute for a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Lo and behold, at some point or rather, the teacher said, “Really, you should be the conductor.” So at one point, when things were really bad at school, I used to conduct because I roughly understood all the instruments and I roughly understood the arrangements, but I couldn’t play very well. Then I started playing in bands. I used to play bass in bands. And similarly, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;because I had an overview, I ended up producing and saying, “Okay, I’ll produce it.” That’s why I first met Robert.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I really started as a sound engineer with Robert, but actually I was never–other than for him–I was never a sound engineer. I was really a producer. I started as a songwriter who became a producer and then I drifted into sound engineering, I think partly because it’s where the money is. The technology drove it like that. So the day when you were a producer and you sat in a studio, which I used to do, with an engineer sitting in front of you, was great, but actually after a while, the budgets were tighter or as things moved into computers, they said, “Actually, you’re now the sound engineer and the producer. It’s the same job, do them both.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So when I very first met Robert, it was purely as a sound engineer to mix a tour. I think the very next album I worked on was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sunday_All_Over_the_World&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sunday All Over The World&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I remember because they were struggling with the sequence of it and I said, “Well, try this sequence.” And Robert said, “Oh, okay, so you’re not really a sound engineer.” So, that’s really my background and Robert has always said that it’s inevitable that we would probably meet because he’s from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorset&quot;&gt;Dorset &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I was running a studio in Dorset. He said, “Actually, it’s a very small county, so hopefully if both of us were good at our jobs, it was inevitable at some point or another that we would come into the same orbit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And now you run a record label together. How has the transition been for you to go from music creation to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Ooh, I think I’m still in denial about “the suit” of my job. I was told the other day, “David, you’ve become a suit.” I’m still in denial about that part of the job. The label itself went through a cycle of being a label and we stopped. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, with DGM we started with this kind of attitude of, “Let’s start the label and we’ll bring the music into the world, place it into the world without having to obey market constructs.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/erWR2-_L_C8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When we make an album–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thrakattak&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thrakattack&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a perfect example. I don’t think any major label–I’m assuming here, by the way, that some of these people will know what I’m talking about. It’s an album based on King Crimson improvisations for one hour and I don’t think any sane record label would have said, “This is a really sane record release. That’s the one you should make.” But, actually with DGM, that’s not what we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We thought, “This is the album we should make. We’ll make it and once we’ve made it, we’ll work out how we might place it into the world.”&lt;/span&gt; So, we were doing that and because, possibly, we were doing it reasonably well, other people were keen we did it for them. There was a period of DGM–about the first 5 or 6 years–when it kept expanding. We had King Crimson, then we had the solo albums. We had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; solo albums, we had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Bruford&quot;&gt;Bill Bruford’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; solo albums, we had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Paul_Jones_(musician)&quot;&gt;John Paul Jones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This was fine and there was a point when I realized I now got out of bed and all I did was I ran a label and we had 20 employees. We had offices in LA and whatever, and I said, “This is not what I set out to be.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You can’t pretend anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: “I can’t pretend anymore and I don’t like it. This is taking me away from what I’m put on the planet to do.” So, we fortunately quietly persuaded everyone that they might like to find another home. It was in an honest way. And we moved DGM to what it is currently, which is just King Crimson, Robert Fripp, and The Vicar. It was wonderfully liberating. I still get a lot of calls from people saying, “Oh, you’re a label and I want you to do this,” and that’s not the business we’re in now. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is what we do because otherwise I’m just a suit trying to solve your problems for you. That’s not the business I want.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Last night you talked about bucking the trend of the industry. Can you tell us a little about what that means and how you’re getting there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: What I meant by bucking the trend–we were discussing how you make a living out of music and generally, music sales have been falling. Downloads, I think, are doing okay, but certainly overall, physical sales have been falling. If you go talk to one of the major labels, it’s been falling for a while. And ours are rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Personally I don’t think that’s surprising. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that there are perfectly good sales out there provided you want to do some work&lt;/span&gt;, which I’ve told the major labels when we go to conferences. In other words, if you want to be lazy and sack everybody and say, “I own this CD and all I want to do is just carry on selling this exact CD tomorrow,” you won’t. Those sales are disappearing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People are now moving to downloading and streaming them–and not stealing them as much as they were. Whereas, if you’re willing to add value and create things that people want to buy, there’s a very good physical market out there. So, the two things we’ve done is: the catalog really has been remastered and remixed and put out in surround sound, and every Christmas we’ve been doing a box set working through the albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Similarly, this isn’t a good example of what I meant about how you live with the market. This isn’t a crass, “We can make some money by putting the album in a box,” which I know some of the labels have tried and it doesn’t work. They’ll say, “Here it is and we’ll stick in a brochure and an extra CD of this, and here’s your box.” Whereas actually we do it in reverse. We say, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Okay, let’s look at this period and empty the archives and lovingly redo them.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2kfwJ8ExFJo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttps://www.dgmlive.com/news/the-road-to-red-tracklisting&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Road to Red&lt;/em&gt; box &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had about 24 CDs of all the shows from that tour plus the album plus the album in surround sound and a booklet that’s full of pictures. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, if you’re willing to seriously go through and honor the albums and present each of the periods, they work very well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Just to show how little we really allow the finances to run our world: it wasn’t until we’d done a few of those boxes that I realized that actually we unwittingly created a fairly major grossing item. Most of them are roughly 10,000 limited run. We can only make so many, so we make about 10,000 of these boxes. And they all sell for somewhere around the $100 range, depending on how many CDs we’ve had to put in. I just talked to Robert and said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Actually, you realize every Christmas, we’ve got a million-dollar grossing item in a world where physical sales don’t exist anymore.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right! And you had a great statement… well, “great” depending on who you ask. You said, “The world doesn’t owe creative people a living.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: No! That was the other thing we were discussing. It’s very difficult, I think, because a lot of people look at the world and there are artists making a living. But equally well, I don’t think the world does owe–that’s part of what I think the joint between arts and commerce is so complicated. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can be a very talented musician and the world doesn’t owe you a living.&lt;/span&gt; Each person has to come up with their answer to how they solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I suffer from that with The Vicar. The Vicar, I suppose, is my genuine heart, lifelong project and I’ve long since let go of the fact that The Vicar owes me a living. I’m dying to find ways of finding ears to listen to it, but I don’t think, “Hey wow, I’m going to become a rock star and the world’s going to listen to The Vicar.” If you go back in history, most of the composers probably had day jobs. They were either teachers or taxi drivers or… So, there is a living to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Oddly enough, I followed up on that conversation this morning with Robert, summarizing what we’d discussed. I realized there was another way of expressing it, which I didn’t use last night, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there is a difference between musicians and artists.&lt;/span&gt; You have to define those two terms. Artists, the world will often give a living to. But, musicians, it often won’t. You can be one of the greatest musicians in the world. Often artists may be, technically, a less good musician, but what I meant by that is the people who somehow speak to the soul of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s why, whoever it is that floats your boat, they speak to the soul. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Those people generally are giving people something they need.&lt;/span&gt; If you’re giving people something they need, they usually will pay for it to some degree, whereas there are a lot of other people who are called to music and are just as passionate about it–“I have to do music and music is what I am”–it doesn’t always earn a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: DGM just put &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radical_Action_to_Unseat_the_Hold_of_Monkey_Mind&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Radical Action&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; out &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttps://open.spotify.com/album/0ga8Q4tTXaFf9q3LvT8hrC&quot;&gt;on Spotify &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-spotify&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and for any King Crimson fan, it was almost sacrilegious. It was like, “How can this possibly have happened?” Can you talk a little bit about the years of…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: The wonderful thing about that with Spotify is that when we–I’ll come to why we did it, but I’ve had at least five emails from Spotify saying, “Excuse me, are you sure? Can we really put this up?” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Because we have spent so long berating them for doing it illegally that when they were finally offered it, I think they were terrified to actually put it up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, suing a record label…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Oddly enough, I think we mixed a trick because–well, we don’t actually like suing people, but the one people we never chased for money were Spotify, who did several times put up King Crimson illegally. And I’ve been told this morning, this band I didn’t know, so they can’t be that large, has just settled out of court for millions with Spotify for the fact that they did use their music illegally. So maybe I should have continued!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A few years ago, long before we were &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttps://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/king-crimson/id627204&quot;&gt;on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-apple&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, when we were a complete digital musical stop-out (we weren’t in downloads, we weren’t on streaming, we weren’t on anything), we were at a conference with EMI, who were at the time Virgin/EMI, and they asked us about our digital music strategy. I said, “I have a more profitable digital music strategy than any of you. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My strategy is quite simple. We don’t put it anywhere. We wait until one of you puts it up illegally and then we sue you.&lt;/span&gt;” For a while, it was an incredibly successful policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OrLC125cGdo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The download world matured into something where we thought, “This is somewhere we should be.” The streaming world is more nuanced. So, within the various people who contribute to the conversations within DGM, Spotify remains a hot topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s the spectrum of views?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: The biggest fear on the left, probably from the people who do our physical distribution, is that it might carve into our physical sales. The danger of that is that physical sales require volume. So, if you lose 10% of your physical sales, you possibly lose all of them. What happens with distributors, is if you’ve got enough stuff, they order that stuff and buy your stuff, but it actually doesn’t have to drop very much before it’s worth not sending a lorry at all. So there’s always been a fear of whether streaming eats into physical sales. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My feeling for a long time is that actually it’s two completely different markets and the one won’t pillage the other.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you’re on the other end of the spectrum?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I’m on the other end of the spectrum where actually I think we should be doing this and I don’t think it’s going to eat into physical. In the middle, I think &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Robert has always been uncomfortable simply with the money flow back out of Spotify.&lt;/span&gt; Not simply, “Is it right?” I was speaking to a very famous producer the other day who has had 14 million downloads last year and was sent a check for $1,000 from Spotify. So, there’s an argument that says, “Is Spotify playing its fair way?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_Wj0c5SqGWE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My children are all Spotify users, I have a young family and they’re all Spotify users. For Christmas, my son gave me Spotify. I suspect I gave myself Spotify since I’m probably paying for it, but he gave me Spotify and he set me up so that on my iPad I can play it and I’ve got a speaker in the sitting room. He said, “Oh, you want to play that on your thing, and it comes out of the speaker.” I’ve always maintained that subscribing to a music library is one of the ways we will all enjoy music. I went to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_La_Land_(film)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Have you been to see &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Mm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I was a lover of &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt;. Musically, I was a lover of it. We’d gone and see it and I was on a high. It was 10 o’clock at night, I went onto my iPad and played &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; and danced around the sitting room. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Why is this not a wonderful thing to do?&lt;/span&gt; So it seemed to me that it was slightly perverse that in my home life I was doing this and in my professional life, I was saying, “But you can’t do it with King Crimson!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So the compromise situation seemed to be that we would put &lt;em&gt;Radical Action&lt;/em&gt; onto Spotify because it doesn’t risk suddenly–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_the_Court_of_the_Crimson_King&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the Court of the Crimson King&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “Hey no one’s buying it anymore because it’s now on Spotify.” If I’m right, then we will add &lt;em&gt;In the Court of the Crimson King&lt;/em&gt; because we will be able to show that it doesn’t eat into physical sales, but with &lt;em&gt;Radical Action&lt;/em&gt;, it’s there so if you’ve gone to see the concert last night, you can go and listen to what it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FhKJgqxNDD8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If young kids want to talk, “You should listen to King Crimson,” there’s King Crimson out there. And actually, I love the fact that the King Crimson that’s out there is the new band and not something historic.&lt;/span&gt; I love the fact that if someone says, “You should listen to King Crimson,” if you did it on Spotify, what you’ll get to hear is &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; band, not some other band from 40 years ago. In fact, the same thing is true since we’ve been adding tracks to YouTube. I think Starless has just hit 2 million, which is a lot of views for King Crimson. And I love the fact that the highest viewed item on YouTube, where there is quite a lot of King Crimson, is a brand new track by the brand new band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. What is happening with the rest of The Vicar’s work? It’s not just a CD, it’s a graphic novel…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: So the irony of The Vicar is that–me, the songwriter, I’m a writer at the core, both a word-writer and a song-writer–I wrote those songs and the excuse to finally make an album was because I wrote a series of books. The Vicar is whodunnits in the music industry. It’s all these wonderful stories about corruption that you hear about and are based around the character, The Vicar, who’s a music producer and his assistant, Punk Sanderson, who writes the books, who’s far wittier and obscene than I would ever dare be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The genesis of that actually was I was in a studio with Robert and somebody called and as usual it was some horrendous story about someone being ripped off. I turned around to him and said, “Why has no one written whodunnits about the music industry?” It’s just such a wonderful thing to set a story in and all these stories exist. And this voice came up from behind me, Robert was sitting behind me, and he said, “It’s because you haven’t written them yet,” which was a challenge I took.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IIAWfL48bQU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/novel1.html&quot;&gt;the first Vicar book &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was actually published as a diary online. And then &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ttp://www.thevicar.com/novel2.html&quot;&gt;the second one &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, well the two of them were put together into a book and put out. I realized that actually having created the character of The Vicar, which is a whole world of semi-fictional real-world however-you-want-to-put-it. Now this was a wonderful opportunity that The Vicar could make an album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s very weird. You start saying things and you realize you’ve got to say, “Hold on, I’m going to start saying things that sound a bit odd now.” But, ironically, Punk Sanderson, who writes The Vicar books, writes a much better book than I write. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve written books by David Singleton and Punk Sanderson writes (although I am Punk Sanderson) a much better book than I write.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve considered previously several times–in fact, at the height of DGM, I considered lots of times putting out a David Singleton solo album and I thought, “Well, what’s the point and who would even be interested?” And The Vicar, even though I am The Vicar, produces a much better album than David Singleton would produce. I know that probably sounds slightly screwy, but it’s undoubtedly true. There was something about the whole–partly, the character was well-defined so even that fed into the album and it’s going to have a particular English sensibility because that’s who the character of The Vicar is–but, it was liberating and had I approached it as a David Singleton solo album, it would not be anything close to what the album is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Last night you mentioned that one of the biggest challenges is not selling, but finding an audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Yes! And oddly enough, I think I’m boring your viewers because we’re talking about a conversation that they weren’t party to last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Actually, the viewers love in-depth long things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: So, you’re hearing the second half of a conversation at a dinner table that you weren’t there for. But, yes, I came away from last night, oddly enough, thinking that we didn’t have at the table the more challenging and interesting half of the conversation. A lot of people are talking about, roughly, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;how do we make a living out of music? To which the answer is, “You don’t.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But we had a lot of conversations about that, but actually I think the other half of DGM is more interesting and more challenging because there are two halves. One half was to try and make the commerce work as well as we could, but the other half was to bring music into the world and to try and find an audience. And, ironically, we never tapped really on that last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t have any secret answers to this. If I did, you’d have all heard The Vicar album by now. I think that is a much more interesting challenge and I think that the way the music world is going is quite exciting. The same way that you can get quite depressed about “how do I make a living?” I think there are more opportunities now for artists to be heard than probably there ever have been. There’s a lot of noise out there and I think probably there always way, but you have to rise above it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8eBmRcVMu74?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And yes, I think similarly, Robert said to me this morning when I was paraphrasing, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“The difficult thing to learn in life is that you may choose music, but music may not choose you.”&lt;/span&gt; It’s harsh, but there is a point at which some people make great records and it isn’t the type of music goes and speaks to a huge audience in a wonderful way, which is very horrible. But, assuming that maybe we’ve made a record for which there is an audience and an audience that would like it–which I believe about The Vicar wholeheartedly, by the way, otherwise we wouldn’t have made it. Cut me and I bleed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I think there are more ways out there now than there have ever been and it’s just as tough as it’s ever been because there is a lot of noise out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But the playing field is so much more level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Exactly. So, previously, really unless you had a major record deal, it was a nonstarter. The irony of The Vicar is that when I was 22 or 23, had EMI come along, I would have cut my hands off if they said “Oh David, do you want to do this?” I would have said, “God! Thank you!” Just when I had just about finished The Vicar’s &lt;em&gt;Songbook #1&lt;/em&gt;, I started having conversations about EMI whether they wanted to license it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I suddenly realized I was having a conversation that was pointless because what were they going to offer me now that I don’t have? I can make the record, they aren’t telling me they have a secret answer on how to promote it, so actually what is their role in this? So, you’re right, it is a much more level playing field where, unless you have a huge, major record deal behind you, nothing is going to happen. Whereas the likes of Spotify and YouTube and social media, it is a much more level playing field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As I said, there are no answers, and obviously there are no answers because if there was one, everyone would be out there trying it and it would stop being the answer again. The moment somebody does something clever, they’ll say, “Oh! That worked!” and it’ll never work again because everybody’s doing the same thing now. I think if you’ve got the right music, the same things that make music challenging financially actually open up avenues for people to hear music, which overall means I think all these things are good for music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think the music business is always a clumsy construct. It’s better out of the way, in a funny way. If the music can flow, that’s wonderful. Artists don’t like being ripped off. That’s Robert’s thing. The core of DGM was because people were being ripped off. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if stuff is being sold, I firmly believe that the artist should get their fair share of it. I don’t think the artist should be ripped off. But, equally well, it’s not wrong that music should maybe be free. If music is completely free, that’s different because the artist isn’t being ripped off necessarily. If music is free, well, music is free. I don’t think free solves anything, either, by the way. If you’ve got real great music, people will pay for it. If you’ve got shitty music, people won’t listen to it even if it’s free and the price is slightly irrelevant.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So we’re running out of time. I wanted to get a sense from you because I recall Robert posting something about planning tour dates through 2018. Is there a longer timeline than that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Oooh, there is a longer timeline than that. There is no set end to this King Crimson. They were originally proposing to maybe take a break and then maybe start again. The break is no longer proposed, so over breakfast this morning, we were discussing what we might be doing in 2019. We don’t have an answer to that, by the way, but I do know what we’re doing in 2018. I don’t think I’m going to tell anyone right now, but there is a full year’s touring in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/a5CQIRSRkyQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Right now, there’s this tour, so there’s the–roughly, it’s a west coast tour, then we zoom across to Chicago, so I don’t know what you want to call it, but there’s this half of a US tour and we still have tickets available. It is not totally sold out. Let’s get that in there. But, then I think in the next couple of weeks we will be announcing an Autumn run that ends in New York, so if this is the “west coast” then we’re doing the “east coast” starting in Austin, just to make it confusing for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s on a coast. [Sarcastic.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: “Yeah, it’s on a coast.” So, this year is entirely in the US. Two tours in the US. Next year, I think, will be Europe and Japan. No, I know it will be Europe and Japan. 2019 we’re excited to try and do South America. Always problematic just in making it happen. We’re excited to try to make it happen because that will be the 50th anniversary to do some radical ideas that I haven’t had yet. I proposed a tour of London the other day and that might happen, as in 7 dates touring London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So there is an exciting future! That’s great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Yes! I think the band are up for it. I think the 8-piece is inexplicably far, far better than the 7-piece. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Rieflin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; will tell you it’s because he’s in the band. I don’t know what it is, but yeah, every year this band reinvents itself and gets better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: David, thank you so much for taking some time. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/david-singleton/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/david-singleton/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Iguesman &amp; Joo</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago (probably around 2010), I came across some YouTube videos of an incredible classical music duo called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igudesman_%26_Joo&quot;&gt;Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; showing absolute virtuosity and top-notch prowess while incorporating some of the funniest theatrical material I’d ever seen. The clips were from a show called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.igudesmanandjoo.com/a-little-nightmare-music/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Little Nightmare Music&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a play on Mozart’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eine_kleine_Nachtmusik&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eine Kleine Nachtmusic&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or A Little Night Music or A Little Serenade). It was one of those nights where you spend 2-3 hours going down the YouTube rabbit hole finding every video you can about someone. Borderline creepy, I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.cdbaby.com/cd/igudesmanjoo1&quot;&gt;buy Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo’s first official CD, &lt;em&gt;You Just Have to Laugh&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They played in my hometown of Mesa, Arizona for the first time in 2013 and then returned in 2014. The concert in 2013 was hilarious because my wife and I sat in the front row and Aleksey Igudesman flirted with her all night from the stage. We did not get to sit so close in 2014, but two of my friends sat in the front row and were chosen as participants in the show. It was hysterical and we all had a blast. I brought them two shirts and they sent me an awesome photo afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Make weird music ? Or just weird faces and weird hand gestures? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic&quot;&gt;@MakeWeirdMusic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/IBeKpXA9lN&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/IBeKpXA9lN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo (@igudesmanandjoo) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/igudesmanandjoo/status/722936041661980672&quot;&gt;April 20, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to say I’m their #1 fan or anything, but I’m definitely a big fan of their work. So, it is a sincere and ridiculous privilege and pleasure to be able to present this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xk3y-vNWtZM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/igudesman-and-joo/igudesman-and-joo.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/igudesman-and-joo/igudesman-and-joo.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Wait, before we start, I feel like we have to do this… [Gives me a noogie reminiscent of our &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai interview&lt;/a&gt;] You should have every guest do that. That should be the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/--URKL94KrU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have a very special guest with me. We are here in Germany and I’m really privileged to be here with him. It’s Hyung-ki Joo from Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo. Thank you so, so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: It’s a pleasure to be here. Good hair by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much. I just had it done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, tell us who you are and what you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right. Well, my name is Hyung-ki Joo. I’m one of the rare Korean Joos [“Jews”] in the world. It’s spelled “J-O-O.” My parents are Korean, hence the Asian look, but I was born in England and I guess I’m a musician. I’m a pianist, I’m a composer, arranger, and one of the reasons why we’re here is because you got to know me through my duo, Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo. We are a duo of violinist and pianist. We are classically trained, but we make concerts-slash-shows that combine humor and theatricality with music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. So, I found out about you years ago through a YouTube video and you guys have found a lot of YouTube success. For me, when I look at what you’re doing, it’s clear that you have a mission of turning classical music into something more accessible and entertaining. Can you talk a little about that mission? And how do you feel you’ve done in executing that mission?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The mission is a byproduct. “Mission” always sounds very self-aggrandizing.&lt;/span&gt; I mean, yes, it would be a lie to say that it wasn’t a mission and it would be a lie to say that the mission wasn’t in the back of our heads. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;What I mean by that is that our first goal was to be creative as we were when we were teenagers. We wanted to create a concert that we’d want to go to ourselves.&lt;/span&gt; We couldn’t understand why a classical concert–let alone jazz or rock concerts…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Actually, if you think about it, the concert format, regardless of genre, is quite square. Even rock music… There’s so little humor and so little fun. I mean, the music is “yeah yeah yeah,” whatever, but they’re actually quite serious and it’s quite uptight in a weird sort of rock way.&lt;/span&gt; They’re on drugs and whatever, but there’s a certain type of rigidity, it’s a certain type of format. Of course, not all the groups, but most. And same in the world of classical and jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There seems to be certain formulas and rigidity and some people have become very comfortable with that, just accepting that as, “Oh, that’s what it is.” We couldn’t understand why. Who said that? Where’s the rule book? Show us the book–the book of laws, the ten commandments where it has to look like “this.” Who said?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It wasn’t that we wanted to be radical or rebels, we just felt that there could be more done. And because we were people that were fascinated by comedy, theater, literature, and other types of art forms, we couldn’t understand why these things couldn’t exist side by side, next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We from a very early age just experimented and put on concerts our own way and then about 13 years ago, we sat down and said, “Okay, why don’t we actually really do what we’ve always wanted to do and create this show/concert?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We didn’t always live in the same city and we spent a few years apart, I was studying in New York, he was studying in Vienna. Of course we’d see each other almost once every year. Most of the times, we’d end up doing something together. But now that I’ve moved to Vienna and he lived in Vienna, we’re both living in the same city, we said, “Okay, come on, let’s do this.” And so, &lt;em&gt;A Little Nightmare Music&lt;/em&gt; by Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0jiu0RNizU8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For those who don’t know what that is, could you describe it briefly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Well, that’s the name of our first show officially as Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo. It’s crazy because I’ve been trying to describe this show for 14 years and now, being put on the spot again, you would have thought by now I’d have some perfect press statement. You know, “It is…” and just have it rehearsed. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think it’s impossible to describe because in a way there’s nothing like it.&lt;/span&gt; On the other hand, you could say that what we do is very retro because if you study the historical documents and you look at how concerts would happen in the times of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart&quot;&gt;Mozart &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beethoven&quot;&gt;Beethoven &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liszt&quot;&gt;Liszt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, they were much more open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are very famous documented examples. For example, the world premiere of Beethoven’s violin concerto–this is quite a well-known story in the classical world. The violinist who was performing, his name was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Clement&quot;&gt;Franz Clemen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–in between movements he was performing tricks with his bow, like playing the violin upside-down, undoing the hair [in the bow], doing tricks with his bow–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the kind of thing that would be just frowned upon today. It would be just scandalous, but this was authentic. People talk about “authenticity” and the “authentic movement,” but &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; was authentic.&lt;/span&gt; Also, people stank. They didn’t take showers. You know, there’s this whole movement, at least in the classical world, about authentic period instruments and playing…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, romanticizing everything…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Sure, fine, but then don’t shave for a month and don’t shower and then put on a concert because that’s authentic. Another document is Mozart when one of his piano concertos was premiered. People started applauding after 16 measures, which–he was so proud of it that he wrote a letter to his father, that’s how we know this. “Papa, papa, you won’t believe it, but just now they clapped after 16 measures and we had to stop and start again. What a success!” So he was bathing in this glory that he had to stop for people clapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NOTE: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therestisnoise.com/2005/02/applause_a_rest.html&quot;&gt;The Rest is Noise &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has the content of Mozart’s letter&lt;/em&gt;: Right in the middle of the First Allegro came a Passage that I knew would please, and the entire audience was sent into raptures—there was a big applaudißement;—and as I knew, when I wrote the passage, what good effect it would make, I brought it once more at the end of the movement—and they went again, Da capo. The Andante was well received as well, but the final Allegro pleased especially—because I had heard that here the final Allegros begin like first Allegros, namely with all instruments playing and mostly unisono; therefore, I began the movement with just 2 violins playing softly for 8 bars—then suddenly comes a forte—but the audience had, because of the quiet beginning, shushed each other, as I expected they would, and then came the forte—well, hearing it and clapping was one and the same. I was so delighted, I went right after the Sinfonie to the Palais Royal—bought myself an ice cream, prayed a rosary as I had pledged—and went home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9X0RmNZKj4Y?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If today, if that happened, it would be a scandal. It would be like, “Shh! What are you doing?! How dare you clap?! The composer will be pissed off!” If I was the composer of a work, especially one of those where it’s, “Bee ahh off pfbfbtbtbt” [atonal], and people were clapping after 16 measures, I’d be like, “Thank you, God!” You know? “Wow! Great! I made it!” You should be fucking happy! Instead of being like, “Ugh, how &lt;em&gt;dare&lt;/em&gt; you interrupt my work with applause?!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Liszt! Franz Liszt! The inventor of the recital! He, apparently, would play a piece, he would stop, he would go into the audience–Franz Liszt, the great–have a chuckle with someone sitting there, have a swig of wine and then go back and play something. This was The Great Franz Liszt! The one who &lt;em&gt;invented the recital&lt;/em&gt;. That’s what they were doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, this was the times, and there was less of this elitist, snobbish divide between the artist and the audience. There was more interactivity and we lost that toward the end of the 19th and beginning of the 20th century. And then with the 2nd world war, it was just, pfbtbtbt. And things just got ultra-serious, at least in the classical world.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, as I said, even with jazz and rock, this music that’s so groovy and makes you want to dance, the musicians are actually quite serious. How many rock groups do you know–because that’s your world–do you know who actually would crack a joke on stage or write songs, which are funny?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt; has an album called &lt;em&gt;Does Humor Belong in Music?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Of course, Frank Zappa is one of the rare exceptions, but he doesn’t quite fit in the mold of anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re right. It’s usually, “I can’t hear you! Are you guys having a good time?” Trying to get the audience into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_(band)&quot;&gt;Queen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had humor. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freddie_Mercury&quot;&gt;Freddie Mercury &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had humor. And there’s this kind of stagecraft. Even songs like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One_Vision&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Vision&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has words like “fried chicken.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fat_Bottomed_Girls&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fat-Bottomed Girls&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right! Yeah. And there’s a sort of humor in the orchestration and the sound. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatles&quot;&gt;The Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had humor in the stagecraft, in their introductions, especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Lennon&quot;&gt;Lennon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But also in the songs, you hear it. There’s a sense of fun. Not trying to say that things have to be funny, but there’s a sense of fun. One of my favorite groups is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/10cc&quot;&gt;10cc &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know if you’ve heard of 10cc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve heard of them, but I don’t know their stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh, they’re fantastic. I love their songs. They have this humoristic element, the fun element. A lot of jazz musicians became ultra-serious. If you look at jazz in the beginning, a lot of these guys have so much humor. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_Ellington&quot;&gt;Duke Ellington &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erroll_Garner&quot;&gt;Errol Garner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ella_Fitzgerald&quot;&gt;Ella Fitzgerald &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When they’re scatting, there’s humor, there’s a sense of fun, they’re quoting. Then these guys came around with this very ultra-serious movement in jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I saw this interesting video the other day. It was a lecture that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cleese&quot;&gt;John Cleese &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gave on creativity. Of course, John Cleese, the whole &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Python&quot;&gt;Monty Python &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gang is a huge influence on Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo, as they are on comedy and many things. John Cleese was giving a very serious talk about creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h7fyOLe-xn4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the things he talks about is that there’s a very big difference between serious and solemn. He also says that in order to be creative, you need to open the portal of humor. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Just because you’re talking about something serious, it doesn’t mean that if you make a joke or find humor in it, it doesn’t mean that it’s any less serious.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It is entirely possible to have a conversation about a serious subject, but with humor. He was even saying that there’s no room for solemnity. He said something like, two of the funerals he’s been to in his life were just full of humor and they were the most moving ceremonies that he’d ever been to. So, in this world, somehow humor is laughed upon, it’s not taken seriously, it’s kind of put aside. But, it’s key!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: It’s &lt;strong&gt;human!&lt;/strong&gt; When you ask holocaust survivors what kept them going, because they basically had death staring them in the face all the time–how did they, for 5 or 6 years, keep on going? Most of them say music and humor. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re very lucky that we do both. We do music and humor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I love your shows, everyone I’ve brought to your shows loves them–whether they know anything about classical music or not–but there have to be musicians that do not love what you do. That don’t appreciate you removing the solemnity in classical music that seems to have taken hold since, as you said, WWII.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: You know, we’ve never come across these people, but it doesn’t meant these people don’t exist. And I know these people exist because sometimes I read the comments on our YouTube videos. We believe in free speech, so if you go to our video clips, there are some shitty comments. We leave them. We don’t delete them or paint this image that we are “holier than thou” and only that people love us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are one or two really horrible messages in the comments. We leave them. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We have a saying, which is “not everybody loves chocolate.” It’s something we really believe in. It’s true, not everybody does love chocolate.&lt;/span&gt; Do you love chocolate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I love chocolate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Okay, you love it, I love it, but I know plenty of people who don’t like chocolate. And even those who do, they only like milk, or they like plain, or–so not everybody likes chocolate. And you have to accept that. So, there’s no reason why everybody should like what we do, but usually people who come to our show end up liking it if they didn’t know what they were in for. And those one or two that didn’t, we don’t hear about it, unless they are the ones that go home later and write online, “It was the worst thing I ever saw in my life!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Not to be defensive, but I find that those comments actually say a lot about the commenter, because there are some comments that say it’s disrespectful or that it’s tasteless. I really do not believe we are disrespectful. This is the last thing that we are.&lt;/span&gt; I can understand how people might see it that way, but we’re not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We trained at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yehudi_Menuhin_School&quot;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin school &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is like an elite &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hogwarts&quot;&gt;Harry Potter school &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for menta–er, musicians. We’re very passionate about music. I think that–orchestras, these institutions like the New York Philharmonic or the Chicago Symphony or the London Philharmonic–they wouldn’t play with us if they didn’t think we were serious musicians. They wouldn’t!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If we were just clowns, they’d be, “Oh yeah, those guys are funny. Let’s watch them on YouTube.” But they’d never lend us the keys to their Ferrari. I mean, come on. And people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joshua_Bell&quot;&gt;Joshua Bell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emanuel_Ax&quot;&gt;Emmanuel Ax &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy_Joel&quot;&gt;Billy Joel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, performing with us. They undestand that we’re serious musicians. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Always for us, everything that we do, the number one priority is the music. And then numbers two and three are the humor and theatricality. And if people laugh, great.&lt;/span&gt; If they don’t, well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not our aim to make people laugh or to do something that’s completely out of–let’s just do something weird, just for the sake of being weird. That’s really not what we do. It’s not disrespectful. If you grew up in a very puritan, rigid upbringing, then anything that goes outside of the box is gonna be like, “Whoa! Those radicals! Those punks!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u04nkEJQPqM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I saw a comment just recently on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universaledition.com/composers-and-works/Hyung-ki-Joo/Chandeliers/composer/4521/work/15794&quot;&gt;your &lt;em&gt;Chandeliers&lt;/em&gt; piece &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was a beautiful piece, but somebody said, “A serious piece of music from Hyung-ki Joo!” And I thought, “Everything is a serious piece of music.” Even the music police sketch, you’re playing serious music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That’s true. Yes, that’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Really, really difficult, complex music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: You see, that comes down to–nothing against that person in particular, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it comes down to our general human inability or need for everything to be in boxes. To put things in categories. And that’s why people struggle with things like Frank Zappa and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nina_Simone&quot;&gt;Nina Simone &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; “Where are they? What genre?” Who cares?! Do you like it or do you not? Are you moved by them or are you not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you look at people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Gould&quot;&gt;Glenn Gould &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or Leonard Bernstein or Freddie Mercury or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Brel&quot;&gt;Jacques Brel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. These are guys that are not just singers or just composers, they’re bigger. They’re more varied. You can’t just put them in one slot. It’s like, “Oh, Bernstein wrote a musical, oh he wrote a serious symphony, oh he…” Who cares?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Why can’t someone have many different facets? It’s like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woody_Allen&quot;&gt;Woody Allen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, whenever he tried to do something that was a bit more serious, he was torn apart. Why? It’s like, “Oh wait, you’re that comedy guy! You’re that funny guy with the glasses that goes uh-da-bi-bi-bi-duh… You can’t do serious stuff. It doesn’t make sense.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roald_Dahl&quot;&gt;Roald Dahl &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! Do you know Roald Dahl?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh I love Roald Dahl. I’ve read almost everything!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Have you read the adult stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Some of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Okay, so when you say you’ve read everything, you meant the children’s stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All the children’s stuff when I was a kid, but then when I grew up, I was like, “Oh, no I can find those adult books!” But he wrote great stories for grownups!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: But the adult stuff is like, whooooaaa… It’s screwed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s the one about childhood? [NOTE: It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boy_(book)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boy&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeahhh, isn’t that his autobiography?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, it’s brutal, but it’s wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: A lot of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tales_of_the_Unexpected_(short_story_collection)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tales of the Unexpected&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Uncle_Oswald&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Uncle Oswald&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it’s weird stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shel_Silverstein&quot;&gt;Shel Silverstein &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you ever read his stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: No, I don’t know him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He did &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Light_in_the_Attic&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Light in the Attic&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of these children’s poems. But then he has other stuff that’s about smoking weed. It’s fantastic and not for kids, but even I’m like, “Whoa, who is this guy? Where did he come from?” But he’s a human being with interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Look at Mozart. He wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Requiem_(Mozart)&quot;&gt;requiems &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Magic_Flute&quot;&gt;magic flutes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and he also wrote songs about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart_and_scatology&quot;&gt;licking someone’s ass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Which you have a video of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WP7v66ZnqTA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh, whoa you’ve really seen my stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes! Performing the music…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Performing the music. That’s right. Just to be clear! He saw the video of me performing the music, not actually performing the…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s another channel. The adult channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That’s the Roald Dahl adult channel. Yeah. [Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, can you tell us about your creative process and your inspirations that you haven’t mentioned already? I saw you have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86EoPYNZpbA&quot;&gt;a Prokofiev piece &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HP9Q8v2bQaw&quot;&gt;Shostakovich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-youtube-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… You’ve done a lot of out-of-the-box stuff and I know you compose and you educate. Can you talk about your influences and your creative process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Wow, influences. I mean, we’re going to be here all night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve probably got 4 hours of storage on the camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: From the classical world…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It doesn’t matter. Just your influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: My influences? Well, definitely the greats like Beethoven, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debussy&quot;&gt;Debussy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ravel&quot;&gt;Ravel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Mozart, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rossini&quot;&gt;Rossini &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Then some of the early guys like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_Gesualdo&quot;&gt;Gesualdo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Then from performers, already mentioned Glenn Gould, Bernstein. Then figures like, of course, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yehudi_Menuhin&quot;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St%C3%A9phane_Grappelli&quot;&gt;Stéphane Grapelli &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Jacques Brel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Very interesting thing about Jacques Brel is I fell in love with a French girl when I was 15 years old, as one does, right? I don’t think she knows about it. No, she does know about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, as every Korean British child does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: And one day she sent me as a gift, a tape of Jacques Brel’s 20 greatest hits. I didn’t know who he was. I listened to this tape and loved it. I listened to this tape for many many years and back then, there was no YouTube, no easy access, no Spotify, so I was pretty much stuck with that tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Years later, I started to listen to other stuff, but I would say there was a gap of about 13 years until I actually saw him perform. He’s been dead for a long time, but I actually saw video footage of him. I never even thought to think, “Oh what does he look like? What is he like on stage?” I just loved him. And then one day I was watching TV and there was a documentary about him. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I was just mesmerized by this guy because there was an animal. It was like, this guy was not just a singer, he was like an actor animal, something beyond. A real genuine performer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I happen to understand French, but even if you don’t understand French, there’s no way that you can’t be compelled by this guy. You see him and it’s like, “Augh! He’s so in it.” Certain performers are like that. There’s a lot of jazz musicians that have influenced me, or at least turned me on, people like Errol Garner, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Hancock&quot;&gt;Herbie Hancock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith_Jarrett&quot;&gt;Keith Jarrett &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… I recently heard a guy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brad_Mehldau&quot;&gt;Brad Mehldau &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cnH27mxW0KM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, I just saw him live with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Scofield&quot;&gt;John Scofield &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Guiliana&quot;&gt;Mark Guiliana &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Unbelievable. He’s a genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Of course I’ve known about him for many years. I’ve heard him here and there. But, actually going live to listen to him. It was just a few months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: At the Blue Note?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: No, it was in Vienna. The main program was his kind of arrangements, improvisations based on Bach. That was the main course of the program. Very good, very interesting, no question. In fact, I was thinking that every single pianist that studies in Vienna should have been there because it was a masterclass in piano playing. Pedaling, articulation, phrasing, sound, sound quality, production. Everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Even his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bach&quot;&gt;Bach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was wonderful and he’s not a classical player. I was like, “Where is every single student here? They should be just lapping this up.” He played two encores, which were like… He went into his thing. He did jazz standards. He played two jazz standards and I shit you not, I was just like a little kid. I was in between that emotional experience of wanting to cry and wanting to laugh. Not really knowing how to react because it was like, “Ohh hahahaha ohhhh hahaha!” Just amazing. And there’s been very few experiences like that in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So definitely Brad Mehldau is now on my giants list. There’s a guitarist. Actually, &lt;em&gt;you’re&lt;/em&gt; a guitarist. I don’t know if you’ve heard of this guy. His name is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Muthspiel&quot;&gt;Wolfgang Muthspiel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, jazz guitarist. Fantastic. Check him out. Austrian dude. Just recorded a CD with Brad Mehldau. He is definitely a big inspiration. We hung out a lot in New York when I was studying there. He opened up my world to a lot of jazz music that I didn’t know about before. Certainly I’m a fan of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd&quot;&gt;Pink Floyd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, also like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_(singer)&quot;&gt;Pink &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_BKVfbwI3X4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: She’s very creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah! She’s very creative. And she’s also like one of those people that’s like, ugh! She’s there. She’s in the moment. You believe in her. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Even if you don’t like what she does. I think that some musicians, as far as I’m concerned, it doesn’t really matter whether I like them or not. Glenn Gould is one of my favorite artists. I don’t like everything he does, but when he plays, I just shut the fuck up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And people like Pink or Jacques Brel, they’re those type of people that not everything they do I like, but I stop to pay attention. Brad is the same thing. Just listen because these people are not screwing around. They basically–this is what they do. They’re dedicating their whole lives to this and they are hooking into something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I feel like they’re superhuman. I see musicians like that and it’s almost like they forget who they are, they just exist for this music and it’s their identity. That song, that performance is who they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes. Boom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right. You can’t deny it. You don’t have to like it, but you can’t ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I love a lot of things like we spoke earlier off camera about &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;. I love those guys. Obviously I’m a huge fan of the Beatles. Probably not a day goes by without some Beatles earworm in my head. I love a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_%26_Garfunkel&quot;&gt;Simon and Garfunkel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m open to all kinds of music. I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_Enemy_(band)&quot;&gt;Public Enemy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beastie_Boys&quot;&gt;Beastie Boys &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I think are fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not the music I listen to every day, but when I listen to them, it’s also like, “Shut up, pay attention. These are not some dudes in a garage. They’re onto something.” It’s fantastically crafted music. They have fun. There’s a sense of fun and creativity in there. They’re not just out there to make a hit. They’re there to make music, they’re there to make weird music. A lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiohead&quot;&gt;Radiohead &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/F_4fiMIxO2E?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Have you heard &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Day_Is_Done_(album)&quot;&gt;Brad Mehldau’s Radiohead stuff &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes, of course. Ooh! There’s something I discovered quite recently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postmodern_Jukebox&quot;&gt;Postmodern Jukebox &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah, very creative! Very fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; those guys. A lot of those singers are fantastic. Then there are people who are not musicians, but have been incredible influences on me. Certainly people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Chaplin&quot;&gt;Charlie Chaplin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marx_Brothers&quot;&gt;Marx Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (although they are kind of musicians as well, a lot of them). In today’s world, I’m also intrigued by–you know what? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m intrigued by anybody that is passionate about what they do.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes it’s a nameless street performer that I also just shut up and listen. Pay attention to this guy or this girl. They’re playing there on the street and they’re not doing it for fun. They’re doing it because–of course to get a little bit of money, but this is what they do. Some of them are just amazing. There’s no reason why some of those people on the street should not have huge record deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I once saw a guy–and you see these guys everywhere, but you find &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; that’s like the golden child. It was one of those dudes doing this wine glass thing. You see that usually and it’s like, “Yeah, it’s just a party trick and it’s woooooeaeaea wowooooooahaha WOOOOOHHOOO.” It’s like, whatever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I thought I was standing in front of wine glasses just now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: [Laughter, continued wine glass sounds] But this one guy I saw. I even made a video clip of him. I’m so stupid, I should have asked for his name, got his number, his contact because we would have invited him to a show or something because this guy was something. He was a genius. An absolute genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you like everything!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I do! For example, also dance. There’s a dancer called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tamara_Rojo&quot;&gt;Tamara Rojo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. She’s now the Artistic Director of the English Ballet. I actually flew to London to watch her perform. Twice. I’m not a major ballet freak, but for her, yes. There’s also a guy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Thiérrée&quot;&gt;James Thiérrée &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who happens to be the grandson of Chaplin, and he does these amazing theatrical shows. His sister too, Aurelia, actually. Both of them. They created this type of–again, this genre that doesn’t really exist. It’s this type of circus/theater/performance art/contortion/magic fun comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sFFpzip-SZk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you know Barbara Hannigan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: OH MY GOD. I wrote a huge–my first blog, one of my first blogs I wrote was basically a love letter to Barbara Hannigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: She’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: She’s absolutely incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Talk about serious music. She’s doing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gy%C3%B6rgy_Ligeti&quot;&gt;Ligeti &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff in crazy outfits. People are laughing, but it’s that stunned, “I don’t know what to make of this, whether to laugh or cry” thing because you’re so shocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: But Ligeti would have been very happy with this. Ligeti is considered to be one of the greatest composers of the 20th century and he’s also considered to be one of the most serious composers. However, his music is full of fun and humor. He wrote a piece for 100 metronomes. Come on. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The guy is full of fun! He has pieces where the percussionists have to drop plates and stuff. He uses a lot of the types of techniques that those avant garde guys were doing, but because he’s a good musician and he has that sense of humor and creativity, it’s compelling. Then you get someone like Barbara Hannigan, who again is like a golden child, and she puts her approach onto this music. Wow. It’s explosive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So we never got to your creative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh my God, yes. Well I &lt;em&gt;told you&lt;/em&gt; this was going to take forever! But you know, it’s very rare… This is a gift. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s a gift to be able to just talk about people that one likes. And to share that with someone who understands. It’s very rare.&lt;/span&gt; I’ll tell you something, and this is going to sound weird. I’ll tell you something, and I know I’m going off subject here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, go for it. This is &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/T4DCoZRr2SE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Something I realized recently in my world, which is mostly classical. Of course, I know a lot musicians outside of the classical world, but I noticed something a little disheartening, to be honest. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It dawned on me just a few weeks ago that a lot of musicians, my colleagues, people in my world, they rarely talk about music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And it just hit me, like, “Wait a second… We’re calling ourselves musicians. This is what we do. We work our asses off. Our parents spent shitloads of money so we could have expensive lessons and go to music schools. And this is supposedly what we’re passionate about, yet when we site down we don’t talk about music.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You talk about business, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: How did you know this?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m in an industry, too. It’s what people do. They talk about the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;They talk about the business! This is the &lt;em&gt;last thing&lt;/em&gt; I want to talk about. It’s &lt;em&gt;business&lt;/em&gt;. It’s the least interesting part of music. It’s the business! That’s why it’s got that horrible term, “The business!”&lt;/span&gt; And if we’re lucky enough to be in the business, then okay we have to deal with it. But, I want to talk about music! I want to talk about the C major chord, or King Crimson, or lyrics. I want to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felix_Mendelssohn&quot;&gt;Mendelssohn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I realize that very few musicians want to talk about that. In fact, there are even some musicians that will deliberately sabotage and stop you right there when they see you’re starting to talk, and they say, “You know, I don’t want to talk about music. Let’s not talk about music.” …Okay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I could kind of forgive them if the conversation steered toward something at least as interesting, but it either goes to a very low level, which–fine, that’s okay, that’s cool. But, it’s like, “Let’s not talk about music! Let’s talk about very low stuff or let’s talk about the business of music.” That doesn’t make sense to me. So, I don’t really understand. It just dawned on me, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Meeting you and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;being able to talk about music is, like, a rare treat.&lt;/span&gt; I can tell you that, unfortunately, very few people that I come across really want to talk about music. And I find that sad because what are we doing this for? Anyway, back to your question. What is my creative process? By the way, you can cut this however you want…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, I’m just looking at my cameras to make sure everything’s still rolling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: You can cut out all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is the best stuff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rp5jQRyjf5c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: [Laughter] Creative process. Well, of course I’m very, very lucky that a lot of my creative process is done with my friend and partner, Aleksey Igudesman, who today is in the form of fruit [arranged on a small table next to Hyung-ki]. It actually kind of looks like him. We did a pretty good… If &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gualtiero_Jacopetti&quot;&gt;Jacopetti &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Michel_Basquiat&quot;&gt;Basquiat &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; did a high fruit sculpture of Aleksey Igudesman, this would be it! Two apples and a bunch of bananas. This apple represents his sort of chi, and this banana represents his mental state. I know he’d prefer it the other way around. I hate to say it, but it’s more like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, so anyway I’m very fortunate that a lot of my creative process is shared with this guy. Actually, even though we’re doing our own thing a lot of the times, we’ll show it to the other. So if I’m writing a piece, which might be a serious piece or a funny piece or whatever, it’s outside of the I&amp;amp;J umbrella, he will very often make some wonderful contribution and remarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We do that for each other. When we are working together, we call our relationship a ping-pong relationship because I ping stuff to him and he smells, so he pongs.&lt;/span&gt; That’s what it is. No, it’s ping-pong because one of us says, “What about this?” Boom. And the other says, “Okay, but then we do this?” Boom. And it just goes back and forth and there’s a nice rally going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And it always makes it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Always. Yes we do disagree and yes we do argue and yes we do fight. We fight less and less because we’re trying to be more Om about life and more holistic and spiritual and more about love and forgiveness. But it doesn’t always work, so… [Punches fruit scuplture.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BSE-86M_DVk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Man, Aleksey was doing really well until…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: To be fair, he bullied me. No, this is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When you were younger?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah! He actually punched me in the nether regions. It’s actually true. It’s a miracle that I can be reproductive down there because I really thought, “I’m cut off. There can be no Joo dynasty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I wouldn’t have thought he was strong enough to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Oh, he’s strong. He is strong. He is much stronger. He’s always been stronger than me and he still is. [To the fruit] I’m sorry about that. Yes, that’s… yes. There’s no frustration there at all. No issues that need to be resolved. Of course, we have our differences and we have two very strong personalities, but we believe and we work toward the fact that to try and come to a consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes the fact that you have this friction leads to something better, actually. Through arguing and through contesting, then you actually go, “Wait a minute. How about this?” So, I’m very lucky that I have that. I think that some people who are just working as solo artists maybe don’t have that resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I know that a lot of the Monty Pythons, their creative process was having little writing teams. I think Eric Idle did his own thing, Terry Gilliam of course did animations, and Cleese was with Chapman, and Terry Jones with Michael Palin. But when they got together, they would then give the stuff to the other person and the other person would say, “Oh, I know how to finish that.” Or, “Give that to me.” So then it became a collaborative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’d actually love to know how–you know, a lot of these rock groups that stay together like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U2&quot;&gt;U2 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or Radiohead or Queen, if you look at their song credits, it’s all shared. It’s actually a smart thing to do, also, just for the general harmony of the group because a lot of rock groups split up basically because somebody’s houses were bigger than theirs. There is that aspect, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I am much more someone that likes to take time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kbbi_b5K3d8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think it’s partly because I’m slow [laughs], but it’s also because I believe in the magic of editing. I believe in the power of time and editing. Have you ever had this–I’m sure you’ve had this happen to you and to whoever’s watching this–Um, hi–that you’ve written something, like an essay or homework or something creative, a song, a birthday card, whatever, and the coffee spills on it and you’ve lost it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah. You try recreating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah, and then you’re like “AAAHHH!” But I think 9 times out of 10, or 99 times out of 100, when you try to recreate it or do it again, it’s usually better. So what does that mean? It means that subconsciously, with the passing of time, your subconscious has been working on it. You put it down. Boom, enter, save. While the computer’s stored it, or the handwriting has stored it, or whatever, your creative subconscious is still continuing to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So actually, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s a blessing in disguise, while bloody annoying, that you’ve lost the first draft.&lt;/span&gt; Let’s say sometimes I do that consciously. It’s not like I give it to a dog to chew up, but consciously I kind of will let time sit on it and then think about it and come back to it and somehow there’s a natural editing that’s just been done. I just say, “Okay, let’s get rid of this, and let’s get rid of that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t have–I’m not one of those child geniuses that just–I don’t have perfect pitch, I can’t write down something on one hearing. There are people like that. In fact, when I went to the Menuhin school, I was 10 years old and I thought I really didn’t belong there. I thought I’d get kicked out, besides getting kicked in the balls by people like Aleksey, I actually thought I’d get kicked out, also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Because I arrived after playing the piano for about two years, I was certainly one of the lowest on the food chain. There were people there who were a lot younger than me that were already writing symphonies, they were playing Rachmaninoff, and my audition piece was Bach’s first prelude [sings it]. That was my audition piece and somehow they accepted me, but when I got there, I thought, “Oh, they made a mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Fortunately, year after year, I was still there and I thought, “Oh I’m still here.” And the thing that kept me going was that I believed that I loved music more than anybody else. Of course, it’s a very subjective thing, but that’s what I felt. Looking around at everybody, I thought, “They’re much more talented than me, they’re much more naturally gifted, they’ve been given gifts from God and they’re more trained.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SrR9alVhCNU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the thing that I have over them is that I love music more than they do. I’m sure of it because I just love music so much and I felt that this love of music was lacking in a lot of them.&lt;/span&gt; So I felt like, “Okay, if you just give me a chance, just keep giving me a chance, I’ll get there. I’ll get there.”
And after a while, I guess I did. So there’s a part of me that–you know, insecurities lie strong. Things that you feel as a child, so even today &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there’s a part of me that feels like I’m not a qualified musician.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Because of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Because things don’t come easy to me. Because everything I do has to be worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is Aleksey the kind of guy you’re talking about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I would say Aleksey is a natural talent. Absolutely. In fact, it’s a miracle he’s such a good musician because he’s had such shitty teachers, in my opinion. He left the Menuhin school when he was 16 and in a way had arrested development. So it’s a miracle for me that he’s such a great musician, because–if he was here, he would probably argue that, but that’s not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He learned his things in other ways. He probably has a right to say that, but I always felt from the moment I met him, even though he was kicking me in the balls, it still made me realize when he was playing that this guy was absolutely a natural talent. Exceptional. The way he played was unlike anything else. And the sound that he has is unlike anybody else. The sound, it’s a unique approach and an unique inflection of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Seriously, he’s kind of not here, but he kind of is, and I’m not just saying this because I’m on camera, but I really feel like &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m one of the luckiest people to play with one of my favorite violinists. I’m just so lucky to play with a guy like that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you look at yourself and–do you ever compare yourself to his capabilities? Or is it a, “Thank God he is the way he is?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: No I don’t really compare. I’ve never been envious of anybody, I’ve never been competitive with anybody. I’ve had relationships with pianists. A lot of people go, “Oh my God, how can you go out with a pianist?” I don’t have any–I have wonderful friends who are pianists. I’ve never felt anything like a sort of competitiveness or rivalry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ddKHdrUktkY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The older I get, I have enormous respect for anyone who plays the piano.&lt;/span&gt; From one side, it’s a very simple thing to do. Every 5-year-old kid can just go play Twinkle Twinkle. And yes, it’s true, there is a certain simplicity to playing the piano, but when you get to a certain level, when you get to the last level of the video game, that’s not simple stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you talk about these funky pianists, these jazz pianists, these people who have to improvise–any other instrument, like electric guitar, saxophone, violin, I’m sorry, but with all due respect, they just have to play one line. It’s just one line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Or just one scale!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: One scale! Yeah, so you can do Dah-dah! Whatever, sure go nuts, man! But when you’re playing a keyboard, most of the time, you have to play the rhythm, the harmony, and that’s usually with the left hand and a bit of right, but then you have to be totally free and inventive with the right and have at least 3 things going on at the same time and be polyrhythmic and polyharmonic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m sorry, but big respect has to be done for those guys. Not taking anything away from the instrumentalists who improvise, but when you look at somebody like these guys like Herbie Hancock or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chick_Corea&quot;&gt;Chick Corea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Brad. What they’re doing is on another level. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I guess I feel that I’m still a student.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin&quot;&gt;beginner’s mind &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, always learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yeah, I know that sounds cliche and zen and all that bullshit, but it’s true. A few years ago, a student–well, she’s not really a student of mine, but she’s someone that used to come play for me quite regularly, and then there was a hiatus, but–she called me again and she said, “I’d like to come again and play for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I was not trying to be modest or funny or blow her off, I said, “You know? I don’t think I’d actually be good to teach you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;She said, “Why?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I said, “Well, because I’m doubting everything that I’ve ever done before and I really don’t know what the hell I’m doing myself. I’m reinvestigating everything and this would be just terrible for me. All those lessons and all that jargon trash I told you before, just throw it away because that’s what I’m doing. And so I really don’t think I’d be a suitable teacher for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/86EoPYNZpbA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And she said, “That’s &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; why I want to come to you!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did you teach her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I did, yes. How could I not after such a cute comment as that? It’s genuinely how I felt! “I don’t know myself, and I don’t have the answers myself. How can I give an answer to someone who’s looking up to me expecting the answer?” I said, “Uuuuuuh, I don’t know.” I really thought I’d be wasting her time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not a “complex” thing, it’s not an insecurity, I just feel that–yes, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I know I have an access to music and I know that I have a special approach to music. I know that I see music differently. I know that I feel music very passionately. I know those things. I’m not going to be modest about those things and I know that I can put on a good performance. But, because I know for myself how much work I need to get to even do that and I know that some people can just go and pick up the instrument. They haven’t played for a year and they’re drunk and the magic happens. Or they just sit down and write something or improvise something and they have a piece done.&lt;/span&gt; Aleksey is more like that. He’s a faster writer than me because he doesn’t really think. He doesn’t think anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, he is fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: He is a fruitcake. I think that’s also a blessing in disguise. It’s his strength and his weakness that he doesn’t give much thought to thought and he’s more impulsive and just letting it in and just doing it and kind of hit and miss. There’s not that quality control. “It’s good enough.” Boom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He has that midas touch. He’ll write pieces that–and they’re pieces that I listen to and, look, he’s one of my best friends. I love him. I admire him hugely. I listen to a piece and I’m like, “Really? Yeah? Again? The same trick?” But then I go away and I’m humming it and it’s in my head. Well, that’s the midas touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I can objectively analyze it as much as I want and scrutinize and be critical, but at the end of the day, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve walked away and hours later, I’m humming it. It’s in my mind. In that sense, it must be a good piece of music. It must be an infectious piece of music, right?&lt;/span&gt; So, he has that. And I’m a lot more, like I said, I like to tweak things and sit. It’s not so easy for me to say, “Yeah! That’s done! Next!” It’s very hard for me to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vi1JeWrIPeA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The drummer &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Bruford&quot;&gt;Bill Bruford &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; talks about this. He says some people are producers, some people are musicians. Some people can go into a studio and lay down an album in 2 hours. Some people, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Gabriel&quot;&gt;Peter Gabriel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it takes 8 or 10 years to put out an album. It’s not that it’s bad, it’s great. But one guy can put out an album and another can put out 100 albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right! I do sometimes write songs and, again, I don’t consider myself a natural born songwriter. I’m not your &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ira_Gershwin&quot;&gt;Ira &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gershwin&quot;&gt;George Gershwin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not your &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irving_Berlin&quot;&gt;Irving Berlin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but I love the form of the art of song and I’ve written a few songs. But, phew, it’s tough. Really tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I must say I was a little bit heartened, but a friend of mine is Billy Joel. I said, “Man, it’s so hard to write a song. I just feel like giving up.” I even showed him a piece, and said, “I don’t know. Should I do this?” And he’s like, “What are you talking about, man? It’s like giving birth!” He’s one of those people that will just take forever and really struggle with music and lyrics. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He’s considered one of the world’s greatest songwriters, right? If he can struggle, then I can too.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Back to being human, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: I guess I can identify more with Beethoven than Mozart. I love Mozart, of course I love Mozart. But the thing with Mozart is he just literally defecated a piece. Maybe that’s why a lot of his pieces were scatalogical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Maybe that’s why there’s so much Mozart chocolate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That’s right! Mozart chocolate balls. But, Mozart, he really just thought it and it was done. A whole opera. Boom. With Mozart, there’s hardly any sketch. It’s like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pablo_Picasso&quot;&gt;Picasso &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; drawing a perfect circle. That’s basically Mozart. The equivalent. Picasso didn’t have any sketches where he’s trying to draw a circle. He’d just go boom. Perfect circle. Straight line. He had that God-given talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Beethoven, on the other hand, sketches like this [gesticulates a huge pile of papers]. He would cross out stuff, try stuff, try different keys, and there’s like 32 or 64 versions of just 4 notes. Probably before he came to da-da-da-DAAAAA [5th symphony], he did da-da-da-DEEEE, da-da-doooo, da-DI-da-daaa, da-DAAA. It’s not that piece, but you actually see that. Sketches and sketches and sketches. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And you feel the struggle. I guess maybe that’s why I identify more with him.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so… We’ve talked a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes! I’ve probably not answered one sigle question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, this is great! But, you’ve got a CD with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And I want to make sure we talk about it because it’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/64aeM7mtFRU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.cdbaby.com/cd/igudesmanjoo1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You Just Have to Laugh&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. [Promotional zooming and smiling.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Where can someone procure said CD?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Umm, here. If you have that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willy_Wonka&quot;&gt;Willy Wonka &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ability if they can just reach into the camera and pick up the disc. It’s certainly available after our shows. It’s available in the one CD store that still exists in the world. Somewhere in Mesa, Arizona or something like that, because CD stores are relics. But, mostly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/You-Just-Have-Laugh-Igudesman/dp/B01CRT7086&quot;&gt;ordered through Amazon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-amazon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/you-just-have-to-laugh-vol./id1152481360&quot;&gt;download it on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-apple&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us about the album. You’ve got a whole &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Malkovich&quot;&gt;Malkovich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes, there’s some actor called John Malkovich on there and he plays our agent. The thing is, because we’re traditional guys, we grew up in the world of radio shows and LPs and concept albums, which now don’t really exist. We’ve been a duo officially for 14 years and only last year did we make this CD. It’s our first and only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When we were at the drawing board, we were thinking, “Okay, what should we do?” And we were looking at current trends, what do people do? The concept album doesn’t exist anymore, but we’ve always loved things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sgt._Pepper%27s_Lonely_Hearts_Club_Band&quot;&gt;Sgt. Pepper’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all those great concept albums from the 60s and 70s, but CDs… So we wrestled with all these conflicting things. At the end of the day, we said, “Why are we doing what we do? Is it to win a grammy?” [In promotional voice] We hope to win a grammy. [Back to normal] But, is that what we’re doing this for? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re doing it because it’s our creative desire and if we’re lucky enough to do it, let’s just do what we love doing. If it’s a success, great. If not, then too bad. At least we’re doing something we believe in.&lt;/span&gt; So we said, “Screw it. Screw whether people care about the concept album. We’re just going to do our own thing.” So we said, “Let’s make an album that has a line, a kind of shape, and a drama to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We had all these pieces in motion and thought, “Okay, how do we string these together?” Because that’s the thing. Our genre is many genres. We are classically trained, yet we love to mix rap, country and western, electronic, heavy metal, funk, 30s/40s songwriting styles. In this CD, there must be a ton of styles. Film music, cabaret. Just a lot. Even Latin. Something for the Latin grammys. The song &lt;em&gt;Uruguay&lt;/em&gt;. Latin grammy nomination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, great, we want to do a concept album, but how do we make all these things tie together? To us, this is our world. If you’re a black or Asian kid, like I was growing up in Norwich full of white, anglosaxons, you don’t think twice. That’s your world. But, actually, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you look at it from another angle, it’s like, “Whoa, I’m the black sheep.” So, these pieces are like our kids. They belong here, but to somebody else, they’re like, “Why? This is already 27 different iTunes categories. The computer’s going to go nuts.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You don’t fit in the box!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: We don’t fit in the box. That’s right. So, one way we thought was, “Okay, well let’s create this character of an agent.” We called this guy Agent Sir and he’s a kind of persoflage mockup of all the kinds of agents that we’ve come across with the kind of traits that basically in this business that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;a lot of these people out there have no idea about music. The people that are “up there.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9A95yzVgBTs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah. They “make decisions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: People who make decisions about who will play next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;They have no idea about music! Which I could forgive &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; they had a passion for it, but they don’t. They couldn’t care less.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Obviously with streaming services…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: They don’t give a shit. They don’t care, so they have no emotional connection to the job they’re supposed to be working on. Also, those who have some kind of influence over the artist, a lot of them really don’t give a shit about the artist. They’re just there to rape and profit from them. If they get burnt out, it doesn’t matter. They’ll just move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Find another one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Find another one. Yep. This character’s not as evil, but let’s say that’s the background of our agent. We wanted someone to play this, so who better to ask than John Malkovich?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Who suffers from the same problems in &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Yes, of course. He’s and out-of-the-box guy. You’ll see him in &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt;, but that’s not his thing. His thing is doing French theater and weird projects like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;em&gt;Being John Malkovich&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: &lt;em&gt;Being John Malkovich&lt;/em&gt;! That’s him. So, that’s where we’re kindred spirits and he’s always so gracious and supportive. He said, “Yeah, sure I’ll do this.” So, he’s kind of the string, the thread. He sends us off to record all the things. He sends us off to Istanbul because he wants a Turkish lamp. He’s like, “I’m flying into Paris. Got some friends over for some wine and cheese. So, maybe you could record some Chopin to go with our wine and cheese.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He doesn’t care. “Whatever. Just do something while I’m flying around the world making money from you guys. Or not from you guys, but something else.” He even sends us to outer space for some reason. He sends us to Uranus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I have to say it was one of the most fun things to get him to say “Yer-anus.” Not that he had any trouble doing that, but we were like little kids writing the script like, “He’s going to say that! He’s going to say that! And I’m sending it to yer-anus!” And he’s reading it! It’s kind of like a mixture of not greatest hits, but songs that people love, like &lt;em&gt;From Mozart with Love&lt;/em&gt;, which is a mashup of Mozart and James Bond. There’s our kind of version of the disco hit, &lt;em&gt;I Will Survive&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RvWsRt8w664?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of people say, “Oh, but does your stuff work on radio? How can you make a CD because your stuff is so visual?” So we said, “All right. Let’s prove it to you.” So not only did we create a kind of concept for it, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we also rethought every single number to see how it could translate into an audio format.&lt;/span&gt; I know you know quite a lot of our stuff, but you’ll see that a lot of things are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh I love the disc!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: We made a 3D space for the 2D listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And it’s fresh! If you watch the YouTube things, that’s one version of it, but then you get the CD, and you say, “Oh, I see how they twisted this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Right. It’s totally different. They’re all totally different versions. So, please, &lt;em&gt;You Just Have to Laugh&lt;/em&gt; by Igudesman and Joo. The unmaking of, featuring John Malkovich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much, man. What a treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Shameless plugging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s not shameless. That’s why we’re here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: That &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; why we’re here. It’s shameful. It’s full of no shame!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, thanks a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HJ: Thank you so much. I feel like I didn’t answer one single question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Then it’s a good interview.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/igudesman-and-joo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/igudesman-and-joo</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quintuplets and Septuplets with Jan Zehrfeld</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-background&quot;&gt;Some Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; is one of my favorite bands in the world and I was lucky enough to meet up with the band’s creative genius, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Jan Zehrfeld&lt;/a&gt;, at his home in Munich, Germany while traveling with my family. I’d met him in person once before at the Baked Potato in Los Angeles in 2013, but we didn’t really connect until I emailed him and asked him to &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;do an interview in 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jan has written some incredibly complex compositions built entirely on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuplet&quot;&gt;quintuplets and septuplets &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We thought it’d be fun to talk in-depth about what he’s done in these songs and how they work. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have with me–it’s a real honor to be with you–Jan Zehrfeld from Panzerballett. Jan, thank you so much for joining me and having me in your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Of course. Good to have you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you very much. So today, what do you want to talk about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I want to talk about quintuplets and septuplets and how I started experimenting with songs, or parts, that are based just on quintuplet feeling and septuplet feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the songs from your catalog that use quintuplets and septuplets in an interesting and novel way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, the first one is &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk.&lt;/em&gt; The idea is the first song that is just quintuplet-based. Another one is &lt;em&gt;Mahna Mahna&lt;/em&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The Muppets song?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, the Muppets song. And then there is an original composition called &lt;em&gt;Euroblast.&lt;/em&gt; I didn’t know in the beginning how to start it all, so the good start was just modifying something you already know into somethig different. Like &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;, modifying it in a way that it can fit into a quintuplet grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For people who don’t have a music theory background or don’t do much beyond a triplet, what are quintuplets and septuplets and how are you using them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: The quintuplet is basically a division of the beat into five even parts. It might be the beat in half notes and one half note can be divided into five eighth notes quintuplets notes or four quarter notes can be divided into five “notes.” Or, for instance, the way I used it was dividing one quarter note, which means four 16ths and instead of four 16ths, use five 16th quintuplets. Can you say it like that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, you’re putting five notes in the space where there’s normally four notes. In standard music notation, you don’t have to use any “signage.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: You can divide the beat into three 8th note triplets, or into four 16ths, or into five quintuplet 16ths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And a septuplet is seven instead of five.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, which is even harder. This already means that the more notes you have, the slower the tempo needs to be to perceive them so it doesn’t get muddy with notes. If you have septuplets and a fast tempo, you don’t notice a difference between septuplets and 32nd notes or sextuplets. And the fast tempo is just “brrrrrrrrrrrrrr.” For seven, it must be slower. And for quintuplets, it’s similar, but it might be faster because it’s only five notes. The thing is that for quintuplets, I didn’t have any other music to listen to that has only quintuplets and you usually learn music by hearing it and getting influenced. I didn’t have something like this, so I had to build my own stuff and it was hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Most people use quintuplets as a rhythmic device for melodies or very small phrases. If it’s used at all in a song, it’s typically used in a short span of time and used to articulate a phrase. But you’re using quintuplets and septuplets as a division of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And then you’re laying time signatures on top of those divisions, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so how does that work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, for instance it might be a good idea to choose one time signature. For guitar, you might choose 4/4 or 3/4, but 3/4… I started with 3/4. Why? Because I wanted something that had 4x4 16ths, which is 16 notes, but I changed it into one bar of 3/4 with quintuplets, which is 15, which means I have to take out one note in some place. So, it resulted in a 3/4 bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: 3/4 using quintuplets, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah. Like 1, 2, 3–DA ga di ga da, DA ga di ga da, DA ga di ga da. For guitar, it’s hard and tricky because usually in funk guitar, if you have 16 notes in a 4/4 bar, it’s [plays a funk rhythm part on guitar]. So, if you have 3/4, it’s [plays a funk rhythm part with the accented 1 beat on up and then down strokes].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And so much of what we do musically is in two because we walk in 2, our hand goes up and down, so you really have to keep track of where you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, because you have five and it changes if you have a constant down/up movement. It changes whether it’s changing to an upstroke on the downbeat in the first measure and then an upstroke in the second measure. And that’s the tricky thing about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you apply this to &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I started with the melody. You have this [plays the melody] and I started to add just two notes [plays the melody with two new notes] in every phrase. It’s like talking a sen-sentence. So you have the same kind of phrases, but more notes in every phrase to get five out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you maintain the integrity if you’re adding notes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I don’t maintain it. I just make something that I can still sell as the melody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So it’s close enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Close enough for jazz. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you count your version of &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;? Are you counting in quintuplets or are you counting in the downbeats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: In the downbeats. In the beginning, I have a 4/4 with quintuplets, which means 20 notes. The original has 16 notes. Somewhere I have to add 4 notes to it somewhere and not at the same time, but really hide it. That’s how it started. And then there is the “groove” thing. I found what fit better was the 3/4 bar instead of the 4/4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JZ: I don’t know why. It just fit better and made more sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;[Demonstration of the quintuplet groove]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: That’s for the funk groove. Then you have the bass line and I found it with 3, 2, 2, 3, which is close to a triplet feel, but it’s not. [Plays triplet version and quintuplet version.] With triplets, the first note is 33% whereas two quintuplets is 40%. It’s a little percent difference of something that’s already quite fast. But with what you call “feeling,” you have to listen closely and play precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I have to say that when I first heard the song, I couldn’t figure it out and then I heard Sebastian’s drum parts, I clearly heard quintuplets and thought, “That sounds like quintuplets. But why would they make a whole song about quintuplets?” Not thinking about you and what you do, but just like, “No one does that, so it can’t be right.” But it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; right and it did turn out after two or three months of listening, I concluded it must be quintuplets and then you confirmed it for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you even approach this? You have a whole band living in this different time space for several minutes. How do you improvise over it? You solo over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you even do that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Soloing was already the next step. The first step took us about half a year to get through the head as a band without any improvising because we were not that far, but we wanted to play it. So the first shows we played the song, we played just the head of it. We said, “Hey, we’ve got something new.” You may not be that far, but your kids will love this, like in [&lt;em&gt;Back to the Future&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Back_to_the_Future]. And then we started adding the improvisational part, which is extra work, but fun work. Exhausting, but fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so how does the septuplet stuff go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, the septuplets was a year practicing to a click like this. [&lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; 2 3 4 &lt;em&gt;5&lt;/em&gt; 6 7] It’s like a fast 7/8 bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You spent a year doing this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I spent a year learning and improvising over this feeling and learning the riffs. Not with a straight click, but with this changing click. The difference between 4 and 3 is smaller as the tempo gets faster. And when I’m doing only 4 over this click, it’s shifting around all the time. [Plays a note every 4 beats over the 4+3 click.] And then stuff like this [improvises with pentatonic scale over the 4+3 click] doing groups of 4 and 3 notes over this whole thing. Well, stuff like this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How does this prepare you for a band context when the whole band is playing? They’re not going to be playing 4+3 over and over again. That’s not how music works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: No, no. I had to learn it again because the band was playing to a different click than this or the band didn’t practice to this click. The rest of the band practiced to a different click and this kind of threw me out again because I practiced it that long with this click. The band’s click was “DA goo goo goo goDA goo goo goo.” It’s counting 8th note septuplets. [Does a rhythmic difference between the clicks.] It’s a different feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It sounds very Indian, carnatic rhythm-inspired kind of thing. I know you had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trilok_Gurtu&quot;&gt;Trilok Gurtu &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on your album. Were you going through some sort of Indian rhythm study phase? Has that been an important part of your rhythmic foundation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JZ: The Indian rhythm? No. Not at all. Not for me, but I should go there one day. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mattias-eklundh&quot;&gt;Mattias Eklund&lt;/a&gt; told me I should go there to South India but I never had this as a primary influence. I just recognized it later. Probably my influences came from there, like Meshuggah. I guess they must be inspired by those kinds of rhythms. So I guess it was a secondary influence, not a primary influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Yeah, but this septuplet thing was really challenging. So, the first rhythm that was in &lt;em&gt;Typewriter II&lt;/em&gt; was this one. [Plays a rhythm over the 4+3 click.] Again you have the first beat starting with a downstroke and then the second measure’s first beat starting with an upstroke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think &lt;a href=&quot;/share/typewriter&quot;&gt;in my cover version of that song&lt;/a&gt;, I simplified it so I could just record it. It’s so complex. The more I’ve studied your music, the more I wonder, “How do you get a whole ensemble to play like that?” And I saw you live, which blew my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, this part took us quite long to rehearse over and over in loops, really starting slowly. Collectively rehearsing this kind of groove I just played to a click and slowly building it up, rehearsing each part separately from each other and then putting it all together, we spent quite a lot of rehearsals… We don’t rehearse very much, but a big percentage of our rehearsal time was spent getting this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Where do you go with this? Is this just an exercise per song? Or is there a whole other world that’s opened up to you guys?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Both. It’s the consequence of starting with quintuplets, then going to septuplets. I don’t know where it’s going to lead, but with septuplets, there is just one example that we did that’s maybe just an exercise. But on the other hand, I think it opened up now that we’ve already rehearsed it so much, the next time we work in septuplets, it won’t take that long, I guess. Having improvised and played these parts a lot now, I think I can build something on top of it, maybe more interesting or sophisticated. I don’t know yet. I will try to go this way, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s really, really cool. I guess we’ll just have to wait until the next Panzerballett album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thanks a lot, Jan. This was extremely insightful. You’re a madman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I know. I know. What a madman? Me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: No, I’m totally normal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/quintuplets-septuplets</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/quintuplets-septuplets</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Something She Said by Béla Fleck</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/M-fdyC388-s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/something-she-said/something-she-said.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/something-she-said/something-she-said.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soundslice-notation-and-tablature&quot;&gt;Soundslice Notation and Tablature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living sheet music brought to you by &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Wanna know more? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;our interview with Soundslice co-creator, Adrian Holovaty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/71461/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bela_Fleck&quot;&gt;Béla Fleck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s album &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outbound_(B%C3%A9la_Fleck_and_the_Flecktones_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outbound&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was released in 2000 with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9la_Fleck_and_the_Flecktones&quot;&gt;Flecktones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was 18 when it came out and pre-ordered a double-CD release from Barnes &amp;amp; Noble or Best Buy. &lt;em&gt;Something She Said&lt;/em&gt; was one of the songs that really stood out to me because of its odd chord changes and textural elements with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on electric guitar, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawn_Colvin&quot;&gt;Shawn Colvin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on vocals, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_McCandless&quot;&gt;Paul McCandless &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_horn&quot;&gt;English horn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 17 years and here we are! I’ve finally gotten around to figuring out the intro to this song. One reason it took me so long was because trivial efforts to learn it were met with unexpected difficulty. Honestly, I had no idea how hard this piece of music was until this week when I started seriously practicing. My fingertips hurt typing this paragraph just from all the left-hand fortitude required to play it. It seriously tore my callouses apart. Sheesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway every single measure of this piece is difficult. Bela originally played it on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resonator_guitar&quot;&gt;resonator guitar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (I’ve always wanted a resonator guitar). Every measure had some weird trick to left- or right-hand acrobatics to make the piece particularly tricky. If you’ve followed my work for a while, you’ll know I don’t usually pick simple pieces of music to learn, but let me say that this was seriously challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of that, there are speed bumps everywhere you look in this piece. I couldn’t decide on a definitive fingering, so it’s up to you how you want to play it. Watch the video and see if it helps you. If you decide to try learning it, please reach out and let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/something-she-said</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/something-she-said</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Erudite Eyes by Robert Fripp (Cover)</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-old-music&quot;&gt;New Old Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I covered Robert Fripp’s &lt;em&gt;Erudite Eyes&lt;/em&gt; in 2011, posted it to YouTube, and forgot about it. Six years later, I stumbled upon it again and found that I really liked what I did. So, in a fit of creativity and motivation, I recorded this video to go along with the song. I hope you enjoy it as much as I enjoyed making it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, my cover is quite a bit darker/moodier than the original. I spent time “updating” it to something more aligned with what Robert might write and release today. There is quite a bit more dissonance and it’s much less cheerful. The song originally came out in 1968 on the pre-&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Cheerful_Insanity_of_Giles,_Giles_and_Fripp&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cheerful Insanity of Giles, Giles, and Fripp&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an album I grew up listening to and still enjoy decades later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard the original, I highly encourage you to check it out. It’s very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NeWE8Su3sVc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/erudite-eyes/erudite-eyes.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/erudite-eyes/erudite-eyes.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/erudite-eyes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/erudite-eyes</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evil Genius</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Evil Genius is an experimental jazz trio out of Los Angeles featuring &lt;a href=&quot;http://maxkutner.com&quot;&gt;Max Kutner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on guitar, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bonepocket.com&quot;&gt;Mike “Bonepocket” Lockwood &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on drums, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stefankac.com/&quot;&gt;Stefan Kac &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on tuba. They kicked off their 2017 tour in Phoenix and I had the privilege of catching the show and hosting the band at my house. I met Max at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bluemouthpromo.com&quot;&gt;Blue Mouth Promotions &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; dinner at NAMM in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max is the guitarist for several bands, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/GRANDMOTHERSOFINVENTION/&quot;&gt;Grandmothers of Invention &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/TheMagicBand/&quot;&gt;The Magic Band &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (see also &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/captain-beefheart&quot;&gt;Captain Beefheart&lt;/a&gt;). He’s also good friends and a collaborator with &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;. You could say we hit it off pretty quickly when we met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evilevilgeniusgenius.com&quot;&gt;Check out Evil Genius’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UrwtFrJ0Y1g?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/evil-genius/evil-genius.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/evil-genius/evil-genius.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and we’ve got the band Evil Genius here from Los Angeles. You guys wanna introduce yourselves and what you play and how you got to know each other?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Sure. My name is Mike Lockwood. I play drums and am from Reno, Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: I’m Max Kutner and I play guitar. I’m from Las Vegas, Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I’m Stefan Kac. I play tuba and I’m from Minneapolis, Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you’re all based in LA now? What brought you to LA?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Institute_of_the_Arts&quot;&gt;Cal Arts &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh? Is that where you all met?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: I met Mike in Reno, actually. We went to the same bachelor’s school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Same bachelor party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Or several…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us a little about your music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Awkward silence.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: This band was sort of started by Max Kutner, so I’ll let him take that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: I really wanted to put together a group with these people. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It happened to be tuba, guitar, and drums. It could have easily been something else.&lt;/span&gt; But, yeah, that’s really all I was thinking about when I wanted to do it. I wanted to play with Mike forever. Finally found an excuse and I wanted to play with Stefan. And here it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eo8Ce2dxEII?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m so glad I got to see you guys play last night. Seriously, that was one of the best concerts I’ve ever seen. It could have just been the atmosphere and I know you guys were exhausted, but just being in that small place and seeing you play up close and personal. And the music… What stunned me was just total creative freedom. It wasn’t like, “free jazz” or something like that, it was just people expressing creative fun and art. Can you tell me about your composition approach and how you guys put these crazy songs together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Like Max said, he got us together because he wanted to work with us as musicians and as people, not so much because of the instrumentation. So, for that reason, we all bring a lot of different backgrounds. Our three backgrounds are pretty different, although there’s enough overlap, obviously, that we can work together. It gives you a situation where that freedom aspect is very constructive for us because there actually are lots of possibilities for things that could happen because of all the different things we all do and have done in other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Compositionally, I’ll be honest, it took me a whole cycle of a tour and a record and some other things before I really knew what I wanted to write for this group. I had to do a lot of sketching, a lot of drafts, a lot of revision, and I don’t even want to say I thought about it a lot, but I had to let it settle and percolate, ruminate, whatever you wanna call it, before this next batch of tunes that we drew on a lot at the show last night presented themselves. And those were much more designed for these guys specifically whereas things that I had before for us were things I’d already had done and we made them work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now we have more of a custom repertoire for the band that actually comes out of the band, comes out of things that we’ve done. As we were talking earlier, the titles of the tunes come out of band events, events in band history, etc. etc., which I think everyone in a band knows how that works. That’s not anything novel, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s good to have arrived at that point where there’s actually a body of work that we ourselves can draw on and be ours.&lt;/span&gt; Whereas we didn’t necessarily know exactly what we were right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think that part of it is always going to stay undecided and I’m totally cool with that.&lt;/span&gt; There’s something that can’t really be defined about all the abstract things that are happening, a working relationship like this, whether it’s happening live, compositionally… That’s stuff that I feel works best when it’s not completely defined. It’s always developing. It’s not to say that we’re throwing our hands back and saying, “It’s whatever.” It’s always evolving and changing. It’s a real living thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re reading a lot of sheet music throughout the night. All three of you. Are the songs more like jazz pieces where there’s very compositional stuff, then there’s “okay, we’re gonna go break for a little while, then we’re going to come back to it…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: There’s all sorts of charts. Some of them are lead sheet-ish. Very few of them, but… You go that direction and then some things are completely orchestrated, notated exactly. At least for these two guys, most of the charts don’t have any drum information so my role has been to–while they dig through reading, I dig through also reading and trying to make sense of what I feel like should happen with their parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I told you this last night. Until last night, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_King_(drummer)&quot;&gt;Dave King &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Bad_Plus&quot;&gt;The Bad Plus &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was the most exciting drummer I’d ever seen live. And then I saw what you were doing and I was like, “I can’t even believe how this guy thinks.” Who are some of your big influences? I hear a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Cow&quot;&gt;Henry Cow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the band, I don’t know if that’s…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/T0Auumv5leI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Sure. Sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I have no… That’s not…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, for you on the drums, who are your inspirations? It was so stunning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Well, Dave King… I’ve listened to a fuck-ton of Dave King and I have tons of respect for him. That’s one. Early on, lots of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Stewart_(musician)&quot;&gt;Bill Stewart &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ari_Hoenig&quot;&gt;Ari Hoenig &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I listen to a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah there was a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyrhythm&quot;&gt;polyrhythmic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff going on. You were playing lots of different rhythms and changing the feel. It was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: The influences have been wider than I would feel comfortable talking about to some fellow jazz musicians. That’s not true, I would talk about it, but it’s all over the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you used a lot of percussion and percussive…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Trash?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Not instruments, but, yeah, trash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Found instrument things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, we don’t have the baguette bag on this tour, unfortunately. We played for this radio station in Santa Cruz called &lt;a href=&quot;http://kpig.com&quot;&gt;KPIG &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we usually travel without a drum kit and we just played this tiny space and we were kind of like, “Okay, what are we going to give Mike to use?” He said, “I have this stuff. Let’s make this happen.” Things like “cymbal on ground,” baguette bag, toys…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I proposed that we rename the band at that point to Bang on the Baguette, but the proposal was not taken by the other guys in the band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: But, yeah, that’s part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How long have you been together as Evil Genius?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: What is it? 3?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: 3 years at this point, although we didn’t play a lot the first year or so. Mike was living in a couple different places for a while until very recently. So, we’ve had the band for a lot longer than our amount of actual playing out might dictate, but now we’re all gathered in Los Angeles. We’re looking forward to being more functional on an ongoing basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/789-VrBsO4c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Speaking of “basis”–bad joke here–hearing you play the tuba in the band, it’s clear there are very normal bass lines going on, but then there’s a lot of bebop parts going on too. I don’t know what the dynamic of a jazz band would be with a tuba playing a bass. I don’t know if that’s a standard arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I think it’s nice that you say it that way, that you wouldn’t assume. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Most people would assume that he’s just playing bass in the band, but Stefan definitely does that, but so much more.&lt;/span&gt; Max was playing bass a little bit last night, too. Passing the roles is something that enables us to be more free, like you were saying earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So tell me about the dynamic of having you playing tuba in this band and how you approach the instrument in this experimental music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When I write I approach guitar and tuba as two horn parts&lt;/span&gt; knowing that if I got any grander ambitions I have more guitar stuff that can happen because of multiple notes. At the writing stage, I look at it just as sort of two &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counterpoint&quot;&gt;contrapuntal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; lines and don’t really worry so much about function unless the style dictates doing something. If there’s a clear bass harmonic, clear soul function, something like that. That can still happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Writing-wise, I think of counterpoint. Playing-wise, I got way into bebop playing in high school and college and didn’t give a lot of thought to even functioning as a bass instrument. I would only do it when I was sort of forced to, which looking back on it is sort of weird, but that’s just the way it worked out. It wasn’t until I got out of school and out doing stuff, going to a jam session…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Once, I walked in and could immediately see the bass player was sweating and panting and unhappy, probably been there all night playing 25-minute long versions of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stella_by_Starlight&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stella by Starlight&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and sees me come in and take the tuba out. After the tune, puts the bass down and says, “Oh, thank God, there’s another bass player here. Can you…” and I was like, “Hey, I don’t really do that. I’m a horn player. I don’t do the bass stuff.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And he looks at me and is like, “You’re a &lt;strong&gt;tuba player&lt;/strong&gt;.” And I’m standing there in front of this guy I’ve never met and I’m like, “Damn, I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; a tuba player. That’s kind of messed up that I don’t know how to do this.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that was one thing that happened. And then, once I got into it, I realized it’s fun to be the bass instrument. You have more responsibility. You’re a part of the rhythm section “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vulcan_(Star_Trek)#Mind_melds&quot;&gt;Vulcan mind meld &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” thing. When I learned that and started doing it, I got hooked on that. So, I do play as the bass instrument in a lot of different jazz settings and other “rock-ish” weird gigs that come along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I played in a polka band for a couple years and we would play rock tunes because there’s rock tunes those bands play and it’s like you’re a rock band with an accordion and tuba instead of guitar and bass. That kind of thing can totally work. But the final sort of synthesis stage of all this was when I got hooked up with people who were really into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Frisell&quot;&gt;Bill Frisell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Lovano&quot;&gt;Joe Lovano &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Motian&quot;&gt;Paul Motian &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; trio and, I hate to say “similar groups” because there’s no other group like that, but that type of group, that era of “jazz music” where not only were roles not as clearly defined, but the group interplay and the strength of the individual voices was such that the roles couldn’t really contain those people and the instruments they were playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JaCCxBIoEZc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I started working with peers who were really into that way of playing, then the external pressure was, “No, I want you to be able to do &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt;” and if you’re both or neither, you go back and forth. I was like, “Wow, I can’t do that. That’s really hard.” It took a long time to get comfortable. I’m still not super comfortable. It’s very compartmentalized because of the way I went through this process, which I think was a good way to learn. I got to focus on one and then the other, but putting them together is not a simple thing, necessarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This group has been great for me in that way and it’s giving me a lot of new ideas and it’s gotten me out of that box a lot more. I do come from those two functions and trying to put them together, I just go with stuff as it comes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s so much baton passing between the three of you. It’s almost like each person kinda takes a turn at leading the band and I don’t know if that’s a compositional thing, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s clear you’re &lt;strong&gt;listening and communicating.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Rhythmically, Mike might start doing something, and then Max will start doing something different rhythmically, and the whole band starts to gravitate around that. Is that something that evolved through your communication style on the instruments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I would say that it’s a byproduct of just being improvisers at our core. That’s probably what probably drives each of us to our playing music like this. Like you said, there’s tons of sheet music, there’s lots of notes, and lots of things to focus on other than the improvising, but that is sort of the root. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The communication thing takes–it’s hard to do this, but it needs to float above all the other material.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah. I would say that’s the thing. It’s very fluid. When I said forming a group with these particular people, I kind of expected that would happen and it wouldn’t stop happening. It’s keep developing. Human beings change and evolve and get into things and stuff happens and that’s going to change the playing too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The communication only gets deeper and deeper and deeper because of that listening and knowing how to listen.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like you’re almost expecting a kind of response from a thing. It’s very interesting to me, but I think it kinda worked out how I figured it would work out. In some cases, it’s going way deeper than I thought was possible in the writing and everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You have this most recent album. Can you tell us about it and what you’re working on now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, the most recent album came out at the end of 2015 called &lt;em&gt;Bitter Human&lt;/em&gt;. It was released on a three-year-old Los Angeles-based record label called &lt;a href=&quot;http://orendarecords.com&quot;&gt;Orenda Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which fosters this type of thing. Los Angeles artists, a lot of jazz fusiony stuff, a lot of experimental stuff, and all mostly friends of our. Well, all friends of ours. Not most. [Laughter.] Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Yeah, so we put it out on that. That stuff is kind of a compendium of tunes that we’ve written leading up in the band. Not necessarily written specifically for the band. Like Stefan said, there’s three pieces he wrote on that. I think I wrote seven pieces on that. And they’re from different stretches, from different periods in my compositional thing. But, we just recorded another album last year at the end of another tour and we’re working on mixing all that now. That stuff is all specifically written for this band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KTGrM231N48?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: We played a lot of it last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay. Yeah, I recognized a few tunes from your bandcamp page, but most of it was new to me. I was so thrilled. When is that album coming out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Hopefully summer. It depends on a few things falling into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Yeah, just trying to line up the mixing and mastering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, trying to figure out what to do with it. Lots of ideas. Not to get into the larger discussion of CDs, vinyl, streaming, all that. Trying to figure out ways we can do that. It’s a different batch from the first album, for sure. It’s a bit more through-composed whereas the first album was kind of molten and feels kind of primordial and looser and more free playing. But, yeah, that’s our recorded thing for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And how long are you on tour now? This is your first? second date? You played in LA last night?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: No, Arizona is our number one. Ichi ban.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Yeah, we played Phoenix last night and we’re playing Santa Fe tonight. We’ll be out for ten or eleven days. Something like that. Going up to Minneapolis, then back through Chicago, and all the way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool! Great! One thing I did want to ask about… And this is my total ignorance on the tuba. I noticed while you were soloing last night, you were primarily just using two fingers and getting so many notes. I know with a horn, there’s a lot with your embouchure. Can you clarify how it is you were able to do so much with just two fingers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KpjkpSdt9k4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I may be able to clarify, I may make it less clear. I’ll do my best. As you overblow through an overtone series, the notes get closer together and what that means is that there’s a new open note, a new open note, and those open notes get closer and closer so that by the time you get into what normally acculturated human ears are going to detect as a regular “middle of the piano” range of sound on the tuba, you’re already way up in the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;French horn is like this also. It’s pitched much closer to the tuba than you’d thing looking at it. They play much higher in the series than trombones do. So, once you’re up there, you’ve got a lot of open notes just stacked up against each other and getting closer together. What the valves do is they add length, so they lower the note a little bit and a little bit and a little bit. And because the open notes are close together by that time, you don’t need anything but the first couple positions on the valves to get yourself down to the next open note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, because playing the guitar, I was thinking it would be like only using three frets on the different strings, but the range you got and the note selection just between supposedly-three notes…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: The other part of that is there’s a lot of “wiggle and blow” in some of those intense tuba solos… [Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: You weren’t intentionally playing every single note?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I was BS’ing some of the notes because when you’re so high up on the tuba, the notes are so close together, you can BS it and you can use your embouchure and your chops and get the notes you’re after. So, I don’t know if that makes it more or less clear. It’s a physics thing. You watch trombone players, you’ll see the same thing. When they’re up in the bebop-trombone-land, they’re up there and the slide hardly ever comes very far out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, the frets get smaller, basically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Mike, do you play any other instruments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Not proficiently enough to do in front of other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’d never guess because the compositions of yours from last night…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: Just one. I’ve only written one for this band and it came after, like Stefan said he felt comfortable after a year and a tour, I felt comfortable after two years and two tours. And also being out of town, blah blah blah…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That was not a simple or easy song. Not that I would expect it to be, but the stuff you wrote for the guitar and tuba were very complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BPnzjkIAvD8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: I’ve been writing music since I started playing. On the computer a lot, but I compose primarily on the piano and going up through a master’s program in music, hopefully I’ve learned some sort of theory that I can actually work my way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: By the way, that tuba part is a good example of something where you look at it and technically it goes against what they’ll teach you in those orchestration classes. It’s not “idiomatic” or “playable,” but when you think artistically and conceptually and think, “Well if the tuba’s not good for this, we should toss it off the bridge and find something else.” It works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: And you’re an amazing tuba player so if you can’t play it, then yeah we should throw it off a bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I practice his parts a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: Mike writes some really guitar-y guitar parts. From chugging chords to effect-laden feedback drone-y stuff. That’s in the chart. That’s not super common amongst the prior music or charts, so that’s pretty refreshing, especially chunking chordal stuff. Albeit, kinda funky chords. I had to re-tune for that tune. I don’t have to do that in any other tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I was thinking in his piece in particular, “I wonder if Mike plays guitar or tuba in particular” because some of what you were doing seemed very idiomatic. I knew you had re-tuned, but I wasn’t paying close attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Max: It wasn’t a super-out tuning. It was just drop-D. But it’s drop-D, not to get the D. It’s drop-D to get a voicing that would be impossible otherwise and it sounds really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: Someone who taught at Cal Arts while we were there would always say that the way to learn about this was just to be around them and eventually start to intuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/udfZORFCq9Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: And having an ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Study-Orchestration-Fourth-Samuel-Adler/dp/0393920658&quot;&gt;the Adler orchestration book &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at my fingertips at all times, but that’s like 5% of it. I struggle with strings and guitars specifically. Orchestra strings also because it’s just such a foreign way of thinking about things. I know how to write clusters on the guitar that you can mathematically calculate what’s possible and what’s not, but as far as coming up with something that’s got that “guitar-ness,” that’s a longer-term process. I don’t know if there’s a book I can read that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Mike: &lt;a href=&quot;http://guitarplayer.com&quot;&gt;Guitar Player Magazine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stefan: There are books I could read, but I’m not going to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: They’re called monthly issues. Anyway, the show was awesome. I saw Mike not reading in a lot of songs, but he was definitely reading in other songs, and you guys were reading almost the whole night. I had assumed he was making up his own parts for a lot the songs that you had written, but it’s awesome to see the way you guys communicate, you write for each other, and you write music that challenges each other. Mike, you’d even said, “Let’s do something hard,” which was so ironic because every song sounds impossible to play. Thanks so much for spending some time and sharing what you do. It really was one of the best concerts I’ve ever seen. It was really stunning. I can’t wait to see what happens in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Band: Right on. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2017 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/evil-genius/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/evil-genius/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aye-Aye Monster by Mike Keneally and Andy West</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mike-keneally-house-concert&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally House Concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2016, Mike kindly played a house concert in my dining room, which was great fun. It took me several months to finally get around to editing some of the footage and this song was one of the highlights of the evening. Mike and Andy did several songs together and Mike did several other songs on his own. More of this concert will be released throughout 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, enjoy this first release from the concert titled “Aye-Aye Monster” from the 1995 release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/music/discography-mike-keneally/the-mistakes/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Mistakes&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://store.keneally.com/products/ex-2303d&quot;&gt;buy a digital copy from keneally.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FvNgs3dWkas?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should check out Mike’s newest album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.keneally.com/products/copy-of-mike-keneally-you-must-be-this-tall-download-only&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2017 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/aye-aye-monster</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/aye-aye-monster</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weasel Shake by Robbie Seahag Mangano</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;weasel-shake&quot;&gt;Weasel Shake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, I went to New York on a business trip and bumped into Robbie Seahag (more on that in a later video), whose name you may recall from our rooftop recording of &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/33-in-buffalo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;33 in Buffalo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; off his sold-out album, &lt;em&gt;Full Moon Fever&lt;/em&gt;. As I accidentally stumbled upon his residence, he quickly taught me another song from &lt;em&gt;Full Moon Fever&lt;/em&gt; and we recorded this fun video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5z2d9EdBF_4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should check out Robbie’s new album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bumbleweenie.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and buy one of his donation packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-stuff&quot;&gt;Video Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robbie graciously offered to do some wonderful animation to make this video stand out from the rest. I’m proud to feature this song on the site and to have participated in this recording. Thank you, Robbie!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for some really fun, funny, and ridiculous content from my day with Robbie. Gonna make your cheeks hurt. I had a headache from laughing so hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bumbleweenie&quot;&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a commercial for Robbie’s amazing new album, &lt;em&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v6kjkAk0jKc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/weasel-shake</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/weasel-shake</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Another Groan by Nick Prol</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9PSlHJzPyzw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Be sure to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/proletariansmusic/&quot;&gt;follow Nick &amp;amp; the Proletarians on Facebook &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nick-prol--the-proletarians&quot;&gt;Nick Prol &amp;amp; The Proletarians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Prol is an artist and musician based in Tucson, Arizona. He’s a super cool dude and has amassed an incredible roster. He is working on a new album with his band, Nick Prol &amp;amp; The Proletarians. Here’s some information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fproletariansmusic%2Fvideos%2F1256978847712376%2F&amp;amp;show_text=0&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The album is being produced by the one and only &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ianbeabout&quot;&gt;Ian Beabout &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and features artists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R._Stevie_Moore&quot;&gt;R. Stevie Moore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rob_Crow&quot;&gt;Rob Crow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinback&quot;&gt;Pinback &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thymme_Jones&quot;&gt;Thymme Jones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheer-Accident&quot;&gt;Cheer-Accident &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), and members of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sleepytime_Gorilla_Museum&quot;&gt;Sleepytime Gorilla Museum &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knifeworld&quot;&gt;Knifeworld &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_Chiefs_3&quot;&gt;Secret Chiefs 3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking_Plague&quot;&gt;Thinking Plague &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bent_Knee&quot;&gt;Bent Knee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a veritable “who’s who” of weird music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shamelessly begged Nick to let me participate in some way and he offered a guitar solo opportunity. He asked for something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discipline_(King_Crimson_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discipline&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; era. I threw in a little &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Frith&quot;&gt;Fred Frith &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for good measure and captured the solo you see and hear above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I’d like to note: I’ve never let myself “go” like I did with this solo. It’s the first time you’ll ever see me &lt;em&gt;move&lt;/em&gt; while playing the guitar. My wife once called me “an impenetrable monolith,” which I’d say also describes my guitar playing. It was a lot of fun recording this and I was highly surprised to see the video afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/nick-prol/another-groan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/nick-prol/another-groan</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
