<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts. We feature interviews and educational content regarding the most creative musical artists in the world.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 23:35:25 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 23:35:25 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alex Lifeson</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qrOdzTH1qWQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;25-years-after-victor-40-years-after-moving-pictures&quot;&gt;25 years after Victor, 40 years after Moving Pictures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 25th anniversary of his solo record, &lt;em&gt;Victor&lt;/em&gt;, and the 40th anniversary Rush’s &lt;em&gt;Moving Pictures&lt;/em&gt;, guitarist Alex Lifeson spent a good chunk of a Saturday evening with us in the midst of the Covid-19 pandemic to discuss life after the death of drummer Neil Peart, what lies in the future with Geddy Lee, synthesizers, guitar sounds, and selling off his guitar collection. This is a wide-ranging interview. If you’re a Rush fan, be prepared to cover some new ground that most interviews don’t cover with Alex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was conducted by Andre Cholmondeley, who joined MWM in late 2019. Andre is Steve Howe’s guitar tech, which is how he met Alex Lifeson and scored this major interview. We hope you enjoy it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to Kathy Starkey for transcribing this interview.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hello everyone, thank you so much for joining this stream. We are super excited to have Alex Lifeson here to talk about the 25 anniversary of his album Victor and it’s great to see so many people online! Thank you so much for joining! Make Weird Music has been around for about seven years and I know a lot of people are new here because you’re coming to see Alex. We have a lot of great interviews, a long history of videos, a couple hundred videos including interviews with Steve Vai, Devin Townsend, a lot of really great artists. The Residents. We’re all over the map! I encourage you to go check out some of our old content and I’d really appreciate it if you hit “Subscribe.” We have a lot of great new stuff coming up - a lot of King Crimson-related content, we have an interview coming up with Henry Kaiser and Andy West of the Dixie Dregs, and a lot of other really interesting artists. Thank you again for joining us today. I am going to kick this off by introducing you to Andre Cholmondeley who will be the host of this interview. Andre thanks so much for facilitating this conversation and Alex thanks so much for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: It’s a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: A pleasure to be here and YES! (laughs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Good to see you again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Good to see you too! How have you been?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I’ve been okay. You know, as everybody, just dealing with this Coronavirus and all that the pandemic brings changes in our lives. Doing okay, a little bored, but starting to get into a few little projects and just trying to keep as busy as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: That’s great to hear. Yes, we last met at the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame, looking at guitars. We’re here to talk about all kinds of things, folks, but one of the things I noticed just a few weeks ago is that it’s the 25th anniversary of Victor, the great record you put out in 1996. What’s also remarkable is that it happens to be the halfway point in the incredible journey that we’ve all been on musically with you. What’s interesting too is I remember at that time you spoke about the record being very cathartic, very spiritul for you, very cleansing. It was an interesting record lyrically and you said it had you dig down and kind of restart. It was a start. Any Rush fan knows that you guys have always changed and developed and evolved over the years, but after that record, wow, there was fresh stuff coming out of you. Reflect back on that for a minute. Did it hit your goals in terms of a restart?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Sure. You know Geddy and his wife Nancy were expecting their second child and Ged wanted to take a year off. We really hadn’t taken very much time off at all up to that point. He wanted to take time off to be with her and the new baby and all that stuff. I thought a year off might make me kind of antsy but this was a great opportunity to into something on my own. Doing the record was really all about just wanting to do something and keeping myself busy. I worked on the whole thing - writing, the lyrics production, all the record, working on the cover and all the artwork - everything about the project I was involved in, as you would expect a solo record to be. It was a really good exercise for me to explore some of my own musical ideas independent of my two partners. I love working with those guys - Ged - my best friend forever - but this was something about me. It was something I really had to do to prove myself that I could actually make a conscious effort to do something BIG that required a lot of work, dedication and attention. So I dove into it and I got together with a bunch of my friends and they played on the record. It just started growing and growing and became the project basically for that year. I came out of it feeling like I’d really done something special for myself. I was of the opinion that even if no one bought the record, if we just sold one record, it was a success! It was all about going through this exercise on my part. Recorded it in my basement in my little studio on the ADAT machines, all my amps were there and my guitars, friends that came over to work on the record stayed over. It was really a fun event for all of us. Looking back on it lyrically it was a very difficult record for me to do. I’m not a lyricist, and having such an amazing lyricist in the band like Neil. It was hard not to be influenced by that and try to write at that level which was just not possible for me. I feel like I did the best that  I could if I was to do it over again  I would… I don’t know what I would do. Spend more time on the lyrics or try to do it in a different language or something and fool everybody. (laughs) Again at the same time there were a lot of people who were having problems in their relationships around me - friends, family members - so there was a lot to work from at time. But when I got through it was really a treat for me. I still feel very proud of the effort and it’s definitely a love of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Wow! That’s great! I love it too. Many things I love about it but I love the timelessness of it. When it came out - there are some synthesizers on it , some textures, some spoken word things - I speak to Rush fans a lot who still haven’t heard it. It kind of went under the radar. That’s why I was excited to give it a little spotlight. It’s quite timeless - the word timeless is kind of trite - but what I love about it is there was always the discussion of the time when Rush went into a lot of synthesizers. You’ve said a lot about that in interviews that some things you would have changed, some things you’ve liked over the years. Talk to me a little bit about the synthesizer approach - wow - there are synths on more than half the tracks. Beautiful stuff! How do you feel now about where synthesizers and guitar kind of ended up for you throughout all those years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: You know I don’t have a problem really with keyboards. Certainly with Rush we always wanted to go somewhere else - to explore something else. Very early on, in the later part of the 70s when we started to introduce keyboards in the band - we took it upon ourselves to learn how to play those things. Geddy played a little bit of piano so he sort of got into it. I had a little bit of background so pedals and other keyboard stuff. That was always something he did. When we got to the mid 80s with Rush we really dove into the whole production thing working with Peter Collins - he came from that sort of background so the whole exploration of really developed keyboards happened. That happened in the recording process before the guitars. Now I was competing for space sonically amongst the keyboards. It was a real challenge to fit the guitar in once that you had all the mid-ranged keyboards laid in. I’m proud of those records we did back then. I think they are really unique for us in our whole history but it was definitely a tough job to work around what we were doing there. I kind of missed the drive of the guitar because it became so layered. I think in the early 90s we turned around a little bit and started to get back into that groove. By Counterparts we were sort of right back in there and had a nice balance of keyboard events and guitar and the power that brings. With Victor because I had an open slate I could do whatever I wanted. I worked with my son Adrian on a bunch of stuff. He’d been writing and playing a lot of electronic music. Although he started with guitar when he was about 14 or 15, that was the kind of music he was into for his age. He brought a lot of really cool melodies, a lot of the technical end of mapping keyboards and sequencing parts and things like that. It became fun for me to fiddle around and do something keyboard wise on my own, having my own material and being very open about the way I was putting it together. For me it was no conflict at the time - it was all part of putting it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: That’s great to hear you reaffirm that you really did love that material as you’ve said in some interviews which is great. What a special time as a fan, I was a big fan of synthesizers so suddenly when one of my favorite bands integrated all of that stuff into Signals, Power Windows… what’s really cool I think for any Rush fan is that you’ve always changed. A lot of great guitarists kind of pick a sound, pick an axe, and that’s what they use, and there’s nothing wrong with that. Angus Young, SG, Marshall - I’ll take it all day long! But one of the inspiring things is that you’ve gone all around the map - from the stacks to the Strats sounds to the piezo type pickups - back and forth. Really remarkable, Thank you for giving us all the template there to experiment. The question on post-Victor: We can hear so many new things you came up with on that record. Right after that you guys didTest for Echo and Vapor Trails. Things got very textural. One interesting thing about Vapor Trails is that there aren’t really any solos. You’re all very expansive and textural. Talk a bit about that period as we come forward in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Vapor Trails was a very very difficult record to make. Neil was returning after his tragedy - a few years after the loss of his family basically. When Ged and I were writing material, I didn’t want the spotlight, a solo in the song where the attention was on the guitar in that way. I wanted it to feel like it was a real band effort, the three of us coming back together after coming very very close to never working together again. In my mind, I didn’t want to stand out in any way. I just wanted to be a part of the team. We kind of wrote in that way. That record took us over a year, and two or three months, to make. In the very beginning we were writing stuff, we hated it and got rid of it. We’d never had that problem before. Neil was coming back after not playing for a few years. It was a climb for him to get back into shape for recording. There were a lot of challenges at the time. Our souls are really in that record. It’s a very unique record for us and it represents that period that we were going through which was very dark, but at the end of it, we came out of it into the light. It’s actually a positive move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Yea. That’s beautiful. It might sound extreme but there are so many life lessons when folks have really enjoyed the art of Rush and what you’ve all said. Selflessness is one of those beautiful things. Anyone who has seen the movie knows what dear close friends the three of you are - still - in the universe. What a great point that you came to that point that you came to that record and said it’s a team and we don’t need the spotlight. Jumping back to Victor, that’s also something remarkable that you decided you didn’t want it to be “Alex Lifeson’s record” - it’s Victor - the team spirit, with the record. Now, there are some rumors out there that you had some other ideas, wanted to follow it up, something maybe with Sarah McLachlan…? Tell us how real any of that was or if you have any other bank of songs for “Victor Continued”…?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: (laughs) Sarah McLachlan?! I didn’t hear that one! That’s not true. She’s awesome but that was never really talked about. Over the years because I have a studio at home forever when we had time off I always wrote stuff. I don’t know how much - hours - of new material. Stuff I could develop with drum samples. Sometimes friends would come in and help with it. I think I spoke to you about it at the Rock Hall of Fame. Steve Howe was doing this. He was releasing some of his demos and we were talking about it. It occurred to me that this would be a great avenue for me and a way to release some of this kind of cool music from at the time, not super produced, not a big record kind of thing. Cool little musical vignettes of where I was at at that time. I still have all that stuff, still talk about doing it. I’ve done some writing. After we finished the last tour in 2015 I couldn’t sit still so I started just writing on my own and doing some stuff. Geddy was working on his book. We talked about getting together and doing some stuff together but it got very very busy for him even after he finished writing the book, taking it on the road. We never got the chance to sit down and start working or just having fun together. We still talk about it, and I’m sure we will. Of course now with the pandemic it’s kind of wrecked things for a bit. We’re both eager to get back together and kind of get back to that thing that we’ve done since we were 14 years old that we loved to do. We work really really well together. We’ll see what happens with that. I don’t know. I go back and forth. I’m kind of a lazy person. The prospect of doing a record after doing Victor and spending a year on it and knowing what it took…. . I don’t know if I’m in a hurry to do that sort of thing again. The advantage of working on my own, in my own place, is that I can work whenever I want to and it takes the pressure off a big release. Those days are sort of over anyways. I would just love to share some of my music if anyone is interested in hearing it. You know, at some point in the future…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: That’s exciting to hear! I think I can speak for people around the planet who would absolutely be interested in that! You had said you had heard some of Steve’s sketchbook demo releases and they are wonderful. They are really inspiring. I’m going to jump around to some gear a little bit. One of the fun things that day for me was having you and Geddy come by to check out Steve Howe’s  guitars. One in particular - an incredible guitar that you are one of the only other rock guys associated with it - the beautiful Gibson ES 345 Stereo. WOW. Is that in the game lately? Is that something you’ve picked up or done anything with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: It’s a 355 - the white one that I have. I have a 345 and a bunch of 335s back here. In fact the one you see here is a ‘58 - the first year that they made the 355s. That’s a very sweet sounding guitar. We’re renovating our condo and getting close to the end finally. I just took a bunch of guitars off the wall to take to our place because I will have a nice little working space in the new place. That’s where the 335 is going right now. It all depends - I’m fortunate. You can’t see the rest of the guitars but this wall behind me here goes up to about 16’ and is all covered in guitars of all sorts. I’m by and large a Gibson player but I’ve played lots of stuff. PRS I played for many years. They make a fabulous instrument. The Gibsons. I have some nice Fenders. Some Teles that I love. It really all depends on what I’m looking for in terms of character. I just pull it off the wall! They all speak a little differently. Being as old as I am, I’ve gotten to play almost all of them, usually on tour. They all have a little bit of history and I understand them and know their personalities. It’s kind of cool to pull things down and do some alt tunings and really have fun exploring. Lately I’ve found that I’m sort of bored with standard tuning. I’ve been messing around with a lot of alt turnings - really bizarre ones, more traditional ones. Now when I go back to standard, it’s like I’m a beginner. (laughs) I don’t know what I’m doing! (laughs) I’m a little scared about that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: You said after a difficult year you were just now starting to tinker around and do some things. How does that look for the next six or eight months? Think you’ll hit “Record”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: You know after Neil passed it was very difficult to get inspired - you can imagine. You lose anyone who is close, it’s a profound thing. I think both Geddy and I expected to be better with it… Neil was sick for three and a half years. It wasn’t really public information. We thought we would be prepared for the end when it came and we weren’t. We both really struggled with it. The same thing happened when his daughter passed away. I didn’t play for quite a long time. At all. Music just didn’t seem that important. It was the same thing with this and then Covid hit and now we’re all in a different mental space. For me, I think, that first year of grieving is the milestone. Once you get past that, I think, I don’t know, it’s an anniversary you can process and it becomes a little easier to handle. With Neil, I’m always seeing pictures and I’m always reminded of him. That was difficult. Now that it’s a year,  I find  I think of the good times we had together more than the sadness. We had SO many great times! We laughed so much over all those years. Aside from the work that we did, being a partner to one of the greatest drummers in history - and bass players for that matter - I just remember the laughing and the smiles and all of that stuff. It wraps up that picture and makes it a little easier to move forward. Once we got past the anniversary it just so happened that Andy Curran who used to work at our office and played in Coney Hatch (a Canadian band). Andy and I had been doing work together on a side project for the last three or four years - maybe longer - yeah actually longer… and I revisited some of those little projects that  I left behind and started working on them again. In turn something else came up down the pipeline and all of a sudden I started playing and I’m spending more time in here and it’s the best thing. I can’t believe I wasted the last 10 months - well not wasted - but that I didn’t do this for 10 months when I had nothing else to do (laughs). This is the perfect thing for me. I’m just happy that I’m getting back into the swing of it. My fingers feel a lot better and I’m enjoying music and making music again. I’m really having fun with some of this stuff that I’m doing now. I also get to explore different areas of guitars - it’s not all heavy rock - it’s atmospheric very very funky some of it is hard and heavy but it’s an opportunity for me to explore different sounds, different tones. One of the things I really enjoy about it is that I’m trying to create guitar parts on guitar that don’t sound anything like a guitar. That’s a real treat! There are so many plug ins and I have such a pile of old gear - pedals and foot switches and all that junk. It’s a lot of fun to put that all together and go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Beautiful. Guitar that doesn’t sound like guitar!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Yeah, it’s a challenge! It’s more a rhythmic thing or atmospheric thing. It’s really a lot of fun for me to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: One of the things I want to talk about are some of the sessions that you’ve done recently. Speaking of guitar that doesn’t sound like guitar - you did a beautiful track on the new McStine &amp;amp; Minnemann, record where you did this “howling guitar.” Talk about that session a little bit - that is a great record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AL: Marco reached out I guess about four or five years ago and he was doing a solo record. He asked if I’d be interested in playing on it. I knew of Marco but I had never met him or anything. I said - sure, I know I just came off tour - send me something and I’ll have a listen. So he sent me a track that he wanted me to play on and I did some acoustic stuff on it. This is the other thing -  I love doing things where whoever I’m doing it with, they come back and say never in a million years would I expect this on this song, would never have thought anyone would think. For me, that’s the main compliment. So we did the track and  I sent the stems to him and he said ok I’m going to use the stems, your parts, in the song, but I like these parts so much  I want to write another song around these parts! So that’s what he did - he created another song from those same parts and we just sort of developed that. We worked together on a few things. We wrote a song called Lovers Calling. It’s a long song - eight or nine minutes I think. It’s a real epic but it goes through so many changes, so many cool atmospheric things. We brought in a singer that I’ve been working with with Andy named Maya Wynn. She’s just a fabulous vocalist. She has such a sensibility about how she approaches her vocals. They are very very emotional. It’s not rock singing, it’s something else. There’s a real depth to her arrangement - the way she puts these things together. I suggested to Marco that we get Maya to sing on the song which she did do. We had a singer previously that did a great job but was more traditional for a rock vocalisation but Maya turned it into this - oh - this thing you just fall into and the vocal wraps around you. Then the music comes in waves. So I think it was a really successful collaboration and it was great to just be able to share files - everybody works that way now basically. There was a real growth. It took about a year or more for the song to reach the point where we were happy with it. We kept redoing things and updating sounds and parts and stuff like that. Rich Chycki did a mix of it for us. Rich is on a bunch of our records. I don’t know -  I think it’s popped up in a couple of places. I know Marco had it on one of his other releases. I was hoping to get it on a re-release of Victor because that was an idea that the label had, but unfortunately with COVID it all changed. Maybe I’ll send the track to you so you can have a listen to it. We are really excited about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: We would love to hear it! Marco - wonderful drummer. I’ve toured a bit with him and U.K. Now you guys were U.K. fans back in then right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Yes - Good ole Alan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Back to Victor for a minute. You said some things there that again I want this to speak to a lot of people who didn’t get to hear the record. I have a philosophy that it’s brand new to someone who hasn’t heard it. One of the things is that there’s lots of textures, guitars, telecasters, mandola is in there, right? Again with that sense of sharing - it’s really beautiful. Bill Bell does some great stuff on it. I want to talk about a couple specific tracks. Strip and Go Naked for instance - just a great short little thing, instrumental. Tell me about that track and if you’ve got some more things like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL:  Yeah, it’s one of the instrumental tracks of three or four on the record. We wanted to really create a song that had that character to it of the mandola, folk sort of feel about it. Bill is a great guitarist. We did a couple of things - he was working, and still does, for Tom Cochrane. Tom is an old friend of mine - we’ve been buddies for a long time and I really respect his music and his playing and he’s a great guy. We did some work together and Bill and I connected and I said, I have this time off and am going to do this solo record if you’d like to play on it. It would be great to do some stuff together. So, we became very good friends and Bill dove into the project. That particular song - I wanted to build it thru that, mandola sort of character. He’s a great slide player and he played some beautiful slide on that song. It has that double crescendo and a very dark sort of moody solo - that’s super compressed. It was a lot of fun putting it together and recording it and mixing it and all of that. I think we changed what we were going after with that particular song - no drums on it, just a drum machine for the kick and high hat maybe. That’s all the drum personality on that record. It was kinda cool I think. I loved playing the mandola and it’s sitting right over there! Again,  it’s a different sort of instrument so it becomes a challenge to find cool things to do on it. The tuning is always a difficult thing on that particular instrument because it doesn’t really like being in tune (laughs) It’s always a challenge. You learn a lot, I think, by doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Beautiful instrument and of course it’s turned up on a couple of other Rush records. Really great. Beautiful piece, short little journey, that one. Another flavor that’s on the record - some Alex Lifeson brutally heavy riffs - the album starts with some heavy stuff. Start Today and Don’t Care, there’s almost Nine Inch Nails aggressive stuff in there. Talk to me a little bit about the track with Dalbello and the heavier stuff…Don’t Care and the Dalbello track..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Start the Day was really a song about reaffirmation and learning from difficult experiences and putting it all together and moving forward. Understanding in a relationship that it’s a two way street, and what you give is what you get back. Having that in mind in the whole concept about the record I wanted to have a female voice on it and Lisa she had a lot of records out in the 80s and she was quite a well known Canadian artist. What a vocalist! What an experience it was to work in the studio with her and watch her manipulate her voice and the microphone. It was - I was amazed watching her. She would move her hand around in a certain way, and she would get around the microphone another way. She really manipulated the whole thing - she just knew what she was doing in there. Real professional. I don’t think we did more than a few takes of whatever we were doing. She just nailed everything all the time! There’s something about her voice at that time that was kind of reminiscent of Geddy in the earlier days. I think that was an attractive thing for me in that -  I wanted to have a woman singing in there but it was cool there was that connection in there as well in terms of a vocal character. I really enjoyed putting that song together. The acoustics that come in after the solo… There’s a section where the acoustics take over. I must have tracked about 10 or 12 acoustic guitars for that piece. Some were recorded acoustically and some were recorded electrically thru the pickup on the acoustic. I just love the scooped mids in those acoustics there’s a really cool character about that song that really impacts… it’s her voice sitting in that scoop - for me anyway - when I hear it. Which is kind of a cool thing. Riff wise it’s a little reminiscent of Zeppelin but at the same time I can’t deny my inspiration and my roots. I even said that to Jimmy Page when I met him the first time that he had been such an enormous influence. I gave him a copy of the record and I said, “Please accept this with my total respect. You are all over this record. Sorry.” (Laughs) That’s where I came from and that is what I hear. I hear him, I hear Jeff Beck, I hear maybe Steve Howe. I mean all of those guys were so important in my growing up and now I’m an old man who I suppose who inspires other younger players so it’s kind of cool that you move that forward throughout generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: It’s beautiful to hear that. Before I go to a couple other tracks, on this topic, as a Rush fan, too, you always talked about what you were listening to. There are some great interview clips and Neil wrote the book about listening to music on the road. You’ve always said - Hey I’m into this, I’m into that. This is exciting to hear that you are doing some music moving forward because that’s what it’s about. It’s about today and looking to the future. So excited to hear that tonight. Looking back for a minute, I want to remind people, in a couple of days, Moving Pictures is going to be 40 years old. I forget the date but in about two weeks. I don’t have to say what an incredible album that is, and to your journey. A track I want to talk about is the last one, Vital Signs. That track - you’ve got the little bubbly sequencer synth on there, you’ve got your guitar takes a new turn and pre-stages you doing the Andy Summers stab chords. I think it’s an incredible track. Also what’s incredible are the lyrics are about this stuff that no one knew about - filters and random sampling and all this stuff that if you look back prestages a whole bunch of stuff. Take us to that track a little bit - that could come out today with the little “doodoo do do do doo” (laughing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: That’s 25 years…that’s tough enough with Victor. Forty years is a real stretch! Moving Pictures was by far the greatest record that we made, from our perspective. We had such a great time making that record. We were in a great space. We spent the summer working fairly close to Toronto, to home, writing it. When we went into the studio and started recording, everything about it fell into place. We really enjoyed the experience. The material was strong and all that stuff. The recording process itself was really a lot of fun and for the most part quite smooth. That doesn’t happen really very often. I could tell you horror stories about Grace Under Pressure - that was SO difficult to make. And Vapor Trails. But Moving Pictures was really a delight. When we came to that song - that jogged my memory - we had stuff on the record like YYZ (Y-Y-Zed) and Limelight and Tom Sawyer that were pretty big block traditional sort of rock songs. Maybe a little more concise than our previous writing as we were moving into that kind of writing economy that we sort of moved into from the late 70s. But when we came to that, it was just really different in the way we arranged it and put it together. Starting with the sequencer, and having that part, then the guitar part, and Neil was really into that kind of drum approach to that ska sort of more of a reggae-ish modern [inaudible] and he was really looking forward to that, and he was messing around with electronic drums at the time too. It all became a part of this little exploration that touched on certain things that were coming to the world from that point forward. That’s really it. I don’t remember much else about it. (laughing)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: It really kicked the door open to a time and a sound. I’m getting a couple questions in - let’s see -  we’ve got a couple good questions from people. I wanted to talk about Canada for a second too - a country near and dear to my heart. I have a lot of family there. There’s just something in the water, I mean, there are you guys, you talked about alternate tuning before, Neil Young, Joni Mitchell, then there are those great bands, like Gowan, Toronto, Oscar Peterson, Drake, Max Webster. Toronto. I love that you have worked with so many folks, Tom Cochrane, Red Rider. Have you been in touch with Jeff Jones in recent years - the early bass player?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I haven’t seen Jeff in about four years. We did a gig together actually at the golf club that I’m a member at. It was their 10th anniversary in 2016. They wanted to do something really special, the owners at the time. They asked Tom and me if we would put something together and play. At the time Jeff was still playing with Tom for many many years. He was in Red Rider, and he continued with Tom over the years. So they were like a back up band. They came to do the gig. We got a big stage, lighting, PA all over the club and outside, it was like a real legitimate gig! There were about 500 people there. Members and guests. It was one of the best gig experiences I’ve ever had - we had so much fun! I got to play with Jack then. We did a bunch of Rush stuff, some Tom Cochrane stuff. I would bump into Jeff over the years when we played with Red Rider in the earlier days. Like I said I haven’t seen him in a while but we do cross paths. It’s pretty remarkable that 53 years later we still have a connection which is pretty cool. That was really a fun night. Bill came, played with Tom, we played an acoustic set, we had the Trailer Park Boys come in from Halifax and they did their schtick. It was a real special night - we had a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Was that captured at all? Is there video?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I don’t know if there was any proper video done - that was an oversight! We should have done something! I haven’t seen anything ever but I don’t know, maybe there is something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Of course..There are a lot of hard core Rush fans here that know that you and Jeff  - that was the beginning of the band in 1968, with John Rutsey,  and Jeff. Also Pete Cardinali, who plays on Victor. I know you did a lot of jamming with him at the Orbit Room. Tell us - what’s the status of the Orbit these days?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: The Orbit closed down early last year. I sort of drifted away from the club. I was there for 20 years. Things change. I was very excited in the beginning. I used to go and play whenever I had a chance on Friday nights or Saturdays. I played with the Dexters. Pete was in the band. But as things progressed, you know, it’s a tough business. I just sort of, I think I just kind of lost interest and it wasn’t part of my life so much anymore. I hung in there, and Tim, my partner, kept going and eventually I decided to get out of the business and I left a few years ago. He carried on for a while and then  I think it was just too much with COVID coming and it was never going to survive. It was a struggle as it was. The Orbit room was a very cool place. In those early years particularly. It was live music every night in the city you didn’t have that back then, a place you could go to for live music. It was very different night to night. R and B, Jazz, all kinds of stuff. It was really a fun place. I find all those places they have their life and then it moves on. We had our regulars and eventually they grew up or they moved on. Things change and it loses their specialness I suppose. But we had some really great times there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: That’s a very honest and realistic look. There are some great videos out there folks of Alex playing some blues stuff, some funk stuff. A couple questions from the folks out there - Christopher Clements asking: As a total gear head, is there the “one that got away”? A guitar that you still wished you could get or you missed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Not in terms of guitars. I was never a collector in the early days. I regret that. In the 70s for example,  I would have had greater access to a larger number of vintage instruments that weren’t particularly vintage - like older Les Pauls from the 50s and particularly from 1960. So  I never took advantage of that. I always believed that guitar is what YOU do with it.  It doesn’t really matter. Most of my guitars from back then are vintage now only because I’m this old and they are old as well (laughs). In the last seven or eight years I did start to vary my collection a little bit and get a couple of older vintage guitars - a Getsch, a 57 Les Paul Gold Top. The 335 - a couple of those a few from that era. I don’t know… I have a Tele that I used… it’s a ‘58 reissue and I bought it in the early 80s. I traded an SG that I wasn’t crazy about at the time for this guitar at a music shop that wwe used to deal with. I tell you, I’ve probably written eighty percent of our music on that guitar. It’s so comfortable to work on. I took all the finish off the neck. It’s just bare wood and it feels great. I love the sound of it. My hands just feel so comfortable on that guitar. For writing, that was really the one for me. Kind of the standard writing guitar. Of course I used it a lot on the records. Typically back then it was a Les Paul on the left and the Tele on the right, or some sort of combination like that. I have lots of guitars and they are tools and I use them and I know them. There’s nothing that I feel like “Ah Damn it! I missed that one!” Or an amp or anything like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Another question: What a beautiful book Geddy did - Geddy’s Big Book of Basses. Is there a thought of documenting these at all, either on the web or doing a book, or somehow telling that story?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Not really, no. I saw what he went through (laughing). It’s a little different for him. It became this whole exploration for him of all things bass guitar. He started collecting before he did the book. It’s not like he was collecting for forty years. Most of his collection is more recent. Once he got into the book he wanted to get specific instruments or models and write about those things, it’s history and all of that stuff. Like I said earlier, I’m a little lazy. I’m not that committed or feel the need to jump in that deeply into something like that. In fact what I’d like to do sometime in the near future is to sell my collection. Would keep a handful of instruments but I’d love to sell my collection for some charities that I’m involved with. I think that would be really a great way for these fabulous instruments that have been so sweet and dear to me to carry on and do something very powerful and positive for the world. That’s something that I’ve been exploring in fact in the last few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: That’s beautiful and what a way to put it forward. Over to Victor again, on that note, go check the lyrics out on this record. As Alex is speaking about, they get into some very interesting areas. What’s interesting is that the last track on the record, I Am the Spirit, as you’ve said before there are some dark moments, there are some humorous moments. That song just pulls it all together. So positive about life, different things. Talk to me about that song because I love that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I wanted to close the record with a very positive statement. Kind of reevaluating myself or anyone for that matter, your strengths and your weaknesses, they make up your character. They both work together - the yin and the yang. Your weaknesses are just as important as your strengths. This is how we progress, learn and move on. In terms of a relationship, the underlying theme is that it goes two ways. There needs to be an understanding and compromise and care and love and all of those things. I wanted to kind of encapsulate everything in that song. Even the fade out at the end just carries the melody and just gives you a chance to catch your breath and think about it as it’s ending. It doesn’t fade to infinity, it just stops eventually. You know that there is a point to get off and move forward. That’s what I was trying to get at with that. It’s a cool song. It’s traditional in a lot of ways. In a rock format, but halfway through the song it becomes another song that is completely different. It’s a really important part of the story of the song. It’s a chance to catch your breath and surround yourself with a different energy. I know that sounds corny but….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: No, the lyrics, I go back to them all the time. It’s some uplifting stuff. From the Rush nerd side of things, there’s a little Easter egg that I’m hearing. There’s a little Spirit of Radio lick in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: In that one, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: It’s like a cousin of that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AL: Exactly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: At the time you had said that you’d love to put something together and get this music on the road. Looking forward - we’re in this global nightmare and we all hope it all turns and we’re going to beat this. Do you envision that maybe that you might go on a short tour to do this material and some brand new stuff? Is there a thought of that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Honestly I think it’s very unlikely, I don’t think anybody is going to get back on the road for a while yet - probably for another year. It’s great that we have the vaccines. Although it’s been a slow beginning it will ramp up but it’s what - 350 million people in America? And I know in this country we’re in single digit progress with vaccines. Like I said it will get better but it will be a while yet. We’re going to be in this same state for another year and then things will turn around and get back into touring and live concerts and all of that stuff. But I gotta say that I’ll be 68 - if that happens! - in a year from now. I don’t know… At this age I don’t really have an interest in doing it. We toured for 40 years. I’ve lived in hotels for 40 years. I was away from the people  I love and that’s all part of it and I don’t regret it. It was great. That’s the price you pay. I hardly saw my dad when I was growing up because he had three jobs to pay the mortgages. We looked after ourselves. He wanted to get a leg up so he worked like a maniac! We all make that sacrifice I think in whatever we love, and our passion. After spending 40 years of doing that…Honestly, I don’t see myself sitting in a hotel room with the remote in my hand going through channels just because I have to wait for sound check or I don’t feel like going out because I don’t know what to do in town and all of that stuff. That’s kind of out of my life now. The fact that we’ve been off the road for over five years, I don’t really miss it. I love playing! I do a couple of gigs here and there, locally, and it’s always a treat to get up and play in front of an audience. But I can’t say that I have this gnawing desire to get up and do it. I did it! 40 years is a long time to be in a band and touring the way we did. Very very few bands that have done that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: You guys did the miles and wrote the book on a lot of that! Hopefully if there’s one or two special shows, we will travel ! If you just did something in Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Never say never, right? You never know! I don’t know if Geddy feels the same way I do. I think he’d be up to playing something live, whatever form that is, but we haven’t really gotten to that point in the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Never say never! I love that - a great quote from tonight. Thank you so much for spending the time with us. We’re getting to the end pretty soon. Before I forget, I wanted to give a couple thank yous as well. You remind me… talking about how much time Rush has spent on the road. Just one of the bands that really clocked those numbers. I wanted to thank Skully, John McIntosh for putting this together. But I also want to thank you guys - very early on, the selflessness. I think it’s the theme of Rush, you, the material, the fact of sharing, and friendship. I want to thank you for touching base on that personally and lyrically. One thing your band always did was very early on you acknowledged you couldn’t do it without your crew. We all knew those names - Howard and Liam Birt - and all those folks, that was really remarkable. You guys kept the same crew for the whole time! That was amazing! That says so much about the band. Tell me a little bit about your wonderful crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Our band crew, like you say Liam and Skip and Howard, Tony, Jack Secret…..Those guys were all there in the beginning and were there pretty much, Skip wasn’t,  until the end. A lot of other crews lighting or sound or raisers or whatever - the hired crews - they often came back because they said I don’t care what tour is coming up, I want to go back to Rush when they come up. It was a beautiful thing to us - quite a compliment. You know those guys work so hard! We fly in or come in on a nice bus or whatever, and you show up at the gig, sound check, you have to eat, do the gig, everyone claps and cheers and get all the adulation and then you leave, get on the plane and go. THOSE guys, and you know this, - slog it out! Putting the gear up, taking the gear down they’re in our case there was such a loyalty of our crew. They would cover for each other. That doesn’t always happen for a lot of crews. A lot of times there’s a lot of separation between the lighties and the sound guys and the band crew. They don’t always get along. WIth us, those guys were filling in for other guys on another crew because someone was sick or something came up. It was a really beautiful feeling of unity throughout our crew. We always really respected them and always tried to treat them as well as we possibly could. You’d hear stories about some bands and their crews that were treated so wrong. The immediate people you work with - either on stage or in an office - at the end of the day you have to respect them, give them space, treat them right. Who are you big shot? Rock star? NO. These people work hard and they love you for what you’re doing and respect you. You have to give that back. We had such a great relationship with our crew. We honestly loved them all. They were all great to work with and were part of our family. I still talk to Scotty - I spoke to Scotty my guitar tech this morning in fact. We haven’t even worked together in six years. We’re still connected. I hear from Liam it’s a good feeling. Lifelong friends. Brothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Really inspiring! A lesson we all saw early on. To the Rush crew!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I’m glad you brought that up. This world needs more of that - unity and respect. Particularly after the last 40 years in American and now a pandemic we have this fighting… I spent 40 years in that country - longer than I have in Canada! It’s heartbreaking to see what’s going on. Get it together and stop it! You know! Easy to say that but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: As you say…. compounded by this global.. viral thing and I’m happy that a lot of people did take it seriously. At this point there’s no fooling around here  –this is biology! It happens over and over in history. We’re just not tuned in - we can’t control everything. Thank you for saying that. Couple other questions from the stream. Someone - Armin Alic - says knowing that your parents were from Serbia, we’ve all seen some great things in the movie about that, do you have any connections to your Balkan roots? Any relatives there? Influence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I grew up in a very Serbian home. My parents spoke English but we spoke Serbian as well. I didn’t speak English until I was about, well, until I started kindergarten. We lived in a part of the city when we first moved to Toronto that was a very ethnic, ghetto kind of area of Toronto. It was all Czech, Bulgarians, Hungargian and nobody spoke English. All the kids played together. There was always music. Serbian music or Yugoslavian music playing in our house. My mother loved it. My father couldn’t really care less about music, so much. He was sort of a blue collar and not really interested in the finer things. There was always that culture… has always a part of my upbringing. Three years ago I went back to Serbia and took my mother and my two sisters. We went back to my father’s home town of Šabac about an hour from Belgrade. We spent a week there visiting my cousins and the people that are left of my family there. It was a remarkable experience for me. I had been there in 1965 when I was 12. I spent the summer there with my dad and my younger sister. I have great memories of that particular trip. So it was great to back so many years later and still see the town is pretty much the same. There are some newer buildings there but not a lot. The economy is very poor there, people are generally very poor.  What I noticed was it does not matter the things that you have, it’s all about your family, all about your friends, it’s all about sharing. We went out with my cousins a few times, for dinner with their friends, and nobody’s got any money but it doesn’t matter. Everyone has such a wonderful time being together. They all love each other very very much. All the friends. It was a beautiful thing to see. My Serbian was very rusty. It got better at the end of the week. It was a little comic at times, I think for my sisters and me. It was really really a beautiful experience! Now, I’m in touch with my cousins all the time. At least every other week at the very least which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Spectacular. You’re right - family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: My dad used to go back from time to time. He built a shed on their little piece of property in the back that they converted into a home - a one room shed but it’s got a bed and someone sleeps there. My dad built another utility shed back there. He would go and do these things for them because they didn’t have anything. He was that kind of guy. In that way I feel like I’m carrying on his tradition and paying homage to him by doing these things and supporting my family over there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: That’s beautiful. Giving back. Beautiful part of the world. I’ve been there just once on tour but wow! Beautiful old buildings and warm people…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Crazy though… (laughs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: (laughs) You had mentioned a little earlier there was a thought for a minute about re-releasing Victor. Who knows with the record industry stuff. Do you have that now? Could you re-release it online so people could get it with some extra tracks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL:  That was the intention. I wanted to at the very least remaster or maybe remix it. In fact, when they first talked about releasing it last spring  I thought ok well this is an opportunity to do the remix. It’s a little bass light, the record. That’s my fault. I was just not hearing things the way I should have been. So this was an opportunity, for me to get in and remix it and freshen it up a little bit, like we did with Vapor Trails. But as time passed I was going to add a few tracks - Lovers Calling was one of them and a couple of other tracks from my little clutch of my stuff, little bits that I’d had written about that same time. I’m really not quite sure what happened. As time went on with so many other distractions the record company just decided not to do it. They re-released Gedd’s My Favourite Headache, last year and they wanted to do it with Victor but it didn’t come to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: We hope it does! Just judging from the comments and support tonight people…. there is an army of folks around the world that would love to hear it especially with some additional stuff. On the record again, the synths - I just love because I’m a big synth head. Do you remember what you used on there? I’m hearing Prophets or Oberheims? Do you remember what’s on there? Virus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I used a Prodigy, a Prophet  I used some rack-mounted synths. I can’t recall the names. That was all Adiran’s gear that was up in our studio. I just basically took over his stuff. (laughs) As I said, he’s a co-writer on four tracks on the record. They were his keyboard ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: And the correct way to say your last name… and Adrian’s last name….?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: My proper surname? Živojinović (ZIV-o-yin-o-vich)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: WOW. ZIV-o-yin-o-vich. Everyone messes it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Yes, it’s a scary looking name! That’s why I’ve used Lifeson for almost my whole life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Is Adrian doing music these days?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: He does a little bit still. He has a group of 3-4 guys that he likes to work with. We have a studio downtown in the city that’s more like a writing room. All my gear is there and his stuff. I don’t know how much they’ve been doing this last year but up until then they were down there quite a bit. I don’t know if they go there to just smoke pot and drink wine and have fun which is what I think is most of what they do and I don’t blame them. They make use of the space for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: That’s great. So people can Google that and find some of his work perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Yes, they’ve had a few limited releases. It’s good - trancy kind of electronic music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: I’ll be looking for it tonight. (laughs) We have a couple fun questions as we wrap up here, Alex. Again, this has been a pleasure, most of all to hear that you’re doing as well as you can, all the different ways and challenges, and that you do see a path to keep creating and sharing with us which is so inspiring. Couple questions… On that note, well it’s legal now! Did you ever think you’d live long enough? Pot’s legal in Canada and all these places! You guys did a track A Passage to Bangkok - for the Rush fans - go to one minute forty-nine…. (mimics sharp inhale sound) Do you know anything about how that sound got in there? (laughing)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: (Laughing) I forget! Yeah, that was fun to write that song! We were cannabis aficionados early on. Here it was legalized in 2014? 2015? In America… quite possibly on a federal level it’llbe legalized sometime in the near future. It’s about time. Here in this country in the early/mid 70s the Le Dain Commission was set up by the government to write a paper on the legalization of marajuana. They recommended, at that time in the 70s that it should be legalized. But…the American government was not interested in having a neighbor where, you know, everyone was smoking pot. This was the time of Nixon so nothing ever came of that,  until his son Justin Trudeau legalized it in this country. You know what? At the end of the day it was no big deal, everyone was excited about it. We were on both sides of the argument then after a year you don’t even notice anymore. It’s no big deal. You smell it around a little bit more but honestly, it was all those wasted years, right? All the people sent to prison for a joint. (scoffs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: I’m happy that here, we are getting more and more states legal and more people getting released. Fun song and that’s one of those songs - sometimes people think of Rush as this serious band, and there are a lot of serious topics. Again I look back and so many things you were right on about - Witchhunt, Show Me Don’t Tell Me, the concept of Fake News. Neils hit so many great topics. But there were always fun things like Passage to Bangkok, or your Rock Hall of fame speech , your gear stuff in the tour books. I love that! There’s a real yin yang, of just (being) light. Shut Up Shuttin’ Up. Want to close on the title track, that’s just another one. I’ve played that to so many people and they can’t guess who it is because there’s no real guitar on it. I just love that track - just a moody, ethereal, art piece. Of course I’d also like you to touch base on how you ran into a 50 year old poem by the wonderful W. H. Auden. Talk to me about Victor, the title track a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I had received a book of Auden’s poems from my wife as a birthday gift. I wanted to do a song that didn’t have guitar that was completely out of my wheelhouse. I was reading through the book.  I keep it at my bedside and read through. I came across the Victor poem, which is very long. The song is condensed. It really struck me, and when I was fiddling around with some of the sounds there was a real darkness about it.  By being judicious with some of the lyrics, I could create this vision and this dark character and dark story. Bringing in the saxophones and the other keyboard stuff. It was just something I thought that would be unexpected from me as a guitarist in a rock band. That was really the motivation on it. It became one of my favorite songs, on the record because of the way it was constructed. And how it all worked together and how the story line worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Wow. The timelessness. I’ve said that a few times but that’s the beauty of music really. it’s all timeless. You put on Cab Calloway and if you haven’t heard it it’s new. That song in particular is from a time and place - we’re back there! A lot of people are listening to ambient music. Great synthesizer stuff. A couple things on music that we all love and listen to. I know you’ve done some work with Steven Wilson, Porcupine Tree. Have you heard his new work which is very electronic - his brand new stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: No, I haven’t yet. But I will for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Super electronic and all kinds of modular stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Good for him!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: What are you listening to these days, if anything?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: I haven’t really been making an effort to listen to too much outside of this room and what i’m doing in this room. Generally at home here when we’re sitting around we just put in Chill Radio on Apple. I like having that background music. Just not really focused on chasing anything right now. I always find that when I’m working on something the less specific music I listen to the better. It’s ok to have that background ambient stuff but I find it sneaks into what you’re doing and I don’t like that feeling. I like to be really really fresh. You know I’ve always written in such a way that it’s always the early stuff that’s my best stuff, that speaks to me the most. Then I move on very very quickly. Maybe it’s because of the laziness or just being a little antsy. I don’t really belabor a lot of stuff. I’ll come back and I’ll listen a million times. But  I like to get performances out..so l like to keep a clear head,  I tend to not listen to too much new stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Got you. Alex this has been really so special, and I want to thank you again for giving us some time. I think I speak for all the fans here, guitar fans, art rock fans, prog rock fans, Rush fans, that we would love to hear you doing some new music, with Geddy, or on your own, so please do that. I try to not inject myself into these interviews - it’s about what the artist - but I will say a special thank you because this band has meant so much to me. I saw every tour from 1979 to 2012…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Wow - ME TOO! (laughs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: (laughs) You were there! (laughs) Rush college from the age of 14. The music, the guitar playing, the complete textural journey you guys have had. Most of all, that it’s going to continue and that you’re going to do some new music for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AL: Thank you, Andre, thank you so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AC: Thank you! Thanks for checking it out folks, we’ll see you soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AL: See ya!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/alex-lifeson</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/alex-lifeson</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture Book Teaser</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;teaser-video&quot;&gt;Teaser Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LGZhGCMHSaw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-failure-to-fracture&quot;&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a video series I’ve put together about all the things that have stood in the way of my successfully playing the song &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; despite years and years of study, practice, writing, and making videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-list&quot;&gt;Episode List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Episode 0: Introduction&lt;/a&gt; (includes notation/tablature)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/stress&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Tension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/picks&quot;&gt;Episode 2: Picking Picks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/inefficient-picking&quot;&gt;Episode 3: Inefficient Picking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/overzealous-precision&quot;&gt;Episode 4: Overzealous Precision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide&quot;&gt;Episode 5: Alex Anthony Faide Interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/impossible&quot;&gt;Episode 6: Fracture is Impossible to Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/share/failure-to-fracture-book-teaser&quot;&gt;Failure to Fracture Book Teaser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;22-years-in-the-making&quot;&gt;22 Years in the Making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/a&gt; series is much, much more popular than I ever expected. When I started Make Weird Music, I thought, “If I ever get 250 subscribers, this will be a huge success.” Well, here we are 6 years later and there are over 8,000 YouTube subscribers and my Fracture videos have accumulated over 100,000 views. That is a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; way above 250 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late February, I started writing my thoughts on Fracture and then it turned into a book within a few weeks. I made a teaser video after I finished writing all the book content. I hope you enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is YUGE. And it’s going to be so beautiful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also preparing to release “final” performance videos of Fracture and FraKctured alongside the book. Here are some of my latest practice runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;larks-3-intro&quot;&gt;Larks 3 Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0rGrhRvtG-g?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fracture-at-129bpm-performance-tempo&quot;&gt;Fracture at 129bpm (performance tempo)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qMBSM0yCNqQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frakctured-playalong-with-recording&quot;&gt;FraKctured (playalong with recording)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hu_V9V-q-Vo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/failure-to-fracture-book-teaser</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/failure-to-fracture-book-teaser</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Clueless at The Work by Anthony Garone</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-book-for-all-sorts&quot;&gt;A book for all sorts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Buy Anthony Garone’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cluelessatthework.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clueless at The Work: Advice from a Corporate Tyrant&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, published by &lt;a href=&quot;https://stairwaypress.com&quot;&gt;Stairway Press&lt;/a&gt;. Available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Clueless-Work-Advice-Corporate-Tyrant/dp/1949267296&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/clueless-at-the-work-anthony-garone/1133915699&quot;&gt;Barnes &amp;amp; Noble&lt;/a&gt;, and other online retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’m not doing Make Weird Music or with my family, you’ll find me working at &lt;a href=&quot;http://garone.org&quot;&gt;my day job&lt;/a&gt;, advising technology startup companies, working with local colleges and universities, and more. I’m a productive person and I enjoy working. A lot of people ask me, “How do you get so much done?” In fact, so many people have asked me over the years, I thought I’d write about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of what I’ve written comes from lessons I’ve learned through Steve Vai, Robert Fripp, mindfulness, and lots of reading. The purpose of the book&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is an excerpt from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In any profession, 90% of people are clueless but work by situational imitation, narrow mimicry &amp;amp; semi-conscious role-playing. Except social “science” and journalism where it is 99% and 100%, respectively. — &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nntaleb/status/942367860709609472&quot;&gt;Nassim Taleb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know I was clueless until a conversation with acclaimed guitarist &lt;a href=&quot;http://vai.com/&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; on September 29, 2014. Steve introduced me to the transformational power of mindfulness. His life had changed through learning to be present in every moment, a practice developed in meditation. The concepts were so far beyond my understanding and capability, I just pretended to know what he was talking about. I was clueless. I didn’t actually see the depths of my cluelessness until a rude awakening six months later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2015, I was in Tepoztlán, Mexico with &lt;a href=&quot;http://dgmlive.com&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp&lt;/a&gt;, another world-renowned guitarist and composer. I was attending his week-long introductory course about music and the guitar. A few days in, Robert spoke at length about connecting our bodies, minds, and instruments with the present moment. He emphasized the importance of training our bodies to be still, appreciating silence, identifying musical opportunities, and self- control. I listened and nodded intently while mindlessly bouncing my right leg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, Robert said, “Everyone look at Anthony bouncing his leg for reasons he cannot even begin to describe. Is he controlling his body or is it the other way ‘round?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole class turned to look at me and my leg. My brain began processing this unexpected moment of humiliation. I was desperately searching for a witty comeback to deflect and defend my injured ego. Everyone laughed and Robert smiled at me. I decided to say nothing, laugh at myself, and pretend I was fine. It’s better to play it cool and take it in stride, right? It took a few minutes to get my blood pressure and heartrate back to normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I had one of those “a-ha” moments. My brain was flooded with memories of Steve talking about mindfulness. I heard his voice in my head saying, “Being present in the moment means having full acceptance of who you are and what is happening around you. Do you see these flowers in front of us? They’re not pretending to be anything other than what they are right now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt both gratitude and nausea as I began to recognize my cluelessness. I was grateful that two of my biggest musical heroes had personally shared priceless, life-changing wisdom with me. I felt nauseous because I was acting like a hypocrite. Instead of digesting and practicing what my heroes had shared with me, I nodded my head, acted like I knew what I was talking about, and pretended to be someone I wasn’t. Robert saw right through this and I became the perfect example of mindlessness for the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brief moment of embarrassment led to a much greater realization. I had spent 33 years of my life learning how to appear successful to the world through “situational imitation, narrow mimicry, and semi-conscious role-playing.” I had no idea how to respond to my cluelessness or how to fix it. Yikes. It was time to change, quit acting, and start authoring my own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve’s gift of knowledge and Robert’s gift of feedback helped me to start living life more earnestly, authentically, and humbly. I began studying every aspect of my own behavior and with great scrutiny. I learned to sit still, quiet my mind, and be comfortable with extended periods of silence. My relationships changed. My control over my body improved. My awareness of thoughts and mental habits changed. And for the first time in my life, I started feeling a calm confidence in my capabilities while being tested by life’s challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 33 years, I represented the cluelessness described in Nassim Taleb’ s quote on page 1. Though my cluelessness was revealed to me through musical practice, I learned that I was just as clueless in my professional work life. I’ll share dozens of stories about that in the following pages. Addressing my cluelessness has meant spending the last several years voraciously reading, observing and analyzing my behaviors, having in-depth conversations with mentors, practicing what I preach, putting my skin in the game, and failing. Through this work, I have developed the invaluable skill of knowing when I actually am clueless and sensing when I probably am not. I now feel as though a veil has been lifted from my eyes and I’m able to see myself and the world much more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Taleb’s “90% of people are clueless” bit, I’ve since seen plenty of that in my own work experience and personal history. From CEOs who can’t make decisions until they’ve met with some advisory group to fresh-outta-college young people in their first real jobs, many people just don’t know how to succeed in their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People unfamiliar with Taleb are likely to misunderstand his words. He does not believe people are stupid idiots living with their heads where the sun don’t shine. He does, however, hold people accountable for their beliefs and is quick to call out their hypocrisy, especially if those people put themselves in positions of authority. Having read all of his books, nearly every tweet over the last few years, and watched every speech of his on YouTube, I think he’s largely misunderstood. There’s a big difference between believing people are idiots and telling people they are acting like idiots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are “clueless” and “work by situational imitation, narrow mimicry, &amp;amp; semi-conscious role-playing” because they simply don’t know any better. Schools don’t teach us how to succeed. They teach us how to be good at school. I’ve mentored and coached C-suite executives, departmental leaders, line managers, and individual contributors who’ve all suffered from these (and other) symptoms of cluelessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most of these coaching conversations, it’s clear they haven’t augmented their real life experience with honest discussion, meaningful books, community participation, or failure. They often haven’t sought out help before. They do well enough in one job, move up the ladder, apply for and get other jobs with increasingly longer titles and higher pay, and eventually find themselves in jobs that no longer make sense to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb wrote a chapter in his book Skin in the Game about a type of person he calls Intellectual Yet Idiot, or IYI. The chapter is available to read for free online and I highly encourage you to check it out. Read it from top to bottom, and don’t stop when you find yourself offended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main point is: he has no tolerance or respect for armchair experts who make decisions for other people while keeping all the upside and transferring the downside to others. Once you grok his message, you start seeing it everywhere you go. Bureaucratic and political managers at work who don’t seem to do or know anything, but never get fired. Family members with pot bellies giving diet and nutrition advice to others. “Entrepreneurs” who never started their own businesses and bought their way into leadership positions. Cluelessness everywhere you look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are a lot of IYIs. They often enjoy positions of high status and visibility, never getting their hands dirty with real work. They somehow manage to have high salaries and get to decide who to fire when the revenue is running dry. They get undeserved bonuses during economic downturns. They have corner offices and no discernible relationships with people “in the trenches.” They provide drive-by decisions in meetings, take conversations off the rails, and leave teams unnecessarily bewildered. They go back to school when they are bored in their careers. They think education will close the gap between the current and desired circumstances, all the while believing they have a clue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They want to change the world, but they can’t even keep their bedrooms clean and their beds made. They rarely have original ideas. While they aren’t the entirety of the 90% (and they couldn’t be or else the world would fall apart), they’re probably a decent chunk of that 90%. I certainly don’t want to be part of the 90%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Buy Anthony Garone’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cluelessatthework.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clueless at The Work: Advice from a Corporate Tyrant&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, published by &lt;a href=&quot;https://stairwaypress.com&quot;&gt;Stairway Press&lt;/a&gt;. Available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Clueless-Work-Advice-Corporate-Tyrant/dp/1949267296&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/clueless-at-the-work-anthony-garone/1133915699&quot;&gt;Barnes &amp;amp; Noble&lt;/a&gt;, and other online retailers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/clueless-at-the-work</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/anthony-garone/clueless-at-the-work</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Angels and Demons That Play by Paul Sears</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FLfK175hQsg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-podcast-download&quot;&gt;Audio (Podcast Download)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/paul-sears/angels-and-demons-that-play.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/paul-sears/angels-and-demons-that-play.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This transcript is in progress. Here’s the first 16 minutes…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Drumroll. Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Paul Sears is a drummer who has a really crazy history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Fact!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And he has detailed a lot of amazing stories about his career in his new book. It’s called Angels &amp;amp; Demons. It’s published by Stairway Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Angels &amp;amp; Demons That Play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Angels &amp;amp; Demons That Play! Yes. So, it’s a new book on Stairway Press. It’s a really great book. I’ve known Paul a few years now. We met on Craigslist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: 2011?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, something like that. I knew you were an amazing drummer, but I didn’t know that you could write! This is a great book, man! [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Good. I’m glad you liked it. It was a real chew to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: I’ve always liked to talk. I’ve had the gift of gab. Basically what that book is is me gabbing and writing it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. Well, it’s funny because as I was reading it, I could hear you speaking. I read this whole book in your voice. And it’s very clearly your voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: And you didn’t go insane?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, I didn’t. Before we got too deep into that, for people who don’t know much about you or your history, why don’t you share some of the major highlights of bands you’ve been in and work you’ve done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Well, for most of 40 years, I was in a group called The Muffins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Walking the Duck excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Based in Washington, DC and we started a home-grown record label back in the 70s. The Muffins were, oh gosh, probably the 5th or 6th band that I was in. I joined up with a group of people, The Muffins, who were amazingly the only people in that area, or anywhere that I had run into at that time at the young age of 22, that were into the Virgin Records and the European progressive rock scene. Henry Cow, Fred Frith, Gong, yada yada yada, and they were the only people that I had ever met in my life that were into that sort of scene and listened to that kind of music. So, it was like a ready-made club. We got on really, really great and made a splash in the 70s and we lasted until 1981. Our last album then during the Mark II phase was with Fred Frith and that’s actually resulted in my favorite record of ours ever, which is 185.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: All right. That’s the only record that we made after a tour where we really knew the music when we walked into the studio. We knocked that thing out in two days of recording, three days of assembly and mixing, and then off to New York for mastering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is that the record where in the book you share a story about doubling your drum part and it was so precise…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Not me, not me. It was Tom Scott’s saxophone part. It was the alto solo that’s in The Antidote to Dry-Dock tune. He had played that solo the same way for so long it became a part and it’s pretty insane solo. It’s probably 20 seconds long, if that, but listen to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Antidote to Dry-Dock excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I did today before you came over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: After Tom played that, the engineer and Fred were having a chuckle and said, “Wow. Bet you can’t do that again.” And Tom said, “Take the first track out and give me another track.” And I thought those gentlemen were going to wet their pants because it was so spot-on, you can’t tell it’s two saxophones. But we knew our parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So after 185…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: After 185, The Muffins sort of ennui set in. A couple of these guys were starting families and so the band drifted apart. Billy and I kept the house for about another year and then he started a family. My dad got ill. He was diagnosed with stomach cancer, so I moved home to help with family and not much music happened of any organized fashion until the very late 80s when I went to see a dear friend of mine’s group, the Teresa Gunn Band. Great group from the Washington area. She had an amazing bass player. He was playing far beyond what the music needed. He was really quite the hambone. This was a guy named Mark Smoot. I decided, “Teresa, I just might swipe your bass player.” So in between sets, I got to talk to him and found out that he was not only a Muffins fan, but a fan of all the other stuff that we all shared in common with The Muffins. So, he and I played together for about a month, just the two of us improvising and building on systems, then we built a band called Chainsaw Jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Chainsaw Jazz excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And then you got back together with The Muffins…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Well that… gosh [whistles]. Long time there. Back when the web became publicly available, I jumped on it and, just for spits and giggles, I started looking around for The Muffins and I’m like, “Wow! There’s a page here about The Muffins on some newsgroup.” So I’d print it out. And then about three weeks later, I had filled up a notebook that fat with stuff people had been writing about The Muffins on the web, on various newsgroups, like alt.music.progressive, whatever it was back then in the early 90s. And so there was so much written about us, I got a bug up my butt to try to get the band back together. Nobody had any real confidence in that ever happening, but in 1998, while I was working with another group, 9353, I found the stars aligned and I had accumulated enough evidence to present to the guys that, “Hey! You’ve all had your families and paid your mortgages and all this neat stuff. You want to play some music again?” And, lo and behold, they did. So we had another run from 1998 that lasted until 2016, or 2015-2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, and you released the Live at Orion DVD, which I’ve got right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: That was done in 2002 at Orion Sound Studios with the help of several of our friends. Tom–this is an amazing thing for you techno people out there–Tom Scott put together that DVD, edited it all together, rendered it, did everything on a Windows 98 DOS computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: I think it took him 72 hours to render it or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, I’ve gotta watch it again with this new appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Maya excerpt from Live at Orion DVD]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: So that’s pretty cool. And then we made several more albums after that. We went to Italy and we went to France and did not see the Queen’s underpants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs.] Alright, so you as a drummer, you’re one of the most powerful drummer I’ve ever heard play a kit. One of the things that astounded me so much about your playing is your ability to compose parts when the music may be so “off.” You know, like there’s just so little to grasp onto rhythmically or melodically, but somehow your parts unify everything. So I wanted to get a sense of where you’re coming from as a listener and as a musician and how do you view the drums compositionally in the context of a group like The Muffins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PS: Well, two things come into play. One, I’ve been playing with other warm bodies in bands since 1967. So, I’ve got a lot of experience. I grew up with a lot of music that the 70s progressive-style bands were borrowing, so when I would hear Frank Zappa or Renaissance or Genesis or somebody, I’d go, “Oh, that’s Stravinsky. That’s Polank. That’s Jahanna Lane. That’s whatever.” So I had all this music in my brain thanks to my dad ever since I was a little kid. Improvising, I never really did until 1972. I was working with a very fine piano player named Steve Freeman. I have no idea where he is these days. He played grand piano and a Rhodes, but he preferred to play his Yamaha grand that he had in his apartment. He and I had jammed and he said to me, “One day, bring your drumset over to my house and we’re going to just do an improvisation. Just grand piano and the drums.” And it was one of the most liberating fun days I ever had, playing off this guy and having him play off me. So then, I went off later on and worked in a couple of more rock bands: Tinseled Sin and I went to New Jersey and worked with groups Pandemonium and Whisk. In Whisk, the guitar player, one of the main guys, was Kenny Siegel, who designed the Snarling Dog guitar effects pedals that you see everywhere nowadays. Really great guy. After a year or two of pooting around with them and having fun and joining the New Jersey musician’s union, which was a trip–AFLCIO and those guys in those days–I was frankly getting bored with the direction of the band. I’d go on back to visit my family over the holidays and I ran into my first ever bass player from my first band, Pepe Gonzalez. Pepe had since evolved and gotten heavy into jazz and he said, “Why don’t we do a fusion group? Like Weather Report, Mahivishnu-type thing?” So I said, “Okay!” So I went back to New Jersey and had to sever my ties with those guys. We’re all still friends. And came back to DC and built a band with Pepe. Again, I always start with a bass player if I’m going to start a project and I have any control over it whatsoever. I start with the bassist, get tight, and then I bring in other people. That’s what we did and we put together a really cool group called Magic Theater, which was–oh gosh, the biggest influence was probably 70s-era electric Miles [Davis]. You know, Garth [Webber] type stuff. And then, Pepe started bringing more straight up jazz into the picture and that’s anathema to me. I didn’t want to play in a jazz band. Didn’t then, don’t now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/paul-sears/angels-and-demons-that-play</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/paul-sears/angels-and-demons-that-play</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gently Disturbed by Avishai Cohen</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4TothIYckG4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-perfect-album-video-transcript&quot;&gt;A perfect album?! Video transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you catch the time signature of that piece? Yeah, I didn’t either the first time I heard it in 2010. Don’t worry though, I’ll share the answer with you at the end of this video. Anyway, back in 2010 my good friend and then-coworker Andy West played me this song in his car on the way back to work after lunch. He said, “I just heard of this jazz bass player from Israel. He’s unbelievable. Check out this song and see if you can figure out the time signature. I think you’ll dig it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy was right. Not only was the time signature otherworldly, but I really did dig the piece. When the song ended, he said, “You gotta listen to the whole album. The guy’s name is Avishai Cohen and the album is called Gently Disturbed.” So I bought the album on iTunes later that day and gave it a listen. It immediately blew me away. The opening piece, titled Seattle, was one of the most beautiful and tender pieces of music I’d heard in a long time. It warmed my heart to hear such a beautiful melody complemented by these exotic-sounding harmonies. And since nearly all of my own music starts out as piano compositions, usually in strange time signatures and with unusual harmony, I felt right at home as a listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second track, Chutzpan, is the one Andy played me in his car. Its bombastic ostinatos, energetic drums, aggressive piano, and awesome improvisational interplays completely captivated me. It was my first time hearing Mark Guiliana on drums, which was an ear-opening experience for sure. He does things in this piece that are just so out there, from how-did-he-think-of-that rhythmic permutations to how-does-he-do-that, crazy-fast cross-sticking. I really can’t imagine the amount of effort and practice it took to get a song like this to sound so musical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third track, Lo Baiom Velo Balyla, offers an unusual mix of peaceful groove, airy space, and what sounds like a Phrygian dominant or harmonic major scale, all of which are representative of Avishai’s unique musicality. Given my total ignorance about the Middle East, I’ve researched and learned that he often arranges traditional Jewish songs into jazz pieces. This one is a traditional Hebrew song and the title means, “Not at Day, nor at Night,” and seems to be about a girl wondering who her future husband will be. It’s a gorgeous piece of music that’s very singable and catchy. It starts as a slow waltz and evolves into an upbeat, very danceable, groove. I love it. There’s another song on the record with many of the same musical qualities called Puncha Puncha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other tracks are like musical tongue twisters with very challenging rhythms and overlapping cyclical motifs. You’ll hear this in pieces like Pinzin Kinzin, Eleven Wives, The Ever Evolving Etude, Umray, and Structure in Emotion. Some of these songs have that same level of complexity and multilayered structure as Gentle Giant songs like Knots and On Reflection, which feature multilayered vocal parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t go song by song through the whole record, but I will say that I think the album is perfect. Yes, like, actually perfect. A work of perfection. I have listened to it many, many times, particularly while traveling, and it has always touched me in some way. It feels like an old friend now. Many of the songs feature masterful gentleness, pauses, and melody lines that make it stand out from nearly every other record out there. It is very dynamic, sounds fantastic, and makes you feel like you’re in the studio with them. It’s extremely intimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s talk about the band. Gently Disturbed features Avishai Cohen on the bass, Shai Maestro on piano who was only 19 years old when this was recorded, and Mark Guiliana on drums. It was released in 2008 on Avishai’s record label, Razdaz Recordz. Avishai has played with several jazz heroes, including Chick Corea, Bobby McFerrin, Kurt Rosenwinkel, and a jazz hero of mine, Danilo Perez, whose Providencia album basically broke my brain when I first heard it. Also keep in mind that there are two Avishai Cohens, both of whom are jazz musicians born in Israel just a few years apart, but one plays the trumpet and the other plays upright and electric bass. This video is about the bassist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I’ve listened to Avishai’s albums, the more I have discovered and enjoyed. I even bought two sheet music books from Avishai’s website just to study along with the music and and connect with it even further. A couple of songs make really interesting use of chromaticism and dissonance, like the title track, “Gently Disturbed.” It’s got some melodic lines that almost make the piano sound like a microtonal instrument. At other times, the middle eastern scales really add a sense of tension to my western ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the overall beauty of the album is the very unique use of rhythm. Each band member layers polyrhythms in nearly every track. There are times when you can hear one of the musicians counting time by clicking their tongue on their teeth. It’s just wonderful, like those moments in some Frank Zappa vocals where you can hear his mouth opening and closing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shai Maestro’s use of chord substitutions in several solos makes me feel like every instrument, including the drums, briefly twists itself into alternate universes. None of these techniques are overused, though some friends have criticized Avishai’s use of repeating patterns and ostinatos, to which I say, “Go listen to Philip Glass or Steve Reich and then talk to me about repetition.” Others have said Mark’s drumming is too busy for the record, but they’re just wrong and don’t yet realize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which leads me to mention what an absolute beast Mark Guiliana is on this record. There are times when he really supports the melodic and chordal work on the piano and bass, and then there are other times where they support him on some very adventurous drum solos. He is a truly unbelievable player that I wish would do more records with Avishai, though Avishai has somehow found some secret well full of the most talented young drummers in the world instead. I did have the pleasure of seeing Mark play with John Scofield and Brad Mehldau at the Blue Note in New York City, which was such a treat. Mark is one of the best live drummers I’ve ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to the whole album on YouTube on Avishai’s RazDaz Recordz channel, but I recommend you just go out and buy it. It is really a work of art. And if you like this record, I recommend you check out these albums, too: Seven Seas, Aurora, and Lyla. Stunningly beautiful records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve unfortunately not had the chance to see Avishai perform live, but I’ve heard from friends that he’s fantastic in concert. Instead, I have watched several full concerts on YouTube that are quite enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know in the comments if you are a fan of Avishai or if he is new to you. I’d love to hear your thoughts on this music. Thanks for checking it out and thanks to Andy West for pointing me in Avishai’s direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and the time signature for Chutzpan is 17/8.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/avishai-cohen/gently-disturbed</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/avishai-cohen/gently-disturbed</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trey Gunn and Markus Reuter at SeaProg 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I flew out to Seattle to spend some time with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; and several others for &lt;a href=&quot;http://seaprogfest.org/&quot;&gt;SeaProg 2019&lt;/a&gt;. It was a great time and I was able to film a few shows. Here is one of them. Here are Trey Gunn (ex-King Crimson) and Markus Reuter (Stick Men) performing a largely improvised set over some pre-composed motifs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance-video&quot;&gt;Performance video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Uorh9X4FVBM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Music:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trey Gunn, Warr guitars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Markus Reuter, Touch Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Dennis Rea and the SeaProg crew for letting me film and making my life pretty easy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/trey-gunn-markus-reuter-seaprog2019</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/trey-gunn-markus-reuter-seaprog2019</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EchoTest at SeaProg 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I flew out to Seattle to spend some time with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; and several others for &lt;a href=&quot;http://seaprogfest.org/&quot;&gt;SeaProg 2019&lt;/a&gt;. It was a great time and I was able to film a few shows. Here is one of them. This is EchoTest featuring &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/julie-slick&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt; (bass), &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/marco-machera&quot;&gt;Marcho Machera&lt;/a&gt; (bass and vocals), and Alessandro Inolti (drums) performing a majority of their latest release, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/daughter-of-ocean&quot;&gt;Daughter of Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance-video&quot;&gt;Performance video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/delItL4njoI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Music:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Julie Slick, bass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marco Machera, bass and vocals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alessandro Inolti, drums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Dennis Rea and the SeaProg crew for letting me film and making my life pretty easy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/echotest-seaprog2019</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/echotest-seaprog2019</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nik Bärtsch's RONIN</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few years ago when I started listening to Nik Baertsch, I thought I’d never have the chance to see him perform live. And then the unexpected happened: my generous friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://stairwaypress.com&quot;&gt;Ken Coffman&lt;/a&gt; sponsored not only &lt;a href=&quot;/concert/nik-baertsch&quot;&gt;a solo piano concert&lt;/a&gt;, but just a few months later he sponsored Nik and his entire zen funk band, RONIN, to perform in Apache Junction, AZ on March 21, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would have filmed and recorded this show myself, but I was part of the opening act. Maybe there will be video of that some time in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I hope you enjoy this performance of &lt;em&gt;Modul 60&lt;/em&gt; from RONIN’s album &lt;em&gt;Awase&lt;/em&gt;. You can buy &lt;em&gt;Awase&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikbaertsch.com/shop/&quot;&gt;Nik’s online shop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance-video&quot;&gt;Performance video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2vGqZSLpzGo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Music:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nik Baertsch, piano&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sha, clarinet and sax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kaspar Rast, drums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thomy Jordi, bass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All music (c) Ronin Rhythms Production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Executive producer:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ken Coffman, &lt;a href=&quot;http://stairwaypress.com&quot;&gt;Stairway Press&lt;/a&gt;, Bytech Concert Services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Videographers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deb Kay, &lt;a href=&quot;http://fishgateproductions.com/&quot;&gt;Fishgate Productions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zachary Olson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rita Betti, &lt;a href=&quot;http://fishgateproductions.com/&quot;&gt;Fishgate Productions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sound production:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Ross, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pasoundsystemrental.com/&quot;&gt;Big Deal Entertainment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Post-production sound:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://russmullersound.com&quot;&gt;Russ Muller Sound&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/nik-baertsch-ronin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/nik-baertsch-ronin</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Damon Shulman's Plausible Cause</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SJzmRn0eLU0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-podcast-download&quot;&gt;Audio (Podcast Download)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/damon-shulman/plausible-cause.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/damon-shulman/plausible-cause.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-transcription&quot;&gt;Video Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Anthony “Ant” Bowles for the interview transcript.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;Buy &lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://damonshulman.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;Damon’s Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When I interviewed Damon Shulman about his album &lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt; in July 2017, almost two years ago, I had no idea that both he and I would face so many technical difficulties. But it’s really been on my heart the last couple of years that I never released the interview because Damon really is an artist that’s unique and worth your time and attention. Now if you’ve followed this site for any amount of time, you know that I like to try to release the highest possible quality of video and audio quality content, but that’s just not really an option on this one. Nevertheless, I really hope you enjoy the interview. It’s deep and philosophical, just like most of our other interviews, but it just has been difficult for me technically. Anyway, please enjoy this interview and check out Damon’s music at &lt;a href=&quot;https://damonshulman.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;DamonShulman.bandcamp.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VX95Ba74kS0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Damon Shulman is a musician from the south of England and he has a new album out called &lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt;, which I heard when it came out and I think it’s fantastic. It’s a very adventurous and fun album and Damon is here to talk to us about it.
Damon, thanks so much for joining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Hello, thanks for inviting me, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you share with us a little about yourself and a little about the album?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Yes of course. Well my name is Damon Shulman as you said. I am from the south of England, as you said and I am a musician, a full time musician and composer, producer, recording artist and sometimes live artist as well. I’ve been playing for a very long time. I’ve been playing in bands for forty years when I was about eleven and obviously I did a bit of schooling in between but obviously, I’ve been playing for that long and I started off as a bass player and was writing songs as well during what was called the Punk, New Wave era and was, funnily enough, influenced by people like my brother and my father, who showed me all kinds of music and it had a big effect on me. I could kind of tell, really from day one that I wanted to pursue this quite seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Music that is and so I have. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s been periods when I haven’t done it but now I think it’s full-on till the end and I’ll keep going and keep going. I just love playing music, basically. And recording more than anything and writing. And basically that’s it.&lt;/span&gt; I come from, you probably know, I come from a musical family anyway. At least 50%. My mother can’t hit a note but my father was basically quite a serious musician at one point. His father as well - my grandfather. So there’s a tradition - Oh and my uncle as well so there’s quite a tradition in the Shulman family. So why not keep it going? My sons are also musicians, so we just love music. It’s a huge benefit, I think, to the world and I want to be part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s fantastic. Can you tell us a little about &lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: &lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt;, yes I have to count them off &lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt; is my sixth solo album project. I had a bit of a gap. I’d done a project with a band about three or four years before. The last solo album was done in 2010. I was due to do something and I wanted to give it some kind of concept. Actually, I tell a lie there [laughs]. I forgot I actually did an album two years before called &lt;em&gt;Transition Process&lt;/em&gt;, which was actually supposed to lean to a new album, some new form of concept and that’s what it was called. I wanted something very definite to focus on and all I could think of is - I’m not a great person for anniversaries. You know, birthdays, decades - ‘Oh well done, you’ve survived’ that kind of thing. But I just broke through turning fifty and, well you know, let’s have a little review of my life. Maybe it’s not a bad thing to look at and what I thought was ‘What makes me me?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I went through a lot of back history and things that had happened to me. You know certain behaviours that I’d had throughout my life. So I thought this has got some substance. And about half way through this process, I realised I was embellishing, in my own mind - in my own internal dialogue embellishing things, which is odd. You might do it over drinks, that kind of thing.&lt;/span&gt; You know the fish, the fish, the ever growing fish that you’d caught but I started realising this is a very odd thing that I’m doing. Everything I was thinking was true (and that was where the plausibility came in) was true to a degree but not the entire truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I found myself saying, you know, I don’t think I’m being entirely honest here. This is how I became THIS from THIS. So it kind of broadened out. I thought, ‘Well if I think like this, surely there are other people who think like this’. So I started looking at all kind of things. You start looking at history, you know, how history is reported, how differing views of history, politics current affairs and you always see there are two sides to something. Well if there are two sides, there’s got to be - well there are two sides to the brain but there’s got to be multiple ways you think about oneself and this was why I was interested in this and this was before I got to the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So this was all about literally, plausibility and what we think causes certain things. I didn’t have to be specific about it. I didn’t have to focus in on what I consider controversial which I kind of want to avoid. I’m not that, I don’t want to be specific about things. I’m not really here to upset people or anything like that. I just have a world-view of things. Kind of a well rounded view and what I consider… erm it’s just for the listener to decide on the impact, you know, of what occurred. I basically got all these ideas together - this is about, essentially people like myself, so I had to be musically quite accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had planned to go a bit further off the edge but I felt there had to be some accessibility, sense of humour and just as if you were having a conversation with somebody, a long one. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The album’s not all that long but you know those nights with a friend, you go through everything and maybe you’ve known people for a long time and someone points and says ‘No that’s not true.’ You know you could be talking to a friend and they say, you know ‘I was there.’ and ‘these things you’re saying are not true, what you’re saying.’&lt;/span&gt; And it doesn’t have to be confrontational. It’s just like, it’s funny. You know the fact that you can have all these ideas and in a cold kind of sober moment, suddenly realise ‘Oh No, I’ve made a fool of myself.’ So that’s kind of interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And musically, I wanted to convey that through various different means. I was most grateful for what you said about &lt;em&gt;Clarity Phase&lt;/em&gt;, the second song on the album. Interesting case in point. I wanted to create a very simple idea of a diatonic, simple climb up a scale and then on the ride a simple idea, simply played - tritones in major sevenths on the way down and then 2-5-1 at the end. And I was playing this cause everything you play, I mean I enjoy messing around and I can tell you how my process goes for writing, in a minute but with that one it just amused me, the idea - ‘Oh this seems like something.’ and it’s actually not but it kind of develops into something quite maudlin at one point in the middle, you know. That was all kind of funny to me, really. Also - I mean without wanting to be too dramatic, it actually develops into something I wanted to sound quite touching as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So there you go, all those kind of things going on. It was all about - ‘Here’s a thought.’ It seems fairly valid, whether it be musical or not, there then is an alternative to that and you’ve kind of got to be accepting of that or hopefully be successful as a writer. Accepting both approaches. Does that explain some of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, yeah. I think it’s fantastic. Actually, I have a big bookshelf right behind the camera and it’s full of books about what you’re talking about. We don’t ever make decisions rationally, at the time. We just make a decision and we rationalise looking back and we are often embellishing and believing things about ourselves in a positive light because we’re our own best friends. Whether we’re depressed or not. We tend to and have to, to survive we have to see the best things about ourselves. So it’s been a very interesting journey for my myself, the last few years of reading and researching. So a lot of that album’s material does connect with me in that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: That’s great. I absolutely agree with you as well. Funnily enough, when I’m writing, recording, just thinking about anything in particular - you know what, I kind of had the opposite kind of approach. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t read at all. I try and avoid those structures of influence because I want to be purely me.&lt;/span&gt; Without wanting to sound pompous, to create the art, because the art is, for me I suppose, although I don’t have a direct definition on me but the art for me is creating something from the imagination that is very much real, is insight - not insight but in our sight	and we can develop it through the imagination and hopefully through some skills as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Like I say with my writing process, though you haven’t asked me the question but I’ll volunteer this - how I go about writing generally comes from practise. Believe it or not, I love to practise. I’m a guitarist first of all; that’s my first instrument. As I said I started on the bass and that was one of several things - I started on the violin when I was four. It was literally thrust into my hands as if to say ‘Well you’ve got to play an instrument.’ and I was alright because I learned some music from that. I had some tuition and I learnt some music, some dots and also the idea of how to make sounds that were interesting for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You know and then I learned trumpet but it was all uncomfortable for me all that stuff. Never learn the trumpet if you’re looking for an easy life, you know. It’s physically demanding and it’s just incredibly hard to play but that’s my father for me. He’ll do that kind of thing - ‘Try that son it’s what I play.’ ‘OK dad.’ but then it’s ‘No I don’t like this.’ ‘No, carry on.’ ‘No I really don’t…’ And eventually it was a case of I do want to play but no. And eventually a guitar was put in my hands and I did try a few things but funnily enough it was my uncle Ray [Shulman of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt;] who said ‘Try him on the bass.’ He was a bass player and I did and ended up being recruited into my brother’s Punk band, who were a bunch of sixteen and seventeen year old geezers from Portsmouth and wow, I had a great time at eleven and twelve. But what was I saying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Practise, That’s where most of my music ideas come from.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like delving into, I’m interested in the whole process of music. I think it’s a fascinating thing. I think it’s fascinating when humans have created this amazing complex language that has so many variations. From a western point of view, twelve notes and you think this is unbelievable and you just think, wow so many combinations and the methods you can go around things and you can make it be the most complex thing in the world or the simplest thing in the world and vice-versa and through juxtaposition you can communicate with people, sometimes without a single word. That to me is fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I dive straight into it and use this in my practising and it becomes composition and that’s how it happens and how &lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt; was created - an awful lot of ideas from memories and influences. I’m deeply, sometimes burdened but deeply influenced by certain musicians and certain sounds as well. It’s sometimes the most obvious, if you like, popular music that I’m interested in. Also at the other end of the scale, the weirdest if you like. I think, at least I’ve been told that it really does come to fruition and you can hear those influences. You wouldn’t necessarily know exactly who the influences were. This is not contrived in any way, it just happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Over a period of years I just used to write songs, like we all do - write a song but that wasn’t enough for me. I really wanted to be interested. I kind of like the autodidactic process - teaching yourself and trying to educate yourself and pushing always pushing. In which case you have to be curious, I’m very curious - investigative. Looking at those intriguing little passages that are kind of dark and unknown to you. Go and research, go and have a look at them and I think that’s how you move on. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Sometimes you reach a dead end, other times these tributaries really have gold at the bottom of them.&lt;/span&gt; So that’s what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plausible Cause&lt;/em&gt; was like that. There are different styles in there and the way I structured the pieces not songs. Does that sound snobby? But you know from one to seven you’ll find if you listen, the styles kind of, or this was my intent anyway, but the intent was to start with a kind of dissonance. The lyric in the first piece is straightforward and simple. It’s about confusion - a general observation of what people I talk to are saying - ‘What’s it all about?’ They don’t know anything yet they they carry on and tell you what they think they know - certain people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So there’s a certain level of confusion that it always seems to be to leave me feeling perplexed. I thought, ‘Well I definitely don’t know anything having spoken to you. I know even less.’ So I have those sort of conversations. So I have these opening salvos of flat five arpeggios going up and down with a minor seven arpeggio and it sounded interesting to me while I was practising and I wanted to build something up with what was a fairly facile lyrical idea. You know it’s getting a bit dark really, saying ‘I don’t know what it’s all about.’ - just saying that. So I thought there was some kind of interesting contrast there and bit by bit that unraveled. It’s really quite jerky, quite quirky, the first piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s more fluency there and by the time you get to the end, it’s almost Rock and Roll. I mean track number four could sound a bit balladeery. Kind of a love song but it’s a bit of an acerbic lyric there. A bit self self pitying actually in certain respects. That is based on my love of old jazz standards. It’s not a tribute but it is a nod to it and how, in their syruppy sentimental way, they really do have some impact and that’s what I wanted. There’s really quite a serious lyric on that. I said self pitying but I really meant self deprecating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s not entirely about me, there’s just two or three lines in there but you get autobiographical about these things. And that was what you really could consider a very straightforward song. This is track four called An Honest Man. Just thinking about that (because I skipped over two) &lt;em&gt;Honest Man&lt;/em&gt; was in fact being earnest - being honest about something and musically, just straightforward. Just play this three, sixes dada da da dada da kind of thing, which sounded a bit, half Doowoppy - half Jazzy. But then it has that middle guitar and piano solo. I’m a real hack piano player by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I solo on the piano I have to use me left hand. And you build up to this, rationalising things. There’s a sudden rationalisation of the end by the time you get to track four to record. Just explaining, I’m doing them out of order. Which is probably how they came to me. Obviously I don’t write them and at the same time decide say this is track 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You may be rationalising right now, I don’t know. [Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: But going back to the pieces, it almost became an exercise, initially and then it became a process of seeing both sides of an argument and the point was and the obvious cliche was a moment of clarity. The song doesn’t mention me having a moment of clarity. It’s all about making an initial decision and then doubting that decision. I might be right or I might be wrong. I’m not really sure about this and that’s what sends you into awe for the people of power, who are so assertive and affirmative with their decisions and of course, they’re not really that assertive. They’ve got to show that. Yeah, so that’s where it was going to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Some people become president like that. [Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Absolutely! And what can you do about it? You can go march on the street if you want but all I can do is laugh. Because, what can you do? Write music I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One thing I wanted to bring up - It takes a special kind of insanity to play every instrument on an album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: Well, it’s because I have no shame really. I don’t mind embarrassing myself. I’ll give anything a go. I’ve been doing it for some time, that kind of thing. If I’m really honest, first and foremost, I am a guitarist and that is what I work on but I have in my time, played many different instruments. I’ve encouraged other musicians to do this, because if you’ve got a certain propensity for musical instruments, I believe you can give most things a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;To be honest the drumming on this was written using drum samples. My setup, at the back of my house, you can’t get a reasonable sound there. That was one hell of an research job because I have strong ideas of how I wanted the rhythm to work. I don’t write it down on a stave or anything and that was difficult to sort out. Eventually, it all came together how I wanted it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And also I work on a budget of between seven and ten dollars [laughs] If I’m spending nine dollars fifty, I’m really stretching it.&lt;/span&gt; So you know I can’t go to a studio and play it. I’m not a great drummer but I’ll play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So was that done on a keyboard, you program a MIDI grid? The drums sound really good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: It’s Billy Martin playing - Billy Martin samples. All legal - all bought. My budget isn’t that bad really. It was all taken from his kit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I was really impressed with the drums and how they fit in and drive some of the songs along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I like songs like that - driving and also that kind of polyrhythmic kind of thing, working against the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Very, very interesting drum parts but I have to say the guitar parts are so adventurous. I’m a guitarist too. Like that whole last part of &lt;em&gt;Clarity Phase&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Clarity Phase&lt;/em&gt; excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s so twisty, turny, adventurous. This is the most astounding guitar work I’ve heard in years. It’s just so different and you’re not trying to fit, you’re not trying to do anything idiomatic to the guitar. You’re playing like a written, interesting part on the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I really appreciate you saying that and thank you very much. They were written parts, not improvised but the guitarists I love to listen to are improvising but I didn’t want to do that on this album. I’ve done that on recorded pieces but I don’t think it would have worked for where I wanted the guitar solos to be. I wanted the guitar to scream a particular message, whatever that may be, whatever the listener wants it to be. Therefore the use of certain scales against certain chords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Certainly it was necessary to write the parts although if you wanted to hear my track recordings, it wasn’t two takes. The high risk of going through a number of bars, certain shapes and certain runs is enormous. You could be like ‘I got it, I got it, I got it. I haven’t got it.’ So it got to that twenty five, thirty take thing. But so what, I just had to do it. I’m really glad you noticed that. I thought long and hard about that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And that came from practise drills but it’s that intrigue and it depends how far you want to push it - how far you want to push that dissonance. How close you want dissonance and consonance work together. How close can you go?&lt;/span&gt; At what point does someone listening say that is dissonance and I’m saying it’s not? That’s what I’m doing and hopefully, it works. It worked for you and that’s good enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It really works and it’s really interesting and it goes way beyond what other guitarists are doing. I can hear one who’s had a night of four hours just trying to play one part. I can hear the frustration coming through and you’re stretching yourself on certain parts of the album and I don’t say that in a pejorative way. It’s really cool to hear someone stretching themself to their own limit and it still works musically. But for a musician who knows about recording, who knows about performance, I can hear that you are really striving and I think it’s awesome that you put it out the way that you did. It’s a little bit messy at times and it’s just in a little universe that stands on its own and is pretty different from what’s out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I really appreciate those observations because they’re correct and I feel, fortunately or unfortunately for me - probably unfortunately and that’s why I’m on a tight budget. There gets to a point when the striving bit is absolutely right. I got to my fifties but I don’t feel you can rest on your… I’m not a satisfied guitarist. I’m never happy with what I do. I don’t think I’m good enough, particularly when I watch someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Wc7Qvp8Zs6U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My first influences on guitar - my dad introduced me to Robby Robertson - &lt;em&gt;Give Me Some Time&lt;/em&gt; - harmonically played and with so much tenderness with the guitar but then when I discovered Jazz quite early, I was eighteen, nineteen and the first time with Joe Pass. A beautiful guitarist, beautiful harmonies. Fluid, the chord changes - everything about him was fascinating for me. And then Wes Montgomery and then later on Pat Martino - his ideas. Using parental forms and all that kind of stuff. Talk about pushing you - making your mind work, thinking ‘What’s he talking about ?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially when you don’t know, it’s like WHAT IS HE TALKING ABOUT? And then after the elucidation - Ah! The revelation. You realise what these people are talking about, all of a sudden and that’s why these people play like that. They don’t use it every five seconds. They’re usually playing with what most people understand. Having that in there somewhere is really useful for you and of course - John Scofield, I adore. Fabulous guitarist. He’s one of those guitarists who, when he plays a note, you know instantly that’s John Scofield. So those are the types of guitarists I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZPUWhmQ1Hvk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What about Allan Holdsworth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I know a lot of people like Allan Holdsworth and I appreciate what he does but it almost gets scientific. I like the approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He’s exploring other boundaries to those other guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: He’s very much doing his own thing. I mean, poor fella’s gone now. You’ve got to appreciate people like that because they are very much doing their own thing and creating their own sound. I think the problem for me is emulation. I mean when people try to be Allan Holdsworth. I guess it kind of clouds my judgement. Yeah, obviously he’s a very good guitarist but not a big influence on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I only brought him up because of the exotic scales you are using in some of the solos on the album. I was curious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I’ll take that as a complement. If I’m being compared to Allan Holdsworth, it’s a massive complement. Blimey!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Your note choices are really different. So I love it; I thought it was great. So for people who don’t know about you and where to get your music and find out about you, where do they go to support you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;DS: I should have written this down somewhere. I’ll tell you what, I used to operate a small web site but it’s a complete waste of time business wise. It’s a lot of money to do these things so I literally just run off BandCamp. I have my BandCamp site, which is https://damonshulman.bandcamp.com/ and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/damonshulman/&quot;&gt;a Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DamonShulman&quot;&gt;a Twitter account&lt;/a&gt;. That’s all I’ve got. No wonder I’m so famous. I can’t stop people knocking on my door all the time. [Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah the video I published recently with an artist called &lt;a href=&quot;/share/shawn-persinger/halloween-baptizm&quot;&gt;Shawn Persinger&lt;/a&gt;. He wrote a book called &lt;em&gt;Nobody Knows I’m Famous&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DS: That’s right. Maybe we should get together and he could write a book about me. No one will read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LYuThacYhVA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/damon-shulman/plausible-cause</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/damon-shulman/plausible-cause</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2019 Studio Tour</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sjEOizX4j_o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-podcast-download&quot;&gt;Audio (Podcast Download)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/2019-studio-tour/studio-tour.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/2019-studio-tour/studio-tour.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcription&quot;&gt;Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, I was building a Lotus Super 7 replica using a wrecked Mazda Miata donor car and a body kit. After my wife and I had our second child, I had to sell the car due to lack of time. That’s when I said to my wife, “By the time I’m 40, I want to have a home studio and a Lotus Super 7.” Her response was, “You can choose one.” It was a tough choice, but I eventually went with the studio. And in early 2018 at the age of 36, I bit the bullet, got a home equity loan, and got started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my studio and this is the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a home studio is easily one of the best and most fulfilling things I’ve ever done. Sometimes I sit in here and gaze with childlike wonder over how much I love this private 280-square-foot creative oasis. Part of me knows it’s because of all the literal blood, sweat, tears, and money my friends and I put into it. Part of me knows it’s because I’ve built a place where I can find peace. Part of me knows it’s the ikea effect on a pretty large scale. But the most interesting aspect is what it represents: freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many musicians, I’ve dreamt for years about moving my gear out of a cramped bedroom and into a proper, dedicated creative space. It all started as a teenager when my dad and I built a small studio in my old bedroom using an Alesis ADAT XT, a PowerPC Mac tower with an A/V card, a cheap 8-track Mackie mixer, a CD burner, and a CD stomper. We would track directly to the ADAT, run each output through the Mackie, and print to the stereo inputs on the Mac’s AV card. From there we put the audio files into a CD-burning app called Toast and we were able to get our music into people’s ears quickly and easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We mixed and recorded several albums there, including his musical interpretations of the Mesopotamian story The Epic of Gilgamesh and the Navajo story Big Star Way. I also recorded  my first two “albums” Hansel Vs. Gretel and Mytopia there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teenager, I saved every dollar I could to buy music gear, including a Johnson Millennium amplifier, several instruments, strings, ADAT SVHS tapes, blank CDs, and CD label stickers. It was an incredible, hands-on learning experience for several years. Then in 2002 I got an internship with Steve Vai and learned how things are done in the big leagues. My dad and I went all-in on Pro Tools after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I moved out and got married, I still kept a bedroom studio, complete with Tupperware containers full of cables, hard drives, CD spools, and instruments. When my wife and I had kids, I got rid of my amplifiers and got a digital drum kit, which allowed me to record at any hour without waking a sleeping baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, when I started MWM 5 years ago in 2014, the recording studio also became a video production studio and required a ton more gear, including lights, cameras, tripods, and a backdrop. The site grew and grew, as did my collection of gear, until I just couldn’t fit in a 110 square foot room anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2017, after a couple years of discussion, we bit the bullet and decided to build something new in the backyard. We set a budget of about $25K, got a home equity loan, and I worked with my neighbor who runs a construction company. He and I got a design together and spent several months refining and getting through the permit approval process until we finally broke ground in May 2018. We went through every idea from an upgraded Tuff Shed to prefab kits to structural insulated panels to storage containers to tiny houses. I spent hours and hours and hours researching this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live in Arizona where it gets very hot in the summers and fairly chilly in the winters. I also live next to a main road with lots of traffic, so insulation was a major concern. We decided on 2x6 16” on center construction for the walls with R-19 fiberglass batts. We did 2x12” 16” on center for the roof with R-38 fiberglass. I wanted a southwestern-style building with a single sloped roof so I could have a square wall to film against in the back of the building. I wanted to walk into the building and have a rising ceiling to give the illusion of more height and it worked out great. This also had drainage advantages to handle Arizona’s flash-flood rains that could drop several inches of rain in just a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of drainage, we also had to design new drainage flows for the areas surrounding the building. We put in a French drainage system and graded the dirt so water would flow into the French drains. We also added gutters on my house to help with the drainage. The last thing I needed was any chance of flooding or risk to the foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My neighbor and I designed the inside with two zones in mind. The front half would be the entry zone with computing, socializing, and slumber functions. I work from home a lot, we like to have company over, and we frequently have touring musicians looking for a place to stay for a night. The back half of the studio would be the video production zone where I could film and keep gear set up without constantly tearing down and reassembling when I wanted to film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major consideration was electricity. In the old bedroom studio, I tripped our circuit breaker in the summer pretty regularly because of all the electricity I needed to film at night with lights, computers, and a dedicated air conditioner. That room shared a circuit with our kitchen appliances, so if I drew too much power and my wife used the microwave, it was bad for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of grand ideas in mind when designing this thing. I wanted tons of shelving, everything on wheels, a ramp system outside the house to make it easy to transport rolling gear, and more, but a lot of this was pure fantasy for someone who’d never built something of this scale before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had an in-ground hot tub in the backyard with its own 160-amp circuit and subpanel. We used all that amperage for a dedicated HVAC mini split system and two 15-amp circuits inside the studio. I knew I would primarily use LED lighting and camera gear, so the 30 amps would be overkill, but better safe than sorry. I made sure there were plenty of outlets in the design, so we put in floor outlets, ceiling outlets, and lots of four-gang outlets on the walls. Altogether, I believe there are 52 outlets in the building, as opposed to the 6 outlets I had in the bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We faced several weeks of delays in the permit approval process. We ripped out the hot tub, my neighbor’s company poured a slab, and we framed it very quickly. I spent weeks putting up OSB and plywood sheathing waking up early before the scalding Arizona summer heat would begin. I usually started at 6, would have some meetings from 730 until 8, then I would work more until 9. If I could work through lunch, I would. Then I would work from 5pm until dinner and sometimes after dinner until about 9pm or sometimes later, like until midnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hours were grueling, but I was incentivized to finish as soon as possible. The quicker I finished, the quicker I could start working out there. I barely published any MWM videos during that time. Plus it was so hot that I just wanted to be done with the project. I almost passed out several times nailing down plywood sheathing on the roof in direct sun that was easily 120 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My kids helped out a lot too and learned on the job. They used a skillsaw, measured wood, and helped out with the fire blocking pieces protecting the roof from risk of fire. They also helped a lot with installing electric wiring and outlets. It was fantastic even though we were all so so hot out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t articulate how difficult and painful the framing process was for me. I hit my thumb so many times that it bled internally under my fingernail. I had dried blood in my thumbnail for at least 4 months. I dropped hundreds of nails when they would bounce out of the OSB sheathing. It was so infuriating that I had emotional breakdowns at least once a week that ended with me smashing 2x12” scraps into pieces with a hammer. I’ve never been so angry at my mistakes as I was in this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the framing was complete, I hired a contractor to install a membrane roof and “dry in” the building. This was a major milestone because I could then leave tools in the building without worrying about weather. Many beers were had to celebrate and enjoy this milestone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another friend helped me with all the electric work and the ceiling lights. I hired a contractor to install the high voltage wiring and subpanel inside the building. He also helped me get my wiring up to code. I learned how to wire outlets and switches on YouTube and used the pigtail method on every outlet, even when it was unnecessary. I loved doing pigtails, cutting and stripping wire, capping everything, and preparing the building for live power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the electric was done, I bought some windows off a friend who was remodeling his home. Then I had another couple of friends help me install them and the doors. They also helped with the insulation installation. This was a very grueling process because our framing wasn’t exact and required a lot of unnecessary cutting of the fiberglass batting. We spent several days working on that. It was painful. Really painful and we worked past midnight for several days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part of the insulation installation was that I could bring my portable air conditioner into the building. Between the windows and the insulated walls, I could keep the room in the 80s as opposed to the 90s or 100s in the weeks prior. This was amazing, although the air conditioner kept filling up with water and I had to drain it almost every hour during the rain season. It was a pain and I eventually just let the water drain onto the floor so I wouldn’t have to drain it manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was drywall, which was a bit of a fiasco because I wanted the ⅝” longest sheets possible for the ceiling. I ordered 12-foot sheets from Home Depot and my friend and I installed them with a lift. These sheets are REALLY REALLY heavy. This was easily the most frustrating part of the construction because we kept measuring and cutting incorrectly. We had to buy replacement sheets and it was a huge mess. I still can’t get all the gypsum dust off the floor. I will never do drywall installation on a ceiling again, especially with 12-foot sheets that weigh more than 100 pounds each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it easier, I bought a tool called a rotozip and it was the greatest tool I’d ever used. The best $80 spent on the whole project, without a doubt. If you are doing anything with drywall, get a rotozip. You will not regret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned everything about drywall installation on YouTube. I also learned that drywall installation isn’t easy, especially the mud, tape, and texture process. I installed all the drywall on the walls by myself and did not want to deal with the mud and tape. So I hired a local crew and they did a fantastic job. Absolutely fantastic. They made all my flaws disappear. It was stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the texture was finished, I started painting the inside and the room came to life. I also hired a crew to put exterior insulation and smooth finish stucco on. This process took a couple of weeks because it’s many coats of concrete and the process requires curing. It was also raining a lot during this time, so it took much longer than I expected for this to get finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this I was able to hire a guy to install the HVAC system. He did a great job, but the first unit he installed was defective. He also went on a 3-week vacation during all this and I had work travel so it was a real headache coordinating with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of headaches and coordination, dealing with the permit approval process was not easy either. Wow, did I learn a lot through that. Every major step required an inspection and there are only two inspectors for my area. To put this into context, my county has been the fastest growing county in the United States for many years. We have more new construction and building permits than anywhere else in America. And my city of several hundred thousand people only has two inspectors. Those guys visited more than a dozen sites per day and I had to schedule days or weeks in advance. This is a real problem when you’re trying to get something done quickly! Especially when one of them goes on vacation for a couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it took about four months for the building to be totally usable. By August 2018, I had a “studio opening” party and hired the band Evil Genius to come play. It was an awesome concert and there’s footage of that show on our channel. In March 2019 we finished the installation of the exterior patio, window and door trim, and baseboards. The studio is finally complete (except I have to paint the trim and baseboards). The only thing that remains is metal cap flashing on the parapet wall, and if you know what that means, then you’ll know it’s relatively trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all the tools I used for this project were borrowed from friends and family. Even though I probably built 50-60% of this building, I could not have done it without the guidance, contributions, and talents of many friends. Seriously, I owe it to all of them because I am not a particularly handy person. I have a master’s degree in technology, so most of my expertise is in computer stuff. I learned a ton from them and from YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project helped me to learn about things like crickets and scuppers, UFER grounds, termite treatments and orange tags, pigtails, j-bolts, z-hangers, strong ties, fireblocking, 20 ounce hammers, rotozips, mud rings, and more. I went to Home Depot and Lowe’s 3-10 times per week. I taught my kids how to use power tools. I learned how to best hammer a nail through OSB on a 2x6 frame. I learned how to fail inspections and install windows. I know where every screw and nail and beam are in this building. There is literally still dried blood on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never felt so free and empowered in my life. This building has taught me that I can do anything I set my mind to. And now I have my own little slice of heaven. It’s not perfect and there are definitely some things I would do differently if I could do it again, but man what an experience. In a day and age where my hands are primarily on computer keyboards, glass touch screens, or guitar strings, to get my hands dirty and bloody was just awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for numbers, here are the basics: the building cost me $25,000, so about $80-100 per square foot, but the real estate market is selling at $150 per square foot and higher in my area. It increased the value of my home significantly. Other people in my neighborhood spent $50K doing similar projects in their yard. The outdoor flagstone patio work was another $10,000, but that can be done much cheaper with concrete or stone pavers. We could have done a lot of things cheaper too, but I didn’t want to compromise much on quality. This is a once-in-a-lifetime type project for me, so we wanted to do it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re thinking of doing something similar, I want to encourage you to bite the bullet. It’s good for you and it’s good for the world. We need more people who have hands-on experience instead of armchair expertise. More people creating their own destinies instead of waiting for life to happen to them. More people producing than consuming. More doers and fewer intellectual yet idiots. Feel free to reach out with more questions and please share your own studio projects if you’ve made one yourself. Even though I thought this project would be boring for people, there sure has been a lot of enthusiasm so thank you for all your support! You inspired me to finish and share! So thanks for listening to all this. I plan on sharing more about the studio in the future. If you have suggestions of what you’d like to know, let me know in the comments. If you would have chosen the Lotus Super 7 instead of the studio, I’d also like to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/2019-studio-tour</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/2019-studio-tour</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
