<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>A resource for musicians to discover new artists, learn weird music techniques, listen to interviews, and share their weird music.
</description>
    <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 16:17:05 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 16:17:05 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Prog Cover of BWV 1060R by J.S. Bach</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In December 2013, I released a math-rock/progressive cover version of one of my favorite Bach compositions, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keyboard_concertos_by_Johann_Sebastian_Bach#Concerto_in_C_minor.2C_BWV_1060&quot;&gt;Concert for Violin and Oboe Mov. 1, Allegro (BWV 1060R) &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a total shred-fest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OUDXsoV6-ak&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/concerto-for-violin-oboe-in/id767515367&quot;&gt;Purchase this song on iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This performance features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sebastianlanser.com&quot;&gt;Sebastian Lanser &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; on drums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dixie_Dregs&quot;&gt;Dixie Dregs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on bass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adam Strand (an organist I met at my church) on keyboards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bryce Bickham of &lt;a href=&quot;http://crimsontone.com&quot;&gt;Crimsontone Amplifiers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Re-amp&quot;&gt;re-amped &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; all my guitar parts through his awesome handmade amps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian’s drum parts are jaw-dropping. Andy’s bass parts are so fun. Adam’s arrangement contributions brought new life to my too-technical work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Artwork for my 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/bach?src=hash&quot;&gt;#bach&lt;/a&gt; shredfest. Thought it&amp;#39;d be funny to draw myself as Bach. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/F1QXIJX7u3&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/F1QXIJX7u3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/708064442823479296&quot;&gt;March 10, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-and-why&quot;&gt;How and Why&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a piece of music I’ve loved for many years and always knew I wanted to record my own version. I put my stamp on it by messing around with the rhythm of the main motif, which is in 11/8. It took about 10 months to complete the arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s incredibly complex and difficult to perform, well beyond anything I’d previously recorded. There were several parts I couldn’t easily perform as originally written, so I translated those parts into different time signatures and added notes to make them playable. Some parts require some pretty tricky finger-tapping on both hands. It’s more like playing a keyboard on a fretboard than finger-tapping like Eddie Van Halen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I entered all the notes into Logic Pro and used its tablature features to determine the best way to play (and memorize) the various parts. Then I recorded all the parts direct into Logic and sent them to Bryce to re-amp through his beautiful Crimsontone Amps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian, Andy, and Adam each told me that this was one of the hardest songs they’d ever performed. I guess that’s some sort of stamp of honor. Heh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/bach</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/bach</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Theory of Obscurity</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 05:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/https:/vimeo.com/ondemand/theresidents</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/https:/vimeo.com/ondemand/theresidents</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Panzerballett Typewriter Contest Entry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In November 2015, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; launched a contest where fans could submit their cover of the song &lt;em&gt;Typewriter II&lt;/em&gt; off their new album, &lt;em&gt;Breaking Brain&lt;/em&gt;. Here is my entry for the competition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HRdk3HoknWk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to know more about Jan Zehrfeld (the mad genius behind Panzerballett), you should &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;check out our extensive 5-part interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this was quite a bit of work and stretched my capabilities as a player and a person who makes videos on the internet. I’d never tried doing a split-screen effect before, which is tough in my humble little video studio. The sheet music Jan provided to contestants was difficult for me to read, so I had to put every note into a notation editor, then tab it all out so I could remember how to play it. I also improvised through my solos in an effort to retain Jan’s spirit of jazz and improvisation amidst a highly-composed piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone wondering, that is a 6-string guitar with a banjo body called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.deanguitars.com/query?upc=819998000554&quot;&gt;Backwoods 6 Banjo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I picked up used for about $170. The acoustic is my trusty Alvarez Yairi DY-40. And the keyboard is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivetti_Lettera_32&quot;&gt;Olivetti Lettera 32 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; lent to me by my good friend, &lt;a href=&quot;http://elevatingideas.com&quot;&gt;Will Mejia &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who also designed the MWM logo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took about 4 weeks to notate, learn, practice, record, and film the whole thing over many evenings from 9PM til about 1AM. All told, I’m guessing I spent about 60 hours on it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;download-the-mp3&quot;&gt;Download the mp3!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an mp3 of the song (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/typewriter/makeweirdmusic-typewriter.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/typewriter/makeweirdmusic-typewriter.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;original-recording&quot;&gt;Original Recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/breaking-brain/id1043463853&quot;&gt;Purchase Panzerballett’s &lt;em&gt;Breaking Brain&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the official music video for the original recording of the song:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5OGoftbnqLM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here’s a promo video for the new album:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bEdh3IjJ9Gk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;contest-info&quot;&gt;Contest Info&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial offering for winning the competition was free tickets and aftershow passes to see the band perform and hang out with them on one of their European tour dates. Since I live in the USA, the idea of making my own cover of the song was appealing, but geographically limited and financially impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Isvjirm1K8M?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months later, Jan announced there was a chance to win an Ibanez 8-string guitar. I saw that video and knew I had to cover the song in a unique way and make a fun video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RbtWb6edQJ8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like what I’ve done, leave a comment and/or share the video. Thanks so much for checking this out! And thank you, Jan, for providing this opportunity to your fans. It was so much fun!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/typewriter</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/typewriter</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Favrio Guitars ATG7</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In January 2014, a friend of mine had shared one of my guitar videos on Facebook. A friend of this friend left a comment like, “I’d love if this guy would try one of my guitars!” His name is Rob Fick and he’s a guitar luthier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rob and I started chatting online about the guitars he’s built and his workshop. Then we started talking about building a custom guitar. I live in Arizona and our mutual friend is from Arizona, so I presumed this guy lived in Arizona. I said, “When can I come check out your shop?” and he wrote, “I’m in Bodrum, Turkey!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the logistical challenges, we decided to proceed with the custom “Anthony Garone Signature Model” anyway. He told me about some of the woods he had access to, which sounded intriguing: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millettia_laurentii&quot;&gt;wenge&lt;/a&gt;, Stradivari &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spruce&quot;&gt;spruce&lt;/a&gt; from E. Ciresa in Northern Italy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sapele&quot;&gt;sapele&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whos-behind-favrio-guitars&quot;&gt;Who’s Behind Favrio Guitars?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;asdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-atg7&quot;&gt;What is the ATG7?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;asdf&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/favrio-atg7/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/favrio-atg7/</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture, Episode 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a video series I’ve put together about all the things that have stood in the way of my successfully playing the song &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; despite years and years of study, practice, writing, and making videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Check the episode index for more content!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-1-stress-and-body-tension&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Body Tension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite quotes is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_are_known_knowns&quot;&gt;this beauty &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Rumsfeld&quot;&gt;Donald Rumsfeld &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reports that say that something hasn’t happened are always interesting to me, because as we know, there are known knowns; there are things we know we know. We also know there are known unknowns; that is to say we know there are some things we do not know. But there are also unknown unknowns – the ones we don’t know we don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look back at videos of myself playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; as far back as 2006, I see someone who didn’t know what he didn’t know–someone confounded by the unknown unknowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fracture/id978457922?i=978458012&quot;&gt;Purchase King Crimson’s &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.nexternal.com/dgm/starless-and-bible-black-c228.aspx&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Robert Fripp’s website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the video to accompany this episode of &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/o4f1POCrKXE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;self-taught-unknown-unknowns&quot;&gt;Self-Taught Unknown Unknowns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started learning Fracture at the ripe young age of 18 or so–somewhere around the year 2000. My father had said to me, “Learn &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; I’ll talk to you.” He was trying to challenge me with impossible songs and I was doing my best to teach myself to play. My aim was to shred, not to play an instrument with ease nor to understand any of the musical concepts behind what I was playing. As a teenager, I wanted to play fast and loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifteen years later at an introductory &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Circle course &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Mexico, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; said to me (and 7 other introductory students), “Please raise your hand if you taught yourself how to play guitar.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I raised my hand as did a few others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fripp’s response was, “What you’re effectively telling me is, ‘Someone who knew nothing about music, nothing about the guitar, nothing about performance taught me everything I know.’” My internal response was a little defensive. I couldn’t help but admit that he was right, though. What had I really gotten out of studying recordings, reading magazines, and learning from transcriptions? The ability to move my fingers around on a fretboard through rote memorization?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[NOTE: For more intelligent discourse on this subject, check out &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jeff-berlin&quot;&gt;the interview we did with Jeff Berlin&lt;/a&gt;. He has incredible insights about music education and being self-taught.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few days of the Guitar Circle course focused on something called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_technique&quot;&gt;Alexander Technique &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [AT] led primarily by two AT teachers with support from Robert and his “guitar buddies” (experienced co-instructors). I hated Alexander Technique. We spent a bunch of time talking about how to sit, how to stand, how to breathe, how to position your head on your neck… A few of us intro students were irritated and felt like it wasn’t a good use of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And every morning, we spent 45 minutes with Robert &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgmlive.com/diaries.htm?diarist=3&amp;amp;entry=4424&quot;&gt;doing &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Literally. We sat in a room staring in silence doing nothing. It was surreal and, frankly, bizarre. I went from never thinking I’d meet Robert to sitting in a room with him staring at a wall at 7:45AM in a small town outside Mexico City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We barely seemed to do anything on the guitar until the third or fourth day. That’s when my back started &lt;em&gt;killing&lt;/em&gt; me with constant pain and burning. &lt;a href=&quot;http://sandrabaincushman.com/&quot;&gt;Sandra Bain Cushman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; said this pain was due to my body undoing all of the poor habits I’d developed over so many years of misuse of my body. Suddenly, I felt awakened to a new me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;change-is-good&quot;&gt;Change is good!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of doing nothing started making sense. As Robert said, “You can’t ask your body to do something until it can appreciate doing nothing.” This practice was revealing a quiet, relaxed version of me that I always carry around, but never listen to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I picked up the guitar, I could feel my body fighting new, good use techniques with old, poor use techniques. From the way I sat, the way I positioned my skull on my neck, the way I automatically tensed up playing the guitar… It was incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next several months, I worked very hard at sitting regularly and doing nothing, paying close attention to where stress appears in my body during everyday moments, while at work, while walking, while playing guitar, and more. The more I loosened up, the more I was able to navigate the picking for &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. One night in August 2015, it happened! I immediately started filming myself and sent it to my friend, Yehuda Kotton, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uiX_ewhngbA&quot;&gt;an Israeli guitarist from the band Ahvak &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who’d also been working on learning &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the Alexander Technique and the practice of doing nothing, I have learned so much about myself and my habits. There is so much I didn’t know I didn’t know and I still discover new things about stress and tension in my body as I pick up the guitar and start playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stress-is-visible&quot;&gt;Stress is visible&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, I discover new areas where I’m stressing myself out. Most recently, the stress is appearing in my right forearm near my elbow and in my right shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guitar instructor named &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reverbnation.com/glennwintersmith&quot;&gt;Glenn Winter-Smith &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; emailed me after &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Episode 0&lt;/a&gt; telling me he could notice that I wasn’t loosened up. Admittedly, the practice performance in that video was the 50th take over the course of 3 nights and I was stressed and tired from playing and filming myself, but more importantly was the fact that an experienced instructor noticed my stress despite a year of concerted effort in relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, he wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your wrist and fingers on your picking arm could be a lot looser and manipulative than what they are,. I always tell my students to think ‘loosey goosey’,…pretend your arm is almost stuck in one position and you can only swivel/turn your wrist and swivel/turn your thumb/fingers with pick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have a long way to go, but I know the goal is within reach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/fracture/stress</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/fracture/stress</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-0-introduction&quot;&gt;Episode 0: Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put together an introductory video for this series. Further episodes will be linked and embedded as I make them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x5LPldcjeH0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-episodes&quot;&gt;More Episodes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/stress&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Tension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheet-music&quot;&gt;Sheet Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;Soundslice&lt;/a&gt; is an incredible web app that offers HTML5 sheet music without the need for Adobe Flash or any other plugins. It’s super-duper awesome and is hosting the sheet music you see here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/40913/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-we-learning&quot;&gt;What are we learning?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past 15 years or so, I’ve been intensely studying a piece of music called &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; and have developed a unique type of expertise: the expertise of failure. &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; is, without a doubt, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the most difficult piece of music I’ve ever tried playing&lt;/span&gt;. Through study, practice, blogging, and YouTube videos, I have failed more visibly and effortfully than most anyone else on the internet attempting to play this song. This video series is an attempt to share what I’ve learned through my failures to save others the time and energy as they attempt to learn and play the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fracture/id978457922?i=978458012&quot;&gt;Purchase King Crimson’s &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.nexternal.com/dgm/starless-and-bible-black-c228.aspx&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Robert Fripp’s website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I will only be focusing on the &lt;em&gt;moto perpetuo&lt;/em&gt; section&lt;/span&gt;, which starts at about 2:50 in the original recording and lasts (endures!) for about 4 minutes. “Moto perpetuo” is an Italian term meaning “perpetual motion.” It applies here because this section of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; is a barrage of 16th notes (or “semiquavers” as Robert Fripp, the British composer and performer of the song, might say).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People all over the world have contacted me about playing this song. They’ve kindly sharing videos of their own, offered their time via Skype to talk to me, etc. It’s been such a fun and humbling experience and I’ve met people from every continent! There is quite a community of Fripp-following guitarists and I’ve been overjoyed to meet so many of them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, please note that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I am not teaching anyone how to play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, but rather showing you all the ways I’ve discovered that will prevent or inhibit progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;downloads&quot;&gt;Downloads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re interested, here are the &lt;a href=&quot;http://musescore.org&quot;&gt;MuseScore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and MusicXML files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/fracture/fracture.mscz&quot;&gt;MuseScore (.mscz) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/fracture/fracture.xml&quot;&gt;MusicXML (.xml) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/fracture/fracture.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF (.mscz) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-videos&quot;&gt;Other Videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re interested, check out these other videos I did of myself playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;FraKctured&lt;/em&gt; since attending the Guitar Circle intro course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EoWx3sUMQEo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_wmbfrPx6EY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/fracture/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/fracture/</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Best Frank Zappa Albums</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2016 05:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/http:/echoesanddust.com/2016/02/echoes-of-the-past-frank-zappa/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/http:/echoesanddust.com/2016/02/echoes-of-the-past-frank-zappa/</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jeff Berlin Interview, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; our interview with the incredible Jeff Berlin. Missed part 1? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jeff-berlin/part-1&quot;&gt;Watch/Listen to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, then!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Berlin&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Jeff Berlin is? Check out his wikipedia page! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was conducted on Friday, February 5, 2016 at 2PM AZ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/jeff-berlin-interview-mwm-20160205-part2.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/jeff-berlin-interview-mwm-20160205-part2.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jWeTqBNnA6g?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: I remember I used to follow you on Facebook and then I stopped and then a friend of mine (Andy Kub) a couple years later said, “You should follow Jeff Berlin.” I said, “Okay, I’ll do that.” And then I remembered the reason I stopped following you was because it was almost like you were inviting controversy at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Now, just recently, you do a public apology to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_Wooten&quot;&gt;Victor Wooten &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Bailey&quot;&gt;Steve Bailey &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you’re talking about huge personal transformation and growth. Was it primarily your ego getting out of control and then you had a self-realization event? What led to what you’ve been going through and how were you operating at the time before that and how are you operating now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jeff: Thanks for asking that because for me, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;this is more important than maybe music is right now.&lt;/span&gt; I grew up in a dysfunctional family. I know a lot of us have. The way that I ended up was hurt, ungrounded, out of balance, and the ego compensated. I’m doing this in a nutshell. All my life, since I was 18 years old, I felt something was wrong with me. I started, actually earlier than that, it was 18 that I went to therapy. Things were not right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I noticed people seemed to be content, seemed to be grounded. You know, everyone has their problems, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I could not get a grip or a handle on how people kindly and calmly get through life.&lt;/span&gt; And I’ve been in and out of therapy, my own voluntary seeking of it, since I was 18 years old. I’m 63 now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I was 60, I was just in a period where I did a lot of my Facebook stuff challenging, not polite, very hard-edged–it was just a symptom of even the messages in my columns, in my interviews, how I may have interacted with people–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was all based in fear, all based in shame, it was all unhealthy and I could not resolve it. I tried.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I turned 60, I fell apart. I literally lost my mind and felt that this is the end. I understood why people commit suicide. I understood it. People commit suicide, I feel, when they feel there’s no option or hope to extract yourself out of the awfulness, the hopelessness, the pain, the fear–when you’re in this, you can’t imagine, people who’ve been through this can–the awfulness, you get to think it’ll never end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I have a guitar player friend here in Clearwater who recommended somebody who I went to and I went when I was 60. In this time, she was wired differently, let’s say. I still see this person and she was a licensed therapist who renounced her license, not believing in therapeutic things (her thinking) and went into a kind of a spiritual bent and she kind of amalgamated a soupy spiritual thing with therapeutic things and came up with something where, instead of “my mother did” and “you, Anthony, said” and “Victor Wooten and Steve Bailey and all bass players,” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;instead of this, I went inside.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And man, let me tell you, nothing was harder than to do that. Nothing.&lt;/span&gt; Because now whatever was going on wasn’t your doing or your fault or how you’re doing or “you don’t understand.” I spent about 7 or 8 months on the floor of my house, crying, sobbing, shaking like I was in an Exorcist movie, buddy. I mean, it was murder because feelings that I had suppressed–I don’t know. It’s not like, “Oh Mom did this and she said that and this happened and she said and not this,” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s that these things get internalized and they’re feelings so they started to come up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was getting worse and worse and worse by each passing month. I would write to Beth because we have a communication relationship where I would see her and she would sit there and go, “Nope, you’re doing fine. You’re doing fine.” I said, “Beth! That ledge looks really good now, Beth!” “Nope, you’re doing fine.” And what she meant to say was that this was a passage where people often, in fear, don’t go through it all the way. I got on that train and I had to ride that train to its conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Ultimately, I felt–Can I tell you this? I felt on a Monday, I said, “Beth, it’s worse. I’m getting worse, Beth!” And I wrote her. She says, “Hang in. This is what you gotta go through.” Tuesday, I wrote her again because I was seeing her on Thursday or so. “I’m going crazy, Beth!” She says, “Nope, you’re doing fine. Hang in.” On Wednesday, Anthony, I was so bad I suddenly felt as if I hit bottom. I felt it. I physically felt hitting bottom and I went totally numb and I went, “What is this?” And from that moment, I started to get better. She said later, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“You hit the bottom in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_Night_of_the_Soul&quot;&gt;dark night of the soul &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (it’s called).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XN0TkIGsJak?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was into spiritual pursuit and people experience this where the essence of what we construct for ourself collapses. When it collapses, we collapse. If everything you, Anthony, believe in falls apart, what are you? You know what the answer is? Nothing! And that, what you are, you’re nothing in the sense of everything you have and everything you believe in, it’s nothing, it’s false, it’s not real…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When that happens, what do you do? What do you trust? Who are you? What are you to rely on? And that happened to me, man…&lt;/span&gt; Talk about losing your essential self as a human being because that’s what happens to people like me in the dark night of the soul. What happens is this is a healing process and then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;as you come out of it, you reconstruct from another place, not a damaged place.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In the subsequent years, I would practice being nice. “Hi guys, I’m sorry I did this stuff.” Okay, three months later, “You know, you stupid idiots out there, you’re all…” And then I would catch on a couple months later and go, “Whoops, I’m sorry I did it again and I don’t know what happened. I feel so bad, I’m really…” And I did. I would work to be nice. “Hey Anthony! Hey! How you doing? Everything good?” You know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It wasn’t natural, but I did make the effort. And finally in December of this year (2015), I had another collapse. About a month before, I was dancing in Beth’s office, saying, “Man, I feel as great as I’ve ever felt.” And I did! I had this collapse and I said, “What the hell is going on here?” She said, “People sometimes get strong after their first diminished and long-term depression to be strong enough to experience the next stage in a collapse of something internal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And what happened here is I, for better or worse, even lost more ego ground. I feel it like talking to you now that what I’m discussing isn’t the ego part of me, which I recognize that sensation, and try and conscious–I’m conscious all the time. “Ah, there I am. I did this. I see.” The watcher part. I’ll give everyone a little test here to show you the different–if you’re interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7emS3ye3cVU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Absolutely! I love this stuff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: This stuff and the readings that I’ve done, the dark night of the soul, I’ve gotten videos from her about people lecturing on it, different aspects of spiritual growth. What is spiritualism? It isn’t [hands in prayer] “Ommm” or maybe it is! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the natural you. You without the pollution&lt;/span&gt;, the “You know what? I hate the Pittsburgh Steelers! I only love the Raiders!” It’s a construction, in a sense, and if I could do away with and appreciate the Raiders &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the Steelers, although I’d probably prefer one or the other, that the sense is that there is a more natural sense of me that should have been before I was hurt and deviated from a healthy growth path. My parents unknowingly did this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; had a great example for me. I’m sorry to interrupt. This has been so helpful. He said, “A lot of people are holding this jar and the jar is empty. Every life experience you have gets put into that jar, every opinion you have gets put into that jar. And people end up believing that they are the jar or the contents of the jar. But, you’re still the person holding the jar. You’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; that person that has these experiences. You are the person holding those experiences!” My boss said, “Just because someone makes you a crap sandwich doesn’t mean you need to eat it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;It’s kind of like: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we have a choice of taking what’s in this jar and believing it’s us, or believing that we are the person holding the jar and that the jar and its contents do not define us.&lt;/span&gt; Other people, no matter what they stick in there, that doesn’t need to change who we are. We’re not in touch with being that person holding the jar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is all about this notion that we are–well, there’s a guy named &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gurdjieff&quot;&gt;Gurdjieff &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that he follows, this philosopher, and that most people are in a sleeping walking state, almost like zombies and we’re never truly awakened. So, all of this stuff has been so central to a huge transformation in my own life since September 2014. Just huge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;The conversation with Steve and then the guitar camp with Robert Fripp and then all the other experiences and all the reading, so I’m glad I haven’t had a dark night of the soul, I’m lucky and very fortunate to not have had that, but those examples right there really feed into my understanding of what you’re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I think Steve nailed it and it’s true. I agree with him. I’ll give you a little example of the person you are rather than the person who thinks and this goes for everybody else. I’d like to do a little experiment and here it is. In your mind, say the word, “House.” Tell me when you did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: In your mind, louder, say the word, “House.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: And the final one, in your mind, scream as loud as you can the word, “House.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Here’s a question and I’m curious what you would say. Did you notice in all three experiences there was a part of you watching?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh yeah. Absolutely. The third one especially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And this is an indication of something that I’ve been developing because in the sleeping mode that you’re discussing, many of us are sleeping and usually people that are highly opinionated, gossipy people, opinionated to the degree that I know I’m opinionated in music ed, opinionated for its own sake, which is what I used to be, are asleep.&lt;/span&gt; We are governed by the thoughts, not only the jar, but the things like, “I like this football team,” and, “Metronomes are bad.” Why? Just because I say so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mind_monkey&quot;&gt;The monkey mind &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” Fripp calls it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yCBalosvT9U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: The monkey mind! See, good for Fripp. I’m joining an elite club, and so are you I think. We like to invite people to join us. It’s a good thing, especially us being the sick or the damaged or the mentally unhealthy or the soul-spiritually-imbalanced people that are seeking and getting better. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I never thought I’d find this kind of balance and now that it’s happening to me, I never thought it would come, man.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I just wanted to point out that in the development, we develop that watcher part and that’s when I began to see this ego part who went, “Ah well, Anthony… Weird! What a funny word. Anthony and his weird .com.” And of course, that’s not the watcher, the guy who screamed, “House,” perhaps. Or screamed “cookie.” That is, in a nutshell, what I am developing. It’s very important to me. I probably talked too much about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I don’t think so. To me, it’s the stuff of life and you don’t realize the value of it. Like you said, you don’t think you’ll ever get there, and then when you’re there you realize you could have had it the whole time. It’s not so distant, it’s not so hard, but we spend decades defending a worldview with rules and opinions and these kinds of things that we grow to believe, “These must be true!” And when somebody does something that violates some of the rules, or makes us feel jealous or something like that, it’s because we’re defensive. It’s our ego saying to us, “That person doesn’t live by your rules and that person is doing well.” You know? What’s wrong with &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;? Why can’t you do that? You know the rules. It’s been &lt;em&gt;hugely&lt;/em&gt; transformational stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yeah, and I appreciate that too. By the way, this probably should be a two-parter, shouldn’t it? Maybe a 5-parter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: If you need to get going, we can end it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: No! I’m happy to chat. It’s just I would assume a lot of this is going to make people go, “Oh yeah.” [Snoring.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I don’t know. The Steve Vai one, people are eating it up. They love the non-musical/musical context. A great exercise that I read about is if you envision in your mind a room with two doors. If you think of a difficult situation, something that made you upset, let that come in through one door. The two doors are on opposite ends of the room. Let it come in to one door and you visualize it and get a sense of what it is and it might look like colors, shapes, sounds, whatever. You watch it from a distance and you get to develop a familiarity with that feeling and you wait for it to leave out the other door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;If you do this mental exercise for long enough, these feelings that you get, these feelings of discomfort or ego or whatever it is, you start to train yourself that things enter and then they leave. You also teach yourself that you can have compassion for these feelings. And, when these things come up in your life, you teach yourself that they will leave, that it’s not permanent. “This feeling, I know what this feeling is.” As soon as you feel it, you know what it is. It’s this thing entering the door and you know what it looks like because you’ve studied it. And we spend so much of our lives avoiding these feelings, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Which is what my dark night was. It was all my life avoiding things and you said you hope you don’t get it and you probably won’t. The dark night could be different. You could be just sort of depressed or just sort of down. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Mine was an utter and absolute loss of self. That, for a highly egotistical being, loss of self is freaking terrifying.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, somebody like you, who I sense is a sort of a lower-keyed guy, if comes a time where your system decides to auto-correct, you may just sort of, “Man, I don’t feel so great.” And it won’t be as awful, but it is predictable. And you will emerge. And really, often, there’s nothing to do about it except recognize it. You said to, honor those parts that come through the door?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Have compassion for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Have compassion for. That’s a good synonym for my world, which is “love it.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s a part of me that was so badly hurt that it caused the ego to say, “Well, I’m the best. If you don’t study like I say, you’re a doodoo,” which is an industry term for “poopoo.”&lt;/span&gt; In my case, I’ve learned to love this injured part and I would embrace it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I actually gave myself permission recently, not terribly long ago, I made a declaration and it’s made a difference in my life, which is &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;no matter what I feel, no matter how I feel it, I’m going to honor it and I’m going to feel it.&lt;/span&gt; I’m going to let it come and I’m never going to restrict or restrain. If I’m in the middle of a session, I guess I won’t pay too much attention, but later at the hotel, I will lay down and I’ll go back to that and I’ll bring it up. I’ll bring it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s that integration element that these things that were not known and not dealt with are now–okay, they come up and, “Okay, I feel this, oh my goodness yes, oh I’m so mad! Yes you are.” It sounds a little silly, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I feel a great deal of the ill psyche in me and I’m as grateful as can be, man. I’m really grateful. My bass playing is better.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I was gonna ask that. Over the decades, how did your ego influence what you were playing and now that you know that feeling–you said you have a new awareness for when the ego pops in–how does that affect you as a musician and as a bass player?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Well, I feel I’ve never played better and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I feel that pretty much my entire musical career is a fraud. It’s a fraud in the nature of what I constructed it on.&lt;/span&gt; So, it’s an honest and, I feel, a true assessment. I agree I played maybe music that people may enjoy, but I played a lot of stuff that was, “Love me. Love me. Love me! Love me! &lt;em&gt;Love me!! Love me!!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: All right, well, I’m gonna get rid of this then. [Holds up Bruford’s “One of a Kind.”]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Well, that thing endures and I’m grateful for it, those Bruford things.&lt;/span&gt; That was the thing of this. I mean, “Love me love me love me,” fast, fusion, grrrr… And &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; I’ve found a whole new way to play bass. I’ve found other things. My playing isn’t as virtuosic because, quite frankly, I don’t qualify anymore. Not with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadrien_Feraud&quot;&gt;Hadrien Feraud &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that new young crew of firebrands around. You know, these guys are simply beyond belief! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’d be foolish if I were in my ego state, “All these young kids! I’ll show them a thing or two!” Which probably would have been my bent a while ago.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GZ_VzFq5ZSQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So now that I’ve kind of abandoned that kind of “need to” whatever, I’ve come 1. to love these guys and respect the living heck out of them, and 2. with a calmer nature as a bass player, I said, “Wow, look at this! I’m finding some interesting new things!” And so, it’s the liberation and allowing the spirit to flow and I never knew what spirit was and I guess I’m still not sure. I guess I take it to mean “the natural me.” What I was, as I said earlier, what I was meant to be. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Yeah, my bass playing is satisfying. It’s great! It’s flowing out of me like juice out of a blood orange.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Have you written any new songs since going through this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes. Not a lot, but I have. I’m not what I would call a gifted composer. I’m more of a “worker at it” composer. Some guys have that gift. I’m sorta like, “Da da da da da da da.” No. “Da da da da DAH da da.” No. “Da da da da DAH da da da DAH da da.” Okay that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you compose on the bass? I see you doing keyboard gestures. Do you write on the keyboard?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yeah, on keyboard and on bass. I write on both. I’m fortunate. I write a lot of nice bass things now that are slightly different. [Bass gesture] This is bass. [Keyboard gesture] This is piano. [Trombone gesture] This is slide trombone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: [Violin gesture] This is violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: [Flaps arms like a chicken] This is wock-a-doo-wock-a-doo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Frank Zappa [hair curl gesture], this is reggae, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Frank was an interesting guy, man! He’s a guy that I think would have benefited from spiritual pursuit.&lt;/span&gt; He had a lot of angst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You played with him for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I did and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I got myself thrown out of a band through bad behavior. You know. And rude attitude. I’m telling you, man, I left bodies in the wake. It was a lot of humble pie.&lt;/span&gt; A &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of humble pie that I have to eat in order to own my thing and grow from there, so I’ve come to develop a rather appreciative taste for humble pie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, you did lose opportunities as a result of this attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I lost them and I threw them away. I burned bridges. I was fairly out of my mind and fairly out of control. You can find a lot of that stuff on the internet. There’s not too much hidden evidence of that. You know what karma is? You’ve gotta pay the tab, man. You know the dark night? You gotta pay the tab. I put something out, I’ve gotta pay the bill for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; is in one way why I confess these stories and open up like that because I don’t want anything to be hidden, I don’t want to lie about anything, I don’t want to make one flipping excuse about anything in me that I’ve earned. So, I’m okay with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: You’re getting maybe more of a sense of the kind of guy, at least today, maybe in 3 months I’ll be different again because I feel calmer, I feel more loving, I feel more centered, more grounded, I still think music education needs fixing, I still think I need to practice my bass, I still think Victor Wooten and Steve Bailey are helping people and doing well for people and I owe them an apology and other people, if I’ve cast aspersions against them and all other teachers. I still feel metronomes don’t work, but if people wish to use them, of course they should, so I’m firm in my thing. Apologetic where it needs to be and I’m fine with it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Have you heard from any of these people that you’ve apologized to or you feel like in the past you might have wronged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Give me a second, I want to answer. Not really. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You know, I’ve apologized before and fell back, so I don’t think they’re wrong.&lt;/span&gt; “Here Berlin goes again, man. Apologizing and then the next thing he’s like, ‘Don’t slap bass! Don’t use a fretless!’ I’m not sure what.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, if I go through a dark night of the soul, your phone’s gonna ring at 2 in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: You can call any time and your dark night I’m fairly imbued with a little bit of an understanding of things. Again, that doesn’t make me anywhere qualified as a teacher or expert in any way, but I do have a sense of things now that I didn’t. If you do experience it, it will be a tolerable and less vicious form than mine because you aren’t losing a great deal of that collapse where you’re a more solidly-formed, emotionally-stable guy than I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s like a house falling down, or the Empire State Building falling down, or (forgive me) the Twin Towers falling down. Bad analogy. It’s that collapse. That collapse was me and it was devastating. And then it was necessary. So you said, “I hope,” and it didn’t happen. You know what ironically happens to guys like me that go through it? We’re as grateful as ever for the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, I bet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I went through murder, man. Really murder. Hell. I thought thoughts. I said, “I can’t tolerate this. Bye world, I’m gone. Do it.” Something said, “I gotta get through this.” Beth helped me out, I read a lot of literature, I cried, I suffered, I shook. I apologized, “Oh what did I do? What did I say? What is this? What is this?” And finally it just began to ease up and now I play bass pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well thank you so much for sharing this very human story. I really appreciate it and I think it takes a lot of bravery and candor and it’s really kind of you to offer this time and these words. So, thank you so much Jeff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I’m honored to be here and thank you for the chance and the opportunity. I apologize if I talk too much. It’s actually something I’m attending to in my therapy. This need to just go blah blah blah bleh bleh blah blah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I love it. Don’t apologize. There’s no need. Thank you so much, Jeff. Maybe in a few months, we can talk again and see where things are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I would like that. I would like that very much. I wish you well and hi to everybody. Thank you for listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: All right, Anthony. Cheers, buddy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Thank you very much, Jeff.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/part-2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jeff Berlin Interview, Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; our interview with the incredible Jeff Berlin. Already done with Part 1? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jeff-berlin/part-2&quot;&gt;Check out &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, where we get super-deep!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Berlin&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Jeff Berlin is? Check out his wikipedia page! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff and I connected via Facebook over some mutually-passionate comments regarding an obvious personal transformation he and I have both been going through. I was fortunate enough to get his attention through some comments and posts. After he watched some of our &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;interview with Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt;, he reached out to me and tried arranging some time for us to get together at NAMM. All this happened in a matter of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I was disappointed I couldn’t meet up with him at NAMM, however the resulting interview is so much better than I think it would have turned out if we tried talking amidst the chaos of NAMM. There are &lt;em&gt;so many&lt;/em&gt; deep and wonderful statements and interactions in this interview. I hope you get as much out of it as I have. Thank you for your attention!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was conducted on Friday, February 5, 2016 at 2PM AZ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/jeff-berlin-interview-mwm-20160205-part1.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/jeff-berlin-interview-mwm-20160205-part1.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_suLx937mKU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with the incredible bass player, Jeff Berlin. Jeff, thank you so much for being with us today. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jeff: Well, thank you for inviting me. I always like these chats. It gets me a chance to open up interesting topics for old friends, people that know me, and possibly new fans that don’t know me and might want to know what I do and what I’m about. So, thanks for the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Thank you so much! One of the purposes of MakeWeirdMusic.com is to allow musicians and music enthusiasts to find out about new artists and to find out about new music, new techniques, things that make certain people unique. You certainly have a great history and I thought it would be great if you could introduce yourself and talk about that history. Then we’ll get to some of the meatier stuff that you and I have mutually wanted to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I’ll begin by saying the title of your website, Make Weird Music–in regards to the “weird” part, you were thinking of me. So, I own the “weird” element as a person, possibly as a musician. I’m Jeff Berlin. That’s my name. It’s Jeffrey Arthur Berlin. Family and people I grew up with refer to me as Jeffrey. Everybody else refers to me as Jeff, which I find the more intimate and friendly interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Preferring one over the other, I like Jeff. It’s just more social. Jeffrey sort of makes me feel like I should probably get you a cup of tea and possibly, if you live out of the United States, a copy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pravda&quot;&gt;Pravda &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You know, a butler element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m a bass player. I’m a fortunate musician. I’ve eked out a career, an international one, and have the &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; good fortune of playing really among the greatest musicians that ever played in several styles of music. So, that is a blessing to me. It occurs to me sometimes: why me? Why did this happen? I’m very grateful for this life in music. And that’s what I do. I’m a bass player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-the-violin&quot;&gt;On the violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How did you get started with the instrument? I know you were playing violin as a child. Something like that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: All Jewish children in the 50s that exhibit–let’s say a natural propensity for music–inevitably are guided by their equally and possibly more strict Jewish parents to pick up a violin or a piano. It’s hard to find a Jewish trombone player in the world. I think that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nathan_Milstein&quot;&gt;Nathan Milstein &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaac_Stern&quot;&gt;Isaac Stern &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Itzhak_Perlman&quot;&gt;Itzak Perlman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; will sort of relate to the Jewish-ness of the classical instrument (violin) that we were encouraged to play if we exhibited music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0d4XtOrs7xc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I do acknowledge this: certain people may be sports-motivated. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiger_Woods&quot;&gt;Tiger Woods &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; exhibited a genius for golf as a child. He actually appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johnny_Carson&quot;&gt;Johnny Carson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s show &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_wHkA_983_s&quot;&gt;as an unknown kid &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who had genius in that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wouldn’t say I had genius, but I did have a natural musical propensity.&lt;/span&gt; I sang Italian songs before I could speak English. You know, &lt;em&gt;speak&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And how that happened was my father was an opera singer and when he sang these songs and repeated and repeated them, I would sing, [sings in falsetto in Italian] and we have a film–not a film, a recording of it somewhere in the family where I was 9 months old singing Italian songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, “we gotta get this boy a violin.” I began on violin and as much as I wasn’t really into it emotionally, I have to say it was probably the greatest foundation of music to help me prepare for the career that subsequently ensued. So, I am grateful for my mother and father having not pushed, but gently coaxed, gently shoved, encouraged, “Come on, son” … “I want to quit” … “I know, just do this and I’ll get you a gift.” They blackmailed me in a positive manner. They were smart. And I played violin until I was basically 16 and then I stopped altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-the-bass&quot;&gt;On the bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And then how did you get on to the bass?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Oh, well that’s right. When the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatles&quot;&gt;Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came to America, I saw the very first performance. I saw it on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Ed_Sullivan_Show&quot;&gt;Ed Sullivan show &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There was a kid in our neighborhood, he came out and said, “The Beatles are here.” I’d never heard of them. He said, “They’re playing tonight.” I said, “Who are these guys? What is this?” And I watched them and wasn’t impressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JC0MEF6d1eU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was 11 years old, I imagine, or 12. I can’t recall. And, you know, “What’s this?” It wasn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pyotr_Ilyich_Tchaikovsky&quot;&gt;Tchaikovsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I wasn’t moved. Ironically, I would say, not terribly long later, I was not only smitten, bitten, and knocked on my backside by these guys, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when I listened to the records, I knew I &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to do this.&lt;/span&gt; It was inevitable that music had to figure into my life, not in the symphonic manner, which was probably the career that I may have been guided toward, but by picking up an instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I didn’t pick up a guitar because the bass is tuned like a violin is, except in opposite intervals. A violin from low string to high string is tuned in 5ths: G D A and E. A bass is tuned from low string to high string in 4ths: E A D and G. So, the associated names were exactly the same and my thinking is, “If I can get through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violin_Concerto_(Mendelssohn)&quot;&gt;Mendelssohn violin concerto &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I’ll learn this bass in two weeks.” And that was my childish egotistical arrogance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I quickly did learn the bass, probably in ways that people didn’t really wish for me to do because I would be hired to play in bands and then get fired from bands because I didn’t groove and I didn’t know what a rhythm section thing was. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It didn’t interest me as much as playing the solos on bass that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_Clapton&quot;&gt;Eric Clapton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; played on guitar.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross_Road_Blues&quot;&gt;Crossroads &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; solo I guess when I was 16 or 15 or something, and would play &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cream_(band)&quot;&gt;Cream &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; solos, Beatles melodies… &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wasn’t driven toward the rhythm or the bottom of the bass, but rather toward the top.&lt;/span&gt; And I suppose it went hand in hand with the violin training that I had done, which is the violin is intrinsically a melodic instrument, so I put that in and didn’t quit understand. “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Jamerson&quot;&gt;Jamerson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? Yeah, it’s a nice bass line, but listen to–” you know… “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Son_of_a_Preacher_Man&quot;&gt;I’m the son of the preacher man &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.” I think that was Jerry Cogbill–Jerome? [Sings and scats] [NOTE: it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy_Cogbill&quot;&gt;Tommy Cogbill &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0vR9d--Zk-U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now I’m excited as all get out by these bass players. Back then, I wasn’t interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;influences&quot;&gt;Influences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You obviously don’t play music that’s like the Beatles anymore. A lot of your music is very jazz-oriented and there are some fusion releases you’ve done with a few bands. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Henderson&quot;&gt;Scott Henderson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dennis_Chambers&quot;&gt;Dennis Chambers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–that album is incredible. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruford_(band)&quot;&gt;Bruford &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff. Can you talk about how you got into jazz and fusion and rock?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wNCSTNHejAY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes. My initial influence was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Bruce&quot;&gt;Jack Bruce &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When I heard Cream, the studio records were enjoyable. The live records &lt;em&gt;slayed&lt;/em&gt; me. When I heard those live jams, including (I might add) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginger_Baker&quot;&gt;Ginger Baker &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s drumming… To me, Cream most affected me via Jack Bruce’s–I would call “original.” I don’t think it’s a stretch. One of a kind. Original and utterly unprecedented bass playing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He, for me, is the first virtuoso on my instrument in history.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Ginger Baker also, ironically, is a little bit maligned these days due to the “beware Mr. Baker and his rather curmudgeonly attitude.” Let me tell you: be that as it may, when you listen to those earlier Ginger Baker recordings, you will hear a drummer with an utterly original tone and an utterly original approach. His thing was &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; original that I was flabbergasted. Although I wanted to be a drummer, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I still wanted to be Jack Bruce more than I wanted to be Ginger Baker.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But it’s really about having this opportunity. I wanted to just make a statement that this, at one time, Ginger was considered the greatest drummer in the world. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elvin_Jones&quot;&gt;Elvin Jones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and his area of music, of course, was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Art_Blakey&quot;&gt;Art Blakey &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, all these guys. But in rock, Ginger was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Okay, enough of that. So, this influenced me. Going a long way around the barn to answer your question. I got into Jack, learned about virtuosic stuff, went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berklee_College_of_Music&quot;&gt;Berklee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when, at the time, I felt that Berklee was entirely a school focused &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; on musical content. In the era that I went, we had ear training, bass lessons, harmony classes, arranging, composing, line-writing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herb_Pomeroy&quot;&gt;Herb Pomeroy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; line-writing, which people still state is the greatest original melodic musical writing class ever. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And the school at that moment was only interested in educating in musical content with no other distractions.&lt;/span&gt; I learned from that and it actually put me on the path of music education that I’m on today and put me on the path of understanding music from an academic point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lYBDRBnpF5I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-a-career&quot;&gt;Building a career&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Again, a long way around the barn, I got out of school, I went to New York, I became a successful studio bass player and I’d go to the union, pick up my union checks for beer commercials and pantyhose commercials that I’d played bass on and all kinds of stuff, and–while you smile–the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brecker_Brothers&quot;&gt;Brecker Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were sitting next to me playing the horns on those same pantyhose commercials. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Gadd&quot;&gt;Steve Gadd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was playing drums on them as well. So, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby_Rosengarden&quot;&gt;Bobby Rosengarden &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–you know, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dick_Cavett_Show&quot;&gt;Dick Cavett &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; drummer. It was a slew of the crew of the greatest New York musicians. And I was in that mix because I could read music and I was considered an over-player being a young hyper kid. Psychologically, probably way out of balance at that juncture. And yet, I could play and read and do my job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What got me into Bruford and what got me into these bands was, at that particular time, I had played with a whole lot of the musicians that were famous in the 70s. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Mann&quot;&gt;Herbie Mann &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Martino&quot;&gt;Pat Martino &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I recorded with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Moraz&quot;&gt;Patrick Moraz &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when he was the keyboard player in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yes_(band)&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when Yes was at its absolute height. I recorded and played, oh goodness, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Benson&quot;&gt;George Benson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Liebman&quot;&gt;Dave Liebman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we had a band with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfred_%22Pee_Wee%22_Ellis&quot;&gt;Pee Wee Ellis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was in Europe as the house bass player for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_Records&quot;&gt;Atlantic Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; hired by Herbie Mann to record and play a great deal of the artists that were featured at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montreux_Jazz_Festival&quot;&gt;Montreaux Jazz Festival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bruford-and-van-halen&quot;&gt;Bruford and Van Halen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, my pedigree was good, my thing was growing, and then &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raygomez.com&quot;&gt;Ray Gomez &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who was a guitar player and a friend of Patrick Moraz, who got me on the Patrick record, recommended–or, Patrick recommended me to Bill Bruford. Wait, I gotta get this straight. Patrick mentioned to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Bruford&quot;&gt;Bill Bruford &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about this great guitarist, which he is, named Ray Gomez and I was playing with Ray Gomez in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmine_Appice&quot;&gt;Carmine Appice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s band. So, Bill came to America to check out Ray. I was the bass player and Bill ended up hiring me for his band. I played with his band, did several very-well-received records, toured quite a lot with that group, and am as grateful as can be to have had the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Bill opened &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; up for me.&lt;/span&gt; He is, or was because he’s retired now–I would call him a guy that had the intelligence and the spiritual wherewithall to utilize every element of his playing in an original manner. He was arguably one of the more average technical drummers around, kinda quirky and [scat drumming], you know–that thing. And yet, there was an infectiousness in it &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; he was utterly original in that. So, a lot of guys who, let’s say had more physical technique, weren’t as identifiable in their style approach as Bill Bruford was. And &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; was a very big lesson for me. That proceeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uim0FMZvADk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_Holdsworth&quot;&gt;Allan Holdsworth &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was in the group. Later I played with Allan, went to Los Angeles, and, you know, things ensued. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Halen&quot;&gt;Van Halen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_Van_Halen&quot;&gt;Eddie Van Halen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I became friends at that time. I was invited to play in the band, an invitation which I turned down, but I think they wouldn’t have had me anyway. I don’t think &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Lee_Roth&quot;&gt;David Lee Roth &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; felt I was of an attitude to have in that band, but nonetheless, Eddie did make me that offer and I did consider it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For reasons I &lt;em&gt;won’t&lt;/em&gt; go into, I didn’t accept it, except to say I would love to play with him today. We’re older gentlemen. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He’s, to me, as great a musician as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&quot;&gt;John Coltrane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in that Coltrane changed &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; in the way that the saxophone was viewed and the manner of playing&lt;/span&gt;, he originated everything. So did Eddie Van Halen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He is one of the great and unique talents that I’ve ever heard on guitar. And &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; felt that somebody like myself, a Billy Sheehan, someone of a more adventuresome nature, might make even Van Halen sound greater, although I do admire what his son has done and I am quite a fan of Michael Anthony having felt that he was, even still, the perfect bass player for Van Halen. No doubt about it. So, there you go, and now I’m 63.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2mnipvcmVdE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching-methods&quot;&gt;Teaching Methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Somewhere along the way, you got quite interested in teaching methodologies. You were a student, obviously, and along the way you evolved, learned technique, mastered the instrument–or, have been trying to and continuing to over the decades…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: “Trying to” is more correctly put.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: The better the musician, it seems, the more they “try” is what I hear about. Can you talk about what got you into teaching and what informed your teaching methodologies over the years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: In a nutshell, my teaching methodologies that I formed came out of my years on violin and my tenure at Berklee School of Music. At the time it was called “School of Music.” Both areas were entirely focused on musical content. Very little that I ever recall was ever referred to in terms of the word “groove,” “feel,” “heart,” “art,” “artistry,” or anything… Rather that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;people that learned their instrument and practiced their instrument already had enough of an inspiration and a feeling for it that the art part was sort of already taken care of.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The part that might not have been taken care of is where to put the fingers on the neck or where to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drum_rudiment#Diddle_rudiments&quot;&gt;paradiddle &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyrhythm&quot;&gt;polyrhythm &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a snare drum or play the vibes or play the guitar or the horn. This became noticeable to me when in the 80s, I noticed, at least on bass, a detour from musical content and a new paradigm began to show up, which included non-musical methodologies. “Non-musical” meaning “learning for its own sake.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Learning music, like anything well-done, takes time and isn’t easy.&lt;/span&gt; Where a story began to evolve that “study with us” or “study with me” or “there’s a million ways to learn” (which there are, by the way), but ironically, there’s a million things to eat, I’m just not sure I want to eat them all. Do you follow the logic? I agree there’s a million ways to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I began to sort of, at that time in the sort of imbalanced area that I was–I’ll get to that later. I’ve been psychologically imbalanced for many years. I grew up hard, very dysfunctional family and paid the price for it up until rather recently where there was a rather combative and not very pleasant aspect to me that I know existed, but didn’t give a hoot that it did. “You don’t like it? To hell with you.” So, I was almost deliberately supporting and constructing a rather evil personality, but not aware of what the results would be. Not outwardly, but inwardly. That I’ll discuss in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The educational thing came about where a lot of people who are popular in music started to teach and in my opinion, in my &lt;em&gt;opinion&lt;/em&gt;, taught incorrectly in that people say they were getting better from the methods I would do a lot of clinics in those days and I’d developed a way where “Come on up! We’ll play what you wanna play and I’ll do a little critiquing” because if I tell you personally, “Anthony, you’re holding the neck too hard or you’re not representing the notes in a G major &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triad_(music)&quot;&gt;triad &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” probably quite a few guys in the audience also grip the neck too hard and don’t represent notes correctly. So, what I offer to you as a demonstration usually applied to most people that were there anyway. We all share a common beginning in pretty much everything, so music seemed to be the same thing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Art is universal. To me, learning it is not.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, I got into saying that these methods “aint g’wine t’work.” They’re not gonna do you what you think that they’re gonna do you. And I took notice that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;a lot of people were content to follow advice and never question the advice being given&lt;/span&gt; because they’re admirers of bass players or guitar players or drummers who offered this advice, but who were either self-taught or not fully supportive of music itself. Having partially come from a training background, but usually abandoning it or not relying on it, philosophically going in other ways. Often what was being shared was emotionally satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If I tell you, personally, that whatever you play is great, has meaning, and you’re expressing your heart, and what you do is fine, it exists, this is how you feel… That’ll be $100. In the essence of the sharing of this philosophy, I took note that it became so popular in so many other areas of teaching, generally again from self-taught people that might not have understood the meaning of music. I can’t understand the grammatic meaning of French having never really studied it. I can Spanish because I have studied it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I began to object and in a rather mean-spirited way, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I began to attack and covertly and overtly slander people and it was all based on a psychological instability.&lt;/span&gt; I wasn’t wrong, and to this day I don’t feel that I was wrong or I am wrong about anything that I ever felt about education and about learning. I feel a generation… I feel two generations have been let down by the well-intended and kind advice from people that meant no harm and meant no collusion that “we’re gonna fake these guys out and get their money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rzpfeIDxBs4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-taught&quot;&gt;“Self-taught”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;People believe the things they say. What I’ve come to believe is that it’s their right and I’ve no right to criticize anymore.&lt;/span&gt; That’s my alert/awakening and I’m living this. But, in the terms of advice to people in the educational thing, there’s only two ways to learn that I’ve ever thought about, which is being self-taught and by learning musical content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Self-taught includes you taking that guitar off the wall behind you and putting on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stevie_Ray_Vaughan&quot;&gt;Stevie Ray Vaughan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; record, listening, imitating, going out, jamming with your friends, trying a Fender amp, then going to a Marshall cabinet, now trying to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.markbass.it&quot;&gt;Markbass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; amps, now trying &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallien-Krueger&quot;&gt;Gallien Kruger &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, testing this, trying that, putting on these strings, pedals, playing with this drummer, that drummer… Anything that you’ve done under your own auspices, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;anything you’ve done under your own control is a self-taught endeavor because you’re not paying me or anybody else to teach you.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The second way I felt–and this produced, by the way, everybody. I’m a trained musician, but I’m self-taught. You’re a guitar player, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: And I know you’re self-taught. I know you’ve picked the guitar up. No matter what you’ve learned, I know you’ve listened and done stuff on your own. Am I right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: And the reason I say it with such confidence is because everybody is! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Everybody, the most trained musicians are self-taught.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaco_Pastorius&quot;&gt;Jaco Pastorius &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Jack Bruce, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rick_Wakeman&quot;&gt;Rick Wakeman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–I showed him a piece of music recently… Not recently. It was actually about 21 years ago! “The other day! No, that was 21 years ago.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;academic-learning&quot;&gt;Academic learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, the second way is academically, which is the elements related to music that you can’t or have trouble getting or one can’t find on their own because there’s a million books, many of which I personally feel will not get you to play better. There is a manner to learn academically and I notice that in music history since the time of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bach&quot;&gt;Bach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or before, up until the time of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gershwin&quot;&gt;George Gershwin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, up until &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benny_Goodman&quot;&gt;Benny Goodman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Miller&quot;&gt;Glenn Miller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and up into the 50s and 60s that they’re training musicians, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Burton&quot;&gt;Gary Burton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;s, the schooled guys, the great arrangers, the people that are–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Williams&quot;&gt;John Williams &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a trained guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m wandering here because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;everybody since the early 17th century and earlier have all been trained the same way. The only thing that really has changed is the music itself.&lt;/span&gt; They sat students down at 3 or 4 or 5 years old and a teacher or a parent said, “This is a G, this is an A, and I want you to write it like this.” And subsequently, a tenure, an apprenticeship began. Now recognize this, everybody with a little deviation–I know they’ve got the Suzuki method and they’ve got this approach and that approach–it all was based in the center of you and I sitting down with a guitar, bass, or piano and a teacher saying, “Play A B C D E.” All of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Gershwin learned how to write and compose in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apartment&quot;&gt;tenement apartment &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Do you follow? &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_van_Beethoven&quot;&gt;Beethoven &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was taught, obviously, by many, many people. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Armstrong&quot;&gt;Louis Armstrong &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had private lessons. Exhibited a thing that a teacher taught him to play, more or less, and you see the indentation on his lip. What had changed was musical content, not the manner in which to teach (for the most part).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jaco Pastorius is a self-taught bass player. I mention him because everybody knows Jaco. Jaco learned how to arrange and compose physically and academically in a bus and in hotel rooms. A guy sat him down and said, “This is how we do it.” What was his name? Bret? Brent? Charles Brent, who passed away, I understand. So, when I got the idea that everybody learned music this way, and again there are no exceptions that I can think of–maybe one guy in Istanbul and another guy in Rotterdam–do you follow? The trained guys, they all learned the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nRFbfBGgpbw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Suddenly I noticed that bass players aren’t being trained that way at all. In fact, a new paradigm was being invented and new approaches that I can now tell you my story and say things like, “Here’s an idea that worked for me. It may not work for you, but it worked for me.” And I thought about that principle and thought to myself, “That’s interesting,” because in my case, I guarantee you Anthony or anyone that’s listening, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;whatever worked for me, I’m &lt;em&gt;guaranteeing&lt;/em&gt; you, is going to work for you.&lt;/span&gt; And that, to me–and I’m &lt;em&gt;guaranteeing&lt;/em&gt; this. It’s not just a statement. Because I made that statement publicly and could fulfill that declaration, it occurred to me that music and education was compromised, that a feel-good endeavor–am I talking too long by the way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: No, the whole purpose of this website is to allow the artist to speak at length. I’d rather hear as much as you have to say and as little as I have to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I just want to make sure I’m not wandering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: No, please go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: It was just that when this became–this replaced music because when I fought so hard to emphasize music in music education, I took note that some people that weren’t into it sort of went, “Well, yeah, music is good too.” This was a contribution, I suppose, because of the pressure that I’d put on that–I lament the pressure part of it. That’s the thing about this whole thing. I do feel that bass education and, again, done by well-meaning people–nobody’s evil here. Nobody. I just feel the whole system’s been compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I recently heard about a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scratching&quot;&gt;record-scratching &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; class at Berklee and I heard about a heavy metal class in a school in Nottingham, England, that you can get a degree in. “This is heavy metal. You’ll study and play &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica&quot;&gt;Metallica &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Sabbath&quot;&gt;Black Sabbath &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You’ll go on tour and you’ll get a degree.” I simplify the thing. And now record scratching and other elements of education–there’s things in bass that I think are shocking, but, to make clear: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;this is &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; feeling, people don’t have to agree with it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ll share what I think and hopefully, without wishing to cause harm–I don’t want to cause harm to anybody. That’s where my whole thing is utterly changed. What I do want to do is change focus back to where I feel it has deviated from, which is deviated from the fact that musicians only get better if they learn correctly, practice correctly, and play correctly or incorrectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You play, you grow in that, you listen to early Clapton, which I have, and he wasn’t the guitar player that he subsequently became. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimi_Hendrix&quot;&gt;Jimi Hendrix &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; apprenticed with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_Richard&quot;&gt;Little Richard &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Isley_Brothers&quot;&gt;Isley Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; playing [50s rock and roll scat]. He had his thing, it was still coming out, but since music is deviated from what I consider the true message, which is: musicians, if you want to get better, it’s not entirely easy, but &lt;em&gt;so what?&lt;/em&gt; It’s fun! My bass is never far from me. I pick it up and I practice and I play and the endeavor to do something that I don’t know so that I can eventually become better seems a positive thing to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Jw6oOXuq10&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;music-is-hard-work&quot;&gt;Music is hard work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There is a statement made that music, I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_Wooten&quot;&gt;Victor Wooten &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; said this, that “academic music is proven to work, it just takes too long.” And I heard that and I thought and I remembered something that Obama once said, “Anything worth having isn’t easy.” There’s a million philosophical messages that we work for the things we love. They don’t always come easy. In my mind, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“So what if music, learning it properly, takes a long time. So what?”&lt;/span&gt; What artist–look at the history of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Gogh&quot;&gt;Van Gogh &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who studied and suffered his whole life through mental illness, but eventually evolved to the master that we know today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;All musicians–I saw early &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luciano_Pavarotti&quot;&gt;Pavarotti &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; singing locally and developing his career and he took vocal lessons for many, many years. So what if it takes “too long?” I’m against the idea that musicians will embrace an easy way out when it’s intended that the work is not supposed to be a detriment, it’s supposed to be an enhancing thing. It builds our character. We’re working for our music, for our artform. Holy mackerel! Is that not too great or what? “I did an exercise today and I couldn’t play it. I really was terrible at it.” You know? Not literally, it’s just an example. And the answer is, “Sure! Because tomorrow it might be better.” That’s progress. That’s improvement. So what if it’s bad today? You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I’m not happy with the general all-round vision that working for our artform is an awful thing because everybody I know who is either self-taught or trained in music–and as far as I’m thinking, I’m curious–and, by the way, “self-taught” means playing, jamming, hanging… Anything that’s free. Free! You know, except buying the guitar and toys. It’s the human development of your instrument. I can’t think of a third option other than learning music or being self-taught. I don’t know if there’s a third option and yet, I’ve seen that an industry has presented a third, fourth, fifth, sixth, seventh, eighth options. My message is: my vision is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Have you talked to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by any chance about this stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I know Robert, but I haven’t talked to him about this. Why? Is Robert in the same mindset?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I went to a week long guitar camp thing that he leads called the Guitar Circle and he said, “Everyone who is self-taught, raise your hand.” So, of course, I raise my hand, so do nearly everybody else in the class and he says, “What you’re effectively telling me is somebody who knew nothing about the instrument, who knew nothing about music as a craft, who knew nothing about the technicalities of playing taught you everything that you know about what you’re doing. Tell me how that’s effective.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: It’s exactly and precisely my same philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I think you two would have an interesting conversation around some of this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Well, it’s important to point out that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;my only comment here is about education. It’s not about art and the way one plays and the way one chooses to play.&lt;/span&gt; I was told that I am not welcome at many music schools because of the fact that I’ve lambasted more mean-spiritedly music education schools, teachers, magazines, web–I mean, I put ‘em all in and cocked my rifle. In that manner, I lament it and I’d like to talk about that in a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What hasn’t changed is perhaps I’m finding another way to relate a thought to people and if they don’t believe in it, of course they must go through their own way. I don’t want to cast aspersions against someone different than me–anymore! I don’t want to be to be rude to anybody. I quoted Victor, but Victor changed things for the better by opening up music to 10,000 kids. You know what I mean? Our philosophies diverge, mine with other guys diverge, but if the intrinsic need is to educate, then I imagine they’re doing a good thing, a kind thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I just think that in the specific end of things, I could quote several guys and offer thoughts where I feel that the message is misleading people. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The problem with me is political.&lt;/span&gt; If I do this, I’m not so sure, especially with the harm that I’ve caused before, that it would be taken that way. So as a part of my penance, for the most part, I can only offer my thoughts and keep it as neutral and show love and respect for different people who teach differently than I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wQON9fHPJsk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;love-what-you-learn&quot;&gt;Love what you learn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you believe that if people were taught as historically people have been taught music, the music scene, the music industry would be wildly different? Do you think that pop music of today would be produced if a requirement was that formal training be introduced to all musicians, like there’s some sort of threshold in order to be able to release music or something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Well, I imagine that the level of awareness of music would be higher, so perhaps some of the music that is going on today that, to my ear, is rather [long pause] different, that perhaps a higher awareness from people might not tolerate that kind of music and demand from artists and themselves something that isn’t supposed to be virtuosic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People often try to find holes–I notice people will work harder to find loopholes in what I say than to try to get the general message and often they’ll say, “Well, I don’t want to be a virtuoso.” And my thing is I say, “Well, I never mentioned the word!” I simply say that the level of music–I’m a fairly good Beatle bass player just because I happen to know so much about the bass that I don’t even have to think twice about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I can play Beatles songs with real feeling. Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Will_Lee_(bassist)&quot;&gt;Will Lee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fab_Faux&quot;&gt;The Fab Faux &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Will is a studied guy and can do this. But to answer your question, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t look at music education as a part of an artistic success story.&lt;/span&gt; I don’t look at music ed as being done in order to have a career. I look at music ed as done so that one could be a better player and therefore qualify to have a music career. Now I know it’s a subtle point of thinking, but often people will practice thinking, “Well, I’m ready for the gig,” or practice and “Maybe now I can audition for a famous band,” or whatever. My thinking is, “I wouldn’t go that way.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I would say to everybody, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Practice &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; you love &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/span&gt; and that this instrument, in my case, deserves to be learned better for its own sake! I have my bass nearby and I’m always practicing ideas and the thing is that I’ve developed a career that coincidentally occurred because I was qualified, it seems, to have one, rather than, “I’ll practice this scale and then I’ll use it tonight on a gig.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You might be surprised to find out that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;scales were never meant to be used in professional music&lt;/span&gt; because professional music and all its artistic different parts isn’t based on scales. It’s based on the artful use of melody and rhythm and harmony that coincidentally sometimes might include a scale, but what you practice is not usable on a gig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People erroneously have been saying, or asking, “How do I use this?” And I say, “You don’t! You don’t use this on a gig.” I’m a Spanish student and they say in Spanish, “Yo voy a la playa. (I go to the beach.) Tu vas a la playa. (You go to the beach.) Nosotros vamos a la playa. (We go to the beach.) Ellos vama los playa. (They go to the beach.)” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There isn’t a Spanish-speaking person on earth that talks like that&lt;/span&gt; and yet I conjugated these verbs in class to learn the conjugations and eventually, the artistic element began to take place. Can I give you another example?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Of course!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;music-as-a-language&quot;&gt;Music as a language&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: People refer to music as a language. It’s a very popular tenet of function, belief, that music is a language because it communicates things. Okay. I took note that when we learn English, in our case–obviously other countries and other societies learn their languages &lt;em&gt;by ear&lt;/em&gt;–it’s interesting to note that probably close to 100% of us went to school to academically develop our skill in our language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We learn reading and writing and giving book reports, which is us standing up in front and, “I read the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Tale_of_Two_Cities&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Tale of Two Cities&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,” and we’re working on our speech and enunciation and use of words and it’s all an academic endeavor and we all went into academic use and learning and practice of language since we’re 1st grade or kindergarten up until 12th grade and then there’s English literature and higher forms of it in college and universities. What musicians have not done that I can see is recognize that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if music is a language, why aren’t they &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; it as one?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OZgpiMrsC5U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clichs-of-belief&quot;&gt;Clichés of belief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Musicians sometimes have built in to their belief systems clichés. The clichés are the things that bass players feel, “Keep the bottom,” “Gotta play a groove,” “The groove is the most important thing, more than notes,” or something of this nature, when ironically, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you don’t play the right notes, there’s nothing to groove on.&lt;/span&gt; So, the concept is a backward concept. A groove is a &lt;em&gt;result&lt;/em&gt; of first using the right notes the right ways–according to the feel of the song–and hence, in the comfort of doing that, a groove ensues. A groove is a result, it’s not the principal thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t sacrifice words to communicate with you so that I have a groove in the manner of communication. I will say to you, “I feel like eating, um… what is that word? Spaghetti! At the end of our interview, I’m going to go in and cook it.” So, what comes first is the word, so next time, I can say, “Ya know man, I gotta have me some spaghetti because I’m an Italian food freak and I ain’t kiddin’ and I’m gonna get down in the kitchen and I’m gonna be pitchin’ a nice bowl o’ s’ghetti in my face.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, I’m being ridiculous, but there is a jazz development to that that the creative development is that I use words and then invent words. First comes the words. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;How do we speak if we don’t know the words? How does anybody communicate in time?&lt;/span&gt; And in time is the time of communication, the ebb and flow of it. If you want to see how hesitant you will be in the communication area of language, I would ask you to say something to me in German or Dutch where I also could not do it. Or Italian. Spanish is my language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If we can’t speak these languages, can’t “groove” in the language, it means because we don’t know the words. That’s my thing. That’s as far as my thinking goes. So when one says, “Groove is the best,” I say, “Eventually it is. But, if you don’t know the right notes and you don’t know how to play, why try to perform something that isn’t natural for you to play?” I’ve seen guys work on groove and playing and they’re all over the place! Their time is all over the place and their notes are all over the place because they teach a lot of guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I say, “Look at a tightrope walker.” You’ve got &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nik_Wallenda&quot;&gt;John… what’s his name &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? The guy who crossed the two towers when they were up and crossed the Grand Canyon. You look at these guys. Do you ever notice that they take a couple steps backward sometimes in order to get their balance? They stop and they put a foot back and they wait and they wait and they balance and then they go forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Musicians are always going forward without stopping or going backwards one or two steps to see what they know to see what they don’t know.&lt;/span&gt; And if they did what I said, or people like me, they would change their entire sphere of playing. I could, me personally, if I were king of the music world, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I could change everybody’s playing in 3 to 6 months. Easily!&lt;/span&gt; If they did what I said. No democracy, you know what I mean? I’m good. I could hear you and say, “Okay, Anthony, here’s what you’re going to practice today and in that way I’ll make you better.” So, that’s sort of a benefit to me. I’m sharing these thoughts. I hope it doesn’t seem too hard or too mean-spirited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uEk5rZkBxFo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’m curious. Personally, this resonates a lot with me and it’s part of the motivation behind the website itself. I see this every day in my work as a professional in the IT industry. The barrier to entry for software development is much lower than it ever has been and I know that I’m young, I’m 34, and I’m sure that there are people that have computer science degrees from 1980-some or 1990-some saying, “Oh, look at this whippersnapper. He thinks he can appreciate the barrier to entry,” but what I’m seeing as I manage software developers is completely improvised skills that were built alone with no formal instruction and I hire them and we have to train them in order to get them to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;It also reminds me of religious, spiritual contexts where Catholicism as one example, you go through years and years of schooling to become a priest, but in many Protestant non-denominational Christian churches, they’re started by people with no real formal background. They just have a spiritual zeal and they develop a following and sometimes they develop a church and that turns into an institution and you have to live with, if you’re Catholic, you have to live with the informal and say, “Well, anyone can start a church now,” whereas somebody who might attend that church might say, “Look at those guys and how formal they are. I can’t believe they think this is what it takes to believe in God.” So, those are two very personal examples that it reminds me of. Is there any relation there for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Sure! The relation would be the impact I got from what you’re saying is that, well it goes back to something that I’ve come to believe greatly now is that everybody has a choice and everybody has a right to choose and everybody wishes to improve can be a “Protestant” or a “Catholic.” I’m leaning more towards Buddhism these days than having the needs for it, but again that’s my choice and the variety of choices–there’s a little bit of a danger in choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Choice is often based on emotion and this is just a fact. We’ll choose a car not only on the gas mileage, but, “Man, check out how that looks!” Painting a home, the color that resonates with one. People will regard music in their manner of viewing it based on how they feel about things. “Feelings” are honest and I actually trust more my body than my mind in that my mind got me into trouble all the time. It would think that, “Well Anthony’s sitting there and asking me about this. He’s trying to trap me. And Anthony and Anthony and Anthony!” You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You sound like my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: That’s what she does?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: No, I’m just kidding. She’s very kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: “My wife. You kiddin’ me? My wife.” I’m trying to think of “my wife” jokes. Oh yeah, “I take my wife everywhere, but she finds her way home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henny_Youngman&quot;&gt;Henny Youngman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; one-liners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZGtlxHgKUA0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;messages-and-cultish-behaviors&quot;&gt;Messages and cultish behaviors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: So, the thing is &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I just believe there is a lost society today in musicians in that they 1. are trusting the wrong messages, 2. I feel that often they have a cult attitude.&lt;/span&gt; The cult attitude is that if their hero or someone that they admire or location or center or being or something presents information, if they trust it, they never question it and woe to you if you criticize or question that person or institution. Woe to you because people will attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This denotes to me a cult where the leader is infallible, never to be questioned. The institution, the philosophy, the book–I don’t know. Whatever it is. Don’t question it. Don’t even think that this source of information is wrong. And this is the downfall in part of music education because I have advised people in clinics, “Look, try anything because no harm will come from it, but don’t be so sure that even I, Jeff, be so sure that people are like, ‘Yeah, I like Jeff now…’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Don’t trust everything I say as if what I’m saying is gospel. Question it.&lt;/span&gt; Investigate my thoughts. Don’t fall into the trap that you substitute one perfect vision of guidance of music for another. If what I say makes sense, investigate it.” Example, rock education. Again, I’m not welcome in many schools, I’m not welcome and am not appreciated by people that teach rock because I’ve said that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;rock education hasn’t produced the results that it’s promised&lt;/span&gt; or at least alluded to and the results would be learning the skill in rock to develop/have a career in rock, or even a good amateur chance at being a rather freed and expressive musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I say this for the most part, not individually. I notice a lot of guys that may have been through rock education may have already been able to play, got to the schools, more or less may have done the same thing, got out, got a careeer, and feel that the school or the teacher or the book helped them. My thinking is that people–now I say this, which of course will not go down well, but it must be said–people need to check this out and find out if what I say is right or wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If it’s wrong, ignore my words because I’m not saying it for evil intentions. I’m saying it to enlighten people that trust a system of learning that might not be producing what it says it should as a general system. If I’m wrong, well, I got this wisdom, 10,000 grads from this and 9,000 are in successful bands. “Berlin’s out of his mind!” I’ll accept that. “Thank you for checking out my statement and finding it wrong.” But I don’t think you will, and that’s my point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Xphugh8RHM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rock-education&quot;&gt;Rock “Education”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You can list a thousand guys. There’s 2, 3 million people that have passed through rock education. I’m grabbing a number out of the air, by the way, and a thousand names are used. Take 3 zeroes off one side and take 3 zeroes off the other and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you’ve got a 1 in 200,000 chance to possibly extract a career as a successful or even a decent rock musician.&lt;/span&gt; My question would be, “What if the statistics were the same if you studied the law? Would it be the same if you studied how to drive?” In all things vocational that I’ve noticed, there’s a real high success to the students for having invested money and time, because there’s a lot of time and a lot of money, and usually acquire careers through vocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In fact, in just about all areas of learning, what I’ve discovered is that rock music hasn’t fulfilled that promise and that people on the belief or again by the feeling, which I’m asking in them to question, that rock music is an entertainment (in &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; opinion! People don’t have to agree. It’s an entertainment. I’m very clear on this because I have a long history in which I was not so forthcoming and I want to make up for that, but it doesn’t mean I’m going to change my spot because I don’t see errors in my thinking so I’ll share it as benignly as possible. People check it out. If I’m wrong, follow your plans.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;From what I’ve seen, there’s a couple of websites, the top 100 rock bass players, top 100 jazz bass players, top 100 rock bands, top 100 you know. If you look at them, and I examined this and I barely could find anybody that claims from any of these sources that they went to a music school or went to a teacher–let’s say, maybe they did, because you know there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; exceptions, or went to some source or camp or tutorship and acquired a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It would be an interesting thing for somebody with time on their hands to do this research and add up a thousand names and find out what area, and I’m very specific on “rock education,” “rock ensembles,” “rock lessons,” “rock music” in its varied forms. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; went to Berklee and studied &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t believe he studied rock. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuart_Hamm&quot;&gt;Stu Hamm &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; went to Berklee and studied &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t believe he studied rock. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Gambale&quot;&gt;Frank Gambale &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Scott Henderson went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musicians_Institute&quot;&gt;MI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to study with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Pass&quot;&gt;Joe Pass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Diorio&quot;&gt;Joe Diorio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Jazz guys. I don’t believe they studied rock.&lt;/span&gt; That’s just the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If I try to support the principle for the good of our industry, for the good of the sake of musicians who really ought to be thinking more alertly and not be so quick to be sold, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if rock education would change its name to rock entertainment, I wouldn’t say a word.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, it’s kind of like when the Buddha says, “If you see the buddha walking to you, kill him.” You need to discover it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Well, I’ll change that. If the Buddha walks to me, I’ll ask and interview him to make sure he is Buddha. If he says, “I’m Buddha,” I won’t buy it right away, so I might spend a little time to find out for myself because if he is, I’m going to acknowledge it and say, “You know what? At the beginning, I thought you weren’t, but I’m wrong.” And this is the thing about all this that I’m talking about today, it is important to investigate for yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It isn’t an 8-month tenureship at a library. You can do it in a week. Look at interviews. Look at what guys said. I just feel that rock has become &lt;em&gt;such&lt;/em&gt; a business and &lt;em&gt;such&lt;/em&gt; a money-maker and as long as people are willing to spend the money, why stop? I’m simply saying, “Go for the fun of it. Be a little on the alert if you feel this may help you to acquire a career because if it does, there has to be a precedent.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9z6g7vBXboA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Rock has been around since the late 1970s when somebody decided to transcribe Eddie Van Halen and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt; solos. I think Steve Vai did a whole book on that. Ironically, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;these transcriptions never &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; helped anybody to learn how to read nor play the guitar&lt;/span&gt;, in my opinion. One guy, two guys… It shows the genius of Steve Vai for having the ability to write it out. It doesn’t mean that a student or somebody buying it actually extracted any real benefit from it. What would have been the benefit was to put on the headphones and get into the grit and dirt and meat of listening and imitating to those Frank solos as all self-taught musicians do to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;What has happened is rock education has sanitized the learning experience.&lt;/span&gt; Rock by its nature, and transcriptions and these things, is a filthy affair. It’s an affair based in grit, dirt, sweat, PHEW. “What the hell was he playing over there? Let me listen to that again. Damn, I still can’t get that.” And in the search, 2 things happen: 1. You develop your understanding of the artist and 2. “Well if he did this by hearing it so much, I got a couple of ideas where I might do it this way.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Hence the evolution from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Johnson&quot;&gt;Robert Johnson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Cray&quot;&gt;Robert Cray &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And the line of Cogbill and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry_Jemmott&quot;&gt;Jemmott &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and who preceded them, maybe the upright guys, to the Jacos and the great R ‘n B players, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocco_Prestia&quot;&gt;Rocco Prestia &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;s and the subsequent great funk players, the Victor Wootens in that unique funk and groove element of his bass playing–the lineage is a self-taught progression, but the sanitized element of “This is a G chord, now turn up your amp, now turn on your sound… There you go! Now check out that sound! Now play that chord!” True! But, a whole element–it’s like taking the trace vitamins out of spinach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You’ve taken spinach and you’ve so concised it, so condensed it, so purified it that it has the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chlorophyll&quot;&gt;chlorophyll &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in it, but vitamin A, B, and trace elements, and biotene, and kerotene, and the nicotine, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heavy_Weather_(album)&quot;&gt;Teen Town &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all the teens is taken out of it so it’s become a sterile food item, which a lot of our foods are. Keep that in mind when you are willing to plop down a check and, for gosh sakes, if I had my way, I would like to change the whole system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People in business aren’t happy with me, and I don’t blame them, but maybe we could replace it in two ways. 1. Maybe the people in business offer more content. Stop letting students run the show. What do they know about it? Teachers in schools and other places saying, “So what do you want to study?” I understand the philosophy in that, but students are picking their own classes and saying, “I don’t want to study this, I want to study that.” What?! They don’t do that in medical school or in the DeVry school of truck driving-lessons driving license. It’s like, “This is how it is DONE!” When people learn this way, they seem to get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Xphugh8RHM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Two questions come to mind. The first is: Do you believe musicians have a responsibility to their listeners or the audience? As they produce new musicians, somebody picks up–and I heard Steve Vai on the radio and said, “I want to play like that.” That happens all the time. You with the Beatles. And then secondly: Do you believe that had you not been educated the way you were, it would have even been possible for you to have the career that you have, to play the kinds of music that you’ve been on? I know that’s a really big hypothetical question, but there have to be some self-taught people without that education who are very great players, but what you are doing is so sophisticated, I’m wondering if you believe that level of sophistication could be achieved without the education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: The point here is this: If you choose to be self-taught, you’re within your right to do so. If you choose to study with somebody, and therefore write them a check, I suggest to &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;make sure that what you’re paying for is what you get. And that’s the whole difference. That’s the whole thing in a nutshell.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The self-taught endeavor is fine. If anyone reviews back, I don’t criticize it. My whole thing is really, quite frankly, a financial thing. “Here’s money, fix my car. You’re going to fix it.” “Here’s money. Cook me a good meal or I won’t come back to your restaurant.” “Here’s money. I have a cold or a cut. Sew me up.” “Here’s money. I’m going to a therapist. Help me to learn about myself.” “Here’s money…” You follow what I’m saying. “I want to buy shoes that don’t fall apart.” “Here’s money. I want to learn how to navigate this instrument in musical ways that I don’t know.” And that’s all there is to it in my personal philosophy. So, your first question is what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I see. That makes more sense. The first question is whether you believe musicians have a responsibility to be educated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: No. They don’t have a responsibility because it’s an artform and an artform is open to interpretation and choice. What I do think is that students that bought a guitar are short-changing themselves by not taking the time to learn the guitar that even a weekend golfer is taking to learn how to hit a golf ball correctly. There’s more guys on the golf course that have taken from the golf pro at the club and learning how to hold the club and learning how to position because I used to think, “What fun is it to have golf clubs and constantly hit it into the trees?” Where’s the joy? “Oh boy! I love this game!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And the same thing occurred to me. People, who I feel are erroneously (some of them, not all of them) say, “Well, I have a guitar, but I’m not interested in really learning. I’ll do a couple of tunes and sit at home and just strum away.” And that’s fair! My suggestion is that if they just put in a few more months, they could get way beyond that and I’m curious if they went and bought a guitar or a bass or drums, wouldn’t they wish to put in the time, which is not 6 hours a day–I’ll put in 6 hours a day because it’s my career, people are expecting something from me or people like me, so &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; have a responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mIdPO3PXX0s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communication-and-entertainment&quot;&gt;Communication and entertainment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, if a guy’s just playing and wants to do his thing, his responsibility might be more to his own investigation. And when he starts to play, I guess the responsibility is not to play in a poor manner so that people sitting in a bar might have a modicum of entertainment because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I do believe in the entertainment element. We need to be entertained. I watch television, I go to the movies, I go to music shows. Music is an entertainment.&lt;/span&gt; Communication and music–you know everybody communicates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a funny thing about, “You gotta communicate with people.” And I thought, “But anybody does! Anybody on the stage plays with authenticity at their level.” They’re playing and they know people are out there watching and digging it. I don’t know anybody who plays that doesn’t want to communicate. “I’m gonna play, but I don’t give a hell about you, Anthony.” What?! That doesn’t happen on a gig. We’re playing. Everybody’s a little excited or nervous or scared or jittery or “ooh, there’s a hot girl there and man, my friends are listening and, oh I hope I don’t forget that song, man.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We are not separate from the emotion and the communicative element of music.&lt;/span&gt; That’s another little false cliché: people play without feeling. I have a feeling that &lt;em&gt;everybody&lt;/em&gt; plays with feeling. Nobody plays like, “I. Have. No. Feeling. Whatsoever.” People that do this are trying to extract the notes and play with feeling. Everybody has feeling. Everybody, but the top players have less mystery of where to put their fingers. You look at a top player and they’re playing the same lines and the same music they played a long time, so it isn’t a mystery anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; they have left is emotion. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s the only element left in the thing because they know what to play.&lt;/span&gt; Look at a Stevie Ray Vaughan video and watch him play and his thing is this [bobbing his head left and right] because that’s the essence of what I wish everybody would get to in some manner. To dismiss the mystery of where to put the fingers, which is what academic music does, and get into the feeling of it because that’s the goal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If there was a law that said, “Jeff, what would you do: play only or study only?” I’d play only and I’d tell everybody to do the same. Don’t study a lick, don’t play a note, just pick up your guitar an play. If there was a law! But since there isn’t such a law, I’ll give advice on how to get better. Hopefully it’s acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vSKDK9eNxQU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-weird-music&quot;&gt;Making weird music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: This brings me to making weird music. “Weird” is a marketing term. It’s a very vague term intentionally. What I’m going for is to encourage people to discover what is unique about them and to put that into their music instead of making something that’s already been made a hundred thousand times, do something that’s unique and interesting to you by you for yourself so that others can enjoy it. How do you believe that what you’ve been talking about here can lead to, and you’ve touched on this a little bit but I’d like to hear a little more in-depth, but how do you believe that these methods can lead to finding your own true self in the artform?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I think the same way that learning English in elementary school, junior high school, and high school has led us to express our feelings and thoughts with great emotion about the presidential candidates, about the state of the country, about the latest news coming out of Europe, about our feelings about our loud neighbor or whatever, our feelings about anything that we feel–and if you go on the internet, you’ll notice everybody emoting with great freedom and liberty, their feelings and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the reason they do is they don’t worry about the words and they don’t worry about the grammar.&lt;/span&gt; That’s the way I feel can answer this whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, another thing, it is, to me, an incorrect order of things to suggest to people to find their own thing on their guitar right now. I’ll explain. People that find their own thing, the “weird music” that they have, the “weird” thing, generally comes from the genius or motivated guy/woman/person who hears it to do it. Most people are not so gifted and most people are not so inclined. Most people can’t tune a guitar without a tuner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In the limitation of playing and in the limitation of understanding how a guitar works the nature of &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;suggesting to add and function in the “weird” element, to me, seems inappropriate at this time.&lt;/span&gt; That the “weird” element of music, Jaco’s harmonics was &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt;, but it came later and it evolved after he first learned the notes because if you listen to early Jaco he was not doing those things. The “weird” playing of Hendrix, he always did that sort of thing and he was fired from bands or criticized by the groups he played with, but the real distinct Hendrix element came later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The “weirdness”, the special thing. The special thing is the “weird” thing. The Ginger Baker drum tones, the way that he played. Jack Bruce’s bass tone, the “fart tone.” He relayed that to me one time. “Jeff, I’ve got a fart tone when playing my bass.” I said, “Yes lad, you sure have.” [said in the “worst Scottish ever.”] I would say to people, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Don’t be so desirous of being unique when people barely know what the note Ab is.”&lt;/span&gt; See, my statement doesn’t interrupt the artistic message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learn-what-you-do&quot;&gt;Learn what you do&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People have said something that is utterly wrong and I’ll quote it now: “I don’t learn reading and I don’t practice music because it can hurt my creativity.” Perhaps you’ve heard this statement. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It is about as foolish a thing as one could say.&lt;/span&gt; “I don’t take cooking class because it’ll kill my creative cooking talent.” “I don’t take English lessons because it’ll interrupt how I wish to communicate my thoughts.” Do you follow? “I’m not gonna take driving classes. I see how they drive. I know how I want to navigate the streets.” “I’m a doctor. I don’t take medical classes. You’re coughing? I know how I want to treat you.” I’m being a little silly here, but you get the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The message is not only false, it’s destructive.&lt;/span&gt; It’s been destructive to young people who have believed this, that as if learning the craft of your instrument and learning the language of it in an academic way, as we’ve all learned, is a detriment to your art. The self-taught people are &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; the only ones who can state that their thing is entirely based on their own merits because they have no infusion of factual and, frankly, unemotional musical information. So, those people have both represented very well the self-taught ethic and how beautiful and perfect it is, and these people have also screwed things up for everybody else!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These guys &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; point to these guys and say, “Well, &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; didn’t go to school.” And in that sort of effort, like I say, I think people were sometimes (not all) seeming to work hard to find a loophole when I used to have these debates, which I’ll never have again. I would make points on Facebook and make a statement about music education and they would come back with every loophole you could imagine. It was amazing to me that I felt &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;people were working harder to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; see the logic of learning well rather than putting in the time to learn music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4MOVvDJxBSU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This gave me an inkling as to this corner of our community of players: people that are within their right to distance themselves for their own reasons from learning. Okay, so be it. The message, I guess, in this–the final element of this–is that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wouldn’t seek the “weird” until I sought the obvious.&lt;/span&gt; If by having the obvious, it’s almost like before I start to build up a really strange construction of a home with weird slats and lats and roof, I’m gonna lay a real firm slab of cement first so everything doesn’t come crumbling down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Musicians are constantly crumbling down and the way you can see it is go to Craigslist or go anywhere they’re selling secondhand guitars. There are people buying and selling guitars every single day and they’re not replacing them with new ones. Some do. You know what I mean? I’m a voice and I’m alone and I don’t mind it, I just am a guy that came out of music education as formally trained as one could possibly get since I’m 5 years old. I’m 63, so that’s 58 years in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I just wrote David Liebman yesterday and asked him for lessons so I could learn some new ideas. I studied with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Banacos&quot;&gt;Charlie Benacos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the greatest jazz instructor maybe of the 20th century. I have here my book of transcriptions of jazz piano and guitar that I review so I can learn to play better. And then I’m not out to just play virtuoso music. I want to play the blues. I want to play funk. I got a call from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_Power&quot;&gt;Tower of Power &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when Rocco was ailing so that I could fill in for them, but I was on the road so I couldn’t do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People are contacting me not so I can play solos. I don’t want to play solos except on my records. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I want to play bass and I can. And there’s nothing that I can’t do and I don’t say it from ego. There’s nothing I feel I can’t express in my English, but there’s a lot I can’t express in my Spanish.&lt;/span&gt; So, I’ve come to a level. Is there anything you can’t really express in English if you know your subject?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You’re not egotistical to say, “Well, no, I can tell you how I feel in my thoughts.” People can be happy if they’re conducting themselves well and learn well. So, we’re all in the same boat. There’s no difference between me, you, or anybody else, except that I learned better than most and because I did I have some thoughts that are kind of rare in this day and age. Hopefully I can share them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-1&quot;&gt;End of Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jeff-berlin/part-2&quot;&gt;Check out &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, where we get super-deep!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jeff-berlin/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gutbucket &quot;LUTON&quot;</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/https:/youtu.be/m4kzVy5SXW4</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/https:/youtu.be/m4kzVy5SXW4</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
