<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 17:33:05 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 17:33:05 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Growing Pains by Courtney Swain</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;growing-pains&quot;&gt;Growing Pains&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Growing Pains&lt;/em&gt; is a fantastic, beautiful, dark, intimate, exciting new EP from Courtney Swain. (If her name sounds familiar, it may be because &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/courtney-swain&quot;&gt;we interviewed her last year&lt;/a&gt;.) Each of the five tracks offers something new and beautiful. I absolutely love this record. It’s moved me to tears on multiple occasions and it’s a quick 24-minute listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s also available for just $5 as a &lt;a href=&quot;http://courtneyswain.bandcamp.com/album/growing-pains&quot;&gt;digital download on her Bandcamp page&lt;/a&gt;. Do yourself a favor and buy this record. This is art as music, folks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved it so much I asked Courtney to do a conversation about it shortly after I’d listened to it on repeat 8-10 times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SBW5DMA1rvU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/courtney-swain/courtney-swain-growing-pains.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/courtney-swain/courtney-swain-growing-pains.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcription&quot;&gt;Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Courtney Swain is the singer of the band &lt;a href=&quot;http://bentkneemusic.com&quot;&gt;Bent Knee&lt;/a&gt;, a very interesting rock band based in Boston. Courtney and the band have just returned from a European tour. Courtney, how did all of that go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Oh, it was amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Awkward pause.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I wasn’t sure if you wanted me to say more! No, it was just amazing. That’s all I want to say. It was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. And Courtney, you’ve got a relatively new solo album out called Growing Pains that I’m several months late to, but I don’t feel so bad because I know that you’ve mentioned before that there’s no press after an album is released, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so here we are. Tell us about the album Growing Pains, when did it come out, and tell us a little about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Sure yeah. So, I put Growing Pains out in November of 2017 and it was something that–it was a collection of five songs that I was working on at the beginning of 2017. So right about a little over a year ago. And actually, literally last year at this time, I was doing a residency. I was awarded a grant to basically have two weeks to myself and I applied with this project where I wanted to write an album that was very much on my laptop and sort of an in-the-box kind of thing. I knew I was going to write a bunch of music there, so before I did that I wanted to get all of these piano songs in my head out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The way I write, I tend to have sets of songs that are very much piano-centric and then I have songs that are way more beeps and bloops kind of I-wrote-it-on-my-laptop types of songs. Growing Pains is the piano songs and I took the album on my first solo tour in December–last December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/p91IkLPKgIw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I, for some reason, had not realized that all the songs are kind of connected. They’re all growing pains of some sort and I was completely oblivious when I named the album Growing Pains. It’s just a line in one of the songs that I liked. But yes, it’s kind of a dark album, it’s kind of painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;After I recorded it, I put it away for a while and I was so busy with the Bent Knee release for Land Animal that I didn’t listen to it at all. After about seven or eight months, after the studio date, I went back and listened to it and I listened to the songs in succession. When I got to the last song, I was just crying uncontrollably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s rare that I’ve had such a breakdown in my life like that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It really struck me how much the music meant to me. It seemed way too personal for it to be relevant to anybody else&lt;/span&gt;, so I hesitated in whether I should put it out or not, but I tried to stick with that gut feeling that I had that made me so emotional and I thought that there’s something to that that I wanted to share with the people who listen to my stuff. So yeah, that’s the story behind that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I am so happy you did because–what an amazing piece of music. Every song that went by, I was like, “This is my favorite song on the album,” and then the next one was like, “Oh my goodness! This is even better than the last one!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And that last one–Prickly Rose, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Prickly Thorn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, Prickly Thorn–Oh my goodness. It’s, like, darkness, and the vocals and the string arrangements. It’s just incredible. What a body of work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The fact that it’s only 24 minutes long is like–you just want to put it on again right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Awesome, awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah. It’s really great. So tell us about the string arrangements and the production of the album. I was really impressed beyond just your capabilities. The whole production, I think, is just a perfect piece of work. So, tell us about the production of it, the arrangements, and all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Well thank you, first of all. I really appreciate that. The production was masterminded yet again by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bentkneemusic.com/about/&quot;&gt;Vince Welch&lt;/a&gt;, who does all the Bent Knee stuff and so far has done most of my work, too. We found this wonderful studio in Lincoln, Rhode Island. We live in Providence, but Lincoln’s about 20 minutes away. We heard about it through friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The guy who runs it is this wonderful person about our age. He’s just the most fun and patient engineer that I’ve ever worked with. His name is Brad. The space is really neat. It’s a huge room. It’s one of those repurposed warehouses, so the live room is massive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a couple different pianos there and when we showed up to record, Brad was really excited because he just had a bunch of his pianos tuned. I think we ended up using two different pianos on the album. There is an upright and then there is a grand. One of the funny stories was that we recorded it in January and the room being so big, in order to heat it, he had to turn on this big Reznor heating apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Between takes, the temperature kind of dropped, so as the day progressed, the pianos would gradually go in and out of tune. A lot of times when I show up to a piano, people are like, “Oh my God, is the tuning okay?” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m actually one to be really excited for pianos that are out of tune, unless they’re unplayable. But, I have a pretty broad palate in terms of quirkiness and tuning. So that was pretty exciting for me.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The string arrangements were something I worked on the previous few weeks before I came into that. The string players that we worked with were all our friends. Most of them have played on at least one or two Bent Knee albums as well and I brought them in because I wanted to work with sort of a female/femme energy. They were all sorts of women and so it was kind of fun being in the live room. We were just having a ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of times, I end up hanging out with a lot of guys in my profession, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there is also something special to having an environment like that that’s filled with women.&lt;/span&gt; I can’t really explain it. But, yeah, I thought they just played their hearts and souls into it and it was really emotional the entire time we were tracking. We did most of it in one day, so I got there early and I did scratch–I did keeper piano takes and scratch vocals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Oops! Sorry my cat wants to say hi. “Hello everybody.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6W8rvEAJILk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This was the first time I tracked the piano and the singing separately. I think originally we were talking about doing it together, but I was really interested in having a really intimate and really raw kind of vocal sound. When I’m playing piano while I’m singing, I tend to get carried away by the piano or I tend to compete with the loudness of the piano. I can’t get as quiet or intimate as I want to, so that was the idea behind that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I showed up early in the day, tracked the piano, did a scratch vocal take, and then the string players showed up around noon or 1 and they just played until 6 or 7. I think we mostly went in order of the songs. There’s only four of the five songs that have strings, so we just went in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At the end of the last song–all four of them have are really wonderful singers on top of wonderful instrumentalists and I think we were trying to explain or try to figure out how the parts were working or something. Then I realized, everybody was singing their parts and it just sounded gorgeous in this massive room, so I was like, “Wait, why don’t we just do that? Can we just have that at the end where we have this wonderful choir?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s how the ending came together. I ended up having to go in for an extra half day to track vocals and the studio, the big nice studio. But that was it, so it was a very minimal production and then Vince did his magic and we had it mastered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.berklee.edu/people/randy-roos&quot;&gt;Randy [Roos]&lt;/a&gt;, who again does a lot of our stuff. It’s kind of the same crew, different approach. But, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I just absolutely love it and it’s such a, as you said, an intimate album. There were times where I was listening where I almost felt guilty listening, hearing too much about your life or something. I was like, “No, that’s exactly what this is about.” It’s a stunning release of emotions. The music just so perfectly supports it. I thought–I wanted to hear a little bit about how you wrote these songs because they don’t really follow the traditional structure, as far as I could tell at least. You’re not “verse chorus verse chorus bridge” happening in the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you talk about how you explore songwriting and how these songs came to be from a compositional standpoint?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah, of course. I think these songs sort of came at the end of my maximalist writing interests. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Right now, I’m very interested in minimalist writing, by which I mean I am trying to get more out of the same chord progressions, but making that feel different by timbre and texture.&lt;/span&gt; For me, in my writing, which is the case for Growing Pains too, when I switch a section, I have to change the accompaniment completely too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But I’ve noticed that in a lot of music, people approach it a lot more economically. Even if the chords are the same, they can actually change the feel by adding different instruments or changing a texture or changing the vocal line. That’s what I’m interested in now, but at the time when I wrote Growing Pains, it was just sort of–I think it’s kind of almost a contemporary classical kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Prickly Thorn is the last song I wrote on the album. Again, the way the album is structured, there’s gradually more strings as the songs progress, and also the order of the songs are roughly in the order they were written, too. I listened to Joni Mitchell’s Blue really recently, I’m ashamed to admit. I was like, “Oh yeah. This is what I want to do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve listened to a fair amount of Joni Mitchell. I’m no Joni Mitchell expert, but actually a funny story. Bent Knee did a Halloween show once where we covered Joni Mitchell exclusively. I might have told you this. A Joni Mitchell Halloween. So, I know of her music and I love Hejira, so I think that was a big influence that I was pulling from for Growing Pains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Compositionally, yeah, I do like to stray away from the “verse chorus verse chorus” thing, but it’s not always a conscious thing.&lt;/span&gt; I think in my own writing, and also in Bent Knee, what’s happening is that we tend to have extended and very complicated bridge sections, so what you would call a C section–because it’s usually A B A B C B, right? Verse chorus verse chorus bridge chorus. The bridge is always complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s the case in the first song, the second song also has a weird bridge, the third song also has a weird bridge, the fourth song is a little bit different. It’s just more of an extended chorus-y bridge. The fifth song, Prickly Thorn, is just–it’s craziness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I did a really cool session in Brooklyn where there’s a guy who has an old direct 2-mix to vinyl machine. You just play in the studio–actually it’s not even a 2-mix, it’s a mono. It’s a tiny room and he cuts it directly to a 7-inch, so if you want to make five 7-inches, you have to play the song five times. Every one is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, we were prepping for the session, and I’d asked &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chrisbaummusic.com/&quot;&gt;Chris Baum&lt;/a&gt;, Bent Knee’s violin player, to play with me. We were talking about Prickly Thorn and I was trying to write down a form for him so that it would be easier to follow because we just had one rehearsal. Chris is just a genius at going with the flow in terms of improvising and playing his beautiful–so I was like, “Okay Chris, there’s A… B… A B C A… D.” I was just going, “Oh my God, this makes no sense. This is so not helpful.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YNuoBoPL2Gw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know how I ended up at that, but I remember sort of cutting sections and pasting sections and being, “Well this feels too long. This feels too short.” And it somehow ended up like that. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So how was the touring experience? These vocal performances are really raw and very powerful. Was that an emotional experience for you? Did you go deeper in as you toured or did it become more casual, like “yeah I can do this?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I think a little bit of both. It was kind of nice not to–to do a tour by myself. It affirmed something–a thought I’ve had for a long time about how taxing Bent Knee is on my voice because I can–if I’m singing by myself, I’m not competing with that much sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I’m on a Bent Knee tour, I don’t drink at night. I’m basically chugging water all day every day. On a solo tour, it was like, “Oh, I can have a drink once in a while!” It was really nice. But in terms of the delivery, I really loved doing that tour for a lot of reasons. I did it with my college freshman year roommate, who’s a singer-songwriter in LA. So, I kept joking about how, worst case this is just going to be a girl’s road trip and best case it’s going to be a couple of shows that are great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I had this, for me, really profound realization where I gained a lot of confidence in what I was doing. In the beginning I would go into these shows and I felt like I had something to prove.&lt;/span&gt; And before the tour, I had a couple of these shows and I would listen back to the audio and I would just feel kind of unsatisfied. I couldn’t understand why because in terms of the accuracy of the performance, it was good. The tempos were good, the notes were right, but it just didn’t feel quite right and I realized that I was leaning too far into it. I had to come out of it a little bit and let the music breathe and be myself instead of trying to push. I think it’s something that I’ve heard people talk about a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I took this really expensive vocal lesson a couple years ago because I was having a hard time managing my voice in certain rough sections of Bent Knee. The guy was like, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“You have to create the sound of you going all in, but you can’t actually be going all in.”&lt;/span&gt; It was kind of like I finally understood what all that meant because when I did get really emotional, and when your brain is 100% AAAUUUGGGHHHH, I didn’t sound the way I wanted it to sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I learned to sort of perform, draw this line in my performance where I saw it as this thing. It wasn’t less satisfying in any way. It was more satisfying, ultimately, because I knew I was coming across the right way. But I also learned a lot about stage presence and anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s not a lot of points in Bent Knee’s live set where we talk. We normally don’t really talk that much because we do seamless transitions between songs and we usually say hi once during the set, but I found out that that didn’t really work when it was just me and the piano and a solo set. I had to talk in between stuff and I realized that had this anxiety, or this nervousness that was selfish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was ratcheting myself up to be anxious, so when I’d talk, I’d be like, “Umm, thank you for coming.” I’d talk really fast and really intense. I just realized, “This is not doing anybody a service. It’s not doing me a service. It’s not doing anybody who’s watching–to have fun.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So I learned that I just have to be confident in that I have something to say that’s worth listening to.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I started talking slower and I started talking more at my normal talking volume. I realized it was just a way better way to communicate. So, I started introducing each song before I would play it because I found that when I would not introduce all the songs, when I would finish my set, people would come up to me and they would tell me that their favorite song was the one that I introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It wasn’t always the same song. It was whatever song I introduced and I gave a background to, people seemed to enjoy it more. So I was like, “Okay, well, if that’s a thing, I should just do it for all my songs.” It was a real growing process for me where I had to commit to doing thing instead of–you know how when somebody’s really good at something, sometimes they’re bad at taking a compliment? I think I was that way for a really long time. This was something where I realized: me not being able to take that compliment was actually harming my art more than doing it a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Have you heard of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&quot;&gt;imposter syndrome&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: No. Oh yeah! I think my therapist told me about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, yeah. That reminds me of that. It’s a real personal struggle that talented people have to overcome and I think what you’re talking about is basically that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah. It was a really amazing experience. Night after night, doing the same thing. It really makes you evaluate how you can do better, because otherwise it’s just not fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So I sent the album to a friend of mine and he fell in love with it instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Oh, awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He said, “She’s gotta know about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryuichi_Sakamoto&quot;&gt;Ryuichi Sakamoto&lt;/a&gt;.” Do you know him?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LGs_vGt0MY8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah yeah yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, okay. Does he have any sort of influence or bearing on what you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: No! No, I know of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Only because I’m half Japanese, but I think in a way, probably. I’m working on this project where–well, I’ve had a couple of projects recently where I’ve been asked to introduce my tracks and what influenced me. They are completely obscure to a lot of western listeners because they’re basically J-pop tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I think Ryuichi Sakamoto is a fixture in Japanese music, so I think a lot of J-pop and Japanese music that I was listening to growing up takes from that. I think I’m kind of in the line of his music, even if I don’t have a direct correlation to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay. And this summer, you and Bent Knee will be on tour. Can you share a little bit? Do a little Bent Knee promo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah! So we’re going on the Paper Earth tour. We’re starting the last week of May, right after the week of Memorial Day. We’ll be going clockwise this year. We normally go counter-clockwise. So, all around America. I’m really excited this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9u8HvvTaLNU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We’re going out with this band called &lt;a href=&quot;https://gatherersband.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Gatherers&lt;/a&gt;. They’re on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.equalvision.com/&quot;&gt;Equal Vision&lt;/a&gt; and they have a new album coming out that hasn’t been announced yet. They’re really, really fun folks. They stayed at my house once and I’m really good friends with the guitar player, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This is our first summer where we’re doing our entire long-ass tour with other people. So, it’ll be interesting. I’m sure there will be real highs and real lows as there is to every long tour. We’re really excited. We’ve been writing some new music in the studio, so we might be playing some of that out and we also just premiered a piece that we wrote for Bent Knee and a percussion ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That half an hour sort-of-through-composed piece is called Paper Earth, which is where the name of the tour came from. We haven’t figured out if we’re going to play any of the snippets or the small song kind of things of Paper Earth as part of the tour. I think it’s quite possible that, yeah–every year we do this. It’s something I really look forward to in my life. I’m excited to go out on tour again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, and you guys are coming to Phoenix in June. I actually rearranged my vacation schedule so I could make the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Ohhh, my gooooosh. Yessss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so we will be there and I’m super excited to finally see you guys live. So, that’ll be awesome. All right, for people who want to find out more and to support you in the best ways possible, can you share where to get that information and what they can do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Yeah! I’m really easy to find online as well as is the band. I’m also starting a Patreon. I don’t know if I’ll have it booted by the time this interview comes out or not, but it’ll just be at &lt;a href=&quot;https://patreon.com/courtneyswain&quot;&gt;Patreon.com/CourtneySwain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Tah5q89iNcg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that’s a place if you want where you can pledge a monthly amount and get access to, basically, my blog. That’s a short way of talking about it. I was having a conversation with Bent Knee’s guitar player, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/ben-levin&quot;&gt;Ben [Levin]&lt;/a&gt;, last night. We were talking about how, for a long time, we’ve drawn this line between the band and us as people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For example, Ben’s drawn this line between his incredibly successful YouTube channel and the band. For me, I’ve always felt like a “meh” moment when people call me “Courtney Swain of Bent Knee” instead of just “Courtney Swain.” We were sort of agreeing about how that’s not the point anymore and it’s just about all of us doing all of this together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So anyway, long story short, it would be a place for what I’m doing, but also a lot of my point of view of what we’re doing in Bent Knee. I’m hoping to talk about my keyboard parts in Bent Knee, the story behind the songs, whether it be Bent Knee stuff or my stuff. I’m going to do a book club where we’ll just be listening to an album every two weeks and we’ll hang out and talk about it. It’ll be kind of a fun place to hang out, if anybody’s interested. Otherwise, I’m also available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://courtneyswain.com&quot;&gt;CourtneySwain.com&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://bentkneemusic.com&quot;&gt;BentKneeMusic.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you have any physical copies of the Growing Pains album left?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I do! Yeah, I have some left. I pressed them at a local letterpressing company, so they’re beautifully pressed. It’s a limited run. I always do limited runs for a lot of stuff, like a lot of the first edition Bent Knee stuff for the first and second album, we had limited runs. And I’m hoping one of these days that they’ll hold value and someday I will find out. I don’t know how many more years it’s gonna take, but I’m gonna hang onto those copies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, save me a couple. I’m definitely going to buy some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: I certainly will. I certainly will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool. Thank you so much, Courtney. I really appreciate you taking the time to talk about your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CS: Thank you, Anthony. It’s always a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/courtney-swain/growing-pains</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/courtney-swain/growing-pains</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aaron Comess</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Aaron Comess is a genre-busting musician who plays in several bands, has a diverse catalog of solo albums, and has played on over 100 albums for dozens of different artists. His new album, &lt;em&gt;Sculptures&lt;/em&gt;, is a fantastic foray into electronic and ambient jazz. There’s tons of great rhythmic stuff going on throughout the album. There are some great melodies. There are pretty sections, goofy sections, ugly sections. The album has everything. Even my wife likes a bunch of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/59u88cOJxiI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/aaron-comess/aaron-comess.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/aaron-comess/aaron-comess.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Aaron Comess is a drummer based in Brooklyn, New York and he is most notably known for his work with the rock band, the Spin Doctors, which have been active for how many years now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Believe it or not, it’s gonna be 30 years this October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh my goodness, 30 years! And believe it or not, Turn It Upside Down by the Spin Doctors was the first CD I ever bought with my own money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Well thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, yeah! I fell in love with the album previous to that, I can’t remember the name right now. Krypto–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pocket_Full_of_Kryptonite&quot;&gt;Pocket Full of Kryptonite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wsdy_rct6uo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Pocket Full of Kryptonite. Yeah. I listened to that over and over and over, so when I had money–I got that BMG membership. You know, the 10 CDs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Oh yeah. That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So I got Turn It Upside Down. That was the one that I bought for $18 or something at the time. But anyway–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: That’s cool. That’s great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Enough about me! [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Well thank you. Thanks for buying it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, sure. So, yeah, Aaron–why don’t you talk about what you’ve done, not only with the Spin Doctors, but you’ve had a long career. You’ve been playing drums as a musician for 30 years now–beyond 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m sure most of us don’t know what you’re doing outside the Spin Doctors. So, let’s talk about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Well, okay. There’s been a lot of different things over the years. I grew up in Dallas, Texas and I started out playing out of books like this, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/14-Modern-Contest-Solos-Snare/dp/0769228232&quot;&gt;rudimentary drumming&lt;/a&gt;. My first teachers taught me how to hold my sticks like this. That’s why I play traditional because basically day one, I walked in there and he said, “Hold this one like a hammer.” That was easy. And then when he showed me this, I was nine years old and it just feels totally weird. But I stuck with it and I love it and that’s the only reason that I play traditional grip, really, is because my very first teacher, Jack Iden, that’s how he showed me to hold the sticks. And I like it. I’m glad that I do it because so many of my favorite drummers play that way. I like the way it looks, I like the way it feels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, growing up in Dallas, I had a lot of great teachers there. I was really lucky to have a really good music program going on in the Dallas school district back then. I went to a really great high school called the Arts Magnum High School. Half the day I was playing big band, small group, music theory, and it was great. I had this whole collective of friends in Dallas. I still do. Great musicians. We would basically jam after school and jam on the weekends and there is just a ton of great musicians down there. All kinds of people who’ve gone on to do tons of great stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mgtpZxKPZLc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, so then I moved up to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berklee_College_of_Music&quot;&gt;Berklee&lt;/a&gt;, did a year at Berklee, which was great. That was the year I practiced ten hours a day and just lived in the practice room. It really did a lot for me. I really developed good discipline for practice, which has stuck with me to this day. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think practice is a really important thing and it’s good to have some discipline and have a routine with it. I always practiced, even in high school, I studied and took lessons and worked really hard.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But it was that year that I think things really changed because it’s the beauty of going away to college and graduating high school and having that opportunity to not have to work a real job and just focus. Live and breathe the stuff. It really can change–I think you can change the way you play. Anything that you put a ton of time into, you can see massive changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That one year at Berklee was the year that I think I really got my stuff together. A lot. It changed the way I played. I moved back to Dallas for a year and played in a bunch of different bands. I played pretty much every gig under the sun. From jazz bands, rock bands, blues bands, wedding gigs, you name it, I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I decided I wanted to move to New York. I always knew that I either wanted to be in LA or New York. I was kind of attracted to New York. I liked the vibe here. A lot of the records I grew up listening to, particularly the jazz records, I’d look on it and see so much of the stuff was going on here. I’d been here a few times from when I went to Berklee. I’d take a bus down and check out the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, I heard about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/School_of_Jazz_(The_New_School)&quot;&gt;The New School&lt;/a&gt;. Actually, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy_Hargrove&quot;&gt;Roy Hargrove&lt;/a&gt;, the trumpet player. I went to high school with Roy. In that year that I was back in town between Berklee and New York, we did a lot of gigs together. We were driving up to Denver to a gig one night and he handed me the–I was telling him I was thinking about going to New York City and he handed me this pamphlet. He was like, “Man, I heard about this place, The New School. They’re starting a jazz program there.” So that’s how I heard about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I came up here and auditioned and this great, great saxophone player and teacher named &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnie_Lawrence&quot;&gt;Arnie Lawrence&lt;/a&gt; was the head of the school. I auditioned for him and it was a great audition. I basically did the playing part of it, everything was cool. Then he said, “Okay, cool. Come on up to my office for the interview section.” So he looks me in the eye and said, “You really want to deal with this bullshit?” And I said, “Yep.” He said, “You’re in the school.” It was great, you know? Of course, I had no idea what he was talking about. I was 19 years old, you know? Of course, now I get it. But anyway, it was great. I moved up to New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xb1e3EyVMtA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This guy was incredible. He was a real mentor. I turned out doing a lot of gigs with Arnie and once the Spin Doctors got together, he would play a lot of shows with us. Anyway, at the time, it was just a great group of people at The New School. I met the guys in The Spin Doctors there, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spin_Doctors&quot;&gt;Eric [Schenkman]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Barron&quot;&gt;Chris [Barron]&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Popper&quot;&gt;John Popper&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blues_Traveler&quot;&gt;Blues Traveler&lt;/a&gt; was there. And then you had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brad_Mehldau&quot;&gt;Brad Mehldau&lt;/a&gt; was there, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry_Goldings&quot;&gt;Larry Goldings&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Bernstein_(guitarist)&quot;&gt;Peter Bernstein&lt;/a&gt;, and just a ton of incredible musicians. So many of them have gone on to do great stuff and are active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was just a really cool environment and there was none of this–we were the rock band in school. I was playing jazz, too. I was always doing all the jazz stuff, but I was also in this rock band. We were gigging around town and we’d rehearse up at the school. Then you often find in the jazz school world that people are very snobbish and the jazzers don’t want to hang out with the rock guys and the rock guys don’t want to hang out with the jazz guys. You felt a little bit of that at Berklee, although I was also the guy at Berklee that was–I’d be doing a jazz session, a blues session, a heavy metal session. This was 1986 when I went there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I always just ignored all that stuff. I was like, “Listen, I’m into everything. I’m going to do everything. If you don’t like it, I don’t care. This is who I am.”&lt;/span&gt; But I found in the New School, everybody there was just so open-minded. Brad Mehldau, he would come out to our gigs and I remember him saying how much he liked &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Allman_Brothers_Band&quot;&gt;The Allman Brothers&lt;/a&gt; and he dug our band. Same thing with Peter Bernstein and Larry Goldings. It was just a great environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, to make a long story short, we started playing all over New York. We took kind of the opposite approach to most bands at the time, which was everybody wanted to get a record deal. Everybody would rehearse five nights a week and try to get a big showcase and get a record deal. That was the goal. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;For us, we just totally flipped it. Our goal was we wanted to write songs, we wanted to be a really great band, we wanted to be unique and do our own thing and we wanted to get gigs and pay our rent playing our own music. That was pretty much it. So we decided, rather than rehearsing five nights a week, let’s try to play five nights a week.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We just played everywhere in New York. We used to call it “the tour of Manhattan.” We just gigged and gigged and gigged. There was a lot of different clubs we could play at. We kind of had our core spots. We were always trying different places. Everybody was like, “There’s all these rules,” which they still have. Like, “If you play here, you can’t play anywhere in town for two weeks beforehand.” We were like, “Okay.” And we would be playing down the street the next night. It’s ridiculous. How are we supposed to make a living playing one [place]?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We just ignored all that and the cool thing is because we were doing it so much, a couple things happened. For one, it was the greatest way to develop our sound and our music because, let’s face it, nothing beats playing in a group in front of people. Rehearsing is great, and that’s key as well, practice is great, but there’s something that happens when you’re actually on stage in front of an audience. It doesn’t happen in the rehearsal room.&lt;/span&gt; And so we really developed our sound fully from just playing night after night and we would play three hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It wasn’t like now where you get a 45-minute set. We played places where we could play the whole night. We would do–we might do a set–we played this place called The Nightingale Bar on 2nd Ave, it was kind of our home turf. We’d go on at 10, we played til 11:30 or 12, we’d take a break, and then we’d play til 2. Sometimes we’d do a third set. On weekends, we’d do the classic third set and we’d play until 4 in the morning. We’d literally play five-hour gigs. It was great. We got really good doing that and we developed a voice of our own. Our own sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MtFEgnSnBG8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As a drummer, it was a great opportunity to be in my own creative band where we could pretty much do what we wanted to do and kind of develop my own sound. So that was great. Through that we, just based on getting a big fan-base, the record companies started coming and we got a record deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, so based on just the constant gigging, we built up a really big fanbase in town. Eventually it just became this undeniable thing. Management and record companies started approaching us. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We were very standoffish because we were a very self-sufficient band and we didn’t want anybody to come in and fuck with us.&lt;/span&gt; Eventually, we found a manager we liked and he got us a record deal and blah blah blah. Went on, obviously. It took a long time. We did a live record, we put out the first record to really–kind of silence. But we kept touring and kept touring and eventually sparked some interest about a year and a half in. And then things kind of blew up and went where they went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, you were totally in the right place at the right time. It’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Yeah, it was a good time. That era was a good time for bands and for the music business. It was really thriving. CDs were only three or four years old, so the record companies had a ton of money because they were selling cassettes, CDs, they were still selling vinyl. People were going back and buying their favorite records from the old days on CD again. So, as hard as it was, and it was really hard, there was that opportunity if you could get to that point where you could get that support. We had to really fight for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Our record company was not really behind us at all. They did pretty much nothing&lt;/span&gt; and–in fact, after about a year, they were like, “Come back. This record’s dead. Make a new record.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We were like, “Listen, we’re out here on the road with absolutely no help from you. We’re making a living. We’re packing clubs around the country. 400-500 people are coming out. There’s a buzz.”&lt;/span&gt; So we decided to just go back out on the road and push it. We had this weird feeling. We could feel something was brewing. And that’s what we did. And a spark came out and the record company decided, “Okay, this is worth it.” They put some money behind it and boom. You know? So, anyway, that was cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e86omL8uzks?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;To go back to your original question, from there that pretty much took me through most of the 90s with The Spin Doctors. I’d come to town and I’d do gigs around town. I’d always do jazz gigs and blues gigs and stuff like that when I was in town with people, but for the most part, The Spin Doctors took up pretty much all of my time in the 90s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Once we got to the end of the 90s, the record sales declined, we weren’t that hot Top 10 band anymore. At that point, our guitar player wasn’t with us anymore. It just felt kind of like it’s a good time to give it a little break for a while and give us the opportunity individually to kind of do some other stuff, which we all wanted to do. So I started to get into–I built a studio in my apartment and I started to get into producing and I started to get into playing on other people’s record and I really wanted to put myself out there as a guy that can do sessions and play with other people as a side man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s something I always–growing up, I was just as interested in being a jazz guy as I was being a studio guy as I was being in a rock band. When I came here, all those three things were kind of–I wanted to do them. I wanted to be prepared for whatever opportunity came to me. I made a decision after being in The Spin Doctors for a while, “This seems pretty cool. I’m going to give this a year or two and see.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I found it’s smart in your career, sometimes you’ve got to make the right decision if you feel like something’s a good opportunity and it’s working for you creatively, which is the most important thing to go for.&lt;/span&gt; So I made that decision with The Spin Doctors and obviously it worked out great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So here we are at the end of the 90s and we’re kind of not really split up, but we’re not active for a while. It was great, but I had to prove myself to a lot of people. I already had a good reputation as a drummer around New York, but I think people thought of me as, “Oh yeah, he’s in that band.” A lot of different things. Like, “He sounds great with them, but maybe he can’t do this.” I had a lot people telling me they thought I’d charge too much money. “He’s in this popular band. We can’t afford him.” All kinds of silly stuff. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I can’t tell you how many times I had people coming to me saying, “Man, we spent, like, 10 hours trying to get your snare sound. That sound you got on that record.” And I’m like, “Dude, just call me. It’s right here, you know? You can spend all day.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/srcmtEUBmE0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think there’s a lot of things that I had to get out there, like, one, I can play. I’m versatile. Two, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m not going to charge you a million bucks just because I come from a well-known band.&lt;/span&gt; Then it was great. It took a minute, to be honest, but after doing that, all of a sudden you get the reputation, “Okay well this guy can do this.” And here we are down the road where I’m very active as a side man, a session guy, and we got the band back together shortly after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Around 2001, we started to get the original guys back together. We started playing some gigs. It’s gotten back to the point where we’ve made three more record and we do probably 30-40 shows a year and it’s just great. The band sounds killer, everybody’s playing as good as ever. I think you saw us out in California, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: In Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Phoenix, right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You played at the Ostrich Festival here. That’s a weird thing that happens here, but I’d never actually–I grew up in New York and I remember hearing an interview with you on the radio and you said, “I’m really a jazz player playing in a rock band, but I like playing rock music.” Or something like that. And that stuck with me ever since I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Oh, that’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And then to hear, when I got to see you for the first time live last year at the Ostrich Festival, I couldn’t believe how good you guys were. Some other bands were playing and I was like, “Wow.” The Spin Doctors actually kept it together. Some of these other bands that played that’ve been around a long time, they were falling apart. And my friend, who has done some work for some of these bands, he’s like, “Spin Doctors killed it.” You guys were really–you guys were on top of it. It was an awesome show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Thank you. That’s why I still love doing the band. For one, it’s all four original members. There’s not a lot of bands that still have that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;All four of us are lifers. Everybody’s completely dedicated to their craft. People practice, they’re busy, and when we get together, there’s a sound. We don’t fuck around, as you can see. We get up there and we play. We don’t get up there, we’re not just up there trying to get paid. If you come see us, we’re going to do it. If that wasn’t the vibe, I wouldn’t even think about doing it anymore because I see a lot of these bands you’re talking about and it’s one guy left in the band or something.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A bunch of side guys and they’re just going through the motions. There’s a lot of great bands. Listen, I realize that it’s hard to keep a band together. And a lot of them sound great, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you definitely see the bands that are just out there to collect a check. I get it. You gotta make a living, but for me I can’t–sure I gotta make a living too. I’m not going to do something that doesn’t feel–for me it’s gotta feel good and creative and I’m getting satisfaction out of it or I’ll just get depressed. I can’t do that kind of thing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, well one way I can tell is having followed you on Instagram for a while, I’ve seen you post this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Stick-Control-George-Lawrence-Stone/dp/1892764040&quot;&gt;Stick Control book&lt;/a&gt; and videos of you using a metronome, hitting your practice pad, and I was like, “Wow that’s really cool. This guy who’s been playing probably 40 years has kept up a practice regimen and that’s been important to him.” Yeah actually, why don’t you…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qFnlwYt8w1Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: I got my books right here. You’re absolutely right. I appreciate that. Listen, I started taking lessons again five years ago from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Carvin&quot;&gt;Michael Carvin&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s very important, the older you get and the more that you’re busy, it’s very easy to–you gotta do things so you don’t get into a rut.&lt;/span&gt; To me, it’s just a neverending kind of thing. To continue to get better and expand the way I play and how my style–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t want to play the same way I played 20 years ago now, or 10 years ago.&lt;/span&gt; The cool thing is you’ve got all that stuff. I got all the things I’ve done and all the styles and my own little language, but you don’t want to just stop. Like, “Okay, well that’s what I do.” You want to do all that, but the idea is to keep adding to it. I’ve been really focused on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As far as practicing, I always have my trusty Reflexx pad here in my kitchen and I have all my books. A bunch of books I love to go through. This is one that I–I got them dated. This is crazy. I used to do this shit–look at this. This is my old–May ‘83. And I opened these books a while ago and I’m like, “Holy shit.” I don’t even know how I did it back then, but it’s been cool to go back to them and go through these things. I make a point to go through this stuff. Here, I’ll give you a little taste of this one here. This one here. This is great. I’m sitting down so it’ll be kind of weird. [Plays]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, it’s great. And I love just doing it every day. I try to spend some time out of these books. Concert snare drum reading. And then I got–where’s the other one here? Well of course, my favorite is syncopation. A million ways to do syncopation. I go through that every day. You know, there’s just tons of–where’s my other favorite? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Portraits-Rhythm-Studies-Snare-Drum/dp/0769214398&quot;&gt;Portraits of Rhythm&lt;/a&gt;. This is the one that I love. Old rudiment–It’s like a rudimentary. Yeah, so anyway, I try to spend a little bit of time every day on the practice pad doing rudiments and reading. I find that it really helps me to focus. And I forgot–I should put this one on. I love this thing. This little &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dr._Beat&quot;&gt;Dr. Beat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OLIs6ta8n78?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, how old is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Well, I used to have one of these when I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: They keep breaking and I just keep buying them on eBay. This is probably the tenth one I bought. Whenever one of them breaks, I just go on eBay and I find that they’re out there and I buy them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Your apartment is sinking again. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Oh I’m sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: I don’t know. There’s something about it. Maybe it reminded me of when I was 12 practicing, but just for at home practice, I just love it. So I always do a little, even if it’s 10 minutes. I walk past this thing every day. Even if I just sit there and do that. And then I like to do–I try to, depending on my schedule–I have a recording studio and my drums are always set up and if I’m free and there’s not a session in there, then I try to go in and practice. I’ve been really into that lately. And I’ve been getting back into all kinds of crazy books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a million ways to do syncopation. I recently went back in this book that I did when I was, like, 20 by a guy named &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Magadini&quot;&gt;Pete Magadini&lt;/a&gt;. The original book is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Poly-Cymbal-Time-Peter-Magadini/dp/B072JN3RW5&quot;&gt;Poly-Cymbal Time&lt;/a&gt; and I think now it’s reissued as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Polyrhythms-Drumset-Book-Peter-Magadini/dp/089724821X&quot;&gt;Polyrhythms for the Drumset&lt;/a&gt;, I think. This is an amazing book and it really opened–I’m really into–if you listen to my music or come see my own band live, I do a lot of weird rhythmical stuff. I’ve always been really into that. This was the book that really opened my eyes to that. It’s very much metric modulation, four-way independence, but with doing things with the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zrJFMAh-WaI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I went back through this book and I was like, “Wow.” It took me a minute. You gotta really–it’s fun. When you practice, I like to work on stuff that I can’t do. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I always think, “If you sound like shit when you’re practicing, then you’re making progress.” If you’re in there and you’re just sounding great–I mean, anybody can go in… I can play all my best stuff and feel like a million bucks, but I’ll save that for the gig. Know what I mean? That’s what you do when you’re at the gig.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But when you’re practicing, at least for me, I want to work on things that I really can’t do, like from a technical standpoint. Go in there and start something up that you can’t do. Sometimes it takes minute, but then an hour in, all of a sudden you’ve got it. Repetitive motion, you do it do it do it, then you’ve got it. And you can bust it out. It’s all about having these tools for when you’re improvising, they’re there for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that’s kind of my concept of practice. I like to divide it up between the snare drum reading stuff, warm-up, hands, and then do all kinds of different books and technical exercises with four-way independence and time. And then if I have time, I’ll spend some time–if there’s some ideas I’ve been working on, some of my own concepts with different beats or improvisation, but I find that the main thing that I do in the practice is work on technique stuff. Things that have been giving me a hard time or just things I can’t do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so what does an expert professional drummer like you do taking lessons? What are you focused on? For some people, including myself, I see a drummer like you, I listen to your new album, I’m like, “Man this guy’s incredible,” and then I think there’s this kind of mentality that once you’re a professional, you don’t need lessons anymore or something. What are you taking lessons on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Think about it. You often hear about actors going back and they’re always studying. No matter how old they are, you always hear, “I’m going to an acting class,” or, “I have an acting coach.” Many times you hear it with vocalists, too. “I was working on…” It’s an instrument. Basketball players, professional top-level guys, they’re in practice and there’s coaches. Somehow musicians think they can just get good and then they’re done. That’s okay, like anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LsrXPaaY3bA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You get very busy and I think for me I’m so lucky to have so many great teachers my whole youth up until my early 20s. I’ve always taken a lesson here or a lesson there from drummers. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;About five years ago, I felt like I needed a fresh kick in the ass.&lt;/span&gt; I’d been so busy. When you get busy running from gig to gig–I was doing so many gigs. Technique things, I was looking at my hands and like, “Wow, what the hell am I doing?” Not that I really care so much about technique. The main thing to me is I feel like you can do whatever you want to get the sound out of the drums, to express yourself, whatever it takes is fine. But, with that said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when I practice, I do like to focus on my technique. And when I get to the gig, whatever.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I’m in the studio recording or I’m on a gig making music, I don’t want to think about anything. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t want to think about what I practiced, I don’t want to think about my hands. It’s all about making music.&lt;/span&gt; That’s the thing. But having that discipline in practice, it carries over. So I was feeling just kind of burnt out and I’m running around, like gig, gig, gig, gig. I felt like I wanted some kind of–it’d be great to take some lessons again. Let’s see what happens. Maybe I can kind of shape up some of this technique stuff, some of these bad habits I’m noticing. Maybe I can get some help to rein them in and let’s just see what happens. I don’t even know. I know how to work on my technique. I know what I need to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m good at picking up books. I’m smart about knowing, “This is what I need to work on. This is what I’m gonna do.” So I started asking around New York, tons of people. This is when I was 45. I’m going to be 50 in April. This was about 5 years ago or so. I started asking people, “Hey man, I really want to take lessons. Any suggestions?” And the guy’s name that kept coming up was Michael Carvin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Michael is a great, great teacher and an amazing drummer too. Incredible. He played with all kinds of people. If you go on YouTube and press in “Michael Carvin with Freddie Hubbard.” There’s this clip that’s just–he’s as good as anybody. He’s just incredible. But he’s also an incredible teacher. His name kept coming up so I was like, “Okay, I’ll give it a shot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2HT3wBgwCO8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://euphorianyc.com/&quot;&gt;Dave Sokol&lt;/a&gt;, who is the guy who runs this rehearsal studio called &lt;a href=&quot;https://euphorianyc.com/&quot;&gt;Euphoria Studios&lt;/a&gt;, which is kind of the best place in town, and Dave, who is a big fan of Carvin’s and had studied with him–he’s the guy who put me in touch with him and I just called him up and said, “Hey man.” He asked me, “What do you want to do? Why are you calling me?” I said, “Well you know, I’m in my mid-40s and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve been playing professionally for 25-30 years now and I just want to take things to the next level. I want to keep learning.” So he was like, “Well you’re really smart. That’s a good attitude.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we had a short little conversation and we went to the lesson. I met him at his place and I go in there and he’s known for ripping people apart on the first lesson. A lot of people don’t go back. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve talked to people that have gone to this guy and they were offended and, “I couldn’t believe the shit he said to me. I’ll never go back again.” But then the other 50% walk away and they’re just like, “This guy was unbelievable. He changed my life. He changed my playing. He changed my life and perspective.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So he definitely ripped me apart. I kind of expected it, but I wasn’t really sure. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He didn’t give a fuck that I was in The Spin Doctors, that I played on this record or that record. It doesn’t matter. He doesn’t care.&lt;/span&gt; At least then he didn’t. So the first lesson, he was just pretty much like, “You’ve got no sound.” He just beat me down. [Laughs.] I took it well and I was like, “Okay cool. Whatever. Great.” And I took it and I went back. And it ended up being this great thing. Now he’s got a lot of respect for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, if anything, he’s helped give me even more confidence, which is great. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You don’t want to go to a teacher and have him tell you you’re the greatest in the world from the get-go. You gotta get somewhere.&lt;/span&gt; But he’s been very good and I think he at first started out with some technique stuff. He got me back into going through syncopation and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Advanced-Techniques-Modern-Drummer-Independence/dp/0757995403&quot;&gt;the Chapin book&lt;/a&gt;. I went to the Chapin book again because I hadn’t in probably 25 years. You know the book I’m talking about? &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Chapin&quot;&gt;Jim Chapin&lt;/a&gt; book?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u_L--a3UCeA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: It’s kind of like one of the bibles for drum set. You should get it. You should definitely get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I only play drums recreationally, so yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Oh okay. Well there you go. Anybody listening, if you’re a drummer and you want to–it’s one of the books that’s kind of a must to go through. And I went through it really young. So, he got me to go back through some of these things that I hadn’t done in a while. That kind of inspired me to pull out all these old books that I showed you before. But the main thing he did was really help inspire me and help push me to do things that I hadn’t done. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He said, “You gotta try to get out of your comfort zone.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Obviously, we all know you can do this, you can do that, you got this gig, you got that gig. Everything’s cool, but let’s do something where you’re going to get out of your comfort zone. Let’s do something you’re not good at and you don’t feel comfortable with.” He was very encouraging to me. He was like, “You have a lot to offer. Why don’t you start doing some drum clinics?” I’d never done them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I always shied away from it because I didn’t want to get in front of a crowd of people and have to talk and have to do that. He really pushed that and at first, I was like, “I don’t know. That’s never been my thing.” But I took his advice and I did one, this was about five years ago. I think the first one I did was at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thecollective.edu/divisions/drummers-collective/&quot;&gt;The Drummer’s Collective&lt;/a&gt; and I just did another one last week. Since then I’ve done quite a few of them and I love it now. It was really–I think I learned a lot about it because, for one, when you have to sit there and talk about yourself or about music, especially &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when you have to demonstrate things, you learn a lot yourself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JbHsMosfxqE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The main thing, it was just an example of something that wasn’t necessarily in my comfort zone that I did. When you do that kind of stuff, it just opens up all kinds of other possibilities. I had already started making my own records and doing my own band, but I’ve obviously kept that going and done–I play regularly with my group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I have a couple of different groups that I do on my own. It’s really been great to–for all these years, Spin Doctors and playing on people’s records and playing with other artists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Osborne&quot;&gt;Joan Osborne&lt;/a&gt;. All these people, which I love doing, I love it, but to have your own group is kind of the ultimate thing. Something that represents me 100%. It’s my music. It’s my concept. I use players that I want to bring into that, that I work well with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s just been great. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s just been such a great creative outlet for me to make these records and do these shows.&lt;/span&gt; I don’t look at it as–for me, it’s just 100% creative. All the stuff I do is creative, but obviously as a career musician, obviously the reality is you gotta make money. You look in the different things that I have going now, it’s taken me a long time to get to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Luckily, 30 years into New York, I’ve got my band Spin Doctors, which are up and running very well these days. I’ve got my side-man stuff, working with people like Joan Osborne, I play with this great artist in Germany named &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marius_M%C3%BCller-Westernhagen&quot;&gt;Marius Westernhagen&lt;/a&gt;. He’s a big star over there. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Maddock&quot;&gt;James Maddock&lt;/a&gt; and a lot of the different groups that I play drums for and doing records with people. Having my studio. And then I’ve got my own music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And obviously these other things pay the bills. I usually lose money with my band. [Laughs.] But I don’t care. It’s part of the whole portfolio, as they say.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Some gigs you’re gonna make a lot of money, some gigs you’re gonna make a little money, and some gigs you might lose money. As long as it balances out, but it’s very important to–I think it’s always a bad idea to base all your decisions on money. I’ve always tried to base everything I do on creativity and being fulfilled. Any time I’ve ever taken something that felt like it was just for the money, I think it just never felt right.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5ftDRl4kNXI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the things that I’ve kind of–I’ve actually learned to say “no.” Drummers, musicians. We don’t know the word “no,” man. “Hey can you play Tuesday night?” “Okay!” I think for a while, when I first started seeing Carvin, I was just running around, I didn’t want to say “no” to anything. It was cool because we all want to be really busy and I’m really grateful. Sometimes, the more you’re out there, the more you stay busy, the more gigs you get, and that’s part of it. But it’s also important–you can also wake up, which is what happened to me, waking up overloaded. “Oh my God, I’ve got 10 sets of music I’ve gotta learn. I’ve got this gig…” It can get a little distracting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve realized I’ve learned how to say “no” to stuff. I really try to–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I realized “no” is not a bad word. It’s actually healthy. Don’t put yourself in a situation that’s going to run you down and it’s not going to really be creatively fulfilling for you. You don’t want to be out there playing stuff that’s not good, either, because people see that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So speaking of that, you have so much great music out there available for free on YouTube. Your performances at the Rockwood Music Hall with &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/teddy-kumpel&quot;&gt;Teddy [Kumpel]&lt;/a&gt; and I’ve seen gigs with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jojo_Mayer&quot;&gt;Jojo Mayer&lt;/a&gt;. You’ve got all-star lineups sometimes playing with you and your bands. I was wondering if you could get into some of that and how it’s led into your new album, Sculptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Yeah, absolutely. Basically, I started making my own records in 2006. My first record is a record called &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/catskills-cry/id187132927&quot;&gt;Catskills Cry&lt;/a&gt;. It’s me, I wrote all the music on guitar–a lot of what I write is on guitar. And I got Bill Dillon, who’s an amazing guitar player from Canada, who I met–he played on a lot of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robbie_Robertson&quot;&gt;Robbie Robertson&lt;/a&gt; records. He’s just got this vibe. I did a record with him in the late 90s with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc_Cohn&quot;&gt;Marc Cohn&lt;/a&gt; and I was like, “Who’s this guitar player?” I was like, “This guy’s unbelievable.” He just stuck with me, so about–whatever it was, 8-10 years later when I got around to doing my record, I was like, “I gotta call this guy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZUhKqirfnss?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I called up Bill and I was like, “Hey man, I want you to do this record with me.” So we worked it out. And then I had an idea to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin&lt;/a&gt; and Bill knew Tony and inside of about an hour, we had the whole thing. It was done. We had it booked. Bill hooked me up with an engineer in Woodstock named &lt;a href=&quot;http://romanklun.com/&quot;&gt;Roman Klun&lt;/a&gt;, who’s now my partner in my studio. We share a recording studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So it all led back to that record. And it’s a great record. I’ll always really love that record. It was the first one I did. We never did any gigs because everyone lived in different places. It was just a really cool vibey record. I owe a lot to those guys. It’s just great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was the beginning. And then a few years later when I decided to make my second record, which is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/beautiful-mistake/id436071053&quot;&gt;Beautiful Mistake&lt;/a&gt;, I’d always loved Teddy Kumpel. You know Teddy. Incredible musician, guitar player. We’ve done a lot of playing together over the years. I knew right away, “This is the guy I want to have play guitar on my record.” I also knew that I wanted to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://richard-hammond.com/&quot;&gt;Richard Hammond&lt;/a&gt; on bass, who’s another amazing bass player. Really good friend of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He is incredible. I listened to–it was a live album. I think it was a trio. You, Teddy, and Richard. I listened to that yesterday or the day before. I couldn’t believe Richard’s playing. He is such a melodic player and he fills in so much. I couldn’t believe it was a trio at times as I was listening to it. And Teddy is on another planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Teddy’s incredible. Yeah, Rich, we’ve done so much together. We both played in Joan Osborne’s band for 11-12 years together. We’ve done a ton of gigs. You’re lucky when you meet–every drummer and bass player, you always have a couple of bass players you just really gel with. Richard is just one of those guys. We get together, we don’t have to say a word to each other. It just happens, no matter what kind of music we’re playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ixwf6rH9tgM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I knew that I wanted to get Teddy and Richard together. I made demos. I wrote most of the songs on guitar, so I made demos and I sent it to those guys and I was like, “Listen, I want to make this record. Here’s the music.” We didn’t even rehearse. I was like, “Learn the music. This is the basic structure. These are the parts.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I felt kind of bad because, particularly on those record, it’s very guitar-oriented and there’s very specific parts on the melody sections, the heads of the songs, they’re very specific. And then there’s parts of the songs that are more open. I can’t thank Teddy enough for putting up with me. He did such an amazing job of learning the stuff that I wrote and making it his own, but totally respecting the parts. It was amazing. So, I told those guys, “Look we’re not going to rehearse. We’re doing two days, but you gotta do your homework. I want to come in–We’ve all played together, but this is a new band. I want it to sound like we’ve been playing together for five years.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Those guys did their homework. We just had a great session. Some really magical moments happened off the floor. When you get in the studio, you have an idea of what something is going to be. Like the song “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iBqSUZa5VMs&quot;&gt;Past, Present, &amp;amp; Future&lt;/a&gt;,” which is one of my favorite songs, it’s a song we play live a lot–when we got in there and started playing it, I had this kind of simple bass line and Rich came up with this thing and it just turned into this amazing moment. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Those are the things that make records so great. You come in prepared and you have an idea, but then something special happens off the cuff and then you grab it and work with it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iBqSUZa5VMs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, so after that record, that was the first time I started doing gigs. We did a record release show. All of a sudden, it was like, “Wow, I’ve got a band. We’ve got songs.” So we just started, ever since then. That trio has been playing maybe once a month or so around New York and we go out of town every once in a while. It’s just turned into a great band. We did another record a few years later called &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/blues-for-use-feat.-richard/id826564090&quot;&gt;Blues for Use&lt;/a&gt;. And then we did that live record that you were talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That waltz track is hysterical, man. That lead melody, I’m like, “Where did that melody come from?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8XvlpLEA5Hs&quot;&gt;Catskills Last Waltz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8XvlpLEA5Hs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Actually, I used to have a house in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catskill_Mountains&quot;&gt;Catskills&lt;/a&gt;. I sold it. I was sitting on the couch right before I was getting rid of it. I was literally about to leave, all my stuff was packed up and I was getting ready to get in my car and say goodbye to the house and I had my dobro there and I just wrote that little melody. So I called it Catskills Last Waltz. It’s kind of like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thelonious_Monk&quot;&gt;[Thelonius] Monk&lt;/a&gt; vibe. I think it was kind of a Thelonius Monk-type melody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I could see that. Yeah. Yeah, a lot of kind of close notes and very chromatic but fun. I just thought it was a really cool track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Thank you. So, from that, I also did a jazz quintet record with Teddy and Rich, Keith Loftis who’s an incredible sax player, and then &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barney_McAll&quot;&gt;Barney McAll&lt;/a&gt;, a bass and piano player. We did a record live up in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smokejazz.com/&quot;&gt;Smoke Jazz Club&lt;/a&gt; and we put that out. And then I kept all these groups going then I started doing this band called the Air-Conditioned Gypsies, which is basically just a collective of musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s all improvisation and I basically–for a while, I was doing every three months, now I’m maybe doing it twice a year or so. I just call up different musicians that I want to play with to play. I think about it, “Who’s gonna play well together?” And it’s just been great. I’ve done some great ones. I’ve done a couple double drums with Jojo Mayer. They’re on YouTube, like you said. A couple with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Guiliana&quot;&gt;Mark Guiliana&lt;/a&gt;, both on YouTube. Those are both–those guys are both incredible, innovative drummers who’ve influence me a lot. So that was great. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vernon_Reid&quot;&gt;Vernon Reid&lt;/a&gt;’s done a bunch of ‘em. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerry_Leonard&quot;&gt;Gerry Leonard&lt;/a&gt; did some. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.olirockberger.com/&quot;&gt;Oli Rockberger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johndavismusic.info/&quot;&gt;John Davis&lt;/a&gt;, Richard Hammond, Teddy–it’s a long list of great musicians that have been involved in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RczweEBTtXY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyway, so when it came to thinking about making a new record, which is the record that’s coming out next Friday, I believe. March 16. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/sculptures/1332320542&quot;&gt;Sculptures&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to do something a little different. I had made two records with Teddy and Rich that were kind of based on my acoustic guitar compositions. Me sitting around and I write a lot of stuff on acoustic and that’s where those songs came from. I wanted to do something different. I’ve been experimenting with all the improv stuff, which I’ve always been into. Getting into a little more of the electronic vibe, which brings me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leongruenbaum.com/&quot;&gt;Leon Greunbaum&lt;/a&gt;. Leon’s the guy that I always use on the Air-Conditioned Gypsies. I always use different people, but Leon is in every gig. So far, he’s been available for every one I’ve asked him to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He’s the guy who plays that invented instrument, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leongruenbaum.com/samchilliankidchillian&quot;&gt;Samchillian&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Exactly. He plays the Samchillian. You can look it up. It’s this crazy thing that he invented and I just love him. He’s just an incredible musician. He’s so creative and he comes up with such great ideas and sonic sounds. So I really wanted to bring him into this new record. Originally, the idea was: “Let me get together with Leon in my studio. We’ll just do some short improvisations.” So the record started with just the two of us in my studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I didn’t want to do this jam for two hours and then cut and paste. I was like, “I want to come up with some idea before we start. A little concept, even if it was just a beat or an idea, and we’d do these things. I didn’t want any of them to be more than three minutes. Maybe four minutes. Some of them were even one or two minutes. We did a whole bunch of that and that was the start of it. And then I had a couple of songs that I had written on acoustic guitar, but they’re a little different and I recorded those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I played the guitar on those, the acoustic guitar, which I’d never–well I’d always played a little bit of guitar on my records, but not much. So that was kind of one section of it. Then I’m sitting here looking at this, I have these kind of cool improvs–and the improvs were great. Usually it would start off with just me and Leon and then sometimes Leon would overdub something on top of it. Ultimately, I had a few other people come in and play some stuff, but it was just based on these improvs. We had the improv section, we had these couple of acoustic guitar-based songs that I played, and then we had this part three, which I hadn’t really figured out yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DL-kxy7GqQQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My friend Oli Rockberger, who’s an amazing piano player, he’s just phenomenal. He lived in New York for a long time. He’s from London and he moved back to London about four or five years ago. He was in a band called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.misterbarrington.com/&quot;&gt;Mister Berrington&lt;/a&gt; with Zach Danziger and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Owen_Biddle_(musician)&quot;&gt;Owen [Biddle]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I used to play with them in this band with this great songwriter named James Maddock, who I used to play with a lot. He’s just always been one of my favorite musicians. He was like, “Hey I’m going to be in town, man. We should hang.” I was like, “Shit. I gotta book a session around Oli’s coming to town.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I confirmed Oli and then I confirmed Leon and then I wanted to get–I played a few times with John Davis, who plays in Jojo Mayer’s Nerve. He lives right across the street. He can probably see me. I really hit it off with him. He filled in for Rich a couple times on our trio gig, which is now actually a quartet because Leon plays. He did an Air-Conditioned Gypsies gig. Where the music was going for this record, I felt like, “Yeah, this will be cool. I want to do something different.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So me and Oli and John and Leon got together one afternoon and I’m kind of thinking, “Shit, what am I going to do? Shit this is happening in two days.” I tend to work good under pressure. I didn’t want to–I knew I wanted it to be improv based, but I didn’t want it to just be like, “Hey kids, let’s go.” So at the 11th hour, I wrote some ideas. I wrote a couple songs. I came in there with these loose kind of song ideas. About six or seven of them. And we did them and it was just a really great session. It just clicked really well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think out of those seven, maybe four of them went on the record. Between those three different things, that’s how I came up with this record. And then I should mention, too, that there’s a guitar player in town called &lt;a href=&quot;https://cantaloupemusic.com/artists/grey-mcmurray&quot;&gt;Grey McMurray&lt;/a&gt; who’s just incredible. He’s just this totally unique, very ambient style of playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And so I wanted Gray to come in and just play over everything. So Gray came in and–actually, this was before the session with Oli and John and Leon. So he came in and played on all the other stuff and he just did such a great job. He added such a cool, vibey element to it. After that last session, I had him come in and play on that stuff. So it ended up being this really cool kind of vibey sort of experimental, sort of electronic-y, still really organic record. I was psyched about it. I did this really great video for the song Sculptures. You can see it on YouTube, just click in Aaron Comess Sculptures. It’ll come right up. Check it out. These really great guys did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah it’s beautifully done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uAZivqNXv7g?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Thank you. I’m really, really psyched. I feel really good about it. I really wanted to do something just really–a nice piece of art to go with it. That one song is kind of a special moment for me and it’s one of my favorite things I’ve ever done. That song Sculptures was just an improv. It was one of those days Leon came in. It really was based on this rhythm. I kind of had this triplet-y rhythm idea inside of this groove and really all I said to Leon was, “I just want you to do some ambient weird stuff. I kind of have this rhythmic motif that’s going to kind of appear throughout it and let’s just see what happens.” We just did one–it’s basically just as you hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s really no editing on all the record. Everything you hear is done. And that song in particular, it just had such a beautiful shape to it. When I go back and listen to it, I’m like, “Wow this is really cool. It has a shape.” So we decided–Leon is doing all this stuff, but there’s this harmonic element, chords, so I suggested, “Why don’t you play”–he gets these great bass sounds on the Samchillian. Probably about half the record is John on bass. The other half is Samchillian bass, which is real subsonic sounding. It’s like a Moog or something. I said, “Can you figure out the harmony you did and just add bass to it?” So he did that and that was pretty much it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1lAQG2unSfs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I listened to the record, like I said, five or six times yesterday as I was working. I didn’t have any meetings. I’m working from home. It’s this kind of record–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Lanois&quot;&gt;Daniel Lanois&lt;/a&gt; has an album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shine_(Daniel_Lanois_album)&quot;&gt;Shine&lt;/a&gt; and he designed it so it could just stay on repeat. I felt like this album is really interesting to listen to, it’s short enough that you want to listen to it again right after it’s over, and none of the songs are throwaways. You know? Everything is really good and, like you said, there’s three different vibes going on, but there’s a good mix or a blend of it as you listen through the whole thing. So I really love it. I think it’s a very creative album. Your drumming–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: I appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Your drumming is really creative and I really enjoyed that. And the songs are interesting. So, great job on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: I appreciate it. Thank you. So, it’s funny because Daniel Lanois is a really big influence on me, particularly on my solo stuff. I love all of his instrumental records. I listen to them all a lot. Like you said, the thing that I like about his records–I really like music that is really very much musical and you can listen to, but also it’s not too abrasive. You can almost have it on in the background as well. That’s what I love about all of Daniel Lanois’ records. It’s this very moody vibey thing. But there’s so much music going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s really exactly what I personally tried to go on this. I purposely made it short. The bottom line is I probably recorded about two hours of music and I really kept taking stuff out, taking stuff out, and at one point the record was 12 songs. I’m trying to figure out the right order. “Ah, it doesn’t make sense, but if I pull that song out, all of a sudden it makes sense.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s hard to let go of songs, but after doing records for so long with so many people in my home, I take it really seriously&lt;/span&gt;, even though I know a lot of people don’t listen to records all the way through, I do and I make records that are meant to be listened to all the way through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t like long records. I think 37 minutes–like you said, I don’t want to hear–you want everything to be strong. That’s the idea, you know? So, I appreciate it. One last thing, going back to the song Sculptures. The final element of that is that Grey came in, Grey McMurray came in and played guitar on it. And it was really pretty amazing. This was just improv that me and Leon did. Harmonically, it’s not crazy, but it’s definitely moving around in some weird ways in weird places and Gray just–I couldn’t believe it. He just somehow tuned into it. He played the most beautiful stuff. It was like he was there and I remember–it was one of the most amazing things I’ve ever seen in the studio, how he was able to just tune into the thing. He’s really an amazing guitar player. He added a lot to the vibe of the record, for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So if people want to find out more about you and your music, where’s the best place to find that information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: You can go on my website, which is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aaroncomess.com/&quot;&gt;AaronComess.com&lt;/a&gt;. I recently simplified it, but it’s got most of the records I’ve played on. That’s about it. It’s got the video up there. Links to my records. The new record is coming out March 16. It’s available anywhere. Easiest place to get it is probably iTunes or come to my gig and I’ll give you a CD. Facebook, Instagram, Twitter. All that stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MWYXrjLdIRE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: And one last thing! I’m doing a record release. A 50th birthday bash at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bluenote.net/&quot;&gt;the Blue Note in New York&lt;/a&gt; on April 23. It’s going to be my band with Teddy, Rich, Oli Rockberger’s flying in from London for it, Keith Loftis, the sax player, he’s gonna be there. We’re gonna do all my stuff as well as two really special guests. James Maddock, who’s an incredible songwriter I’ve worked with for years. He’s gonna do a few songs as well as Joan Osborne, who’s also going to be a special guest on a couple songs. It’s gonna be an amazing night. If you’re in New York, get your tickets and come out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, cool! Happy 50th birthday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Not yet. Not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Almost! And congratulations on 30 years of the Spin Doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: Thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The new record is really awesome. I’m looking forward to releasing this and telling people about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AC: I appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/aaron-comess/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/aaron-comess/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>California Guitar Trio</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-get-real&quot;&gt;Let’s Get Real&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit that a lot of a lot of my interviews focus on my admiration of the artist, trying to get at the heart of what makes them tick, and understanding their creative process. These are important topics and I’m really happy with most of the interviews on this site. However, this one gets pretty real. We talk money, streaming rates, and the “different scales of nothingness that artists are paid.” If you’re interested in how a troupe of acoustic guitarists who studied with Robert Fripp have survived for 27 years, this interview will shed some light on that. And they bravely discuss real numbers, real struggles, and real plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would be remiss if I didn’t at least acknowledge the influence of &lt;a href=&quot;http://innerviews.org&quot;&gt;Anil Prasad&lt;/a&gt; on this discussion. Most of &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.com/innerviews&quot;&gt;his facebook&lt;/a&gt; posts are about this stuff and recently he’s gotten heated on the topic of the dismal pay for artists in today’s musical climate. I admire him and he definitely made me step up this interview a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZlpIbf8ERMQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/california-guitar-trio/california-guitar-trio.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/california-guitar-trio/california-guitar-trio.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Richards [PR]
Bert Lams [BL]
Hideyo Moriya [HM]
Anthony Garone [AG]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The California Guitar Trio has been a musical tour de force for the last 27 years now and you guys are here in Phoenix, Arizona–Scottsdale, Arizona in February 2018 and I thought it’d be really cool to have a discussion about what life is like as music has evolved, as the industry has evolved, and as people’s tastes have evolved in the 27 years of your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And you have all evolved yourselves as individuals and as a band. I also thought, for people who have never heard the California Guitar Trio, that we could get a brief intro as to who you are and what you’ve been doing. So, Paul, why don’t you introduce yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Sure, yeah. I’m Paul Richards with the California Guitar Trio and the three of us met while we were studying with British guitar player &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp&lt;/a&gt; back in the late 80s. All three of us attended his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft&lt;/a&gt; seminars and Robert had a house in the English countryside called Red Lion House. He invited some of the students to go to England to study music together at Red Lion House and that’s where the three of us–it’s the time period that the three of us met. We met Bert the first time in Switzerland on a Guitar Craft course that Robert was doing there during that time period, but then Bert came over to Red Lion House and we began playing together as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;League of Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt;. [See our &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;interview with Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt;, another former Crafty Guitarist.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/e_fPaRajJ0A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, we were working with Robert for four or five years before we formed the California Guitar Trio. Bert had just moved to Los Angeles and invited the three of us to go to LA in 1991. So we formed the California Guitar Trio in February of 1991. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, we’re just celebrating our 27th anniversary now.&lt;/span&gt; At that time we were just starting out playing and we just took any gig that we could in LA. Tiny little coffee shops, we even played at the Blind Institute and a home for autistic people. Then as we began playing more and more together, we got invited to do different things. Robert invited us to open up a series of concerts that he did with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Sylvian&quot;&gt;David Sylvian&lt;/a&gt;. He and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Gunn&quot;&gt;Trey Gunn&lt;/a&gt; and David Sylvian did several tours together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So in 1992, we did several tours with David Sylvian and Robert and then a few years later, Robert invited the three of us to open for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_Crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We did over 130 concerts with King Crimson worldwide.&lt;/span&gt; Those were just the few things that helped us. As an acoustic guitar trio, a big challenge is getting to the point where we can tour and play and make any kind of living doing this. So, we did have some help along the way from Robert, but a lot of it we did ourselves–and during our first year, Bert was getting on the phone and calling up these venues in LA just to get gigs for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For our first eight or nine years together, we did everything ourselves aside from the short tours we did opening for other bands. But, we booked all of our own gigs and arranged all the details and then around–was it ‘98? ‘98 or ‘99 we got an agency who started helping us book shows and then in early 2001 or 2002, we got with our agent who we have now, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://sroartists.com/&quot;&gt;SRO Artists&lt;/a&gt;. That was a really good thing for us. They had worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Hedges&quot;&gt;Michael Hedges&lt;/a&gt;, who was one of their main acoustic guitar players, and so they had really good connections with acoustic guitar venues. He was one of the first acoustic guitar greats that was playing for large audiences. So, SRO helped us get into a lot of venues that we had previously been trying to on our own. To this day, they help keep us going now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: I’ll talk a little bit about before the three of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sure, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: I was born in Belgium and around the age of 13 or 14 [the room lights went out].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Around the age of 13 or 14, I heard mainly blues music and I wanted to play the guitar. Electric guitar was my first love, so I bought an electric guitar and started playing with my friends around–I taught myself how to play guitar by listening to blues music. I always had this desire to go to America and study the guitar in America, but it didn’t materialize until later. When I finished high school, rather than go to Berklee College of Music, which was a good option but too expensive for me at that time. I couldn’t afford that, or my parents wouldn’t let me do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I went to the Conservatory of Music in Brussels with little preparation and I gloriously failed the entrance exam, but they referred me to a really good teacher and then in a couple of years, I really caught up. That’s where I really started to play the guitar more seriously. In the meantime, I kept playing the electric guitar and listening to electric guitar music. Maybe six or seven years later after I graduated and started teaching, while I was teaching, I found out that these courses were held by Robert Fripp. I was a big fan of his music. Then, finally, it became possible. It was only a five day introductory course in the states in West Virginia. So, I got on a plane and went there and it all started and began for the three of us as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: How do I start it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, yeah a little introduction to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Okay, yeah. I’m born in Japan and raised in Japan and when I was a kid, like 12 years old, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Ventures&quot;&gt;The Ventures&lt;/a&gt; (the instrumental surf band) in the states was very big in Japan. That’s how I imitate to start the guitar playing a Ventures piece because it’s all instrumental so you don’t sing it. That was fun. The Ventures, most of their pieces, the famous one, I copied it and then started listening to other bands, like the Beatles and many, many others. But The Ventures was the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One interesting thing for me is the very first piece–from the time I learned my first piece–I still am playing it now. I’m wondering why, but it’s the music. It’s staying. What I played around that time and now, I still am playing. It’s very interesting for me. I still have some life. It’s not just playing old pieces, so that’s one thing I keep going. So even almost close to 50 years ago I was playing my very first piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Are you the one who’s brought in the surf and 60s influence into the band?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3_Mu2CUrM2o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah. I could say that I think. Of course, people are suggesting to us to play other pieces, like Sleepwalk. I didn’t know it. It’s not famous in Japan, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, The Ventures are awesome. They have a Christmas album that we discovered a couple of years ago and thought, “Why is this not a staple for everyone’s Christmas?” Great album. Really out of tune guitars. It’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;As you were talking about yourselves and how you met, it reminded me of my experience in the Guitar Circle introductory course. It was a life-changing week for me and clearly it’s a life-changing experience for each of you. What do you think transformed about yourself when you went through the Guitar Craft instruction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: At the time I heard about the Guitar Craft course, I was only 20 years old, I think. I was studying–I was in the jazz guitar ensemble at the University of Utah and my teacher at that time just passed away yesterday so I’ve been thinking a lot about him–he was there with Robert Fripp and some other great teachers I had, like Kevin Johanssen. So that experience playing with the jazz guitar ensemble was great and it really helped form the things I’m doing now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Lights turned off again.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SZiWvjRj1AY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So that experience of playing with the jazz guitar ensemble was important at that time, but I somehow knew that that’s not what I was going to end up doing. And then I heard about these Robert Fripp Guitar Craft courses. And another teacher of mine at that time, a guy named Don Ayers, he’s the one who encouraged me to go on my first level one course. I remember arriving at the mansion in West Virginia where these first courses were held and walking in the room and Robert Fripp is sitting in the corner and all the students were sitting on the ground and no chairs around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I immediately had a sense of peace come over me and I felt like, “This is the right place for me to be.” Even though I had no idea of what was going to happen. That whole week was very transformative. At the end of that week–I had this transcription of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discipline_(King_Crimson_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discipline&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the King Crimson song Discipline that my teacher Don Ayers had made–and I wanted to show it to Robert to show what I’d been working on with my other teacher. Everybody was leaving the course and my time was running out. Then I went to Robert’s room and he was practicing his guitar and normally you don’t bother him when he’s practicing, but I knocked on the door and at first he was saying, “Don’t bother me. What do you want?” I said, “Oh it’s Paul, I have this transcription of Discipline.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He invited me in and I sat down with him for a few minutes and showed him the transcription and he said, “Oh that’s very nice.” And then he said, “You need to come on the next Guitar Craft course next month!” And I was kind of in shock. I thought I was just going to do that one thing and then the idea that this was going to be a continual thing suddenly to happen for me. I went on the course the next month there and soon after that I was invited to England–to Robert’s house in England. Then everything changed in my life from attending those courses. It was huge. And what we’re doing now is all a result of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Right. Still riding that wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you talk a little more about the transformation? For me, physically, back pain went away with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Technique&quot;&gt;Alexander Technique&lt;/a&gt;, the guitar technique completely changed, the way I pick, my relationship with the instrument… Can you talk a little about your experience coming from an electric blues background?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: There’s so many different things, but I can relate two instances. While Paul was talking, it just came up. I was used to imitating. The way I learned was listen to something that I really loved and then pick up all the details. Blues music was perfect, you know? The bending strings and stuff. And in classical guitar, the way I would learn a piece, I could read music, but the way I would learn a piece was to listen over and over again to something that I really wanted to play. And it’s the same with these two guys. We get the feel of a piece then it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, when I went to that week, the way I was used to having guitar classes or lessons was I would take jazz guitar lessons, for instance, with a man named John Thomas. He was a black guy, a really good guitar teacher. He teaches still at Berklee College of Music. I would go to his apartment. He was not–I would say he was not a great teacher, per se, but he could play really well and I would just bring my microphone and ask him to play Autumn Leaves, whatever, any standard that would be amazing. I’d take it home and then I’d assimilate. Pick it up and say, “Oh I like that.” Pick it up, imitate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I went to the Guitar Craft courses with the same thing. I brought my little tape recorder and my cassette recorder and I was ready to record anything I could, pick up all the exercises. I had no idea what was going to happen, so I did it the same way. I remember there was a big inaugural meeting, as you remember, with all the students there and Robert would ask everybody to introduce themselves and everything. I was recording everything. [Laughs.] Also, I didn’t want to miss anything. My English was not as good then and I wanted to take it home and listen to what he said in case I missed something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6JTL3uxSYhI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Somebody noticed I was recording and told Robert and when I had my first personal meeting, right after, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Robert pulled me aside. He was really nice, he wasn’t like, “Bootlegging!” He was saying, “Well, you don’t need to do that. Just listen with your heart,” he said.&lt;/span&gt; I was like, “Oh, okay.” And then in one of the first personal meetings I had a question for him because I was teaching full time at that time and I asked him, “How can I apply…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Lights off again.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You have to stand up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, in one of my first meetings with him, I asked him, “How can I apply this–what’s happening here to my teaching and to my students?” Because I was teaching full time. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He said, “When you teach with love, everything’s going to be okay.”&lt;/span&gt; So he gave all these answers from his experience and that really turned me inside out. He wouldn’t have to think about some answer, something smart. It was just from his experience and I think that was a big thing for me to get that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How about you, Hideyo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Oh, well, after teaching myself, I formed a band with my friend playing The Ventures style as a local group. I formed a band and played in little clubs in Japan and decided to keep going so I decided to come to the States to study. After that, I didn’t have any official teaching about the music. So, I went to Berklee College of Music and I was pretty bad. A bad student. Really bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: A bad student? A bad player? Or both?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Could be both. [Laughter.] Compared to the other students, amazing students and people there. But also, something in Berklee and I didn’t get along, I didn’t agree with it. You know, rock is not a style, but it’s said there are styles of rock, but the music is very analyzed, I think. It doesn’t have much–something is missing in what I learned from Berklee. My friend was telling me, “If you like to play rock music, why don’t you go to jam?” I was thinking about the next move and I found Guitar Craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Robert was my hero with King Crimson. So I decided to go and take a Guitar Craft course, but before I knew it was only a 5-day course. Five days of what? I didn’t know what they were doing in the five days. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;For a long time, I stayed at Berklee. About two years and I still was getting nothing. What can you do with five days?&lt;/span&gt; And I don’t speak good English, also. And also I learned Robert’s philosophy behind what he’s doing and Robert went to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_G._Bennett&quot;&gt;Bennett Institute&lt;/a&gt; in England. Guitar Craft course was held in West Virginia, which was doing continuous education. So, I took that course before going to a Guitar Craft course to be familiar with myself with those ideas. For me, that was more shocking. That was more changing my life in a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Learning about yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Learning about myself in the course. I don’t want to get into too much detail because I can’t explain those philosophies and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gurdjieff&quot;&gt;Gurdjieff&lt;/a&gt; works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: You were there for three months or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, three months. Three months and then the head of that school told me to do it another three months. So I took another course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Six months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Because the first three months was very good, but the next three months was getting a little bit, you know… Getting more–ego was coming out, I guess. Whatever. Anyway, so the Guitar Craft was, in a way, shocking but not like what I had in Claymont.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: So, just to wrap that transformation thing up, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think for us the transformation became our way of life and the way that we work together.&lt;/span&gt; It’s a little bit hard to talk about because it’s a normal thing for us now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Of course. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SV6l8U9GfOU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: The way we learned to work together on the Guitar Craft courses was one of the things that propelled us when we started playing together as the California Guitar Trio. We had this whole way of doing things already set up and the way that we worked with Robert and the League went immediately into the way–in everything. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The way we played our guitars, the way we listened to each other, and even when we were staying at Bert’s house in Hollywood during those first years, we tried to apply the Guitar Craft principles that–we were doing morning sitting and all those things that were the Guitar Craft ways of–and we took turns preparing meals. It was kind of an extension of that transformation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s really awesome. So speaking of transformation, it used to be that you would sell CDs. [Laughs.] And you’d make money selling CDs and merchandise and touring. Now, that leg of the tripod of support as a musician is going away. I bring this up because I’ve seen Paul pretty active on Anil Prasad’s Facebook threads about this. So, I wanted to get your take on how the band has survived because I don’t think many bands can survive for 27 years. Especially not as a major act. So, could you talk a little bit about how you’ve seen the band shift and how you’ve been able to manage and maintain yourselves over all this time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: We made our first demo CD back in 1991 and I remember the first gigs that we played when we had the CD. We sold–we were selling quite a few CDs at shows then and I remember after the show, we would all gather and maybe the gig money was a little bit of money, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;but the CD sales–we would lay it out on the hotel bed or something, divide it up in to three, and we were so excited. We had this money from the CD sales! For years that continued to support our work. In fact, when we toured with King Crimson in those 130 concerts, we did not receive any payment for the shows. The only way that we supported ourselves was through CD sales after the shows.&lt;/span&gt; Robert was encouraging us to go out to this CD table after and sign CDs and meet the people, which is funny because he never does that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s ironic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So we paid for that entire tour with the CD sales and then we had various record deals.&lt;/span&gt; We had a record deal on Robert’s label for quite a while, which was very good, and also with Inside Out Record Label. And now we still have some distribution through Inner Knot, which is also part of Discipline Global Mobile. So we still have a little bit of that, but you’re right, the CD sales are dwindling. Like, we never know now at shows if we’re going to sell any CDs. One night, we’ll have–maybe we’ll sell three or four CDs and then the next night, we’ll be surprised and we’ll sell 50 or 60.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So it hasn’t gone away completely at our shows. And our audience is, you know–most of the people are probably 30 and 40 and older. People younger than 30 don’t even know what a CD is and have probably never bought one. One of the other things that was really great was we went through maybe five or six years where we were recording all of our shows and we had a CD burning duplication tower that we brought with us. We called it our ATM machine because we would sell, you know, a lot of them after the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, even just on these last few tours, we had one night in Bainbridge, Georgia where the audience was very small, but everybody in the audience bought a CD. Then the next night, the place was packed in Tifton College. Yeah, at a college place and we sold hardly any CDs. So, it’s now at the point where we can’t really rely on the CD sales from the shows anymore. And the CD sales through stores has gone away. We have a little bit of online distribution and we have our own web store where we sell a few. We sell a few things through iTunes, so that’s still a little bit there, but it’s changed dramatically now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;As Anil says, the thing that musicians need to do is find a way of doing different things.&lt;/span&gt; Offering different sorts of things that people are still interested in buying. And that seems to be one of the keys that we can do now. This is an ongoing discussion that we have a lot on tour. What are the things that we can do now? As far as the streaming goes, the one redeeming thing for California Guitar Trio is that California Guitar Trio is very popular on Pandora radio. We, over the past few years, have received over 60 million plays. From those plays, we do receive some money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: We own our copyrights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Because we own the copyrights, because we’ve set everything up to maximize how much money we get from streaming. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;From 60 million plays, we probably have received 50 or 60 thousand dollars&lt;/span&gt;, which is–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3w3fD54bNvU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Something. It’s not nothing. So, that’s just how it is now. We know from Pandora Radio, we get a little bit of money. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the problem with the streaming is that royalty rates are so low that 60 million plays–it should be way more than $50,000 or $60,000.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And Pandora’s more generous than Spotify. 60 million plays may be a few thousand dollars now, the way the rates have been declining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;so the main problem with the streaming is the rates are way too low.&lt;/span&gt; In the old days, when people sold–if they had a single that sold 60 million singles, that was–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’re set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: That was a fair amount of money. And for those musicians that don’t have their own copyrights. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;For musicians that are signed with a record label on some deal where they signed away their copyrights, those are the guys that you see on Facebook that say, “I had this song that had a million plays on Spotify and I got $13” because the songwriting portion of the royalty–it’s already so small and then the songwriting portion is the smallest percentage of that. The percentage that gets paid to the artist, you know? There’s different scales of nothingness that artists are paid. And fortunately, we took Robert Fripp’s advice when he told us to never give away our copyrights.&lt;/span&gt; We had some good offers along the way. We could have had some great record deal. We were offered a deal on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Glass&quot;&gt;Philip Glass&lt;/a&gt;’s record label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonesuch_Records&quot;&gt;Nonesuch&lt;/a&gt; [Records].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Point Records on Nonesuch. It was like a dream come true to get that offer. We sent the contract to Robert. He said he would read through it for us. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He got to the point that–the paragraph that said that they keep our copyrights in perpetuity for forever. He wrote, “Fuck you,” in the column.&lt;/span&gt; Told his assistant to rip it up and send it back to the record label, which she didn’t do that. But, she sent it back to us. So somewhere we have a box somewhere with this contract that Robert Fripp wrote “fuck you” in the column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Sit on a pointed stick” was another one. He would write it and sign it, next to it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sit on a pointed stick?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Signed RF. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Yeah, so that was great advice, which is helping us now to this day because without that we would be one of the guys that says, “I have 60 million plays streaming and we only got $100,” or whatever. Fortunately, we’re not that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, what are some of these options that you guys are offering that help differentiate your revenue away from CD sales?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: I think for us, it’s still the CDs because people are moved by the concert and they want a token of the concert. And right now, I think it’s still a CD. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;They want something that we sign. They like us to be there and say hello.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: That’s still going away, though. It might be just a few years before…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Yeah, maybe a year, another year I think we’ll sell more CDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: One thing that we’re talking about is finding a new way to do the concert recordings because that was such a great thing for us and people loved to buy the concert that they just heard. So, we’re talking about the idea of recording the concert and then immediately, when we get back to the hotel room, we upload it and at the show we can sell download cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: So, maybe in the next few months, we may get that going. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So that’s the main thing that we’re looking at doing now. Selling downloads of our live show that same night.&lt;/span&gt; Have it uploaded relatively quickly after our shows. So that’s one of the things. We’re doing other things. We have t-shirts and other merchandise. We’re talking about other merchandise ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Our audience kind of wants to buy our music, it seems like. We’ve tried the t-shirts. They buy t-shirts, but–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Like sheet music? Or the actual recorded music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: No he’s saying we’ve always sold more CDs than we have sold other types of merchandise, which is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: So I think the live shows will be a good thing if we can package it right. That’s kind of key so people have some kind of token that we sign. We tried the USB sticks for a while. It didn’t work because you get this little USB stick and it’s not…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: And then the USB duplicator failed several times and we had a line of people that all bought the show. It was too stressful for us. So this download idea may be more better for us than–yeah. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But the main source of income for us is our shows and that’s why we’re touring a lot.&lt;/span&gt; Shows like tonight at this amazing venue, the Musical Instrument Museum, that’s how we can survive. The good thing is that we’re able to keep busy enough that we can just–none of us are getting rich doing this, for sure. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And the months where we don’t have many shows, where we used to have CD income, this is a difficulty for us.&lt;/span&gt; So we need to figure out–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Patreon, right?! [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: There’s Patreon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Patreon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4HqFdQEK6_o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Patreon is the subscription service where people pay a monthly thing. The thing with Patreon is that you need to be good at developing lots of new content and people like Nora Germain and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/julie-slick&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt; are young and they are good at that. She’s good at developing new stuff. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The three of us–we’re not quite as enthusiastic about trying every week doing a new video and doing something new.&lt;/span&gt; So, I think Patreon is great and there’s a lot of people that seem to be able to get it, but I’m not sure that’s a way for the three of us to Hideyo to do another video, you know? Or something that we can get onto Patreon to get people interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The other thing is &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we’re trying to think about the way we release music in a different way now.&lt;/span&gt; Instead of waiting until we have a whole album, we may start releasing things as singles or doing an EP because the three of us live in different cities, it takes us longer to make a new album. We have three or four years in between each official release, but now we’re already working on–you’ll hear some things at the show tonight that will be on our next album, or somehow released in the meantime as a way to generate interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The main thing that’s important for us now is to keep the interest level up for the people that are coming to our shows and finding ways of developing new people to come to our shows but also the people who are big fans.&lt;/span&gt; Over 27 years of time, we’ve played for a lot of people, so we need to find ways of keeping all of those people interested and also developing–continuing to develop a new audience. So, all of these things–doing releases, we’re doing a video, the next week we’ll be in Los Angeles and we’re working with these friends of ours that like to make videos and we’re doing another video with them. And doing this interview with you. All of these little things that help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: We keep busy individually, too, which is nice. Paul is doing his photography, he’s coming out with a new–it’s on your website with all the prints. He’s taking great photos, mostly nature photos I would say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: So he’s going to release that and it’s really worth releasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: We’re each doing things when we have long breaks. I like to keep playing live. That’s my big joy, so I play house concerts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: So I do different little projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xdEAccE7BMs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Like Fabio and Tom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mittinolams.com/&quot;&gt;Fabio Mittino&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thossounds.com/&quot;&gt;Tom Griesgraber&lt;/a&gt;. I like to do that. I might go back to teaching a little bit, but when we have these breaks, I think we need to–we’re looking at other things of developing ourselves, individually and doing things and then bring that back to the group, which is great when we come back together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, the hardest part to me is what Paul’s referring to. You’re no longer just a musician. You’re a brand. You have to market yourself. You have to constantly provide new content and if you don’t, the algorithms shove your content down way, way down in somebody’s feed and they never see it. And you’ve got, you know, 20,000 followers but 300 views. It’s becoming impossible to just be a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Mm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah, yeah. And &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/nora-germain&quot;&gt;Nora Germain&lt;/a&gt; is really good–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: She’s so good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: At that stuff. I talk to her a lot about this stuff. She’s kind of a consultant in a way and I think she’s actually going to be doing more of that. Helping other people get good at what she is good at. That’s exactly this, about getting–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;keeping the interest there and now where everything’s measured in plays and views. It’s a whole ‘nother world. And we’re still figuring it out!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And that’s one of the things I like about reading Anil’s comments and posts because I think he does have a good insight into things that are changing. He’s offered a lot of suggestions, even to California Guitar Trio on things that we could do, different musicians we can do projects with, different ways to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, thank you so much for taking the time. How much more are you touring on this particular leg? Are you doing the southwest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Tomorrow we have to get up early to drive to San Diego, where we have a Sunday afternoon show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: In a church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: In a church. Yeah. So we’ll be in San Diego tomorrow night. Then we go to LA where we have a couple of days before our show there on Wednesday. We’re playing at Herb Alpert’s Vibrato Club in Belair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: So it’s a fancy gig there. During our days off, well not really days off, but we’ll do some rehearing and do some more filming for this video that Jill and Gary Banfield are helping us do there. And then we have a one-week break and then we go to the midwest for about two weeks. Tour in Michigan, Indiana–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: That’s a tough one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s a tough one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Why’s that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Because almost every day we play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Every night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Every night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah, which is also good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You drive between every gig–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So a lot of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: In fact, this tour has a couple of breaks, but it’s going up to mid-April. It’s all one long tour with short little breaks. To me, it’s like one long tour through mid-April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’ve released 16 albums, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is there another one coming soon this year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Hopefully, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: We have a good start on it, but it takes us a while to get enough material for a full album, so that’s one of the things we’re talking about doing. Different ways of releasing things. We have a good start on that. We have a lot more touring scheduled throughout the year. Our agency, SRO, is great in helping us keep busy. But they handle everything that has to do with setting up the concerts and all the contracts for that, but we do everything else. We are our own management, we are our own promotion team, and so when we’re not on tour, that’s the thing that we’re working on. Getting things set up for the next tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m recording sound clips on Pandora–that’s one of the things that they offer now. Artists can record a clip that goes out to the listeners and you can specify who hears the clip and on Spotify and Pandora and–they have things that they make available for artists. So this is the good side of the bad side. They do have some promotional things that help artists. But we do all of–we book all our own travel, we–Bert and I drive the van. Hideyo used to drive, but he doesn’t anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: He’s the navigator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gtlTvW_WnAk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: He’s the navigator. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So for people who want to learn more about California Guitar Trio, and who want to support you, what are the best ways to find out more and what are the best ways to support you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: Come to our shows. Go–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Lights turn off again.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m doing the hokey pokey and it’s not even working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: The best ways to support California Guitar Trio are: go to our website and sign up for our email list. We send out an email, maybe once a month, not that often so we don’t bombard with emails. And come to our shows and buy our music. Even if it’s not a CD, we have downloads and we have other ways of buying music. Signing up for our email list is the best way to find out when we’re going to be in town again next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Yeah. The live shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, live shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;PR: The live shows are what we have now, which is great. It’s always been the focus for us anyway, so that part is only getting better. Like tonight, our first time playing at the Musical Instrument Museum, and it’s sold out. It’s likely that we’ll get invited back again. Across the country, we have things like that happening, so that’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Fantastic. Thank you again for your time. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;BL: Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/california-guitar-trio</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/california-guitar-trio</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>iNFiNiEN</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;iNFiNiEN is a rock band based in Philadelphia making music for all the right reasons. They are passionate about music as art and have a huge variety of influences. Their music is fun, exploratory, dense, and beautiful. The band’s drummer, Tom Cullen, submitted their music to me via Facebook several months ago. When I finally got around to actually listening with intention, I came to realize what a talented group of people they are. I immediately knew they’d be a great fit for the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jordan Berger: Bass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tom Cullen: Drums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matt Hollenberg: Guitar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chrissie Loftus: Vocals and Keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JTTRX8_lXBo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/infinien/infinien.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/infinien/infinien.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[“If I Were a Song” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Infinien is a really interesting rock band out of the Philadelphia area and I am really delighted that they’re here with me because it’s all I’ve been able to listen to in the last couple weeks. So, thank you guys for joining us today and I’m really excited to introduce your music to our audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Of course! We’re happy to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Thanks for having us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, of course. So, could you guys introduce yourself–names and what you play? And I’m most curious about your creative process because your songs are so interesting and they blend so many different styles and I really want to hear about your creative process for your songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Cool. I’m Chrissie [Loftus] and I play keyboards and sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: And I’m Matt [Hollenberg] and I play guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I’m Tom [Cullen], I play drums and percussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: I’m Jordan [Berger], I play bass and sing some background vocals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool, so your creative process. Who wants to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I think…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: It all started with a big bang, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Well, I guess the main thing to understand about the band is we’re all coming from different areas of music, stylistically. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We started out the band as just an outlet for jamming and exploring with no agenda of making a band, really. We just liked exploring music together and it was fun for us to have an interaction&lt;/span&gt; with–just speaking for myself, I was thrilled to play with them because it was such a different thing than what I was doing at the time, which was more metal stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I got to play all this clean, jazzy guitar style and that was just a totally fresh thing for me at the time. And then I think collectively, we got into the genre-busting music in the beginning. Obviously, we share a love of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr._Bungle&quot;&gt;Mr. Bungle&lt;/a&gt;. I think that’s pretty obvious to certain people that like Mr. Bungle. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_(Mr._Bungle_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;California&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is one of our all-time favorite records. It’s not directly an influence. We’re not trying to recreate Mr. Bungle, but just the spirit of adventurousness, free exploration, boundary smashing, off-the-wall. We love everything about the way they approach it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tUOWTmOP4FQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We got in some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Zorn&quot;&gt;John Zorn&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_Chiefs_3&quot;&gt;Secret Chiefs 3&lt;/a&gt; and that world has a little bit of a quirkiness that we maybe wanted to smooth the edge of. So, we like having the soulful vocals and the deep harmony of sort of more conventional styles of music. Maybe not more convention, but more soulful kinds of music. So obviously we love &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esperanza_Spalding&quot;&gt;Esperanza Spalding&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiatus_Kaiyote&quot;&gt;Hiatus Coyote&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MoeTar&quot;&gt;MoeTar&lt;/a&gt;, and those bands are kind of in their own world compared to Bungle and Secret Chiefs. I guess we’re coming from all over the map and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we don’t like any filler or redundancy in our songs, so by the time we’re all happy, there’s just this mish-mash of different stuff that’s very adventurous to listen to and kind of engulfs you in the sound&lt;/span&gt;. I think we’re just going for an immersive vibe with what we’re doing. I know that was a long answer, but that’s a big question. Just bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I would agree. I think our main objective is to sort of fuse all different influences to where–we love so many different types of music. Like Matt’s saying, we’re inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis&quot;&gt;Miles Davis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weather_Report&quot;&gt;Weather Report&lt;/a&gt;, and Mr. Bungle, John Zorn, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candiria&quot;&gt;Candiria&lt;/a&gt;, you know? When we create, a lot of it–that’s the concept, but the working process is probably like Matt writes material, Chrissie writes material	, and then we kind of write a song as a band based on those blueprints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, that’s pretty accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: If you listen close, you can tell the two different writing styles. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steely_Dan&quot;&gt;Steely Dan&lt;/a&gt; or–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Steely Dan! [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hall_%26_Oates&quot;&gt;Hall and Oates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We don’t sound like Steely Dan or Hall and Oates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I don’t know. If you listen close enough, you can sort of figure out who sparked the original thought for the tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Right. And then there’s other tunes we all write together. Everyone equally. And all three modes kind of have different results, so the albums just end up being all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/S74hBpQZ6LU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I wrote this one song. So…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Which one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Brand New.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: The first track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Brand New” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that’s a great song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: It was based on a rhythm Tom came up with and we all worked it out together in the room. That didn’t come from anybody, it was all working together. So certain songs, that happens. Other songs, Chrissie brings the whole thing and it’s a perfect chord progression and we just orchestrate that together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: So there’s no song that’s complete that’s being brought in. It’s at a certain point and we build it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Yeah, I’d say that. I’d say it’s just–usually the process is however we’re going to express it, being the most honest with what we’re currently feeling or what we’re influenced by. That’s kind of why I think it sounds like there’s a lot of different influences just because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;every day is a different influence and every day we’re listening to different types of music.&lt;/span&gt; There was a period where we were really getting into Indian music together. And then we found out about Ethopian music. “Oh shit!” And then everything just kind of builds on itself. It’s just honest expression, I think. That’s the best…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: We move really fast. We’re always telling each other about new music that we discover. Being inspired and influenced by the most creative, newest, weirdest music keeps us on a roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: As far as my view on the process for us, it’s like we’ve said–a lot of writing comes from Chrissie, a lot of writing comes from Matt. Basically, a lot of the divide, or the separation, is Matt tends to bring in more technically-written instrumental lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, that’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Sometimes some really active chord progressions. Chrissie more often than not will bring in a more chord progression and melody with some lyrics already written. Things like that. There’s been a couple of songs where I’ve contributed a section to, like one of Chrissie’s songs or I’ve contributed a section to a song where we were sort of all working on together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I feel that my role in the process is really more of an arranging kind of role and sort of more like, “Well here’s all these ideas, they’re all awesome. Let’s put them all together, let’s see what maybe needs to change to fit the other things that are happening around it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cb-DseJ-s30?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Or a cool chord progression, like the end of “Bottom of the Food Chain.” The ending is all [points to Jordan.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[The Bottom of the Food Chain excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, I’ve written some sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, that’s an amazing chord progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: That’s on the new record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: It’s coming from everyone. Ultimately, everyone has something new that came completely from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: The third record, especially, everyone has a voice on that and I think that’s why it’s all over the place, but it’s thematic because we play in a certain way together. So, the songs kind of have this thing that binds them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, on the third record, if you look at the inside of it, it does break it down pretty cleanly as far as who wrote what, but also what’s interesting about the song that Tom brought in the basis for, that actually credits all of us including the original bass player. It’s a really old song. That song’s called “Brand New.” It’s the first song on our newest record. That one actually credits Justin Carney, the original bassist and he did some writing in the early stages of the band as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: And Justin did, too, have the initial concept, which was cool. I remember he phoned me one time and I was–I had been playing in really obscure grindcore band called Heinous Anus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: It was a great band. Legendary band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: They were really great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: They’re worth talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: It’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: They’re very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Me and Matt collided in the metal world because his band, Cleric, at the time was doing insane shit. That was cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: They still are doing really insane stuff. Cleric is awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I guess I had broken up with that band and I was just distraught. I was fucked up, you know? It was a bad period of my life. So I started rapping and making beats. I wasn’t playing music. And Justin called me and said, “What if we”–I was also going to jazz school, learning about jazz and harmony, and I thought all the advanced harmony was really dope, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, he was like, “What if we do a really low–something with a lot of power. Heavy funk. Metal, almost. Heavy funk metal and then just christen it with this nice keyboards, jazz harmony, female vocals,” and I was like, “Let’s do it.” So I packed up my cardboard box and I went straight to Philadelphia. I swear to God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: That’s amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Yeah. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Everything except the cardboard part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: I know. I think that’s pretty funny, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: This was years ago. But yeah, Justin Carney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, Justin Carney deserves a lot of credit because he–I didn’t understand any of these chords. He wanted to use these 5- and 6-note deep chords and use polyrhythm and he’s like, “The whole thing will just be, like, swirling, man!” And I’m like, “Yeah, that’s cool!” But I didn’t know anything about that. I didn’t go to jazz school. So he taught me all that jazz stuff and kind of formed the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then through jamming, we all were exploring it together. I don’t feel like I was–I just felt like I was along for the ride. I didn’t come up with the idea because I didn’t know anything about jazz when I was 19. Nothing. I was playing metal. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WsPloykBpo8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think we’re making a lot of assumptions of the listener, so can you tell us a little bit about your band’s history and how many releases you have? What brought you together and what you’re up to now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Sure. We’ve released three–we have three releases. One is an EP, the original. It’s “How to Accept.” The first record that I was involved with is the self-titled, full-length album. It’s our first full-length album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: And the year, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: The year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Oh it was 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Oh yeah, sorry. The original EP came out in 2006. The self-titled album is 2009. And we just put out our follow-up to that. It’s a full-length record called “Light at the Endless Tunnel” that came out last year, or earlier in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: And then between those albums, we played all the damn time. Between the first two records, we played all the time throughout Philly. Basements, World Cafe, jazz cafes, metal gigs. It was tough for us because we were doing something that was totally different, yet somehow we were able, in our networking, to connect with bands that were partially like us. We’re so alienated yet somehow we were able to connect with these bands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xl0xviYz3rM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But when we weren’t in the studio dropping albums, we were out on the road. We did three tours. We went to the midwest, down south–we did three tours. We covered a lot of ground. We never got to go out west. But, yeah man, we’ve got tapes of us playing all this stuff live that we’re hoping to release. We just stayed busy. We constantly–the band’s history, too, we were always playing. We were real stern on rehearsing all the time. A couple times a week, gigging. You know, all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Love for Yourself” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: We met originally with the bass player–that was 2004. Three of us were roommates–the bass player, Matt, and I were roommates with, like, eight other people. So there was always music going on of some sort. Usually it was hip hop because a lot of people at that time, it was in college. Other people wanted to rap, you know? But what happened is we just realized we were all in different bands, so let’s just make music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I think the core, the three of us, realized we were kind of finding a voice that we hadn’t found in our other projects, so we just called Tom in and took it and just started experimenting. You know, sometimes with substances. [Laughs.] And each other, and just realizing that that was a lot of fun. Then we just started playing gigs as those came up. Mostly just playing and writing and having fun and being wild and allowing ourselves to be wild. Then Justin wound up moving to LA and he told us, “Get Jordan. This guy’s right on your level.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, Justin not only kind of helped them to stay together when they were first starting, as Tom was mentioning, but his last contribution was to recommend me, which seems to have worked out pretty well. At least, speaking personally. I’m still thrilled after all these years. I knew Justin through school. We were actually schoolmates studying basically on the same track of Temple University’s jazz studies program. We were both upright bass players at the school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: And I was there, too. So we were all in the same music school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, Chrissie was at Temple as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: It makes sense that we would have–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Matt was at Temple for a week, but that’s a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8L8IfJlgarA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: But that’s where I met him and we kind of opened each other’s eyes to different types of music and we realized that was–we were kind of both geeks in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;meeting Chrissie was way better education than the actual teachers there.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So it sounds like you guys have a mission of blending as much music as possible and that’s, to me, very evident on the third album because one song, “Oasis,” I don’t know who wrote that song but it’s a work of genius. [Laughs as everyone points to Chrissie.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u9iCmqCBXB0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s an incredible piece of music. And then, like, two or three tracks later, it’s like all of “California” from Mr. Bungle without any of the cartoon-y sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Right. Well, that’s kind of what I was saying. We kind of smooth the quirkiness a little bit. It’s more beautiful than quirky and off-putting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But then there’s another song where Chrissie is singing Indian melodies with very fast stepping between notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Light at the Endless Tunnel” excerpts]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Oh yeah, yeah. You know, that song was really influenced by that–you know that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consider_the_Source&quot;&gt;Consider the Source&lt;/a&gt; band?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, they’re awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, we toured with them our first tour and me and Gabe [Marin] go all the way back. He’d just tell me about scales. So that song is just based on this one Indian scale that’s their version of pentatonic. The whole song is that scale, so it’s kind of like our version of a raga or something, mixed with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Glass&quot;&gt;Philip Glass&lt;/a&gt; or something totally not related to that. But that was totally influenced by Consider the Source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, that makes sense. All right, so–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: You kind of hear their influence in “AYA” a little bit in moments. We play more chords than they do, so that would be the biggest difference, but yeah we really like them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s next for you guys? Tom, I think, mentioned that you’re in the studio. What’s going on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: We’re just demoing new tracks that we made, but we don’t have a concrete plans as of now, but we have another record written. So, we’re just in the process of figuring out what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nPg12O61Etk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah, if anyone’s been paying attention to the videos we’ve been releasing online, some of them have the full show of the last couple of shows that we played and there are some songs that are not released on the third record, sort of implying that there is more to come. It’s always a good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, I mentioned earlier, I took my daughter to Costco today and we were listening to your album and I said “What did you think of that?” And she said, “It was weird,” which I think is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: That’s fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But I want to know, as a band that is really focused on “new” and “different” and “mish-mash”–these are all terms I’ve heard many times so far–how are you reaching audiences and how are they receiving what you’re putting together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: I think since the third record, we’ve been amazingly well-received. We went down to North Carolina in September and played &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.progday.net/&quot;&gt;Prog Day&lt;/a&gt; and we sold out of all our CDs, we made a ton of money in merch. Everyone rushed us after we were done. People talked about us on the message board, the word got out more, so that was kind of one of the biggest hitting-the-target moments we’ve had booking-wise. All the reviews have been incredible. So the word’s getting out there. It’s just us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We’re strictly DIY. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We don’t have a promotion team, we didn’t hire PR, we don’t have a booking agent.&lt;/span&gt; It’s just us and considering that, the album is standing on its own pretty well. I got a message from Italy the other day, this guy who’s just obsessed with it, he’s trying to get us over there. I don’t push us over there, it’s just getting around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In the age of the internet and the sort of bleak musical economic environment, for a band like us, that’s a good sign. It’s a reason to be optimistic about the future, you know? We’re not making a lot of money, but our goals were artistic, not commercial, and I think we’re all satisfied in that way. And I think that’s what the band’s about. It’s not about what’s working right now in the industry, what’s selling right now, how many likes and followers we have. No, it’s about the record. It’s about the substance and I think that’s what we’re bringing that’s countering a lot of what’s going on.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Worth the Wait” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: I’ll answer this with two answers. It’s difficult for us to attain mass appeal. We gotta understand that from the jump. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But there are millions of people that like weird music.&lt;/span&gt; First thing we did when we dropped the album is we started contacting as many people as we could to get reviews. The reviews were outstanding. We couldn’t–I mean, people were just saying the most amazing stuff. It’s almost like–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We’re humbled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We played last week and someone came up to me and was like, “You’re my favorite band.” I was like, “This is my favorite band!” I couldn’t lie. I was like, “When I go to sleep, I think of music that’s dope and cool.” This is what I imagine.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: That’s cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: It’s been very well received to the right people. Mass appeal? No. But the people who do like this type of music will love it. It’s been a great year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah yeah. So far, the internet’s been really nice to connect us and we’ve been getting a little bit more word of mouth spreading this year. It’s been fun. It’s been nice to see that we can put an album out and people are actually reacting to it. It’s not just like, “Oh, there’s another album on bandcamp,” you know? Everybody does that, and it’s important to do that because you’ve gotta make your stuff available however you can, but it’s nice to see that people are actually checking it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5qY8arvbQCI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, it’s nice not to be ignored because there’s so much out there and most stuff does get ignored. I feel like the people that are connecting with what we are doing, it really means something to them. And I guess for me personally, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the low-to-the-ground approach is better in the long run because 5-10 years from now, you’ll still have those people whereas if you just make a catchy song and a million people get into it for two months, and then they leave, what did you really build there?&lt;/span&gt; It just seems like, “Let’s go up the roller coaster and get off.” I would want something more permanent than that. I like to think that we’ve attained that. I don’t really know, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I would classify your music as art. And that’s what I’m after. True artists who use music as their form of expression. So, it’s funny. Tom wrote to me months ago, I don’t remember–I think you just said, “Hey, here’s my stuff,” and I get a lot of those emails, but when I heard “Oasis,” I was like, “I gotta check this out later.” And when I listened with real intention, I was like, “Oh my goodness, these guys are awesome.” [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Thank you so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: We really appreciate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so what’s going on in 2018 for you and where can people find out more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Well, we’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=122617694436220&amp;amp;ref=br_rs&quot;&gt;on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, we’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://infinien.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;on Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;, we’re exploring booking options right now, we’re demoing new stuff, there’ll be a new release sometime.. In the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When it’s ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Right, when it’s ready is the key there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: But, way sooner than the other–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Yeah, there was a bit of a gap between the self-titled album and the “Light at the Endless Tunnel” unfortunately. But that’s definitely not going to be the case this time. We can say that for sure. We can also say the four of us are very committed to making this record better than the one we just put out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah, that’s very true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We had the same mentality when we made “Light at the Endless Tunnel,” which was like, “We put our heart and soul into the Infinien record,” which is why we had to call it that. We couldn’t come up with a title because it was just like, “Well, this is everything we are,” so that’s why that record was self-titled. But I’m sorry, a little bit of a digression there. But, yeah, when we made the third one, it was like, “It has to sound better, we have to do this, we have to do that.” And it totally fueled us. We put together an orchestra. That was a weird dream–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: That was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: that we took into reality. All of a sudden we were standing–there’s a video of us online recording next to two enormous orchestra-sized harps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aVuFmuShkyE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, there’s like 4 harps on that track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: And it’s real! Those aren’t fake instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: That was a total mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: That was so beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: That’s also in the credits. You can see the list of orchestral players. I was lucky enough to play upright bass on that, too. Saved us a little bit of bread. [Laughs.] But anyway, yeah we’re very committed to making a new release that is even better than the third one, which we’re pretty happy with. All things considered. We can rest easy knowing that we made a really solid album. Or at least I can. Are you guys sleeping all right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: This next album is–like I said, these guys are my favorite band and this next album is just so, so good. I don’t even know what to say. I’m excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: There’s no album yet, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: This year. Maybe not. I hope so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: I feel like one of the reasons why people who like it really like it is because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we’ve always been honest with ourselves and I think that maybe it’s not going to be popular, but it’s our truth and the truth is undeniable.&lt;/span&gt; So, when you’re honest with the way you need to express it, then somebody somewhere out there who’s gets it is going to get it. So, I feel like we can always be proud of what we’ve done because we’ve always been doing it honestly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We never did anything we didn’t want to do to get more people into the band. Ever. Everything was based on curiosity, exploration, innocence.&lt;/span&gt; None of us are innocent, but you know what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I also feel like what I like so much about what we’ve found is that it’s a mix between chaos and beauty. I think that that’s the whole universe. Maybe that’s what weird music is. It’s not just beautiful, it’s not just chaotic, but it’s the blend.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, I totally agree with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: It kind of captures you in all of your facets. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I would love to explore that chaos and order. That’s been a major theme going on the last few months in the philosophy I’ve been reading, but we don’t really have time for that. [Laughs.] So for anyone who’s new to you guys, what’s the best way to find out about you, find out more, and what’s the best way to support you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We’re on Facebook, Instagram, and all the recorded music is available to check out on Bandcamp and all of the other streaming services. Spotify, Google Play Music, Apple Music, Amazon. I believe it’s available. A friend of ours has a joke that you should have a t-shirt that says sorry I missed your gig. And there’s another t-shirt that says, “My music is highly available.” Anyway, Facebook is probably–between Facebook and Instagram is probably the best way to keep in touch as far as that goes. But, I’ve always said this to anybody who’s been interested in the band. Shoot us an email! It’s the band’s name at gmail.com [infinien@gmail.com].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Yeah, we like hearing from people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: We like people reaching out to us. It’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: It’s a core group of people right now, so it’s very community-esque. Don’t feel like we’re on an ivory tower. We love hearing from fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: Yeah and if you go to Bandcamp, you can find our whole collection. You can get our CDs, t-shirts, there’s some merch, a biography, and some stuff. If you want to see us, YouTube. We’re building our content this year, so expect more videos coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6_frjTIDeZA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: You keep mentioning “Oasis,” there is a really good capture of that song that we just released on YouTube through a company called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sun_Sessions&quot;&gt;Sun Sessions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I saw it. It’s all solar-powered. That was so cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: It is really cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Oasis” excerpt]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: And then we just happened to be–it was the last hot day of last year. It was already starting to be a cold fall and then it was just this one day of abundant sunshine and it was like, “Jeez, it’s almost 80 degrees out.” It was kind of weird, so now we’re releasing in winter these sunny videos. But yeah, that’s a good capture of that. If you like that, there’s probably–a little bird told me there’s another one of those videos coming out soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, cool. Thank you guys so much for your time. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MH: Thank you so much&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CL: Thank you so much. I was going to say the best way to support us is what you’re doing. You’re spreading the word and you listen. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JB: Keep making weird music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;TC: And hit us up on Skype! [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JB: Thank you so much for having us. Infinien is a band we all believe in so dearly. We put so much energy into it and we just love so much that it is contagious. It seems to be, anyway. We just want to keep spreading it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/infinien/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/infinien/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>California Guitar Trio Plays Daydreaming By Radiohead</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cgtrio.com&quot;&gt;The California Guitar Trio&lt;/a&gt; performed a show at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mim.org&quot;&gt;Musical Instrument Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Phoenix, Arizona on February 24, 2018. Before the show, we spent about an hour talking and filmed a great interview, which should be online and available later this month. In the meantime, I wanted to release this beautiful performance of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiohead&quot;&gt;Radiohead&lt;/a&gt;’s song &lt;em&gt;Daydreaming&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our first 4K video release, too. So, hopefully you high-fidelity video fans enjoy that! It’s still new to me, but I’m happy with how it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SBW5DMA1rvU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here’s the original music video by Radiohead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TTAU7lLDZYU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/california-guitar-trio/daydreaming</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/california-guitar-trio/daydreaming</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Taurus Bulba E Mixolydian Riffage</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-this-riff&quot;&gt;Why This Riff?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most innovative guitarists to ever live. This riff from his 1996 release &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_Garden&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fire Garden&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has always impressed me since I learned it over 20 years ago. It’s artistic, fun, and caters especially to the instrument. When you actually play this lick, you can really appreciate the intricacies and the craft that went into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fire-garden/190372450&quot;&gt;Purchase Steve Vai’s Fire Garden on Apple Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-apple&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always been one of my favorite go-to riffs that I play to warm up. It’s fun, difficult, and in the key of A (E mixolydian), so it’s hard to play a wrong note since the guitar is basically built for the keys of A and E.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the instructional video for this piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kRR1UtuUlZA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soundslice-notation&quot;&gt;Soundslice Notation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/150973/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/taurus-bulba</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/taurus-bulba</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nora Germain</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nora Germain is a multi-talented powerhouse of music, energy, and inspiration. She sings, she dances, she rips it up on the violin, she writes books, and more. I first heard about Nora through &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; when he told me about her involvement in the &lt;a href=&quot;/share/tiny-orchestral-moments&quot;&gt;Tiny Orchestral Moments&lt;/a&gt; project. Steve got us in touch and we got this interview filmed in December 2017 while she was visiting Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DffgiVSWQZE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/nora-germain/nora-germain.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/nora-germain/nora-germain.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Nora Germain is a jazz violinist and singer out of LA and she is joining us to talk a little bit about her new album, called Nora, and about some of the challenges of being an artist in today’s musical climate. So, Nora, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Thank you for having me, it’s a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Awesome. So, I’m really thrilled that you could be here. I’ve talked to &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt;, a mutual friend, about you many months ago and I saw how busy you were. I thought, “Wow, it’d be really cool to talk to her, but I don’t know if the stars will ever align. So, thanks a lot. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Of course, of course. I’m very excited. &lt;a href=&quot;/shirts&quot;&gt;Everybody I know wears your t-shirt&lt;/a&gt;, so I feel like I’m part of the gang now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, well I’ll have to mail one out to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: I’d love to have one. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Nora, can you give us a brief history of your musical career and then tell us a little about your new album?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Sure, so I started playing violin when I was really small. My parents were both violinists. When I was 15, I found an interest in playing jazz, so I sort of switched from classical violin to jazz. And then two or three years ago, I realized that I really wanted to sing. I didn’t really realize I wanted to do that until kind of later on. I’d already been playing music for 20 years or whatever. So I made some jazz violin albums and then slowly started to introduce the voice into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then in the last year or so, maybe two years even after I started singing jazz, I thought, “Well, maybe I should write my own music.” So I started exploring with this last record a sort of funk and pop sound because I love that stuff so much. And right now, I’m kind of working on how to make my jazz violin sound work with the original music that I am doing kind of as one big world. So, we’ll see how it goes. This record I did, this one that just came out, is sort of my first attempt at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m a big believer that you have to actually do something to know if it works. You can’t just think about if it would hypothetically work. You have to really try it and find out.&lt;/span&gt; So I’m learning a lot about myself and all that, going through the process, but it’s been a lot of fun. So, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZuyTYmQ_BcA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us about the world of jazz violin? I saw a quote on your website that might have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Taylor_(guitarist)&quot;&gt;Martin Taylor &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I forget who it was. It said that you’re keeping the world of jazz violin alive. I didn’t know there was a “world of jazz violin.” I imagine there’s a history, it’s just not an instrument that we normally associate with jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah, well, I mean people should associate violin with jazz because the violin was a very integral part of the blues music that jazz came out of, so the violin was kind of part of it even before the saxophone, which is a much newer instrument than the violin. The violin as we know it now has been around for 400, almost 500 years. Most of the violinists, the great jazz violinists, are from the past. There are a few living today who are great, but people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Nance&quot;&gt;Ray Nance &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuff_Smith&quot;&gt;Stuff Smith &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who played in a lot of the big bands, they were very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P_lrTmLknNA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then there was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Venuti&quot;&gt;Joe Venuti &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_South&quot;&gt;Eddie South &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who were one of the inspirations to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Django_Reinhardt&quot;&gt;Django Reinhardt &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St%C3%A9phane_Grappelli&quot;&gt;Stéphane Grappelli &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who of course were &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quintette_du_Hot_Club_de_France&quot;&gt;the first European all-string band &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And that, obviously, changed the world as well. Stéphane Grappelli is probably my favorite of all of them. But, there are a lot! Throughout history you find a lot of them. Most of them were American, but once Stéphane Grappelli and Django Reinhardt became famous, then this wave of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gypsy_jazz&quot;&gt;Gypsy Jazz &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came around and then you see a lot of all-string jazz bands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, especially this year and last year, I’ve seen there’s been a huge renaissance of that for some reason, which is very exciting. The violin in jazz was a lot more popular in the last century, but now because of this gypsy jazz renaissance, it’s becoming more popular and there are quite a few young people around the world who play jazz violin. But I don’t see that many violinists these days using what I use in the band, which is piano, bass, drums, and guitar for more of that kind of traditional American sound rather than the gypsy sound, which usually doesn’t have piano or drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, there’s definitely a world for it and I hope that I can continue to bring it more into the forefront of music rather than kind of a niche thing because I really do think, just like any other jazz instrument, it should be something that everybody can hear once in their life. But, yeah, there is a world for it, it’s just a little bit in the background right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve spoken to several out-of-the-box classical musicians and people who were trained with a classical background that ended up in the world of improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s not normally something that’s taught on classical instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: No, it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What was your background in moving from–I would assume you learned classically first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah, I did. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you get into improvisation and jazz, specifically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MpsLWI2vLHY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: There are a lot of ways to improvise on string instruments. There’s a lot of improvisation on American fiddle music and Celtic music. A lot of those fiddle tunes have a lot of–you sort of learn the tune and then you kind of make it your own and sort of pass it around a group of people. That was one of the first ideas I had about improvisation, was learning a lot of different styles of fiddle music and kind of making up my own fiddle tunes that were loosely based on the ones that I knew before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But then the jazz thing came around when I heard Stéphane Grappelli. I really remember the moment, it really changed my life.&lt;/span&gt; I heard it and it was a funny thing. I heard it and I felt like I already knew how to do it even though I didn’t know how to do it, but I heard it and I thought, “Oh yeah, I can do that.” Even though it took me many years to actually do it. [Laughs.] But, yeah, string instruments are not usually used to improvise, which is a shame because we see–to take another example, dancers, there’s all different types of dancers. There’s ballet dancers, modern dancers, tap dancers, flamenco dancers. And if you grow up as a ballerina, you might not have the kind of swag that a tap dancer has, you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think it’s all about taking different things in and figuring out what speaks to you because if it speaks to you, you can probably do it.&lt;/span&gt; That’s what I’ve found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HfwouH794jI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I watched a video of you playing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy_Emmanuel&quot;&gt;Tommy Emmanuel &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He’s one of my heroes. I attended one of his master classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Oh yeah, he’s great. I love him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But, I think I saw in one of the comments that you guys hadn’t even rehearsed the songs you performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: No. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I heard so many influences, particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_O%27Connor&quot;&gt;Mark O’Connor &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in your improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I was just floored at your ability to play over these changes, especially–I mean, obviously, the song and Tommy’s an incredible musician himself, but to see you two just getting up and playing–do you attribute that to your bluegrass study or is it just something that you started doing when you were young and it’s natural to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, obviously, when you play with somebody who’s so great and you feel like you can click like that, you don’t really have to think about what you’re doing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s like saying, “How do you go to a restaurant with your best friend and not get into an argument?” Well, you just sit down and you have a great time.&lt;/span&gt; There is no argument. It’s a very effortless thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The things that do take effort are, obviously, being able to play at fast tempos. You have to work on that. You have to keep yourself pretty loose. Practicing songs in all of the different keys so that if somebody says, “Let’s play this” in a different key than you’re used to and you’re in front of a thousand people, you don’t panic. You can just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Stage presence is something I work on, making the audience feel like I care that they are there and not just taking them for granted. And really playing so that they can enjoy themselves, not so that I can enjoy that they’re enjoying me. There definitely are skills that are part of that, I think, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I feel like the less you think, the easier it is.&lt;/span&gt; I really–you have to think about it when you practice and you have to think about it when you’re researching things. If you go to school, you have to think about it then, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when you’re in the moment of actually doing it, you have to let it all go otherwise you’re not really there.&lt;/span&gt; You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You won’t be able to use all this background information that you’re consciousness kind of has. It’s not really words. It’s kind of like feelings. I don’t know exactly how to explain it. What I’m trying to say is that if you just let yourself be natural, there is all sorts of help that you already have to making whatever you’re trying to do great without overthinking it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, the knowledge is already there. You’re just losing any of the firewalls that stand between you and connecting with the music at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, right. I’m not saying that I could have done that the same way when I was 10 years old. I’ve been practicing for a long time. Obviously, it’s not just automatic, but once you have the skill down, if you just let your mind go quiet and just enjoy it, it’ll always be much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I couldn’t believe how fast you guys were playing. Not just performing, but playing off of each other and spur-of-the-moment decisions… As a musician myself, I saw what you were doing and I thought, “Oh my goodness, they’re at a whole other level of communication.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well yeah! That’s what I’m saying. If you stop thinking about it, you can actually communicate really quickly between people. Like if you watch any of the great performers. If you watch the Rat Pack or anybody in any genre, you always see this kind of instantaneous thing and you realize people are not really communicating using regular communication techniques of human life. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Tommy and I are not going to talk about what we’re going to do. I don’t have to look at him for him to know what he needs to do. You just kind of let it run free. It takes a little bit of telekinesis, maybe, but I think that humans do already possess a bit of telekinesis.&lt;/span&gt; I think it’s possible. Maybe not in the, you know, conspiracy sense where I could think of an object and you would tell me what the object is. But certainly in a way that if two people have a vision in mind and they don’t really think about much else, that vision will probably come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you said you’re trying to put some ideas together in the context of who you are and what you’re capable of doing and this new album is an expression of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yeah, right. I’m definitely trying to do something new. Always something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the things that you feel are “new” about this record and who you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s so easy for people to say, “Oh, I’ve seen you do ‘this,’ therefore you’re this one thing.”&lt;/span&gt; “Nora, you’re a great jazz violinist, so why would you ever try another style?” I just think life is short and you don’t want to save anything for the next go-around because you’re not sure if you’re going to get one. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, you might as well try everything that you love right now even if it comes out a little bit messy in the beginning.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People might say, “Oh, you needed more time in the studio,” or, “You should have re-recorded that vocal,” or, “Your videos are not the greatest thing I’ve ever seen.” That’s fine and I’m fine to take criticism because at least I have experiments that I’m doing. You know? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’d much rather find out by doing something and releasing it, find out what I like about it, what I don’t like, what I can do better, what I might do again, what I might not do again, and then change accordingly or not change accordingly, rather than not test anything out and just never sing and never dance and never write anything and never make any music videos. I just think it’s so much better to experiment, even if sometimes you have to learn some hard lessons. But God, why shy away from that?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Done is better than perfect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: I think so. Maybe at this stage. I’m not sure if I’m going to keep going–you don’t want to experiment in the same way when you’re young as when you’re older because hopefully when you’re older you’ve gotten a lot of that stuff out of the way. But, I’m 26. I’m on the young side of life. I have an opportunity to do something, maybe, that hasn’t exactly been done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Who says that you can’t have a show when you sing a pop song and then you play a lovely ballad on the violin? Or, whatever! Who says that you have to do any one thing? So, I guess I’m just trying to figure out how to put it all together, but definitely don’t want to have any passion that I don’t test out. That would be–to me, that would be a big mistake because you always want to try anything that speaks to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: In the spirit of youth and experimentation, one of the things that drew me to you recently was a Facebook comment thread [laughs].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Oh, God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I don’t normally get into these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: You ought not to. You ought not to, that’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, but you had addressed some of the challenges of being an artist in today’s world of streaming and financial ruin or whatever where I think older people have a sense of, “This is how the industry used to be and now it’s not this anymore.” As a young up-and-comer in the music industry, can you talk a little about your beliefs and some of the spirit of these kinds of discussions? What you see and where you are?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, one thing about being a millennial is you have nothing to compare this disastrous non-industry to, so that’s very comfortable in a sense because I can’t sit around and say, “Oh, back in the 70s” or “back in the 80s things were so great” because I wasn’t alive then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The idea of making money off of people buying your records, making thousands and thousands of dollars off of that, even as a small artist, that to me sounds kind of crazy. Who’s going to buy them?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of these discussions, generally there’s a few different sides of it. There’s usually some kind of a pessimist who says, “It’s all over and there’s no point in anything anymore.” And then there’s somebody who’s usually very ignorant who says, “Oh, but I support artists because I stream their music and hopefully they see some kind of revenue from that.” And then you see some kind of a tech person who says, “Oh, it’s just the kinks. It’ll all get worked out. There’ll be a future with different types of revenue streams.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then you find somebody who takes things into their own hands and says, “Well fuck the whole industry. I’ve got my Patreon and I’ll be fine.” And then maybe you find somebody who’s still kind of clinging on to what once was and thinks they can get a major record deal and, for better or worse, they can kind of make it work. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m kind of all of those people wrapped into one, I guess, because I do believe that we’re in kind of a dire situation, but I also believe that we don’t know what is going to happen with the music industry five or ten or a hundred years from now.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are ways that we purchase and consume music that nobody could conceive of a while back, so obviously there are going to be new ways that come up that people haven’t thought of yet. But yeah, I’m trying to figure it out. I don’t think that anybody really has a total answer for you, even somebody who would say, “Oh yeah, I know what’s going to happen,” or, “I know the best way to make a living as an artist.” They’re probably just lying to you because I think that every artist has their own possibilities for making money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Again, you just have to try stuff. You really can’t just sit on your couch thinking, “Oh, maybe I could try this. Maybe I could do that. Maybe I can sell 500 records doing this. Or maybe…”&lt;/span&gt; You really have to try, so that’s kind of the route that I take. I just try what seems appealing to me and I learn from doing it. I’ve done a couple of crowd-funding campaigns that were really successful and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/noragermainlovesyou&quot;&gt;I’m thinking of going over to Patreon next &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-patreon&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I play with other people and I do recording sessions and things. It’s a hodge-podge, but we’re in a transition so you’ve gotta try stuff if you want to make it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4zH9Zca1vRM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so I see you forming a lot of one-offs with a broad variety of artists. You’ve recorded with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knower_(band)&quot;&gt;Knower &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and you’ve performed with Tommy Emmanuel and Martin Taylor. Kind of two ends of pretty different spectrums, you know? How are you reaching out to these people and connecting with them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, with Louis [Cole] and Genevieve [Artadi], I used to live with them so I’ve recorded on a few different projects for Louis and he used to play drums with my group sometimes. Genevieve would sing with my group now and again and I’m in a few of their music videos as well, so we were just roommates that were trying to help each other out whenever we could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But in general, one thing I really believe in in my life is if you get in touch with people, some of the time they will respond. I mean, a lot of people don’t even believe that is true. I think of a list of people I want to work with and I write to them and tell them I want to work with them on something. I’ll ask if I can be a guest on their show or if they want to have me on their record. Some of the time it does happen and it’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I think you just have to reach out to people and be honest and try to see in your mind what you want to do with them before you ask them. It would be great for me to work with Elton John, for example, but I haven’t really thought about–I guess now I could. I haven’t thought about exactly what he and I would do together, so I would probably have it in my mind, like when I did a show, Postmodern Jukebox, last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There was a video we did that got some pretty good views. When they reached out to me to be in the video, they had an idea. They had a song they wanted to do, they knew how they wanted the violin to be featured. Once you reach out to somebody, you want to kind of envision it so that if they get back to you and say, “Well, sure, that sounds cool. What do you want to do?” You’re not thinking, “Well, uh…” You want to have something in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If people reach out to me and say they want to work with me, I’d definitely consider it because we’re artists. We want to create stuff. We want to have fun. And it’s great to share audiences.&lt;/span&gt; It’s great when my audience will discover somebody new or somebody else, discover me, whatever. That’s kind of what it’s all about. I like to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Speaking of collaborations, you worked with Steve Ball and lots of the crafty guitar crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Recently on &lt;a href=&quot;/share/tiny-orchestral-moments-2017&quot;&gt;Tiny Orchestral Moments&lt;/a&gt; projects. How’d you get connected to them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Okay, so that happened through my brother. My brother was involved with those projects and he’s been a crafty for a long time and he’s known Steve for a long time. They were in Los Angeles working on a different project, happened to be my birthday actually, and Carl [Germain] was in LA and he said, “Well, I can’t really hang out with you, but why don’t you come to this rehearsal and hang out and listen?” And I said, “Okay, great!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vcXo3owlGpY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I came and I had my violin because I always have my violin and Steve and Paul Richards from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Guitar_Trio&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who I’ve also worked with, they invited me to play on this tune called Blockhead. I think there’s a video of it somewhere, but–so I just jumped in. I didn’t know what I was doing. It’s like twenty-five guitar players and me, you know? But Steve thought it was cool and fun and wacky and whatever, so I think he was kind of interested in breaking out of the traditional guitar craft modalities and sort of getting into something a little bit more out-of-the-box, inviting other types of instruments to play along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So he decided to do this Tiny Orchestral Moments thing. We’ve done two projects with that. I’ve been a part of both of them and I’ve made some amazing friends. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/julie-slick&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt; has been on two of them, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Petra_Haden&quot;&gt;Petra Haden &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was on one of them, who’s an amazing violinist, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigel_Gavin&quot;&gt;Nigel Gavin &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who’s a long-time crafty and an amazing kind of world music musician. My brother and I have gotten closer doing it and I got to record with California Guitar Trio on their last album because of this collaboration. It’s been a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I never would have considered that I would do something like this, necessarily, but music is an amazing thing because you can’t really be hurt by it. There’s nobody’s life that is at stake when you try something new. You just jump in and see how it goes. Most of the time, it’s a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MogTq30DMYU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One thing I really appreciate about your music is there’s a recurring theme of being yourself, expressing yourself, being true to yourself. Can you talk a little about that and where that motivation is coming from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, I think I was a victim of repressing a lot of my own creative passions for a long time. [Laughs.] And I only realized that kind of recently. A couple years ago. I grew up singing and dancing and playing piano and I–oh my God, I did so many different types of dance. I was a really creative person, really creative kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Violin was always something I took very seriously, but I had a lot of other talents. I was in musicals and I did all sorts of stuff. And then when high school came around I discovered jazz, I thought, “I want to be the best in the world at this thing and I want to bring this thing back. I want to hold the torch up. I want people to love jazz violin.” And that became a very deep focus for me for about ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In high school and then at both of the colleges that I went to, I really focused on that. And also because I didn’t really have any jazz violin teachers except for one briefly–I took lessons with the late John Blake Jr. who’s an amazing player, but that was only for one semester. So basically for nine and a half years, I was on my own. I didn’t really have any jazz violin teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I guess because I had to study so hard and I had to figure so much stuff out, I didn’t really sing or dance or write anything because I just wanted to be good at this one thing. It’s like hyper-focused. And I’m very grateful for that because I love the way I sound now and I really am proud of how far I’ve come with that. It was not easy. But anyway, a couple years ago I thought, “You know, there’s this whole side of me that I kind of left in the dark.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So, being yourself, expressing yourself, is really about remembering who you were when you were a kid, who you were before you cared about if people were going to subscribe to your stupid YouTube channel and all that stuff&lt;/span&gt;, which matters. It definitely matters, but you’re not going to live a rich life if you’re blocking out… “Oh I can’t do this, I can’t do that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not who you are that holds you back, it’s who you think you’re not that holds you back.&lt;/span&gt; [Laughs.] So, it can be messy. I’m not saying it’s easy to incorporate all of your interests. And maybe some of your interests just are hobbies. I’m not saying that everything you love in life has to be part of your commercial product, but I definitely think if there’s a part of you that you kind of left when you were a kid, if there’s a skill that you had or something that really gave you a lot of joy, you don’t have to start from scratch. You just have to remember how to do it again because you did know how to do it before. If that makes any sense…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZPAmDULCVrU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I’m just trying to not let anything go. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I just want to be myself and all of my favorite performers are people who do lots of different things.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Gaga&quot;&gt;Lady Gaga &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; comes to mind. She’s done so much different art, but it’s all very authentic because it all really comes from her. She can sit down at the piano and that’s one mood and she can light herself on fire or whatever she’s doing and then make a record with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Bennett&quot;&gt;Tony Bennett &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then be on stage with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica&quot;&gt;Metallica &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-wikipedia-w&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s all available to you. You know? You don’t have to close yourself off. So that’s kind of the place I’m at now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That is awesome. That’s ultimately what this Make Weird Music website is about. I get a lot of people reaching out just sending me some of the most outlandish music you’ve ever heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Sure. Sure, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: While I appreciate that about the word “weird,” mostly I want people to be connecting with who they are because we’re all unique and weird in our own way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes we are. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, yeah, I completely resonate with that and I’m really appreciative that there are artists like you who not only are virtuosic and incredible at what they do, but see that the picture’s not completely dry yet. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There’s still plenty of time to keep working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Well, right. And also just letting go of the fact of the idea that it has to be perfect the first time you try it. You know? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I just feel the things you create don’t have to be masterpieces the first time you create them.&lt;/span&gt; I guess there’s a whole school of thought about “Should you release something that’s an experiment? Or should you not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;People can go back and forth about that. You know, “you should only release the stuff that’s absolute perfection” or “you should release everything and the chips will fall where they may” and then there’s everywhere in between. But if you’re going to try something new or try something that you used to know, but you’ve left it and now you want to bring it back, you can see the total person and not just an adult version of yourself. It’s okay for it to be a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m not saying this album that I did is my full and total potential, but definitely it’s a new thing and it’s a step in a direction that I’ve never taken before. That definitely makes me proud, so there you go! [Laughs.] I’m proud of my mistakes!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. All right, so where can people find out more about you and your music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Right, okay, so I have a website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://noragermain.com&quot;&gt;noragermain.com &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-external-link-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And I’m on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/nora_germain/&quot;&gt;instagram &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/noragermainmusic/&quot;&gt;Facebook &lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-facebook&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and everything. But my website is kind of the hub for everything. I’ve got my videos and biography and some links to other stuff, so definitely go to my website. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Cool. Thank you so much for taking some time out of my day to talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Of course, I’m so happy to be included in your community and I’m thrilled. I consider it a badge of honor that you think I’m weird enough. I love it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs.] Well, I don’t think anyone would listen to the music and go, “That’s really weird,” but I think it’s what you’re doing, the way you’re doing it, it’s just another definition of “weird.” You’re being true to who you are and I think it’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;NG: Yes, well thank you and thank you for being true to who you are by doing all of this. You’re doing an amazing thing. People should remember that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you. Sweet. That’s very kind of you. All right, thank you so much. It was really great spending time with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NG: You too!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/nora-germain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/nora-germain/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aspirations by Gentle Giant feat. Keneally, West, Green, Mortimore</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;aspirations&quot;&gt;Aspirations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of my favorite Gentle Giant songs and I was incredibly honored to be asked to join such tremendous musicians on stage for this performance. Never in my wildest dreams did I think I’d have an opportunity like this. Gary Green was a guitar hero for me growing up, and to look over to make eye contact while performing music with him is just indescribable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qNHidpbISNo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was performed live in October 2017 in Albuquerque, New Mexico for the 2017 &lt;a href=&quot;https://gorgg.org&quot;&gt;GORGG&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/gorgg-2017/aspirations</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/gorgg-2017/aspirations</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jan Zehrfeld Guitar Clinic</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;concert-trailer&quot;&gt;CONCERT TRAILER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DP2bb2Yu_Oc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incredible &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Jan Zehrfeld&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; will be offering a guitar clinic at our HQ (my living room). He’ll be covering fretboard navigation; 4-note chord voicings for 6-, 7-, and 8-string guitar players; and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nvite.com/JanZehrfeld&quot;&gt;Purchase tickets for the guitar clinic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm far fa-ticket-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Proceeds will go directly toward reimbursing our airfare and hotel costs for Jan.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-thanks&quot;&gt;SPECIAL THANKS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to our awesome sponsors Ed at &lt;a href=&quot;https://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mad Hatter Guitar Products&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fas fa-external-link-square-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Bobby at &lt;a href=&quot;http://guitaranswerguy.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Guitar Answer Guy&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fas fa-external-link-square-alt&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks also to the &lt;a href=&quot;/support&quot;&gt;generous donations we’ve received online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/concert/jan-zehrfeld-2018-clinic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/concert/jan-zehrfeld-2018-clinic/</guid>
        
        
        <category>concert</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Support Make Weird Music on Patreon</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/link/mwm-on-patreon</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/link/mwm-on-patreon</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
