<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>A resource for musicians to discover new artists, learn weird music techniques, listen to interviews, and share their weird music.
</description>
    <link>http://makeweirdmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://makeweirdmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2015 00:24:56 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2015 00:24:56 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Steve Vai</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks-to-our-sponsors&quot;&gt;Thanks To Our Sponsors!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://softwareplusplus.com&quot;&gt;Cory Berg at Software++&lt;/a&gt; and to &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlkingdom.com&quot;&gt;Carl King Creative&lt;/a&gt; for sponsoring this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cory is a software development and management expert who’s written a fantastic book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Software-Must-Have-Skills-Engineers-ebook/dp/B00U4ZRQC6&quot;&gt;Software++: Must-Have Skills for Engineers&lt;/a&gt;. There are a lot of software people I’ve met via Make Weird Music and Guitar Circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl is an expert filmmaker, author, and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/carl-king&quot;&gt;former musician&lt;/a&gt;. His book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Youre-Creative-Genius-Now-What/dp/1932907920&quot;&gt;So, You’re a Creative Genius… Now What?&lt;/a&gt;, has been a huge inspiration for me and many others. He filmed this interview and provided lots of great equipment and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-little-about-steve-vai&quot;&gt;A Little About Steve Vai&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Vai is a forward-thinking, virtuosic guitarist based in Los Angeles. He started his career in music with Frank Zappa in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-so-weird&quot;&gt;What’s So Weird?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of Steve’s work makes use of the following weird music techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time Signatures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Composition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virtuosity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-care&quot;&gt;Why I Care&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1996, I heard an instrumental guitar song on the radio (!!) that had the most incredible guitar playing I’d ever heard. It opened my eyes to new potential on the instrument and I had no idea that level of technicality, virtuosity, and musicality. The DJ said, “That was Steve Vai with his track &lt;em&gt;Juice&lt;/em&gt; off his new album, &lt;em&gt;Alien Love Secrets&lt;/em&gt;.” Immediately, I scrounged up all the cash and change I could, went to Best Buy (when they actually had a good selection of music for sale), and bought it for $9.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little did I know, Steve Vai was–and still is–one of the most innovative, inspired, and ambitious guitarists in the industry. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt; credited him with “impossible guitar parts” as the “stunt guitarist” of his band between 1980 and 1982. Between solo releases, he played with Alcatrazz, John Lydon’s Public Image Ltd, David Lee Roth, Alice Cooper, Whitesnake, and Ozzy Osbourne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His solo releases through the 1990s were mind-blowing. &lt;em&gt;Passion and Warfare&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alien Love Secrets&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Fire Garden&lt;/em&gt; were in my CD player for months. I bought every used guitar magazine and tablature book I could find to learn those songs. There are enough weird music techniques in these albums for decades of worthwhile study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through Steve’s music (especially sheet music), I learned an incredible amount about time signatures, composition, instrumentation, key modulations, humor, crossing multiple genres, experimentation, and virtuosity. He’s been a huge inspiration to my own guitar and composition techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Vai has had a long, incredible history of trailblazing in the instrumental rock genre and he shows no sign of stopping. Every album features intricately planned and executed melodic explorations, rapid-fire blues-based riffage, and new sounds like you’ve never heard out of a guitar. His discography covers all sorts of ground from straightforward blues/rock to completely whacked-out alien noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-should-hear-first&quot;&gt;What You Should Hear First&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve never listened to Steve, here’s where to start:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For groundbreaking guitar rock: &lt;em&gt;Passion and Warfare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For completely weird, Zappa-esque outlandishness: &lt;em&gt;Flexable&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For compositional complexity: &lt;em&gt;Fire Garden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for an album with one genre/version of Steve, you’re not going to find it. He sticks to no particular genre and offers something for everyone. My favorite pieces of his are the extended-length exploratory pieces, like &lt;em&gt;Freak Show Excess&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fire Garden Suite&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Story of Light&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Lucky Charms&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you’re looking for something REALLY out there, check out his performance of &lt;em&gt;Fire Strings&lt;/em&gt; with the Tokyo Metropolitan Symphony Orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-vai</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-vai</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hell&#39;s Bells by Bruford</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Let’s pick apart the catchy hook from the song &lt;em&gt;Hell’s Bells&lt;/em&gt; off the 1979 release &lt;em&gt;One of a Kind&lt;/em&gt; by the fusion/rock band, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/bruford&quot;&gt;Bruford&lt;/a&gt;. (NOTE: It is not a cover of the AC/DC song with the same name! At least, I don’t think it is.) It features Allan Holdsworth on guitar, Jeff Berlin on bass, Dave Stewart on keyboards, and Bill Bruford on drums. The song’s intro alone contains odd &lt;a href=&quot;http://makeweirdmusic.com/techniques/time-signatures&quot;&gt;time signatures&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://makeweirdmusic.com/techniques/key-modulations&quot;&gt;key modulations&lt;/a&gt; that make it an interesting topic worthy of study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wNCSTNHejAY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/art/master/bill-bruford/hells-bells/hells-bells-slide-time-signatures-section-A-1067x600.png&quot; alt=&quot;A section: 19/8 = 7/8 + 7/8 + 5/8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is each phrase is 19 beats (eighth notes/quavers) composed of a bar of 7, a bar of 7, and a bar of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/art/master/bill-bruford/hells-bells/hells-bells-slide-time-signatures-section-B-1067x600.png&quot; alt=&quot;B section: 19/8 = 4/8 + 4/8 + 4/8 + 4/8 + 3/8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section starts with the Gb chord (fingers in the section below) and ends with the Am7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/art/master/bill-bruford/hells-bells/hells-bells-slide-time-signatures-section-C-1067x600.png&quot; alt=&quot;C section: 19/8 ¿ 11.3/9 ≥ 17/3 ? (It&#39;s a joke)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just kidding on that last one…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/wNCSTNHejAY&quot;&gt;watching the video&lt;/a&gt; above to make sure you hear me play through each section and you can count it out yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this song makes use of odd &lt;a href=&quot;http://makeweirdmusic.com/techniques/time-signatures&quot;&gt;time signatures&lt;/a&gt;, but what may not be obvious by glancing at the chords is that it also employs regular &lt;a href=&quot;http://makeweirdmusic.com/techniques/key-modulations&quot;&gt;key modulations&lt;/a&gt;. What I find most interesting about the key modulations is the keys change between Bb major and E major, two notes that form &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tritone&quot;&gt;a “tritone” interval relationship&lt;/a&gt; that sound pretty ugly when played together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the chords and fingerings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;      BbM7add2   Bb2      Gb      Fm7    Cadd2/E     C        Am7
  e   -10----   ----   -------   -----   ------   ------   --------
T B   ----10-   -11-   -------   ---6-   --8---   ----8-   -10p8---
A G   -10-10-   -10-   -----6-   -8---   ----7-   --9---   ------9-
B D   -10-10-   -10-   -6h8---   -6---   -10---   -10---   -10-----
  A   -13-13-   -13-   -9-----   -8---   --7---   -10---   --0-----
  E   -------   ----   -------   -----   ------   --8---   --------
         E2         Gb2
      -7-----   --9-------
      ---7-9-   -----9-11-
      -9-9-9-   -11-11-11-
      -9-9-9-   -11-11-11-
      -7-7-7-   --9--9--9-
      -0-0-0-   ----------
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several brave souls who’ve recorded covers of “Hell’s Bells” on youtube, often of varying quality. The song is quite complex and was proven to be a challenge even for Mike Portnoy, Billy Sheehan, Derek Sherinian, and Tony MacAlpine! (Skip to 1:50 to check it out)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/QmCJRciBZRQ?t=1m47s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should you find yourself learning this song, let me know! I’d love to hear it!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://makeweirdmusic.com/learn/hells-bells</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://makeweirdmusic.com/learn/hells-bells</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
