<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>A resource for musicians to discover new artists, learn weird music techniques, listen to interviews, and share their weird music.
</description>
    <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2016 22:28:31 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2016 22:28:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discover Barbara Hannigan</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/barbara-hannigan/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/barbara-hannigan/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Paul Hanson Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is our interview with the amazing Paul Hanson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Hanson&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Paul Hanson is? Check out his wikipedia page! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview was conducted on Sunday, December 6 at 11AM in Paul’s home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AUDIO COMING SOON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/paul-hanson/paul-hanson-interview-mwm-20151206.mp3&quot; controls preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

Or, [download an mp3&amp;nbsp;&lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;](http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/paul-hanson/paul-hanson-interview-mwm-20151206.mp3).--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NtdaEW5ARcQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VIDEO COMING SOON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com. I’m here with Paul Hanson. Paul, part of the mission of the site is to help musicians discover other great musicians who are doing new and different things. So, you’re a perfect candidate. Why don’t you tell us about yourself, a little of your musical history, and how you ended up where you are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Paul: Okay, well, to make it short… Yes, I guess I’m best known as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bassoon&quot;&gt;bassoon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; player (this instrument right here). Outside of classical music, I’d say jazz, fusion, funk, world music, contemporary classical music… I started at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkeley,_California&quot;&gt;Berkeley &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as a high school student playing saxophone in jazz groups and bassoon in classical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1O9wZ_LbxGQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Somehow &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimi_Hendrix&quot;&gt;Jimi Hendrix &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; turned my head around and I started to think, “What is this great instrument that has all these great possibilities and different things it can do? Why can’t I go on stage and play with the band?” So, that’s kind of led to this. I have a career doing unusual music and I’d say unusual for the instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Tell us about that. What about your music is unusual for the bassoon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Well, usually bassoonists don’t improvise and they don’t amplify. It’s a classical instrument and a very classical in the sense that you’re very complementary in most performances. You are a supportive in a kind of mesh of an orchestra. You’re right between the high instruments and the low instruments. You’re kind of in the middle. You’re very homogenized as an orchestral bassoonist. As a chamber music instrument, usually you hear them in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vivaldi&quot;&gt;Vivaldi &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concerto_grosso&quot;&gt;concerto grosso &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You hear the soloist. In the bass part, you’ll hear basses, bassoons, harpsichords playing continuo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What I do that’s unusual is playing contemporary music. I play jazz, I’m pretty accomplished as a musician on this instrument in that style of music. So, you memorize tunes. Most bassoon players don’t do that. What you’re doing is you play in an orchestra, you play in a chamber ensemble, that kind of thing, and you certainly don’t play with drummers or guitar players. That’s usually what I’d call the unique thing that I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Can you tell us how you ended up bridging the gap from playing bassoon in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orchestra&quot;&gt;chamber or orchestra ensemble &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah, well, this is the thing that’s where you’re young, you’re headstrong, you have all these ideas, and sometimes later in life you wonder: “Hmm… Did I really have to get that stubborn?” People have said, “You couldn’t do it. You’re not supposed to do that.” My teacher in conservatory was a fantastic teacher, I used to look up to him. I still look up to him today. When I had some lessons with him, I would be improvising in the lesson. He’d pop his head out when he was getting his coffee or something and say, “What’s that you’re playing?” I’d say, “Well, I just made it up.” And this happened all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xCXoCC83Y14?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Every instrument you play, you have an improvising tradition. I grew up in Berkeley, went to Berkeley High, was in the jazz band there. It was a very well-known jazz program in the 1970s. I thought &lt;em&gt;everybody&lt;/em&gt; improvised. You make up things, you play with people, it’s part of making music. So, when I found out that that’s not at all what the tradition’s about…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And also at the time, I hadn’t gotten some of the things I was looking for in classical music as a young person. I was very into Beethoven string quartets and very &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romantic_music&quot;&gt;Romantic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; amazing music. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cello&quot;&gt;Cellos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were playing and at that time I didn’t see much music like that on the bassoon, although there was and it wasn’t hitting me yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I thought, “You know, I just want to go out there and play with somebody.” It was something like, “Wow, no one’s ever done that.” I felt that this was something I could do and I enjoyed doing it. It wasn’t that hard to me, to a certain extent. I realized there was a lot of work involved, of course, but it was just a challenge to say, “Wow, this could be something that I love. It’s fun because nobody’s done this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also, I had a friend who was playing in the band who could play just about every instrument and the one instrument I knew he was never going to play was bassoon, so I said, “You know what? I’ll do the thing he can’t do.” It’s just the challenge that “something hasn’t happened on this instrument.” That’s kind of what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gi3GP3950KA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What led to it becoming something you could do to make money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Well, you start playing with people. Some of those very friends–they were young musicians, we had a band, people started hearing about me and networking when I was younger (I was probably a better networker then)–I was playing saxophone in many other bands, too. I also play tenor and alto saxophones. “You should hear this guy on bassoon.” And I’d say, “Oh sure, I’ll bring it down and hook it up.” Then, “Oh, it sounds good!” once I started playing the parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I started playing in Latin bands, salsa bands, Latin jazz. People enjoyed the sound of the instrument, not just as a soloist instrument, but also in a section in how it blends. That kept leading to different things. I played with a group called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Apfelbaum&quot;&gt;Peter Apfelbaum &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s Hieroglyphics Ensemble. We made a few records for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Island_Records&quot;&gt;Island Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; back in the early 1990s. They were a pretty big band in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bay_Area&quot;&gt;Bay Area &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the time. I had a forum to play with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I made a transition–a conscious decision–to go after it. It sometimes would involve going to jam sessions or going to a place where people would invite you to play and I’d bring my bassoon and they’d say, “What the hell is that thing?” And just the weirdest faces and you’re hoping that you sound right and they’re going to hear the instrument. I had a few forums when I was younger to get better, including a steady jazz gig where I played bassoon as well as sax. I alternated on the point of being a saxophone player who also plays bassoon versus a bassoon player who also plays sax. So, I just put myself in that position. Things had to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Back 25 years ago, I guess fusion music was more prevalent. You could play in local clubs doing it more often. Now it’s a long local level. It’s musician music, so it’s never been something that the numbers are too big, unless you’re playing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smooth_Jazz&quot;&gt;smooth jazz &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff, which is a different kind of feel. So, we’re playing at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoshi%27s_(jazz_club)&quot;&gt;Yoshi’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in a band with some friends twice a month, I think. Nowadays, you wouldn’t be able to play as a local group that often. It was more of a local club at the time. Getting better, listening to people. I was getting paid there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was also getting paid as part of a group called the Paul Dresher Ensemble. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Dresher&quot;&gt;Paul Dresher &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a musician who went to San Diego State or University of San Diego… He’s kind of more of a contemporary person, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Adams_(composer)&quot;&gt;John Adams &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Reich&quot;&gt;Steve Reich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, kind of that style. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimal_music&quot;&gt;Minimalist &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but really good stuff. It wasn’t minimalist to the point of 15 minutes of the same thing over and over again. It was a modified minimalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was in a group from 1991 to 2002 and during that time, that’s what I did. Each one of us in that group had a lot of things to pull from. I was an electric bassoonist, so I had effects on the floor and the rack, and a mixer, and we had someone conducting, we had a MIDI clock. We had the whole thing worked out and we did a bunch of touring and we went to Japan. We went all over the United States. It was a great production called Raven’s Head, which is a single person opera, which won the best new opera of 1998, I think, by USA Today. So, it was a really great group for a long time. That was something that was making money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That also helped me at the time to continue to focus on playing with other people. As I played saxophone for many years in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acid_jazz&quot;&gt;acid jazz &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; group in the 1990s playing tenor, I also had this bassoon thing going. I got signed to a record contract with a Japanese jazz label called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makimusic.net&quot;&gt;Moo Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; out of Winnetka, California, I think. Sold a bunch of records. Did a bunch of records with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Erskine&quot;&gt;Peter Erskine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Bromberg&quot;&gt;Brian Bromberg &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_Power#David_Garibaldi&quot;&gt;David Garibaldi &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Gs88oXmXIeI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had a band here and we started playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_Bulgaria&quot;&gt;Bulgarian music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, believe it or not. I was playing clarinet in a group called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Klezmorim&quot;&gt;Klezmorim &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We were touring Europe all the time and we were really fascinated by the crazy wedding band music that you saw on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Sanborn&quot;&gt;David Sanborn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; show. The Bulgarian crazy stuff. It was three clarinetists, a tuba player, and David Garibaldi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: The drummer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_Power&quot;&gt;Tower of Power &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah. I know him very well. He’s on at least two or three of my records. We used to have a band together. David and I, &lt;a href=&quot;http://norbertstachel.com&quot;&gt;Norbert Stachel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a fantastic session player who lives in New York now), I think &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.peterhorvath.com/bio.html&quot;&gt;Peter Horvath &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was in it. A bunch of people. This was kind of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazz_fusion&quot;&gt;fusion &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; period here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We had really great gigs and somebody approached me after one of our gigs and said, “I think I can get you a recording contract.” It was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otmaro_Ru%C3%ADz&quot;&gt;Otmar Ruiz &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the great pianist who used to play with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo_Sandoval&quot;&gt;Arturo Sandoval &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dianne_Reeves&quot;&gt;Dianne Reeves &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all kinds of people. He’s a fantastic musician and he was the one who got me signed. So, I had a four or five record deal with him, or something like that, back when record deals happened. They were released in Japan and we got to be released over here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I entered a competition and was chosen to be part of this international jazz competition. I won the grand prize of a woodwinds competition playing the best woodwind jazz of 1995 or something like that. It was my record and it was really nice. I was playing locally, doing all kinds of different things. To kind of give you the whole story as it goes, there was always money involved. Nowadays you have to pay to do records, but back then, they had budgets. So, I got budgets, I got royalties and all that kind of stuff. It got played and I got paid to do those albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, between that and local gigs, playing with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Dresher&quot;&gt;Paul Dresher &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Ensemble, occasional classical gigs, which I hardly ever did and I still don’t do very much, saxophone work, that’s how I got through. Long answer, huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You kind of just inserted the fact that you were doing acid jazz stuff with the amplified bassoon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I did a little bit. I was more of a saxophone player because I was always in a band called What It Is. I played with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Hunter&quot;&gt;Charlie Hunter &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a little bit. It was a big scene around here at that time. A lot of things going on in the Bay Area. There was a group called James T… What was it called? I can’t remember the name of it. [NOTE: It was called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scottamendola.com/bands/tjkirk.html&quot;&gt;T.J. Kirk &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;] A band that combined &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Brown&quot;&gt;James Brown &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thelonious_Monk&quot;&gt;Thelonius Monk &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; together. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Will_Bernard&quot;&gt;Will Bernard &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Charlie Hunter, and I still play with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnschott.com&quot;&gt;John Schott &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He was actually involved in the gig on the small poster [points behind himself]. A Jewish music event. So, I did a little of that back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Basically, I’d just show up with my gear. I had a little more gear than I have now. And I wiped out the audience, I guess, by playing bassoon with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pitch_shift&quot;&gt;harmonizer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, effects, and stuff like that. It’s just like, “What the hell is that?” Often it was good. Earlier story… I was in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_England_Conservatory_of_Music&quot;&gt;New England Conservatory &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I had a little &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wollensak&quot;&gt;Wollensak &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; reel to reel tape recorder that had the greatest preamp in the world. It was like, “Whoa, this sounds so great.” You know… Tubes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had an old &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roland_Jazz_Chorus&quot;&gt;Roland Jazz Chorus &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; amp, which I still have. I put the microphone down my bassoon, completely down in here [points to the basson about 16 inches from the top soundhole], which you’re not supposed to do. I put it in the Wollensak and put it in the amp and just shredded in the practice rooms. They said later on that people used to line up three deep trying to figure out what the hell was going on in there. Of course I didn’t have any real ability on it. I was just flailing, but it was fun. Some things were good, but that was back in 1980 or 1981.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In the mid 1990s, it was kind of when the fusion thing kind of stopped happening. It wasn’t as poppy. It had this kind of new acid jazz thing, so there had to be some authenticness, like it had to sound like older school kind of guys. So, all that bassoon stuff… Acid jazz was more saxophone stuff and I would say the more contemporary–I don’t know, it was kind of a combination of things. For bands I never played bassoon in, some bands I just played sax. But, it was kind of a mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Were you influenced by anyone in particular? Or was this kind of your own trailblazing thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Oh yeah. A lot of people influenced me. As a horn player, there’s all kinds of great jazz soloists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Parker&quot;&gt;Charlie Parker &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&quot;&gt;John Coltrane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dexter_Gordon&quot;&gt;Dexter Gordon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis&quot;&gt;Miles Davis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, many people who made beautiful phrases. The bassoon is a beautiful phrasing instrument, actually. It’s not a noodling shredding instrument. I do some of that kind of stuff, but it’s really about making a phrase and singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The bassoon is really about singing voice. Coming up with phrases that stick. So, those were influences to me. I say &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bach&quot;&gt;Bach &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a big influence, of course. He is for a lot of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6NH_lwHfrNE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Hendrix was a huge influence because, when I say Hendrix, it’s because there’s things that a bassoon–you’re playing in one kind of key that sounds very much like–you can bend notes because it’s got things like… You have holes and you can partially cover them and you can do things with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiphonic&quot;&gt;multiphonics &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that are kind of mistakes. You can hit more than one note at once and they sound mellow on this instrument as opposed to grating. You can kind of slide them down, you can do things that sound like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DigiTech_Whammy&quot;&gt;whammy pedal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff. Also, you can play bass lines and you can play high up, to a certain degree. That’s what kind of got me going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It just sounds like a really bizarre marriage there, but it works out that way for some reason. E is a fantastic key to play on bassoon. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E_minor&quot;&gt;E minor &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; just is great. It’s the guitar player key. So, it was funny because I play a lot of guitar player keys. “You’re a horn player. I thought you play Bb and Eb.” “No no. That’s fine I can do everything. Go for your guitar keys. Fine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;All kinds of things are musically interesting to me. I just had a drive to continue to work and play and certain people heard me and they wanted me to play. Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_McCandless&quot;&gt;Paul McCandless &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had me play on a record in the early 1990s, I think. He had heard me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Cardenas_(musician)&quot;&gt;Steve Cardenas &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Steve Cardenas is a great guitar player from New York. Great jazz player. Fantastic. He plays with tons of people. I’m not sure who exactly at the moment. He was recording my first album for the Japanese jazz record label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He was playing his tape, because back then there were cassettes, on a tour with Paul McCandless and Paul McCandless heard it and said, “Who is that?” And Paul McCandless is, you know, a great oboist. So, he had invited me not only to get to the connection with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Double_Reed_Society&quot;&gt;International Double Reed Society &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a society that puts on conventions. I was able to go in 1995 to play in Holland and play jazz with the rhythm section there and play for bassoonists and oboists and that was a real big event because people hadn’t really heard anything like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GAe0_n97PGw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve always had a relationship with them since then. I do workshops and master classes and I know a lot of bassoon teachers and stuff. That world has gotten me involved. And, like anybody, when someone hears you, they can help you, you owe a lot to them. Paul introduced me to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Béla_Fleck_and_the_Flecktones&quot;&gt;Flecktones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;After playing a casual one day, I went to the Warfield here or something like that. I sat in with the Flecktones, I think, in 1998 and then 1999. Then I also ended up working with the drummer, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Future_Man&quot;&gt;Future Man &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He had a little orchestra playing bizarre, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microtonal_music&quot;&gt;microtonal music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was funky, but it was microtonal and I had to come up with new fingerings and stuff like that. He’s something else. He’s a fantastic musician, but he’s on a different plane of reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was in Nashville quite a bit, playing with people there. There’s a lot of great musicians down there. It’s a very different feel, in some ways, than here in California because the cost of living is nowhere near. Through hook and by crook, I think I was playing at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NAMM_Show&quot;&gt;NAMM show &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 1999. Things developed and then they asked me to play in the band. So, I played for a few years off and on with Paul, me, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andy_Narell&quot;&gt;Andy Narell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and a Tuvan throat singer, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kongar-ol_Ondar&quot;&gt;Kongar-Ol &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s videos of that, there’s all kinds of stuff from that. That was a big moment. I’m talking so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s the point! I want to hear you! No one wants to hear me. You’ve worked with a lot of amazing artists. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonas_Hellborg&quot;&gt;Jonas Hellborg &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Béla_Fleck&quot;&gt;Béla Fleck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and I love how you’re kind of casual about, “Well, this led to another thing.” Are people attracted to when they hear the bassoon? They say, “I’ve never heard anything like this before,” and they reach out to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah. It happens a lot. It doesn’t happen quite as much anymore because I’m not as young and I’m not as active going out to play with people. And I was gone a long time with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cirque_du_Soleil&quot;&gt;Cirque du Soleil &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was in a show of theirs. So, the period after the Flecktones… One of the things that I say to any musician is, “Do you ever feel like you’ve ever made it?” Because you never do. You’ve always got to keep making it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Playing with the Flecktones was always kind of a dream I never imagined. I kind of hoped, but I never thought it would get to that point. But, it actually did. So, when it happens, the reward is not the fact that you got there. The reward is the fact that you get a chance to continue to do that. So, I had some different projects after that point. There’s a band called &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenithpatrol.bandcamp.com/releases&quot;&gt;Zenith Patrol &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I was in, made a couple of records. One’s on Bandcamp, I think, called VU. The drummer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mars_Volta&quot;&gt;Mars Volta &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s on it, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Pridgen&quot;&gt;Thomas Pridgen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He’s a fantastic drummer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, there’s a period there where I found the right thing to capitalize on that. And we had kids at that point. A good friend of mine who’s in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nashville,_Tennessee&quot;&gt;Nashville &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, from here but in Nashville, had gotten an audition with a really unique company at the time. This was 10 years ago. He told me about it and he said, “You should probably audition for them. You might find yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I went to Los Angeles. This was after playing with Jonas Hellborg. We’d played together with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Sipe&quot;&gt;Jeff Sipe &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Jonas had a thing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawn_Lane&quot;&gt;Shawn Lane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the great guitar player. I wasn’t supposed to–there’s no way you can replace someone like that. Nobody can replace him. But, they wanted something new, something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We tried for a little while. We didn’t go on for too long. We made one record, but it was very organic working with Jonas. Improvisation-based. I had all my effects going. And Jeff, I did a few things with Jeff Sipe. I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Coffin&quot;&gt;Jeff Coffin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was involved with one of the things. We had a little trio. There’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abstractlogix.com/xcart/product.php?productid=20834&quot;&gt;a record &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; out there, a few YouTube clips. That happened for a little while, 2003-2004, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was also playing with a band called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davkamusic.com&quot;&gt;Davka &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which a lot of people don’t know about, which is a sort of Middle Eastern, Jewish-but-yet-Palestinian music kind of thing. Beautiful music from the Middle East. A cellist named &lt;a href=&quot;http://mosessedler.net&quot;&gt;Moses Sedler &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who lives here and went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ali_Akbar_College_of_Music&quot;&gt;Kahn School of Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.klezmerfiddle.com/Klezmer_Fiddle/Klezmer_Fiddle.html&quot;&gt;Daniel Hoffman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a fantastic violinist, a guy who lives in Israel. &lt;a href=&quot;http://stolaf.academia.edu/KevinMummey&quot;&gt;Kevin Mummey &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s our dumbek player. Now he teaches history in Minnesota. And me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qzAb2H9BwNQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, we had kind of thing going on here, where this is a great area to be part of creating music at the time. It still is, even though it’s not like it used to be. There’s a bunch of different things I was playing bassoon in. I also taught music down at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ithaca_College_School_of_Music&quot;&gt;Ithaca School of Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for a year. I was a bassoon professor. They needed somebody to take over for a colleague of mine, so I did. It was great fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was thinking of going more into education, too. When you have a family, it changes a lot of things in a good way and also makes it so you have to make more money. Sometimes things could be really great for a while when you’re a unique instrumentalist, but it’s not like everyone’s looking for one of these in a band. If there was! That’s not the way it is. You have to create all your stuff. YouTube’s starting, Facebook, all this stuff. You have to figure out how you’re going to market yourself and you’re getting older and stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, about 2004, I auditioned for Cirque, went down to LA did some blowout, I don’t know what I did… Improvised with loops and effects and crazy playing. I also had my tenor. So, I did a combination of things and then I got cast for a show about 10 years ago. It was a great experience. Both shows were great. The first show was called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saltimbanco&quot;&gt;Saltimbanco &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I played tenor, alto, soprano, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EWI_(musical_instrument)&quot;&gt;EWI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, keyboards, percussion, and bassoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And they never had a bassoon in there. They had a horrible &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIDI&quot;&gt;MIDI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; bassoon part. So I played it. There’s a picture on one of my Facebook pages of all of my instruments. It was crazy. It was a fantastic show. We’d play on the side when we had time. We were playing 380 shows a year, just an amazing amount of shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was great because you have benefits. If you’re a reesponsible adult and you have kids, you have to have healthcare for the whole family and everything like that. You’d get massages every week as part of the deal. They treat you really well. The show they had me in mind for was on bassoon primarily in a show called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zed_(Cirque_du_Soleil)&quot;&gt;Zed &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was in Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A beautiful story. No one even knows about it. There’s a DVD or something out about it. It’s a fantastic show that should have really had more of a chance out here. It was supposed to be in Disneyland in California, but they balked. Land owners in Tokyo, that Disney, wanted it. Called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Oriental_Land_Company&quot;&gt;Oriental Land Company &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it’s a 400 year old land company with oodles of money. So, they bought the show and made a theater. The theater cost $100 million and so here I am moving to Japan, my daughter’s 6, my son’s 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My wife, she has an orchestral career as well as working at the place she works. She left that, it’s incredible. It was tough for her to do that, but she did and we lived in Japan for four years. It was an amazing experience. I played on the side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Wz3LeH8PPGE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We had a group called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Mean-Green-289913964441/&quot;&gt;Mean Green &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was me, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ableton_Live&quot;&gt;Ableton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–our friend Ableton–and a guitarist, Patrick Kelly, our drummer, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rhythmicvisions.com/ronwagner.html&quot;&gt;Ron Wagner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s a few videos. We never made any albums, but we had some fun. We had no time to record. We were just working 5 or 6 days a week. That kind of put a dent in my career. I’d been signed, I had a record on &lt;a href=&quot;http://abstractlogix.com&quot;&gt;Abstract Logix &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; records called &lt;a href=&quot;https://abstractlogix.bandcamp.com/album/frolic-in-the-land-of-plenty&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frolic in the Land of Plenty&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tuZmArruc0o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I love that album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Me too. They had a whole promotional campaign made, just like what you’d want from a record label. It doesn’t trump a really big job, so I took the job. I wouldn’t say I regret it because it was a great experience being over there and a great country to live in, an incredible cultural experience, doing good for the family…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was great, but it was an interesting time. People who were just all about the music said, “How could you have gone to work for a circus?” Well, you know, a lot of money and great treatment really go a long way, and at the same time there were some really great musicians. We got to play on the side and do other things. I played with a great painter who does things with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vinnie_Colaiuta&quot;&gt;Vinnie Colaiuta &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/VisibleSoundByTomReyes/&quot;&gt;Tom Reyes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He’s a fantastic freeform painter. There’s a few video clips of us on YouTube and we’re throwing down doing some great stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Long answers. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Please make them as long as necessary. You also write original music. How did that start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I always wrote my own music. I always liked the idea of being a composer, but for the jazz records I did, it was important that I wrote music because they wanted original stuff. I don’t have much piano skills, but I hear the kind of things I wanted to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I worked with other musicians and there’s something that develops over time from hearing things that you like that kind of come into ideas of your own. You see where things go. Sometimes things’ll be written on an instrument, sometimes things’ll just be written in your head without any drum machine or loop or tempo or something like that. I don’t even know how it starts. Creativity is so hard to figure out how. Something that can be sung…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AuWq3S4SlaY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I always like melodies that can be sung. I like intricacy and stuff, but melodies that can be sung are the best for me. I don’t even know how, in terms of the composition. I just listen to people, study a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I was in school I studied Bach’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandenburg_Concertos&quot;&gt;Brandenburg Concertos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and how they were put together. The form is amazing! These forms were not improvising, but it’s kind of like a tuning session where everyone’s playing and jamming together and then break off for a few bars. Nothing’s 8, 8, 8, 8. Everything’s 5, 2, 3, and then 1. Different ways of getting around things. It’s really fascinating how that basically grew bass music because Bach has a groove to it. It’s consistent. It’s not romantic music where you stop and hold. It’s, of course, not a judgment, but the truth of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Noise heard in the background.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Every time we do something down here, I can always tell my son’s there because there’s always sound coming down. Something dropping down the stairs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: My kids are 4, 6, and 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Oh how fun! They’re a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barrel_of_Monkeys_(game)&quot;&gt;barrel of monkeys &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: It’s great. It’s cool. He used to play drums. Hopefully he’ll play more at some point. There’s a video of us playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unchained_(song)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unchained&lt;/em&gt; by Van Halen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He’s playing drums and I’m on guitar. That was my first instrument, actually, it was the guitar. I have a Strat over there. So, I’d pick up the guitar, put things together, and think “Oh, this sounds cool.” I’d work out a guitar part. I had a duo with a guitarist who tried to figure out things and I’m trying to figure out…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It helps to have it in your hands to figure out how you can cover as much as you can so you know what you’re giving the person to play. “Don’t just strum something.” I guess with composition it’s hard to determine. It’s just part of creativity and part of–I think less something you want to play over as much as something you just feel should be written down because it feels nice to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s some new things we’re working on. I did some solo albums last year for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue_Coast_Records&quot;&gt;Blue Coast Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and there’s a few things on there that are based on little loops I set up on bassoon and looped myself on top of it and then I play something over it. Actually, &lt;a href=&quot;http://oonband.com&quot;&gt;Oon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we’re going to be doing a version of one of those tunes at least. Some new things coming out. Working on a bunch of different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mabjALyZC5A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know. It’s so hard to describe the creative process, but it’s different than improvising. It’s more permanent. It feels more like you’re chipping away at the marble until you see the sculpture there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And you use Ableton?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I have. I use mainly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logic_Pro&quot;&gt;Logic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’m mainly into Logic. I use Ableton a little bit. Ableton is just so dense. It’s incredible. The guys out there that are great loopers make great use of it. It’s just like, “My God!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of my favorite bands is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knower_(band)&quot;&gt;Knower &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You know Knower? Oh, you &lt;em&gt;gotta&lt;/em&gt; hear these guys. The drummer is fantastic. He does everything and I guess his girlfriend or wife sings. They’re fantastic. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timlafave.com&quot;&gt;Tim LeFebvre &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s played with them some. I’m just horrible at remembering things at the time, but I’m sure you’ve heard them. They do amazing covers, people on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirty_Loops&quot;&gt;Dirty Loops &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: A little bit like Dirty Loops in the harmonic sense, but more techno because there’s only two people. They did a really good one of &lt;em&gt;Get Happy&lt;/em&gt;. I can’t remember if that’s the name of the tune. Not &lt;em&gt;Happy&lt;/em&gt;, not the big hit. Not Pharrell, but something earlier that he did. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Get_Lucky_(Daft_Punk_song)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Get Lucky&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;They did a great job of that. Some other &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellie_Goulding&quot;&gt;Elaine Goulding &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff. Is that her name? Elena Goulding? Something like that. I can find them and you should check them out. Just ridiculous. They’re based in LA. He plays that “push” thing. The grid and he is just ridiculous and fantastic. Making great music, pop, very harmonically–oh my God, just incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xdkou0CxS8I?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Dirty Loops is just another fantastic group. Just incredible. So, I don’t get to that level with the stuff yet. I’ve thought about it when I did things with my friend in Ableton, but it was very simple. We have some parts to play along with our song that we don’t want a whole band for. We just use it for parts of the tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We never got in as much as you could. But since Ableton is so in use in a lot of the shows these days, like Cirque, it came natural to use it as a tool for us. We put some crazy sounds in there once in a while when we’d get to a section where a drummer hits a trigger and there goes a crazy sound. Something where you use technology to your advantage. Similar to using pedals to create chords or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What is your process like? You used Logic, but what does that mean to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I use Logic basically in composing. Like, if I want to use, for example, something I’m writing–I’ve been commissioned (of all things, someone &lt;em&gt;asked&lt;/em&gt; for this) on SoundCloud. Basically, it’s got a drum loop or some kind of drum percussion kind of a thing, effected bassoons, and some kind of bass line. A lot of my stuff is techno-oriented or influenced, I’d say. So, I would never call myself anywhere near the league of people who are doing that stuff these days. They’ve really got their stuff down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, it’s all a tool. It’s in my mind that even if I put these crude little–to me, the quality is okay, it’s just some laptop right there, I just spit it out, and it’s entertaining to people because I play the bassoon and I play with effects, sometimes in Logic or something like that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You know, little tunes that have melodies, me playing over it, things that I can do in there. It’s a process that I use. So, we had something in Japan where I played a tune that was on &lt;em&gt;Frolic in the Land of Plenty&lt;/em&gt;. I had to put bassoon loops into Ableton. I was playing the keyboard part on the bassoon, looping this really crazy part and there’s no way to play it at the same time with the melody on the bassoon, so I had multiple bassoons in Ableton at certain times to come in for certain parts of the tune. It was just a great tool like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UQzsICEebnI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I guess you could have put it on the floor in some kind of device, too, but Ableton is king of all that stuff. In Logic, it’s just stuff for writing. Sometimes I take advantage of the processing that’s there. I take advantage of it just to get some ideas out and some things as well as a person like a do-it-yourself-er can engineer that will just sort of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But someone asked me to commission a piece for bassoon and electronic. So, electronic-based driven music with loops. What I’m hoping to do is take somebody–once I’m done with the piece–to remix the sounds and spruce it up so it’s really–I know some people who are very good with sound quality ideas. They can help with that stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you lay down tracks without using structure? Like, do you set tempo, do you set the key, do you compose…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I don’t just improvise, but I think in my idea, “Oh, this’d be really cool.” I get the nugget and I know where I can kind of go after that. Like right now, this guy was asking for a particular tune that had some things he liked about aspects of my music. So, I came up with something similar to what he’s thinking, I think, and he digs it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had kind of a very academic thought, “Oh, it’s this kind of piece. I’ll put a very academic-sounding &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twelve-tone_technique&quot;&gt;12-tone &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing in the beginning.” And he didn’t like it, which is totally cool. I didn’t like it either. So, it doesn’t have to be “academic,” it just has to be music. Just thinking of the things I like to hear, really cool stuff out there, like the Knowers of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I say “Knower,” it sounds like I’m saying “nowhere,” but I mean Knower and Dirty Loops and these people with really advanced harmonic senses with very singable melody and they take advantage of all the advanced harmonic trainings out there. Plus all the different sounds that are out there with the techno stuff, which is really incredible. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drum_and_bass&quot;&gt;Drum and bass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, all the different styles. My son likes a lot of video game music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, yeah. Like the 8-bit techno music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: All kinds of different stuff. I’m doing an approximation because I don’t have the world’s most incredible studio. It’s kind of embarrassing there’s this amazing sound out there and I’m just using this laptop. It’s amazing how many things in this world, that’s what it is. It’s kinda scary. Might as well get in there too and share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: As a person who plays a very unique instrument like the bassoon, is there a part of your identity that says, “I want to be that guy that’s different?” Has there always been a spirit in there…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yes, for sure. I could have made it a lot easier on myself in some ways by just following the rules. I was very talented as a classical bassoon player. I could definitely see it all coming where I’d be in a section playing the parts of people that I know, doing what they’re doing…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I should have taken advantage of that stuff at the time as it was happening, but when you’re young and you’re about the music, for some reason, there’s just something in you wanting to do something different. I was also playing back in the mid-80s. I was playing a lot of saxophone. I still do, but not nearly as much as I did back then. I played with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_Money&quot;&gt;Eddie Money &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Take_Me_Home_Tonight_(song)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take Me Home Tonight&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, there’s a big solo in that. That’s me. So, last year, I started to get, “Where’d these royalties come from?” Then I thought, “Oh, that’s right! Yeah.” Because they didn’t used to report these types of performances as anything you could get a royalty for, but I got something for some kind of subsect of a guild or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/edFWRm_Ul7k?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, yeah, I played with him, I played with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boz_Scaggs&quot;&gt;Boz Scaggs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I did a whole bunch of things as a professional horn player. It’s just the kind of thing where I thought, “Well, let’s see what kinds of things you can do with this instrument.” By the 1990s, I started making a decision, “You could be like everybody else or…. Why don’t I at least try this?” I enjoyed it. I enjoyed playing the bassoon in a different way. It just felt…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The thrill you get from the sound of an instrument you really like to play and playing with other people that inspire you and matching their intensity or being a part of it is a great feeling. When I say “match intention,” I mean in a co-mingling way that creates this huge, big thing that everybody’s getting something from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s a great feeling, you know. Of course, I love being part of a team also. It’s not just about me, I don’t want it to be just me me me me me. I want to be part of a collaboration with other people. And in situations where we’re bringing something great together. That can happen all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was part of the SF Jazz here in the city as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfjazz.org/content/50th-anniversary-duke-ellingtons-concert-sacred-music&quot;&gt;Duke Ellington 50th Anniversary performance &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_Ellington%27s_Sacred_Concerts&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sacred Music&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is amazing music. Back in the 1960s, jazz was not thought of academically at all. It was still “bastard music” kind of. It had gotten further, but when they tried to get art endowments to try fund it, they totally turned Ellington down. Duke Ellington! They turned him down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/r8T5-AxBUwI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, jazz is a totally different type of music. It’s very–I wouldn’t say well-endowed, but it’s become more like classical music where you have endowments and you have the whole funding apparatus going on. A lot of things happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, this time we played, I guess this was September, a totally different situation. I was playing bassoon in that group. It was a group of fantastic musicians. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miguel_Zenón&quot;&gt;Miguel Zenón &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and some other &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SFJAZZ_Collective&quot;&gt;SF Jazz &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; people in a really supportive role. I was just playing a section, but again when you’re part of something really big, you get that feeling, you get the chills in your back, you’re part of something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s kind of where you want to be as a musician. Adding to, not subtracting from. Why not try to take the plunge and do something to the instrument that brings something else out? That’s kind of what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Along the way I found that there were more people before me that were trying to do certain similar kind of things. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindsay_Cooper&quot;&gt;Lindsay Cooper &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, some other bassoon players that I found out were jazz musicians. I know of a few right now. Like the woman in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moulettes&quot;&gt;Moulettes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of all things, you know. Awesome! Awesome to see them out there playing! I’m always hearing from people all over the place, like, “Whoa, I’m a really big fan of yours. Thank you for influencing me!” That’s surreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/F1-pj1Wt7eE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Did it ever go wrong? Did you bring the bassoon and people go, “What is he doing?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I’ve had a couple of times where it went wrong where I just didn’t get the sound right or something like that. A couple times, you know. Sometimes it has gone wrong when you try to overthink it too much. If you don’t hear it loud enough, it’s like, “Well, nice but…” You gotta hear the bassoon loud enough over the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes you have to orchestrate it when you’re playing with a whole bunch of other instruments. You have to find that right volume level where you can be present, you can hear the whole instrument. Sometimes people think they hear you playing, but it’s just a background voice and they don’t really hear it. But, you know, it hasn’t gone wrong in quite a while. Any musician has good or bad days, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you’ve learned to evolve your voice and to adapt to musical contexts in a way that people probably go, “That’s great.” You’ve crossed several genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: The biggest thing that happens, and it’s not really a reward, but it’s part of it… People just play with me because they play music a certain way. It’s not about, “Oh, it’s on a bassoon.” I guess part of it is that, but they don’t know that the instrument is not designed to do that at all. They just go, “Oh, that sounds really good!” It sounds like any horn player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Many people will sometimes say, “Great sax playing!” If you’re just duplicating what a saxophone has done, maybe it’s not the job. That’s why I go for all the different sounds. I go for techno stuff, more acoustic things sometimes. I try to find something that reflects on this instrument in a way that “this is really what it is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As I get older, the biggest thing is… You know Oon, this musical group I have a CD of for you. It’s just bass and bassoon, so you’re really pretty naked. We had to cover a lot of area just the two of us. You show the uniqueness of our instruments and what we can really do. All the time, the thing that’s really rewarding is just playing really beautiful melody. Of course you improvise, but it’s about phrasing. If it wasn’t about phrasing, it’d be like…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m running long a lot with these long sentences I’m saying, but it’s like a really good conversation or poetry. It’s not just, [sings a bunch of notes quickly]. Like a guy at an art auction just blazing… It took me a while to realize that the stuff that really works well is just letting the instrument be itself and phrase beautifully within any kind of situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, it’s not always about &lt;em&gt;Flight of the Fly&lt;/em&gt; or choppy kind of stuff, which is great. It’s fun to show off and often I do, but it’s also about just being a beautiful phrase. If it’s going to be a note competition, I’m not going to win compared to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I was in the Flecktones, we’d play with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Thile&quot;&gt;Chris Thile &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And here we are jamming outside on a really hot day and he’s just… WHOA, man what am I gonna do here? “Trade eighths with this guy!” going 210 miles an hour. And so he’d shred and I’m trying to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; here. It got me thinking that I can do what I can, but it’s never going to be something that’s going to be as fast as or speedy as some other instruments because, just technically, you have all these thumb keys to play and the combinations are crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aKlOJL37vbc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, there’s other things you can do. You don’t always have to play that way. There’s other ways to be awesome. I’ve always loved the singing quality of the instrument. Phrasing is singing. Even when I was younger, sometimes that stuff left behind a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Can you tell us a little about this instrument?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Sure. I don’t have a reed to play it with. Basically, a lot of people don’t see it from this side, they see it from &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; side. Looks like some kind of wind instrument. You know, you’ve got your keys, but then you’ve got all these thumb keys you’re supposed to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s crazy fingerings. On the sax, when you move one finger to press a pad, the same kind of fingerings, you’d have to use all your fingers. It’s an older system. It’s based on some recorder, I would say. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dulcian&quot;&gt;dulcian recorder &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It comes apart in different places. There’s one at the bell joint, there’s another joint here and one there. People can get through security, luckily. Some people, in the days right after 9/11, people were always stopping me because I had a really horrible looking passport picture that got corrupt and made me look like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezbollah&quot;&gt;Hezbollah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Hanson. And of course I had my microphones in the case, really sensitive pickup microphones… I’ll show you that in a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, basically this is where I screwed the pickup in right here. It goes there. And, “What the hell is that?” They’re looking at the reeds because they’re so weird. Some of the metal things in my preamps are unique. I had these preamps made by Gary Hall, who lives in Santa Cruz, did a lot of things for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Hedges&quot;&gt;Michael Hedges &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a system called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aes.org/e-lib/browse.cfm?elib=2539&quot;&gt;FRAP &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time ago. I’m not sure if they were related, but anyway I think he has his own company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But anyway, so there’s bizarre stuff going through airport security with this bassoon player. “No you don’t see many of that because not many people do that kind of stuff.” It all worked out. It never got confiscated. Sorry, I’m a little dry. So, anyway, it’s made out of Bosnian maple. Maple’s a very hard wood and they age the wood for about 12 years. 10 to 12 years. Then they carve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.b-moosmann.de/en/&quot;&gt;Moosmann &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is my bassoon maker. Moosmann is a great company from Germany. Herr Moosmann makes fantastic… They made this for me. A really beautiful instrument. So, this is called the bocal. The neck goes in there. And this is a gold-plated sterling silver and it makes a big deal. Everything in the reed. I play &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legere.com&quot;&gt;Legere reeds &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which are synthetic reeds that are fantastic for me. Yeah, this is the bassoon and it’s a great, great sound. If you don’t pick it up right here [at the bocal]…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A great, really fantastic invention was made by a guy named Trent Jacobs. For many years I played something called FRAP. I don’t know if you guys know about FRAP. Flat Response Audio Pickup. You see old videos of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_Harris&quot;&gt;Eddie Harris &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Galway&quot;&gt;James Galway &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… Um, who else used to play his stuff? There’s a few guitar players who still play his pickups. But, he had a really incredible wind instrument system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emerson,_Lake_%26_Palmer&quot;&gt;Emerson, Lake, &amp;amp; Palmer &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; went on tour in the mid-70s, they contacted him to make all the brass and wind players’ pickups. So, they all had little pickup systems, little preamps. It’s a fantastic sounding orchestra. I heard it and it was just fantastic at the time. He’s really in the era of hi-fi where hi-fi is really celebrated. It’s not celebrated as much anymore because we’re in a totally different time in history. I saw this amazing band called &lt;a href=&quot;http://progarchives.com/artist.asp?id=2960&quot;&gt;Cartoon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is the band… [to Bob] You’ve heard of these guys?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AqoVuCclav0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: I have them on vinyl…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Awesome. Oh my gosh. Herb Dyman was one of the guys I saw playing bassoon with this band. He said it was this pickup. This was when I was in school and &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; gave me a kick in the pants. Here’s a guy playing with a band like &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; and I really liked that band. They were a little bit different from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Cow&quot;&gt;Henry Cow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but that kind of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, music school, these guys are there, these guys playing with this pickup on the bassoon… I’m sold, I’m in. So I got myself a pickup and played it for many years. I had to get myself another one in 1991 because it broke and I used that one in–I had two of them, I think. Those two have lasted me all the way until right about now. I don’t use them anymore because they’re very finnicky. You can’t get them fixed because they’re obsolete. There’s no need for them anymore. No one uses that kind of technology anymore. They do things different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tjbassoon.com&quot;&gt;Trent Jacobs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a great bassoon player from Minneapolis. He’s calling and somebody wrote a dissertation on me, I guess, or something for his college. He invented a little pickup system and has a little preamp. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://tjbassoon.com/little-jake/&quot;&gt;The Little Jake &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it works okay. It works pretty good. I wouldn’t say it’s quite as high quality as the FRAP was, but it’s different. What I’d do when I record is, obviously, use microphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m recording tomorrow, actually. We’re recording the music today, actually. We’re doing a record. And so these microphones in a recording situation, nothing beats the sound of that. But, obviously, when you’re playing with drummers and stuff like that, you go electric. So, I figured a way to dial it in and now I used–right behind that case–there’s the Avalon U5 and I use that. I’m looking for something smaller than that actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I want something that I can put on my pedalboard. And my pedalboard is right–I don’t have anything in it. Oh, I just have my looper in it. Somewhere around here is my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tc-helicon.com/en/products/voicelive-2/&quot;&gt;T.C. Electronic VoiceLive 2 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I play everything through that. For what I do, I could go nuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If I had a roadie, I have this big old rack in the garage with a huge case that cost $300. I can have things like an envelope filter–I have an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auto-wah&quot;&gt;envelope filter &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; up there. I have all kinds of things. An envelope filter is pretty fantastic. You can go really nuts, you just have to have the place to do it. I don’t do it unless someone’s asking for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4WaGnpmgGhw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, for my basic electronics, I’m not sure–I’m answering questions that haven’t even been asked yet. I usually just use pretty straight sounds, maybe with a little delay or reverb and then I’ll double it. I have a doubler. Doubled bassoon sounds really good and the T.C.s are for voice, so it’s bass from voice, it’s similar to what you would do with a horn or bassoon or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, our site is called Make Weird Music. I would imagine you’ve considered your music to be “weird,” or other people have said…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: What’s weird is that I’m using a bassoon to do it. I never think of myself as–Who knows what they think? I’m not trying to be obscure. I really like to reach out to people, but it’s like, “You’re playing this weird instrument. How do you do that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I just don’t know if I wanted to be different, but I wanted to take this instrument that’s really beautiful and lovely and do something different with it. I guess that’s it: be different and not try to make people sick or something like that. But, just do something unique and push the envelope a little bit. What &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; this instrument do? Why &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; it be part of a swinging jazz group or rockin’ out or funkin’ out or whatever? You know? I’ve been fortunate enough to have that opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s actually exactly what I’m going for in terms of “weird.” Just do something a little different. You don’t have to make people hate the music. It can be totally “normal” that anybody could like, but there’s a &lt;em&gt;bassoon&lt;/em&gt; playing that. You don’t know that. The Eddie Money story!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Well, you know the bassoon often–the thing that gets me–it always gets back to the melodies because sometimes when I’m playing, people don’t know if it’s a guitar, some weird synth, because I’ve played a lot of note-y music in the past or something like that. “Wow, what is that thing?” And then I realized, “That’s not really what I want. I want them to know what the hell that is!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also as I get older, I realize–You know, you don’t want to get confused for something else. It’s nice to be chameleon, don’t get me wrong. It’s really nice to imitate different things and be a part of that. What you can do with the instrument is amazing, not only acoustically, but electronically. Then, actually getting back to what it’s really about is a really melodic phrasing approach where you’re singing from your soul and this instrument surely does that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It really surely does. That’s the first thing we all hear. If someone’s talking to you or singing, that’s the first thing you hear–in rhythm. But, when it gets into mixolydian flat gemonist 5 whatever chords, mixophrygolydian… I don’t know. That’s the kind of stuff that’s like, “Hmm…” There has to be purpose for it. You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7Wj0yVW9DlY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You’ve brought up bands from Emerson, Lake, &amp;amp; Palmer to Henry Cow to John Coltrane to Dirty Loops. Do you have a top set of influential bands or for eras you were really listen to a lot &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Brecker&quot;&gt;Mike Brecker &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, of course. Brecker was there of course. There was an era where those guys who came out of that jazz rock thing. Different eras that just really set my alarm off. I think the first guy that killed me was hearing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hymn_of_the_Seventh_Galaxy&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hymn of the 7th Galaxy&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Return_to_Forever&quot;&gt;Return to Forever &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in music camp. Just hearing this incredible music that crossed over wide jazz-rock thing, a fusion thing. It got me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Just as a musician, for some reason, that just grabs you. They’re doing these incredible things. In some ways, it sounds like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustav_Mahler&quot;&gt;Mahler &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, it sounds like funk. It’s just amazing! You know? What a great combination! Chocolate and peanut butter! It works great. That was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Police&quot;&gt;The Police &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were a great group. It’s just all kinds of different things. Hendrix was huge. Coltrane was huge. Brecker was huge. The guys he played with. Some aspects of Return to Forever. I liked them a little bit before–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al_Di_Meola&quot;&gt;Al Di Meola &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a really great player. I like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Connors&quot;&gt;Bill Connors &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; side. That record was really more of a balance for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, then later on… There’s all sorts of different things. There was an era where &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Chemical_Brothers&quot;&gt;The Chemical Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were really amazing and some of the stuff that happened during that time period. Boy–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jamiroquai&quot;&gt;Jamiroquai &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I played in a band that’s very much like Jamiroquai for a while. Nowadays, I don’t know if I ever have any top favorites, but there’s all kinds of different things and people I’m missing and completely forgetting about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s of course, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_McLaughlin_(musician)&quot;&gt;John McLaughlin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… We just did &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Inner_Mounting_Flame&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dance of Maya&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; last night and I’ve always wanted to do that tune because that beginning guitar part is totally a bassoon part. &lt;em&gt;Totally&lt;/em&gt;. It’s very much like a cello, broken chords. That’s &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; idiomatic of this instrument particularly. Oh, it’s ridiculous. I played it with effects and it’s fantastic. So, that was a big influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Uuy5XbhId90&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’d say, lately–really there’s some fantastic–Dirty Loops is great to see someone that popular with that incredible amount of music. They’ve got a ton of energy. Young. Man, ridiculous. And, of course, Knower is fantastic. I’m trying to think of who else that I really listen to a lot right now that will get me going. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is another one. I love Meshuggah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You love Meshuggah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Oh yeah, definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you really &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Oh, hell yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Their &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Brecker_Bros.&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is unbelievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BFoZoTwGfJk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I’ll check them out. I don’t know why I missed out on them for so long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’ll play it for you after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I gotta hear it. I can’t wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It’s stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: The thing is, the older you get, being in a place where people can have the time and the wherewithall to spend time together gelling to make something happen–because that’s the hardest thing to do when all your stuff’s all over the place. Sometimes time and location–our period was 1980s and 90s when I was in the Bay Area, there was a lot of world beat stuff going on and African music and African bands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I played a combination of different things that were happening. That was a time when things were percolating and rents were cheap, or at least for me at the time. I didn’t have as many things. It’s great to hear about these guys. When I say Meshuggah, I mean I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I personally would love to hear a melody on top of that stuff. Even if it was simple. He could scream it a little bit. I mean, nothing against them. They’re a fantastic band. That’s their style. It’s fantastic. I’ll put up with it. The next development to me would be melodic on top of those &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt; riffs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tomas_Haake&quot;&gt;Thomas Haake &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In fact, I wish I could get a recording–if I ever get a grant and get around to it–I did a music night called “Homecoming” for the Berkeley Jewish Music Festival because I played a lot of Jewish music in my life. Technically, I’m Jewish. I played in the Klezmorim and in Davka. It’s kind of a combination of a lot of interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5m9EkYW5O-Q&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, taking some of the old Yiddish melodies and interesting modes–the modes are flat 2nd, major third, flat 2nd. Putting those amazing time signature stuff that’s basically all in 4–But, Meshuggah’s stuff all underneath it. We did something like that, but we didn’t get enough time to really gel on some of that stuff, but we did some of that on the concert for that little poster over there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Yeah, that would be great to do, if I have all these musical lifetimes to find a… Maybe Chever can help out with a few bucks and put it all together. We’ll see. I don’t know why they’d be interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, Bob… You’ve listened to Paul. You’ve seen him live for many years. Do you have any questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: Something that was just in the back of my mind is it looks like a really finnicky instrument. I wonder if you’ve ever had problems showing up and it doesn’t work. Do you ever carry a backup?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I had a backup for a while. I was playing so much in Japan that I had to have one, but I didn’t really ever have a problem. We have a great technician. My wife works at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forrestsmusic.com&quot;&gt;Forrests Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a fantastic double reed store in Berkeley, California. An excellent repair person. I was just there the other day because this is starting to fall off. And real quick he got it done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TrJReTv-DD8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;No, I play my instruments hard, but I get them done every year. You just learn after a while not to drop it. You have this radar around you when you see an instrument like this. It sticks out everywhere. I remember playing a gig where the stage started to go up and down like this [dramatically waving up and down]. “Oh my God! Look out!” I stood there on the stage like this [holding the top of the bassoon]. I was playing another instrument and just thought, “Oh my God, I have to put this down.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Look at it. You have a wire coming out of it, there was something added on here when I was with the Flecktones. I had a different pickup system. It’s very rare, so I had this thing put on because I had to have a cable go up here and get it anchored there because when you step on your cable, it comes right out of the pickup, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that’s why I have this thing here. Now, I don’t need it because it’s a shorter cable and I can put it in my pocket. It’s really hard to get something in the way of it. So, that’s the biggest element because you’re playing bassoon and then you’re stepping on a cable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: It’s not the bassoon, it’s the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah, just that. The bassoon–you just have to be careful. You just have to have your radar up about things that are around your instrument. Once when I was in Japan, some kid came at my bassoon and I just grabbed it. I saw it out of the corner of my eye. It could happen. Anything could happen. I’m just very careful with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Like kids with the cup of milk on the table. You just learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah, you just learn. I think you had some other questions about some other things, right? Like what people called this instrument?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: Well, it does look like could be used to smoke things. I would guess the joke has been told to you constantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: All the time because I played with the Flecktones and they had a lot of tapers, they had a lot of people where you could just smell the marijuana up front. People grooving out. It’s interesting because the music is kind of complex, right? But, yet people are jamming and having a great time and doing the “stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We played a lot of festivals. A lot of those jam bands were playing and a lot of that stuff goes on. I’d get, “Oh man… Dude… That’s the–baddest bong I ever saw.” But the best thing that ever happened, the most hilarious one–people never know what it’s called, right? “What is that thing?” So this guy comes up and he’s fried and he had his shirt off… “Maaannnn, is that–is that–is that–is that and ooba?” Is that an uzi? An uba? I don’t know. So funny. An ooba! I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s funny. You learn a real sophisticated classical instrument that everyone knows in the classical world and you’re in an environment and you’re trying to get somewhere and you get, “Listen to &lt;em&gt;THAT&lt;/em&gt;.” You know? So, it’s funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You mentioned another instrument you play called the EWI?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah, I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Electric wind instrument. You never heard of it??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Bob, have you heard of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: Yeah, Brecker played it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Oh yeah. It’s definitely a period instrument. I have something like that up there called a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yamaha_WX5&quot;&gt;WX-5 from Yamaha &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s behind the cups up there. The EWI is just static. If you touch this little pad, it means you bent the note, but it’s so touch-sensitive I don’t even like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: Kind of like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SynthAxe&quot;&gt;SynthAxe &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in a way? It’s not a real instrument, but it plays like one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6GtbBmNEEWg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I did a lot of it. I did some in Japan. I also played it in Cirque for certain flute parts or trumpet mutes or little things that I’d do. Cues and stuff like that. I played it a lot in my first Cirque show I was in, Saltimbanco. I played that going back and forth between five million different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Anything else, Bob?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: What are you looking forward to for the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Well, I have the commission to finish. It’s something that I hope to release on my own. I think the name, the working title so far is &lt;em&gt;Warlords of Irony&lt;/em&gt; is the name of the piece. It’s pretty heavy duty little thing. I’d like to get it mixed right and I’m not sure that the client–it’s a good friend of mine–I’m not sure what he wants it in, but they have to perform it first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So when they perform it first, then I get a chance to release it on my own. I’ll do that. It’s a cool piece of music. Other bassoonists can play it and go along with it. I’ll probably improvise over it, but it can have sections. Either a solo will be written out or they’ll just have to go out on their own or have something written for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then these couple bands I’ve been playing with. One is just a CD release thing coming up next month in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Jazz_Conservatory&quot;&gt;California Jazz Conservatory &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I think it’s the last day of January. And the group I’m recording with tomorrow, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jeffdenson.com&quot;&gt;Jeff Denson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s group, probably going to Europe next year. And then Oon, we might also be in Europe next year also. So there’s things going on there. And then, teaching. I’ll do some master classes. Different kind of things like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: It wasn’t like a professional concern, but just pure music… What would you be looking forward to? Like a situation, is there a band? What would inspire you without any outside considerations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I get a lot on my plate in terms of the jazz situation. But something that’s more like, I don’t know, something that cross a little more to people, I suppose, some of the time. It depends on if it’s just the purity of music, it’s not about commerce, it would probably be something that I could see people dancing to. Certain people come and groove a little bit, not just staring and going like this [crosses arms and looks skeptical], looking at your chops and that sort of thing. And it’s hard to say. I’m doing a lot of great music right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m enjoying a lot of the music I’m doing. It’d be great to be able to put the things across that I’ve worked on, like they have the funding and the wherewithall to put across the project I worked on commission by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jewishmusicfestival.org&quot;&gt;Berkeley Jewish Music Festival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to write this piece. I’ve got a ton of music, I’d like to have that pulled off and be able to see a tour of that, for example. That’d be fantastic. But, that means I’d have to have the resources to be able to do it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s hard to get everything done and really have people have time to learn their parts and really gel. Anything that was a long-running thing that had a chance to go for a while because I think you really get a benefit out of playing music more than once or twice. Something you could tour with. That’s kind of a thing. That sounds kind of funny, but seriously, that’s what I’m always looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If I was part of a band where I played Dirty Loops kind of stuff, or Knower. That’d be cool. You know, where it’s not necessarily about a jazz solo all the time. That’s just fine. It’s something that gives people a chance to work together for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think that’s a benefit for musicians is not just have one shot and that’s it. It’s different now than it was when you could play with the same musicians, you know, three or four nights in a row. Some people get to do that, but often, people are not incredibly well established. It’s hard to do that, so something that is ongoing a little bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know. That’s kind of a weird question because musically, what are you looking for? I like all kinds of different things, but it’s just that the chance for the music to really develop is what I think I’m looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kOEF7f2HGoE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: Some kind of fairly long-term thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah. Definitely. That’s kind of a funny answer, but I just know a lot of people or I hear about it on Facebook where they’ve got a gig and they hype it up and it &lt;em&gt;happens&lt;/em&gt; and it’s gone. You want to do more. You want to be on tour. You want to find a way to bridge boundaries so that people really get what it’s about. When I played with the Flecktones, it wasn’t real last-minute. They’re playing really complex music. Somehow, they found a way to really get people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: Interesting because the Flecktones started as kind of a one-off for the PBS show and here they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: I know. It’s incredible. It’s amazing. I know Bela does more now on his own sometimes, or with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chick_Corea&quot;&gt;Chick Corea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or something like that. They totally deserve everything. They’re so damn good. Man, incredible. All those guys were ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: I’ve always enjoyed seeing the wrong instruments play the right music, which Bela on the banjo and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patcloud.com&quot;&gt;Pat Cloud &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; before him on the banjo. I don’t know if you know that name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Pat Cloud?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: Yeah. Same kind of thing with the bassoon. It just sounds a little more fresh and unique. You know, you just kind of mess it up a little. It’s like fusion when you mix some eastern music with western funk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Yeah, the thing is to find a way to be musically enticing and at the same time, something that doesn’t just become an academic exercise and looking in too much. You want to look out because you are playing for people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I love playing for people. I love seeing people really enjoying themselves. Of course, that being said, I’m not going to play a bunch of music that was really pandering or something…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;B: No &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown_Eyed_Girl&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brown Eyed Girl&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Probably not at this point. I have nothing against certain covers, but it has to be done well. It’s just the musical treatment. I’m not going to do something like rap covers, do a Drake tune or something like that. I just don’t know enough about that genre to do something well. It has to be something that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Some of the music I hear today, I’m not really up on all the pop music right now. Some of the stuff is very basic, simply. No lyrics and no melody. It’s like, “Well… nay nay na-na-na-nay nay.” I don’t know. It just sounds very–a 4-year-old could come up with it. I’m not going to do &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s just this kind of thing that’s like… I admire people who have a long-standing relationship with their audience and they’re able to–I would say someone even like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rush_(band)&quot;&gt;Rush &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is incredible because, my God, they almost didn’t make it. They were very close to stopping when they did–what was that record? &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caress_of_Steel&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Caress the Steel&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?   Something like that. Then &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2112_(album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;2112&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came out and it was exactly the opposite of what the record company said was going to happen. “Hit singles!” and stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;They did the exact opposite. They said, “We’re gonna go out the way we feel.” And they stuck to their guns and they knew somewhere that people relate to that, and they did. That was great. And that’s one of my top groups, also, was that group in particular. As a bassoon player, I’m trying to figure out how I fit into that. You know? Sorry I’m going on and on…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: No, it’s okay! I think we have to wrap up timewise. But, thank you &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much for your time. This has been awesome. Thanks for welcoming us into your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;P: Thanks a lot. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/paul-hanson/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/paul-hanson/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Favrio Guitars ATG7</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;whos-behind-favrio-guitars&quot;&gt;Who’s Behind Favrio Guitars?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;asdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-atg7&quot;&gt;What is the ATG7?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;asdf&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/favrio-atg7/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/favrio-atg7/</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Experience by Gentle Giant</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-we-learning&quot;&gt;What are we learning?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post contains a transcription I did of the intro to an incredible song called &lt;em&gt;Experience&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt;. This haunting bit of music has remained very close to my heart for many years. It is so unique and identifiable! The musical performance of the entire song is as stunning as the composition itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/experience/id731938339?i=731938359&quot;&gt;Purchase the song on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002SXSQ2Q&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Amazon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried learning the song a few years ago and was completely confounded. I simply could not figure out how it all worked! Thankfully, there was a generous effort by &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgoodhart.com/&quot;&gt;Rich Goodhart &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blazemonger.com/GG/Sheet_music&quot;&gt;a handwritten transcription &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was difficult to believe the transcription was correct when I first looked it over because the sheet music looked too “straightforward.” Sure enough, it was right! The way the ostinato plays around with triplet rhythms… It’s inexplicably cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/interview/kerry-minnear&quot;&gt;Check out our interview with the songwriter, Kerry Minnear!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started learning the piece on piano and thought, “I wonder if this is playable on the guitar.” It sure was difficult coming up with something that made sense on the guitar, but I think I figured something playable out. There are some finger acrobatics on the left hand, but it stays relatively in the 7th, 3rd, and 1st positions. Pay particular attention to the left hand fingerings (those are the little numbers aligned with the notes on the upper staff).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instructional-video&quot;&gt;Instructional Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put together an instructional video that illustrates everything I’m talking about. I play it slowly, then half-speed, then at tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FINAL VIDEO COMING SOON, VERY ROUGH DRAFT BELOW&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;fb-root&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;(function(d, s, id) {  var js, fjs = d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];  if (d.getElementById(id)) return;  js = d.createElement(s); js.id = id;  js.src = &quot;//connect.facebook.net/en_US/sdk.js#xfbml=1&amp;version=v2.3&quot;;  fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js, fjs);}(document, &#39;script&#39;, &#39;facebook-jssdk&#39;));&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;fb-video&quot; data-allowfullscreen=&quot;1&quot; data-href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MakeWeirdMusic/videos/851730681606323/&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;fb-xfbml-parse-ignore&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MakeWeirdMusic/videos/851730681606323/&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MakeWeirdMusic/videos/851730681606323/&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant - &amp;quot;Experience&amp;quot; Intro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;Very, very early rough draft of my solo guitar arrangement of the &amp;quot;Experience&amp;quot; intro by Gentle Giant. I&amp;#039;m still learning and figuring this out, but was too excited not to share. :)&lt;/p&gt;Posted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MakeWeirdMusic/&quot;&gt;Make Weird Music&lt;/a&gt; on Wednesday, December 30, 2015&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheet-music&quot;&gt;Sheet Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an incredible web app that offers HTML5 sheet music without the need for Adobe Flash or any other plugins. It’s super-duper awesome. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the score and tablature for the &lt;em&gt;Experience&lt;/em&gt; introduction. &lt;strong&gt;The time signatures are arbitrarily crazy&lt;/strong&gt; only because it seems to be how the intro was played. Most of the song is in 9/4 and 4/4 beyond the intro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/39032/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: The Soundslice embed seems to be having trouble playing all the notes in the second measure. I’ve reached out to their support team for a fix.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-performances&quot;&gt;Other Performances&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the original band playing the song live (skip to 4:20 in the video), which is a bit different from the original studio release. I personally prefer the studio version for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/r46aOKsFm5U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a great performance on the piano. It doesn’t capture the vocal melody, but that’s okay. It’s still fun to listen to and watch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/n3Lmc-5oj-k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;downloads&quot;&gt;Downloads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re interested, here are the &lt;a href=&quot;http://musescore.org&quot;&gt;MuseScore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and MusicXML files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/experience/experience-intro.mscz&quot;&gt;MuseScore (.mscz) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/experience/experience-intro.xml&quot;&gt;MusicXML (.xml) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/experience/experience-intro.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF (.mscz) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/experience/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/experience/</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Michael Manring Interview</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a 1-hour interview with Michael Manring conducted on Monday, December 7, 2015 at 11AM at Michael’s house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Manring&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Michael Manring is? Check out his entry at Wikipedia! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been listening to Michael’s music since the late 1990s. He is an unbelievable musician and incredibly creative. I never thought I would see him perform live, but I had the opportunity at NAMM 2013 to see and barely hear him amidst the chaotic din of  “shredders.” Two years later, I’m sitting on his couch in his living room having a conversation. What an experience!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/michael-manring/michael-manring-interview-mwm-20151207.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/michael-manring/michael-manring-interview-mwm-20151207.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2naRtBfRFMo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some issues with the audio that were my fault entirely. Sigh. Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://damprabbit.com&quot;&gt;Bob Mendelsohn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for his help filming this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and today we are here with Michael Manring. Michael, part of the purpose of the site is to introduce musicians and music enthusiasts to new kinds of music and new musicians. I thought it would be cool if you could just introduce yourself. Tell us a little about your musical history and what got you to where you are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Michael: First of all, thank you so much for doing this, for helping those of us who make weird music, to get it out there and connect with the folks who are interested in this kind of stuff because it’s not for everybody. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It can be a challenge for people to cut through all the other information that’s out there.&lt;/span&gt; People who have really big budgets to spend to get to promote what they do, so we really appreciate homegrown support for guys like us. I know you’ve talked with a lot of my friends. We’re kind of a team in that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, yeah, my name is Michael Manring and I fell in love with the bass guitar when I was ten years old and it just got a hold of me. There’s something about it that just really spoke to me and has never let go. I wanted to be a rock star when I was a kid. I thought that would be really fun just because that’s all I knew you did with a bass guitar. But as I got older and learned a little bit about the music business, I really didn’t think I fit into professional musician-kind-of-personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zaK2GU9pgos?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I kind of wanted to be a music teacher and I kind of headed in that direction, but I just kept getting gigs and doing a lot of stuff. I got really interested in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_therapy&quot;&gt;music therapy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I really pursued the idea of being a music therapist for a while and everybody just said to me, “Oh no, don’t do that. You’re better off being a player. There’s no money in it and it’s an untested field and you work really hard and you don’t know what’s gonna happen. It’s really very, very sketchy, so you’re better off being a player.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Actually, as it turned out, music therapy is a really blossoming field and there aren’t enough people and it generally pays pretty well. So, it was just one of the many career turns that I probably should have been more intelligent about. But, things have worked out okay. I just love music, I love playing music and I love playing for people. So, it’s actually been okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rock-star-and-woodstock&quot;&gt;Rock Star and Woodstock&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Tell me about that transition. Who did you listen to that made you think, “I wanna play the bass. I wanna be a rock star.” And then, were there musical influences or was it organic development of who you were and learning more about the industry that made you shy away from that rock star element?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: The first thing that we all kind of got into, all the kids in my neighborhood got into was the record &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodstock&quot;&gt;Woodstock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We were all a little young for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beatles&quot;&gt;Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; phenomenon. We knew about the Beatles, but it just didn’t connect. At that point, we were kind of more into younger kid things. But Woodstock really kind of grabbed us all. We were all fascinated by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the things about that was there’s a lot of different kinds of music at Woodstock. You know, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimi_Hendrix&quot;&gt;Jimi Hendrix &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was there, but also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ravi_Shankar&quot;&gt;Ravi Shankar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sha_Na_Na&quot;&gt;Sha Na Na &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richie_Havens&quot;&gt;Richie Havens &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. All kinds of stuff. For me, at least, and I think for some of my friends, too, that was part of the appeal. This whole world of different things going on and there was kind of a lot to learn. “Where is this coming from? What is this doing? How do these people get to what they’re doing?” That was a real fascination. So, the first thing I was into was just kind of everything. Just getting into listening to all of it, trying to figure out what it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3fZBaPS_XvQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For me, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the bass was the common thread through it all. I just loved the sound.&lt;/span&gt; At first I didn’t know what the sound was, actually. As a younger kid, I always loved the sound of the bass, but there wasn’t a lot of information about music in those days, so you’d hear something, you’d hear a sound, and as part of an ensemble, you don’t even know what’s making what. There wasn’t a lot of music video in those days, either. So, it took me a while to figure out that it was bass, but by the time Woodstock came out, that kind of information was much more available and you knew who the players were, what they were playing, and so that’s what really got me into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Really, anything with a bass on it was something that was fascinating to me, and even stuff without bass, except bass was the thing that always tied it together. Hendrix was big early on, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Who&quot;&gt;The Who &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steppenwolf_(band)&quot;&gt;Steppenwolf &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Funk_Railroad&quot;&gt;Grand Funk Railroad &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sly_and_the_Family_Stone&quot;&gt;Sly and the Family Stone &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was really huge inspiration to me. That was one of the many times in those days that I heard a song and just &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; it and finally someone said to me, “You know, that part right there–that’s the bass playing that part.” And I just thought, “Oh my God! That’s the bass? That is so cool!” So, those guys were kind of the original inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-music-industry&quot;&gt;The Music Industry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, I got pretty quickly into jazz as well. Got fascinated by all that. Then got into classical music and contemporary music and avant garde music and different folk musics and just kind of soaked it all up. I just wanted to be part of that. As I got older, when I got to be 17, 18, I started seeing how the music industry works and that it’s… Oh, how can one say politely? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s good in the music business if you’re not an introvert.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Let’s say that. If you’re an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extraversion_and_introversion&quot;&gt;extravert &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that’s really a good quality. And I kind of struggle with that. I’m really, really happy just sitting in my room playing music, always have been. But, getting out there and marketing myself is not a skill I have and, in fact, it’s hard for me to even think that way. So, that made me think that, “Maybe that’s not the best career choice for me because that’s always going to be a struggle.” I met a lot of people who were just really good at that and a lot of them just naturally so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s really impressive when you meet somebody like that. There’s a tendency to look down on that skill, I think–the skill of being able to market yourself. But I know quite a number of people for whom it’s just a natural ability and it’s not forced and I’ll always admire those people. But, that’s not a skill I ever had!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, that’s a very tough one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: It is. But, it’s nice when you meet people who are good at it, especially when they’re great musicians as well and they just kind of honestly are able to share with you the excitement about their own music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-the-road&quot;&gt;On the Road&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And when did you start becoming a professional bass player?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I started doing professional gigs in high school, actually. In fact, I was asked to join a professional big band–you know, like a jazz band–in high school with guys… I would have been the youngest person in the band. I did a lot of gigs with those guys and they wanted me to join, but I had to say no because we would go out and do a gig in the general area, but it might be a gig three hours away, so I’d get home at 2 in the morning and then have to get up at 7 to go to school. And that was a little rough and I didn’t want to quit school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I did pretty well in school, actually, and I wanted to–at least for high school–I wanted to finish. So, I started playing professionally at a pretty young age and just kind of kept going. After high school, I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berklee_College_of_Music&quot;&gt;Berklee School of Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I stayed there for an academic year, but I got a gig. I was doing a lot of gigs there as well and I got a gig on the road at the end of my academic year at Berklee and went on the road playing music. And I’ve been playing music ever since, professionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Who was the first touring gig with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I guess the first touring gig was probably that big band, actually, where we weren’t really touring. It was kind of local, but we would go out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I see. So you were playing regularly with that big band after your first year, which led to other opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;disco&quot;&gt;Disco&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, I did that kind of while I was in high school, but kind of had to back out of it just because I couldn’t finish high school and do that at the same time. It was too much. Right out of Berklee, I went on the road playing top 40 music, which in those days was disco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nvIydHPhb98?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In those days, we wore the platform shoes and shiny, shiny shirts with collars that went out to here. Aerodynamic. And we played &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boogie_Oogie_Oogie&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boogie Oogie Oogie&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disco_Inferno&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disco Inferno&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that band was a road band. We all lived in different cities and so there was no home to go to. So we were on the road always. Usually play out a week or two weeks in one place. Most typically hotels, you know a hotel ballroom or there were little hotel disco clubs. And then we would travel on a Sunday to the next place and then play there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I lasted about 6 or 8 months just touring out on the road. It got pretty tedious pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Musically? Or contextually with business related things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: The worst part about it, for me, was since we were playing–we played, like, 5 sets a night or something. I really couldn’t practice very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: 5 sets a night?! Oh my goodness!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, it was a lot of playing. I would practice for a couple hours in the day, but I was kind of burnt out from playing. I wasn’t really making much musical progress. And for me, that was the hardest part of it. I did have to come to terms with the fact that I really wasn’t that interested in the music. I mean, I loved playing, and it’s always fun to play any kind of music, but when you’re playing the same tunes night after night, every night…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: With no improvisational opportunities…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Well, this was kind of a nice band because we were all Berklee people. Everybody in the band could play and everybody could play jazz. And when they let us get away with it, we would! But, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we got fired from a couple of gigs for that very thing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: 3 sets in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah! And being on the road, that was not pretty, because you were completely dependent on whoever hired you for your meals. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you got fired, you didn’t eat.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-into-jazz&quot;&gt;Getting into Jazz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Tell me about your musical progress, then. You’re evolving as a musician, you’re listening to jazz, you listened to a lot of genres, you go to Berklee for a year, and then you’re playing with a disco band. So, obviously, you have to change some priorities. What did that look like and what did you do after you left that band?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: My education in music was mostly jazz. So, that’s kind of how I learned about music. Even though I was playing upright a lot in those days, too, I had to give up upright after going on the road with the disco band because I couldn’t take an upright for that gig and obviously that was not welcome there. So, unfortunately, my classical career was pretty brief, which is probably for the best because I never got really good at the upright. I guess I was really interested in playing classical music on the upright with the bow, but it’s a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; commitment and I didn’t seem to be making the kind of progress I wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, yeah, so the background in jazz was really helpful. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s two ways to think about jazz. You can think about it as an idiom&lt;/span&gt;, which means you’re thinking about the kind of phrases that are used in jazz and the kind of rhythms that are used in jazz. But, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;jazz can also be looked at academically&lt;/span&gt;. So, in order to be able to play jazz, you have to understand music in a remarkably comprehensive way. Looked at in that way, it’s just a great musical education because, if you’re looking at it that way rather than as an idiom, you can understand and play jazz, in that sense, you can almost play any kind of music because you have this kind of nuts and bolts understanding of how things work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You can apply that to any kind of form that you find yourself in. So, then it’s a matter of just trying to adapt to the other idioms. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Adapting to other idioms can be very, very challenging&lt;/span&gt;, so that can be a big part of it. But at least you can understand the fundamentals of music. You know, what notes can be played and how you can play them, that kind of stuff. So, that was really helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fusion-band&quot;&gt;Fusion Band&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The education I got at Berklee was really helpful in that way and it allowed me to kind of pursue this kind of dream of trying lots of different things. So, after Berklee and then after I left the disco band, pretty quickly I joined an original fusion band in Washington D.C. That was great. That was a lot of fun. In those days, we played about three gigs a week playing original fusion music, which was amazing! I don’t think you could do that now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Paid gigs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Paid gigs! I mean, we weren’t making much money. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We were kind of all living in our parents’ basements.&lt;/span&gt; But, you know, we were getting by and you could afford to get a car and, you know, do okay. And we got signed to Tappan Zee Records, which was–I think it was a CBS offshoot in those days. It was run by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jay_Chattaway&quot;&gt;Jay Chattaway &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_James_(musician)&quot;&gt;Bob James &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We worked on a record and we got a local studio, a really good studio in the area, was backing us. They gave us all their “off” studio time. That tended to be between, say, 8PM and 10AM. And so we would often have run of the play all night long. That was great. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I started to learn how to work in the studio and that was definitely eye-opening and a good experience.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We spent ridiculous amounts of time working on our record and, as is often the case, that only made it sound worse. But it was a great learning experience. The record company, Tappan Zee, folded just before we finished the recorded. So we did all that recording, not for nought certainly, but the record never came out officially. We at least recorded cassettes and sold them to our friends and gave a lot of them away. That was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, then after that band, when the record company folded and things were changing and it was harder to get gigs, we saw the writing on the wall that being an original fusion band didn’t have as much a future as we’d all hoped. So we disbanded and I moved to New York to be a starving artist there instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-new-york&quot;&gt;To New York&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: But, it was a lot cheaper then to be in New York…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: In New York, it was cheaper then, but I think it was still the most expensive place in the country, so it was still a challenge. The thing about New York then is it was really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; rough and where I lived was &lt;em&gt;really, really&lt;/em&gt; rough. I got beat up…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What years were this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I moved there maybe in ‘82 or ‘83. Around in that time. So, it was a hard place to be, but it was amazing. I mean, New York–it still is amazing, but in those days, everybody basically on the east coast who was creative kind of ended up in New York. That’s kind of the way it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Kitchen&quot;&gt;The Kitchen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, the Kitchen was just getting started…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Byrne&quot;&gt;David Byrne &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/the-residents&quot;&gt;The Residents&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurie_Anderson&quot;&gt;Laurie Anderson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… Amazing acts played there all the time for cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B9ZOjpsXxPY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yep! That’s right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You were there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I was there. Yep! I couldn’t afford to go to a lot of the cool stuff that was going on. But I was around a lot of it. And there was an amazing art scene as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith_Haring&quot;&gt;Keith Haring &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You’d see Keith Haring paintings that would just appear overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banksy&quot;&gt;Banksy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of that time, I suppose?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah. I was involved in a lot of dance. The dance world. One way of making a very small amount of money as a musician is to accompany modern dance classes. Some people know about that. I used to love doing that and working with dancers and writing music for choreographers. The dancing was amazing then. It was great to be in such a creative place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jaco-pastorius&quot;&gt;Jaco Pastorius&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaco_Pastorius&quot;&gt;Jaco Pastorius &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was there then, too, and he was my idol at that point.&lt;/span&gt; It was just absolute borderline worship, I guess. And that was neat because I could see him play often. I would bug him whenever I felt like I could get away with it, bug him with lots of questions, and he finally said, “Well, just come for lessons.” And so I took some lessons with him as well. So that was kind of a good experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Kind of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you want to explore that a little bit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Sure. It was kind of complicated for a bit because it was an incredible opportunity to get to spend time with him and see him play often and sit down and play music with him because he was such an idol and such a hero to me. But, it was difficult also because he was such a mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It was really hard to be around him because he was in so much personal turmoil.&lt;/span&gt; And he was very ill. That’s probably the cause of all his very, very bizarre behavior. He was extremely self-destructive. Not sure I’ve ever met anybody who was quite that self-destructive. It’s amazing that he lived as long as he did because he was the kind of person who would do something really stupid for no reason. Jump down a flight of stairs, hit himself in the head with a beer bottle. Just… “Okay?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was hard for me that there was this person who I so, so wanted to be, but he didn’t want to be himself. He didn’t want to be. That was a really complicated conundrum for a 22-year old person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JXOnhzoC-i8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How long were you taking lessons from him?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: It was very intermittent, off-and-on for a couple of years while I was there. Maybe 2 years. He was, sort of by choice, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;he was often homeless&lt;/span&gt;. It was very hard to get in touch with him, even when he &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; an address or a phone number. So, you never knew what was going to happen. He would say, “Hey, show up at this place tomorrow and we’ll do a lesson.” And he wouldn’t show up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So it was very sort of sketchy and I would just meet him at a gig and he’d say, “Here, let me show you this.” He’d show me some random thing! I still feel just so bad for him because he had a terrible reputation, especially in New York. An &lt;em&gt;awful&lt;/em&gt; reputation. And, you know, I guess it was deserved. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I went to a lot of gigs where he wouldn’t show up and gigs where he would walk off the stage and gigs where he would try to get in a fight with one of the other band members or the bartender or &lt;em&gt;somebody&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You can understand why people didn’t think highly of him. I saw him be very, very mean and rude to a lot of people, but he was very, very kind to me. Really kind to me. We had wonderful conversations. Underneath all that, he was a really smart guy. He knew everything about music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We would sit and talk about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Béla_Bartók&quot;&gt;Bartok &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frédéric_Chopin&quot;&gt;Chopin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igor_Stravinsky&quot;&gt;Stravinsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He was very supportive to me, often, especially when it was just the two of us. He liked to just sit and play together a lot and we’d play jazz standards usually. When we were done, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;he’d slap me on the back and go, “Oh man, you’re the best on earth!”&lt;/span&gt; Which was not true. Definitely not true. Especially compared to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, I think he knew I was a nervous kid who was uncertain and he was just trying to be nice. He thought, maybe I guess, I had some potential. I would pester him with millions of questions and he was always very patient about doing his best to answer them. He had trouble concentrating a lot, so you just had  to keep–“Come on back!”–reeling him back in. There was a lot of that. But, he was never really rude about that, at least not with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TgntkGc5iBo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I asked him a lot about specific parts, “When you played this line,” or, “How did you phrase that?” or “How did you finger it?” He’d generally get really spacey for a minute and I’d bring him back and he’d go, “Oh, right. This is how I did it.” There was a whole lot of stuff he didn’t remember or didn’t think about. There were a lot of things I asked about and he said, “You know, I never thought about that.” Or I’d ask him to play something for me and I’d say, “It seems like you’re doing &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;. Is that right?” He’d say, “Yeah, I guess that’s right.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Oddly, he really wanted to teach. He had this dream of having a bass school.&lt;/span&gt; One of his pet peeves was that if you’re a bass player, there was no Chopin and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domenico_Scarlatti&quot;&gt;Scarlatti &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_van_Beethoven&quot;&gt;Beethoven &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; sonatas to work on and to allow you to advance your craft. He wanted to start that process, but he was, as I said, he had so much trouble focusing that that was just never going to happen. So, it was interesting, especially being in New York at that time when it was just so dark and so dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I lived on Long Island as a kid and I remember going to the city. It was, “Don’t look up because people will know you’re a tourist and you’ll get mugged!” I was terrified of New York City as a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, I had a lot of bad things happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;michael-hedges&quot;&gt;Michael Hedges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, not long after that, you started getting involved with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Hedges&quot;&gt;Michael Hedges &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windham_Hill_Records&quot;&gt;Windham Hill &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. How did that happen and can you tell us some of those experiences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, that was really great. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The music in New York in those days reflected the sort of darkness of the social scene.&lt;/span&gt; The kind of music we were doing, I was playing a lot of dark, heavy, complicated music. There were just amazing musicians there then, as there are now, as there always have been. And it’s how I got to play with some people who were just really, really high-level musicians. But, the whole thing just felt so heavy and in those days, I was getting really interested in bass as a solo instrument and the possibilities for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had discussions with Jaco about that as well. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When I talked to people in New York about that, I got a lot of very blank stares.&lt;/span&gt; I think one of the things about New York in those days is there was a lot of artistry, but you kind of had to fit in to one of the available boxes. So, you kind of had to be a jazz musician or a fusion musician or an avant garde musician. Those were three places that I liked a lot. I was kind of interested in all those things and some other things as well. I liked all those worlds, but there wasn’t a lot of crossing between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The lines were pretty clearly defined and I was never really comfortable with that.&lt;/span&gt; As soon as there was a line drawn in the sand, the first thing I wanted to do was cross over it or erase it entirely. That didn’t go over so well in New York and the idea of wanting to be a solo bassist was kind of like that, too. “Well, nobody’s ever done it so it’s not something that can be done,” which is not the way I think. “Well, nobody’s ever done it, so maybe it’s a good idea.” That’s sort of how I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I had already started working with Michael Hedges when I lived in New York. I had known him for a couple of years even. I met him before I moved there, I think, or maybe about the time I moved there. When I met Hedges, he was not the Michael Hedges that we all came to know. He wrote his own music, but it was mostly pop music. I don’t know if he–when I had met him, he had maybe written one or two guitar instrumental pieces. That was about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7aom6WcJRnI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, he looked like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil_Young&quot;&gt;Neil Young &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and he loved Neil Young, and he sounded like Neil Young, and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;he made a meager living playing Neil Young songs in bars every night&lt;/span&gt;, but he was studying contemporary and electronic music composition at Peabody Conservatory. So, he had this really super-high-level musical mind, but loved playing pop music and so we hit it off, you know, immediately. We definitely saw eye-to-eye. He was definitely a person who did not want to fit into one box or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hedges-and-guitar&quot;&gt;Hedges and Guitar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we became fast friends, but we were both starving musicians at that point. We both hadn’t developed much of an independent, recognizable sound. It’s funny, in those days, there was kind of a circle of our friends. We were all music-heads. Michael was, by no means, considered the best guitar player in our circle. In fact, he was kind of down low on the rungs. That group, everybody looked up to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Martino&quot;&gt;Pat Martino &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; more than anybody else, and with good reason. He’s just an amazing, amazing player. So, all the guitar players, and some of us bass players too, wanted to be able to play like Pat Martino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Michael couldn’t really do that. It’s weird. He had all the understanding to do that, all the brain power to do that and more, but somehow it didn’t connect with him. I don’t know, it was kind of odd, especially since he ended up studying with Pat Martino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6KvOkNdZMsU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Right about the time he died, he started being able to play like Pat. He started being able to play that way, kind of with his own style. He was really interested, when he died, he was trying to go in some new directions. He was playing a lot more electric guitar and playing sort of his own version of that way was really neat. It’s a shame that he didn’t get to see that through because it could have been really cool, what he was coming up with in that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But in those days, that kind of style wasn’t connecting with him, but he had all this amazing musical talent and skill and understanding and so, instead, he kind of went this other direction. Instead of working toward playing these sophisticated lines, very interesting harmonically, he kind of did the opposite. He played very orchestrally, slower music and simpler harmonically. He tended to play music that was relatively simple harmonically, or maybe just more open harmonically. Less chromatic, maybe you could say. And developed that into this amazing artform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What a privilege to get to spend time with him and watch him going from being a real copycat to being a real original, watch him go through that process and kind of go through it with him because that whole period, we would have these long talks about music and life and stupid things as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;development-as-a-bassist&quot;&gt;Development as a Bassist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, so what about &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; development? You went from disco band to fusion, which isn’t nearly as quiet as what you did with [Michael] and what you’ve done as a solo bassist. It’s kind of funny for me knowing a lot of your solo music outside outside of &lt;em&gt;Thonk&lt;/em&gt; to hear you talking about being in these kind of rock sort-of instrumentation bands. Yet your solo music is so quiet and what you’ve done with Michael Hedges, that was so quiet. How did you end up taking your technique, which I tell everyone is “extraterrestrial…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Thank you…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I like that you find that a compliment. It’s exactly what I mean. But, can you talk about your evolution? He’s coming from a Neil Young context, you’re coming from fusion and disco and he’s probably had his rock stuff, and then you guys become the faces for New Age music and a new, very soft sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, it was wonderful. It was especially wonderful to have a compadre in that process. We actually came from sort of similar backgrounds, although you’re right–mine was a little more sort of Sly and the Family Stone, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayne_Shorter&quot;&gt;Wayne Shorter &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where his was a little bit more Neil Young and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joni_Mitchell&quot;&gt;Joni Mitchell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jethro_Tull_(band)&quot;&gt;Jethro Tull &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He was a big Jethro Tull head. But, you know, I was a fan of all those people as well. It’s just more that’s what we fell into, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We both had come from rock music backgrounds. Rock music was sort of the gateway drug, I think, for a lot of us into music. In fact, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we both were &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; fans of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Halen&quot;&gt;Van Halen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; when we met&lt;/span&gt;. That was one of the things that we really–I think within the first two minutes of our first conversation, we talked about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton_Webern&quot;&gt;Anton Webern &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_Van_Halen&quot;&gt;Eddie Van Halen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Joni Mitchell, I think, and realized: “Okay, we’re gonna have to hang.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, it was a fascination with all these things and kind of youthful stupidity and enthusiasm where we’re just really into all of it and probably didn’t have as much common sense about wading through the good and bad as we should have, actually, but at that age, it’s probably a good thing. We were just thrilled by all of it and we both really wanted–we dreamed, I guess I should say–about creating our own approach. That was the dream. It doesn’t seem to be as much the case in music now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-holy-grail&quot;&gt;The Holy Grail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know if you find that true, but, for a lot of us in those days, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;that was the holy grail: if you could come up with your own approach&lt;/span&gt;. It didn’t really even matter if that approach was especially sophisticated. Just having your own sound… that was the highest level. Just copying somebody else was something you did out of necessity, but it was a bad thing to do in the long term. That was really only a stepping stone toward coming up with a sound of your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that was our dream: somehow taking all this music and distilling it down to something original. We wanted to reflect all of these musicians we loved. We wanted to carry that sound forward somehow at the same time. And we’re foolish enough to maybe think we could do that somehow. So, you were asking…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Finding your own sound–that was the holy grail. And you guys pursued that and found it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah. He certainly did and it was amazing to watch. Especially amazing to watch this person who had a lot of potential as a musician, but was not somebody that anybody paid much attention to, honestly. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Even at the conservatory, he was not a star student.&lt;/span&gt; Neither there nor in the social circle of us “cats.” But he was able to really–It was a fascinating process of acknowledging your own strengths and weaknesses and looking at the things you love and distilling it all down and thinking about it a lot and having a lot of experiences and trying a lot of different things and feeling things out a lot and creating something beautiful out of all that. It’s really a beautiful thing to watch happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-jaco-and-finding-yourself-in-the-mistakes&quot;&gt;More Jaco and Finding Yourself in the Mistakes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I had read something you said quite some time ago that you were trying to emulate Jaco’s sound and you kept doing things that were “mistakes,” but then you found that those “mistakes” were &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;. They weren’t really mistakes, they were your own style coming through. Can you talk about that and when you discovered it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Absolutely. That was a really interesting experience. Really, my whole life there was this notion that the holy grail was really to develop your own thing. But as I got more into Jaco and started to understand his music more and his approach more, I was just so blown away by it that I thought, “Nobody’s ever going to do any better than this. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The best you can be able to do is just emulate him and try to do it in a good and respectable way.&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that was my point of view when I went in to study with him. That was all there was to the bass. It was to just play in that style and try to do it well. Maybe there were other things you could do, but you, at the very least, had to be able to understand this very deep and rich world that he had created before you could move on. So I just worked really hard at copying him and what he did and, as you said, I would play through his pieces often with his help and with his pointers and there were just certain things I just couldn’t get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wDQlSSOXU6A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He was never critical about it. He didn’t want me to play like him, which is kind of nice. I guess I should have listened to that more from him. I was just trying to get it right, really. There’s some things I couldn’t get and those were the wrong things in the music until I finally realized that those “mistakes” I was making were not actually real mistakes. That was me! I was never going to be able to play like him because I wasn’t him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Spending time with him was really effective in that process, too, because it was obvious we were just such different people. I could never be the kind of person that he was, and I shouldn’t! Part of it was that he was suffering so much, it was just painful. It was so hard and there were times when he would say, “Hey, I can give you a lesson tomorrow,” and I would just say, “Yeah, I can’t do it,” because I couldn’t bear the thought of spending time with him when he was really a mess because it just hurt too much to see somebody like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It made me do a lot of soul searching because it was just what you have to do, it’s the kind of person you have to be to make really good music. I definitely came to the conclusion that it’s not worth it. I still feel that way. If that is how much pain you have to be in–and he caused a lot of other pain, too. I mean, he gave a lot of people joy, but there was a lot of people around him and he caused a lot of pain. I didn’t think it was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, yeah, I realized that that’s just not me and these little reflections when I’d try to play his music, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;those things never &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; going to go away and they shouldn’t because those little things are me&lt;/span&gt;. So, I’d try to turn it around and develop those things instead of just trying to get rid of them from my music. Trying to develop those things, tended to be like little phrasing things, tonal things that he did because of the structure of his hands and the structure of his mind. Certain things that he would play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I stopped trying to do those things and then more and more things that he did. But at the same time, there were things he did that I could do well, so I tried to hold on to those things. I always want my music to reflect the enormous respect and appreciation and love that I have for his amazing accomplishment, but it started to be more about these other places to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Spending time with Michael Hedges was great because he was very much in that mode, too, and he &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; Jaco. Loved him to death. Loved him almost as much as I did, but he recognized that there might be other places to go. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was really great to have somebody to bounce ideas off and to share things with and try things with&lt;/span&gt;. Michael was fearless. Fearlessly creative, I guess you’d say. He would try all kinds of crazy things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kBPKmyH1f2w?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think of myself in somewhat that way, too. At the same time that all this was happening, I’ve always been one of these people who didn’t tend to say “no” to gigs. Largely because I couldn’t afford it! If anybody offered to pay me anything, I had to take the gig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bass-itself&quot;&gt;The Bass Itself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: At what point did you start experimenting with the hardware of the instrument? Nobody does what you do, which is part of what makes you so interesting to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Hah. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Listening to your music, if you weren’t a technician on a stringed instrument, you’d probably never realize that you are constantly changing your instrument and the strings through hardware augmentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Thank you! I’m glad that it’s not that clear because I’m always worried that the techniques will overshadow the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Not when you hear it. When watching, it’s almost like this whole other world of WOW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Good! I can’t say I care that much for how it looks, but I want it to sound nice. That’s the important thing. There were a lot of different things going on and I ended up doing a lot of very unusual gigs of all different kinds. I was also very into avant garde music, so I played a lot of way-out-there stuff. I played in a band once where it was myself, a guy who played a whole bunch of stuff that he had mounted on an old wheelchair that he would bang with things, and another guy who dragged a huge chain around on a piece of plywood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Sounds about right. New York?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Pretty far out there. We were all New York guys. We did this one in DC, actually. All two gigs we had for that band. There was a lot of different things going on and just a lot of experimenting, trying different things. At the same time, I had met &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darol_Anger&quot;&gt;Darol Anger &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Marshall_(musician)&quot;&gt;Mike Marshall &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I’m not sure they get the credit they deserve for how incredibly creative they were. I mean, almost off the charts, actually, because those guys would just do &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At the time, they were well known for creating this fusion of jazz and bluegrass, which is really amazing, but they were just completely fearless creatively. One of the things that really impressed me is they wanted to have this certain kind of band and Daryl, he’s a violinist, he wanted to be the bass player, somehow, in the band. That was his idea. He wanted to be a bass player somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: While you were in the band?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: No, I wasn’t in this band. It was a band that they had. But, he wanted to do the bass function somehow, so he got a cheap old cello and put flat wound electric bass strings on it, but still tuned it in fifths, like a violinist tuned, so that he could play it, and he just played it like a bass. I can’t remember even how he tuned it. He just said, “Okay, I’m a bass player now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That kind of fearlessness really impressed me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The important thing is the ideas and you don’t need to have any barriers to your passions&lt;/span&gt;, I guess is what I’m thinking. So that really struck me and made me think more about taking more chances creatively and trying different things and starting to look at the instrument and different ways the instrument could work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s this tendency among us bass players to think that the bass was perfected in 1962 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leo_Fender&quot;&gt;Leo Fender &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with the 1962 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fender_Jazz_Bass&quot;&gt;Fender Jazz Bass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was the perfect form and that it could never get any better than that. There’s nothing wrong with that way of thinking. That’s a totally fine way of thinking, but there may be other ways to think about the bass and those other ways may create maybe even as much music as has been created by thinking about the Fender bass of 1962 being the highest pinnacle that can ever be reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I hope so, considering you play a 3-octave fretless neck with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detuner&quot;&gt;Hipshot detuners &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; everywhere you look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alternate-tunings&quot;&gt;Alternate Tunings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Yeah, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I kind of decided to join that camp and just see what else was possible&lt;/span&gt;, what could be done. I had always been interested in tuning the bass in unusual ways and was very discouraged from doing that by my friends and teachers and colleagues. And rightly so! If you want to play Led Zeppelin tunes, there’s no point in using a tuning different from what they were using. But if you want to do something else, then it might be wise to use different techniques and tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the things I discovered is that you can tune a bass to anything. It’s such a strong instrument compared to other instruments that it’ll take all kinds of altered tunings. And then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;hanging out with Hedges, he was completely fearless about tuning his guitar&lt;/span&gt;. One of the things he did is he was really interested in using these different tunings and one of the drawbacks of doing that is, especially if you use a really low tuning, it decreases the tension on the acoustic guitar and the acoustic guitar becomes much quieter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, it can be really hard to hear a guitar that’s tuned really low. But he was finding ways of playing the acoustic guitar electrically, really innovative ways of doing that, many of which have become standardizations now that many of the crazy ideas he had when we were poor starving musicians that he was cobbling together with duct tape and paperclips have become standard ways of doing things. Kind of bizarre. But because he was able to amplify the guitar, he found ways to amplify it really, really loud levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In fact, for a while, he was into playing &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;, really loud. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Some of the loudest gigs I’ve ever played were just duo gigs with Hedges.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He was able to use a lot wider variety of tunings and to see that kind of creativity, I would feel stupid if I didn’t try to see if the same kind of lack of limitations could be pursued on the bass. So, there was this wonderful time where I was just around a lot of really creative people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;musical-experimentation&quot;&gt;Musical Experimentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In New York, I had been around this really dark kind of scene and the music tended to be very dark, kind of also very chromatic harmonically, not a lot of prettiness in what we were doing in those days, and I kind of got burned out on that. I kind of started to feel a little–I don’t know, a little unnecessary in some way. I just kind of wanted to play something–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I found myself in those days wanting to play something pretty and naïve.&lt;/span&gt; Something that wasn’t cynical and heavy and dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, moving in that direction, and that didn’t go over well in New York, that was not something people wanted to hear there, but I was coming out here [San Francisco] a lot and people here were really interested in that kind of sound. Hedges was also interested in that kind of sound. He had been doing a lot of contemporary music, a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atonality&quot;&gt;atonal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; music. There’s no &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tonality&quot;&gt;tonal center &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, there’s no “home,” it’s all really dense intellectually and not a lot of hand-holding for the listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we both were kind of in this place where we wanted to experiment with music that was–I guess we didn’t feel obligated to do that. We could go there if we wanted to, but we didn’t feel like we had to. A lot of other people were that way, too. Some of our heroes: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terry_Riley&quot;&gt;Terry Riley &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, still alive, still making amazing music, still a huge hero, was doing that. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Reich&quot;&gt;Steve Reich &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; also, who was in Terry’s band actually, one of Terry’s first bands making amazing music and just a huge hero to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/r4AysS-WN0A?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was something that was kind of happening and we were interested in pulling that into the mix, too. Basically as much as we could get into the mix! That’s what we wanted to do, all these different kinds of sounds. Little by little, these things just gelled out of all these different approaches. And our own abilities and limitations and just wanted to enjoy it, really. Just wanted to have fun at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tuning-the-bass&quot;&gt;Tuning the Bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: When did these hardware augmentations pop in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Oh, right. So, I got interested in all these different tunings that could be used on the bass and I realized there were &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; many tunings you could use on the bass. In fact, I often tell people that it’s really easy to tune a bass string over the range of about a 5th, and that’s 8 notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, if you have a 4-string bass and each of the strings can be tuned to 8 different notes, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the number of possible tunings that you can have on that instrument is 8 times 8 times 8 times 8, which is 4,096&lt;/span&gt;. That’s a lot of tunings! That’s more music than (possibly) pieces you’re going to write in your entire life. So, there’s a lot of tunings to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I got interested in the idea of using tunings more dynamically, not having to be just “stuck” with one tuning for the entire piece, being able to move to different tunings. Hedges was really interested in this, too, something we’d talk a lot about and try different things. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We tried to con guitar builders into coming up with things that would allow us to do this.&lt;/span&gt; Most of them thought we were completely insane. In some cases, probably rightly so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But when I met &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zon_Guitars&quot;&gt;Joe Zon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he was the first guy I talked to that said, “Oh, that’s a great idea! We could do that for you!” I was shocked! He had been coming to a lot of my gigs and bringing his lovely instruments. He started saying, “You know, I’d really like to build you a bass.” I said, “I don’t think you want to build what I want.” He said, “No no no, try me!” So I said, “Well, this is what I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want.” So I started describing something very much like the hyperbass that we made. And he said, “Oh yeah, we can do that.” I think sometimes he regretted being so open to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hyperbass&quot;&gt;The Hyperbass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We started working together in, I think it was 1989, maybe 1990. We started working together on this dream bass. He had a lot of really creative ideas, too. So we said, “Let’s just put everything that we can in one instrument and see what happens.” And so we started working on this bass that he ended up dubbing “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zonguitars.com/zonguitars/hyperbass.html&quot;&gt;The Hyperbass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.” And it was a real project. My part in it was really easy, it was just coming up with weird ideas, but he had to figure out how to make all these things work and it was a lot of things that hadn’t been done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LWPHrRwQqVE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of mechanical challenges, a lot of electronic challenges, a lot of woodworking challenges as well. He made it all work and put it all together and invented this amazing instrument. And I’ve been playing that instrument ever since!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The Zon Michael Manring Hyperbass. It allows me to change tunings in two different ways.&lt;/span&gt; I can change strings individually or collectively on it. It also has a separate output for each string, so it has a quadrophonic pickup so I can process the sound of each string separately. In addition, there are pickups in the body so I can play it almost like an acoustic instrument, I can tap on the body and create sounds or use those body pickups as an additional sound source. And as you mentioned, it has a very long fingerboard, allows me to play in higher ranges than you can on the normal bass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I mean, really super super lucky to run into Joe and we’ve had a really close friendship ever since. He’s built a number of other instruments for me. At this point, that’s pretty much all I play is his instruments because I just love them so much and he’s so good at what he does. It’s really been a great partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;composition-on-the-hyperbass&quot;&gt;Composition on the Hyperbass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How has this instrument shaped your composition and the physical act of playing since you’ve received it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: It really opens things up. For me, I see it as a logical extension of the bass guitar. I know for a lot of people it seems like something, as you said, from another planet. For me, it’s just a logical next step to make. It’s a real blessing to have this tool that has these whole other set of capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aY4Ra2KOyas?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s a ton of stuff I haven’t done with it yet.&lt;/span&gt; There’s a lot more that can be done and there are lots of additional design ideas that we’d like to try that we haven’t had the time and money to pursue. So, there’s an awful lot that needs to be done. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s just a thrill to be able to pursue these ideas and see where they go.&lt;/span&gt; And a number of them have really been very fulfilling. There’s a number of things I’ve done with the Hyperbass in particular, a number of pieces that I’ve written that I’ve been playing for 20 years and have just been enormously fulfilling and given me a lot of joy. And other people sometimes seem to like hearing them too, so all the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;working-as-a-solo-bassist&quot;&gt;Working as a Solo Bassist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Can you tell me about a career as a solo bassist playing the kind of, I’ll call it “weird”…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: Please!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: “Weird” doesn’t necessarily mean “bad,” but “weird” means somebody being themselves in a way that you don’t hear often. “Unique” is probably a better term for it. “Weird” is a marketing term. What is that like for you that you’ve made a career of being a “weird” solo bassist? Bass magazines all over the world write about what you do. How has that been and is that the direction you ever expected your career to go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I definitely didn’t expect it to happen this way. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;All the smart, well-meaning folks around me told me it wasn’t going to happen.&lt;/span&gt; They all said, “You can do a little bit of this solo bass thing, but it’s not something that anybody’s ever going to be really interested in.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And it didn’t turn out that way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s a funny thing about a creative world like music, as soon as you think you have a rule, you might be right for that month or that year or even that decade. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But if it’s a creative world, things are going to change and it’s going to be hard to pin things down.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So for me, it’s been a real blessing because I just love the instrument so much and when you play it by itself, you can really hear all of its nuance and all of its color. All the little poetry that goes on with the sounds and all the emotions that it’s capable of expressing. And all of the ideas, all the intellectual ideas it’s capable of expressing with all of this sound, both subtle and gross, I suppose, that it’s capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It is an enormously rich instrument&lt;/span&gt;, sonically, because all the time it’s creating very low sounds and very high sounds all the time and a lot of sound in the middle as well. So, the idea of playing it solo has always been a passion for me. It’s something I kept on the back burner for a lot of years because I was passionate about playing other kinds of music as well, but the solo thing is something that I could never really give up because it really is such a beautiful sound, I think, regardless of who’s playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Overall, it’s just felt really lucky to have found myself there, especially after Hedges died and I didn’t have somebody, that really close friend, anymore to play with. Then doing more solo stuff really felt good. I don’t know what more I can say on that specific topic, but it really has been a blessing to do that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m just so thrilled and so thankful that people are accepting of it because I think it is a bit of a stretch as a listener.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When you ask anyone to listen to anything new, people have busy lives and most people don’t want to spend a lot of time on music and they’re stretching their minds so much just to survive in this world, you kind of hate to ask them to stretch them anymore just in listening to music. But there are people who like to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And they’re all over the world and you now have the capability to reach them. It’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: It’s amazing. I mean, it really is amazing. That’s one of the thrills about it for me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This kind of music is equally effective in Bogota as it is in Boca Raton.&lt;/span&gt; So, you can go all over the world, there’s kind of no reason not to play everywhere. I’ve had the chance to travel all around and play this crazy music for people and it’s been amazing. I wouldn’t have traveled much, I think, myself if I didn’t need to. If I wasn’t invited to by the music-making process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m actually kind of a home-body. One of the things I enjoy most is just sitting by myself and playing music. It’s been a great privilege to be able to travel around and have amazing experiences and meet incredible people and see incredible things all over the world. That bizarre, amazing, wonderful magic of being able to have music connect people. I’ve played in a couple bands where no two people spoke the same language and yet we could–it’s a terrible cliché–we could communicate through the medium of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Even though it’s a cliché, I never get tired of that magical aspect–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;one of the many magical aspects of music of completely obliterating all kinds of barriers and borders, linguistic and geographic and cultural, even.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Well, that is fantastic. I think we need to wrap it up, but I have a hundred more questions so if we can do this again in the future…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: I’d love to. Thank you so much for coming to my home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;M: My pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/michael-manring/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/michael-manring/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jan Zehrfeld Interview, Part 4</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (the &lt;em&gt;final&lt;/em&gt; part) of our multi-part interview with Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett, the world’s best and only jazz-metal band. Make sure you read/watch &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-3&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Panzerballett is? Check out our Discover post about them!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conducted Part 4 on Thursday, November 12 at 3AM Arizona time, which is 11AM in Munich, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-4&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-mwm-part4-20151112.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-mwm-part4-20151112.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NtdaEW5ARcQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jan: It’s always, yeah, grass is greener on the other side. It’s always that I am wanting the other thing that I do not have right now. When I’m in a metal concert, I’m listening to a metal band and I’m missing the improvisation. At a jazz concert, sometimes I’m missing the wrecking ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Being in the metal community, being the one who’s actually into jazz, or being among jazz guys always wanting to be the metal guy, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;always wanting to be the different guy, to do something different, to be different from the others&lt;/span&gt;… It’s a desire that comes from myself and that’s the same contrast that I need. You automatically get it at the same time when performing songs that incorporate both elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s kind of the fulfillment of this desire. You get something of both worlds in one thing and you don’t crave for the other element anymore because you’re already not far away from it. You’re just performing both. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Yeah, it does. That leads me to two questions: Is a song a small enough context to provide that fulfillment? And secondly, when the song is so complex that it takes so much effort to learn how to improvise over it, doesn’t that take away from the joy of improvisation because you have to work so hard to even get to the point where you can improvise on it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s the hard work of being able to enjoy it: to practice it an extent that you get freedom.&lt;/span&gt; That’s the actual work on improvisation. It’s always to be free, to get options from where you are. To get these options, you need to work out ways to finding these options. That’s the mastering of improvisation. That was one part of your question and the other…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Is within a song a small enough thing? You said, “When I’m in a group, I’m always looking somewhere else.” Does a song provide enough for you to be present in the moment and to be content with the improvisational piece when you’re improvising and to be content with the through-composed parts when you’re playing those?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes it is because the song is designed in a way to fulfill that desire automatically. Some songs that don’t have improvisation, like &lt;em&gt;Mahna Mahna&lt;/em&gt;, which doesn’t have improvisation. The song is quite short, but if it was 8 minutes long and it wouldn’t have improvisation, then I would miss something. Since it’s 2 minutes, that’s okay for a non-improvisational part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When it’s a whole song without improvisation, something is definitely missing. So, most of the songs have a well-balanced ratio–what means “well-balanced?” Well, enough balance for fulfilling the desired ratio of improvisation versus composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bEdh3IjJ9Gk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Once you write these songs, you compose them… I’m guessing you write charts out for people. The band, I assume, has enough freedom to do what they want and what you’re writing is like recommendations in some areas and very specific in other areas. How does the band treat receiving a chart from you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;As far as I understand, you don’t all live in the same place, so you probably have to practice to a certain extent on your own and when you come together, it’s a different form of practice, as you mentioned in part 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: When I compose, I write out the parts and I do a pre-production of every song. Regarding the saxophone and the bass and the first guitar (melody guitar), there are not many modifications that musicians do to it except some phrasing, or maybe for the guitar, Joe adds some expression or articulation or bendings or some special techniques to make it nice-sounding. Joe is a very, very good guitar player. Particularly, this is one of his specialities: to take a melody from a MIDI file and make it sound really nice on guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then there’s the drums. Because I’m not a drummer, I can just offer Sebastian something. Parts of them he takes them as they are, but most of it he rearranges and makes his own drum arrangements. This is totally insane stuff. I would never get the idea to write like it. Much of it is drum-specific stuff that I just don’t know. Extremely specific things and techniques that he practices and ideas that he gets. He gets many, many ideas, and I let him do whatever he wants. His drum parts are way more complex than what I write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TquaiwpQXKc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In the end, every musician has to spend time learning his part, which is kind of hard already. But then there is a second part of it, like putting it together in the band. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you’re able to play along with the computer in pre-production, that doesn’t mean you can play it together&lt;/span&gt; with everyone having his own interpretation. Because the structure is so sophisticated, everyone is making little… playing a little ahead of time, or some notes are a little too long or too fast or too slow… just a really little bit, but this little bit is enough to make the whole construction not sound well and make the parts not fit together well enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Not even putting together the single elements and rehearsing as a collective band is an important part. We don’t have much time to do this because two of us live in Austria and three of us live in Munich. It takes at least… Either we rehearse in Salzburg, which is almost a 2-hour drive, and then we have to set up, which takes time as well. And Joe comes from Linz. When he comes to Munich, he has to drive 3 hours just one way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s a lot of time on the day we rehearse before we play the first note. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the time we have is precious. We have to be very effective.&lt;/span&gt; Everyone has to really be able to play his part perfectly so we can do this process of putting together. It’s like having a complex sculpture and you have all the single parts and you have to then meet and everyone has his part and you have to put them together. You have to make some tiny adjustments. You notice that somebody plays one note a little too long or the phrasing is a little different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Little mistakes lead to collective errors in the band.&lt;/span&gt; Little mistakes are often already enough to make it not happen as it should be in the collective. So, we rehearse, it takes us maybe one or two rehearsals for one song. When there are new principles, like the quintuplet thing, then it takes us longer. I think I already talked about that in part 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dRa_OUPNR58?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you have more that you want to get out of the band? Or is it doing just what you are hoping for compositionally, in terms of performance…? Are there areas where you’re seeing a lot of opportunity for growth? Or it’s just great for what it is and you’ll continue to evolve and you’re excited about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yeah, it’s the latter. It took so much time to find something and rehearse it and bring it on stage and now it’s kind of a working machine. So, I know I can just go on being creative into this direction and I know there will be new, awesome stuff happening at some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s kind of found its own long-term groove of how to create and arrange this music, rehearse, bring it on stage… Experimenting inside of these parameters with this instrumentation, I think there is still a lot to exploit. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is where I’m aiming: becoming more and more awesome and more and more sophisticated and complex.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I guess I can only think of one more question and it’s 3:40 in the morning. But that’s okay. And the question just left me. Give me one second. Oh! Yes! So, how would you characterize or articulate what this music has done for you in your life? How have you grown personally through making weird music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Personally, I would say just &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;doing this thing is the most satisfying experience for me as a musician.&lt;/span&gt; It has been by far the most satisfying because it’s nice to be a side-man playing music from other other composers, other bands, or doing stuff in other bands, cover bands… The diversity makes it exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But, still &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;everything is not half as satisfying as doing your own thing&lt;/span&gt; and knowing that there is no end to it so you can always go on and on and on and finding new stuff. That’s how I assign the importance or priority in doing this Panzerballett stuff. It’s my first priority of what I want to go on with and what I put my efforts into emotionally. As a musician, it makes me my source of inspiration  of what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DnYs2vVi4QA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I wake up and start practicing, I know I want to. It used to be like that. When I didn’t have it, it used to be a random thing I liked, different stuff. What I practiced wasn’t as focused as what it is now. Now I want to be really… I got the &lt;em&gt;Erkenntnis&lt;/em&gt;… What is that in German? The awareness or knowledge that you cannot be able to do everything. A country or recording guitarist or classical guitarist. There are so many great aspects of playing guitar, but the time is limited and you have to focus on something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think by &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;making weird music, I’ve found something that’s really myself&lt;/span&gt; and that’s what I can do good. That’s my cup of tea. That’s what I can do best. That’s what I have to. I know I have to really specialize in order to get a chance to be recognized by the world. Otherwise, I don’t have a chance because there are so many good musicians. You have to find a way to do your own thing &lt;em&gt;and then&lt;/em&gt; putting 100% into it and then you have a chance to be recognized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think I’ve found the thing that I can do best so now I know what to focus on way better. I know, “Well, maybe I should check out more of this technique or that technique” and it’d be great to be a nice flamenco player. Why not? But, when just starting to do it, I recognize, “No!”” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It would take so much longer and it would distract from what I can do best&lt;/span&gt;, which is this weird thing. I need to focus on the weird stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Personally, I’ve recognized in myself: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;focus on what you can do and not what you can’t do&lt;/span&gt; and can do not that well and what’s “nice,” but maybe not nice enough. Focus on something you really do well. That’s what I think and that’s what I’m going to do. It makes the choice so easy when getting up! “What should I do now?” I focus on just getting better in what I already do, which happens and gives me satisfaction. I’m getting better and I want to get even better. I won’t become a big shredder, probably, but in my own style, I will become better and this makes it exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s great. Well, thank you so much for your time. I really appreciate you spending all this time with me and exploring these themes. It’s really wonderful. So, thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: You’re extremely welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: All right, Jan. I appreciate it and, I don’t know, we’ll talk again I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I’m wishing you a good night. My day starts now and I’m going to have some breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: All right. Have a good one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: You too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-end&quot;&gt;The end!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After four magnificent interview “parts,” this interview can be considered complete.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-4/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-4/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jan Zehrfeld Interview, Part 3</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of our multi-part interview with Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett, the world’s best and only jazz-metal band. Make sure you read/watch &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Panzerballett is? Check out our Discover post about them!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conducted Part 3 on Thursday, November 12 at 2AM Arizona time, which is 10AM in Munich, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Jan’s camera could only record ~40 minutes at a time, so his footage from Part 3 ends abruptly. Thankfully, I figured out how to record from my iPad and captured his audio straight from the Google Hangout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-3&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-mwm-part3-20151112.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-mwm-part3-20151112.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZVYPm6fDisg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This third attempt at a videoconference interview went much better is the best so far. Hopefully, Part 4 is even better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Do you ever get invited to play at jazz festivals or at heavy metal festivals? And when you play at these festivals, do you ever offend the sensibilities of the audience where the jazz audience is expecting pure jazz or the heavy metal audience is expecting pure metal? How do they respond to you playing what you play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jan: That’s a good question. We’ve played mainly at jazz festivals and not at metal festivals. Almost not at all. The only metal festival we’ve played at is Euroblast, which is a technical metal festival, because there is this djent community…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/&quot;&gt;Fredrik Thordendal &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yeah, the kings of djent are Meshuggah, but there are tons of bands that created this new metal genre. Well, it’s not that new anymore, but it’s at least the newest metal genre. They see us being in this scene, but we’re not really a djent band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Some of the stuff we do is related to djent music, maybe. That’s the reason we played at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euroblast_Festival&quot;&gt;Euroblast &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Actually, the name of the song &lt;em&gt;Euroblast&lt;/em&gt; is called that because it was supposed to be the trailer music for the Euroblast festival, but they didn’t take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yeBm_tTy6Aw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, I was wondering about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes. I didn’t want the work to be in vain. I thought it was a cool song, so I wanted to keep it and perform it. Okay, blind alley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Dead end. I don’t think anyone says “blind alley.” They say “dead end.” Or, “I digress” or “I’ve gone down the rabbit hole.” I’ve never heard “blind alley.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: All the other metal festivals have not even invited us because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;they think we have a saxophone and that means that we play jazz&lt;/span&gt;. They don’t like jazz. So they don’t book us because they &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; jazz. Because we have a saxophone, we must play jazz! And they also hate saxophone. It’s shitty because &lt;em&gt;doodle-doo-doo-doodle-doodle-doo&lt;/em&gt; sound like “jazz,” but I don’t like that “jazz.” So, we cannot be good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There were many great jazz festivals where we played. This was exciting. We opened for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chick_Corea&quot;&gt;Chick Corea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Frisell&quot;&gt;Bill Frisell &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenny_Garrett&quot;&gt;Kenny Garrett &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in big opera houses and big stages. It was an honor to do that. It was fun &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of the audience. They were not expecting anything like this. It was not our audience. It was the &lt;em&gt;Chick Corea audience&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For them, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it was of course a punch in the ears and their eardrums went bleeding&lt;/span&gt;. 1/3 left the hall, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manowar&quot;&gt;Manowar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; says, “Wimps and posers leave the hall.” They just didn’t expect anything half as loud as that and they left because I think they’re too faint at heart for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aOm-lJme3Ec?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Another 1/3 just suffered and stayed&lt;/span&gt; and thought, “Well, that’s really ugly music. That’s just noise. Random free jazz noise.” No, “free jazz” is what the metal guys say. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If anybody says Panzerballett is like “metal and &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; jazz,” that’s the biggest bullshit I’ve ever heard.&lt;/span&gt; “Free jazz!” It has absolutely nothing to do with free jazz! Nothing is free! There are some improvisational parts, but free jazz? Oh my God! Makes me angry! Free jazz…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This is like an angry dead end again. Where was I? Oh, the jazz audience! They don’t say it’s “free jazz,” they just say it’s “random noise” and it’s “total noise” and “annoying.” That’s the other third of the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hXf7wtX4vWk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The third third is the good 1/3 which stays and digs it. They like it. This is very polarizing. This effect is always at most in festivals where it is not our audience and it’s a mainstream audience. Except the mainstream mainstream audience we have, if a tenth of the people even considers staying there, then it’s already great. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;For the mainstream mainstream, it makes no sense to play for them.&lt;/span&gt; But, a jazz audience, let’s say it’s a third that’s digging it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You said last time that you use music to “channel aggression.” You talk about punching in the face and bleeding ears and stuff like that. Do you get any sense of joy when you see people leaving or when you know that they’re “suffering” (in your own words)? Is that part of your intent? Do you get anything out of knowing that you’re going out to “punch them in the face” when people don’t like to get punched in the face?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I love the win/lose situation.&lt;/span&gt; No, I would not really say that. There are mixed feelings about that because of course I want many people to come to the concert and like it. What musician would not like to have an audience? On the other hand, when looking into the faces of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; audience, it has some kind of “genugtuung”–satisfaction!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There is some kind of satisfaction because people are–I don’t know why, but I have the urge to make a statement to people sitting there and listening. Many of those people who are attending these jazz festivals just go there not because they dig the music but because…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GvKFCGqdNeM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: They go with an expectation of hearing nice jazz or something close to it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: No, maybe because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s respectable to attend a jazz concert and they have to stay&lt;/span&gt;. There are so many other people who say, “This is good,” they don’t find it “good” because it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; good, but because other people say it is good. There are many of that kind. I have that feeling at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know if it’s true, but I think I can see it by looking into people’s faces. “Ah yeah. Interesting, yes! Ah, mm-hmm. How much time is left? When is the concert finished? But it is so amazing! Jazz music!” When talking to some of those people–I don’t know. I have the feeling that many of them don’t know where the quality comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Is it just because this music is at this event and it wouldn’t be respectable to not attend the event? Those people–if you show them something that has a similar quality of music–I don’t want to compare myself to all those greats because they’re jazz greats…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IZY_2t_dt5M?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I just want to say that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you have music with the same kind of content or density and you just present it to them with a different sound that they’re not used to&lt;/span&gt;, or they’re used to other genres of music, they don’t like it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It scares them off.&lt;/span&gt; That proves that they’re not actually–well, maybe they’re not so much into the content, but it just has to sound nice and they think it’s nice. If you play the same thing with a not-so-nice sound, then it scares them off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You started our first part of the interview saying, “I consider Panzerballett to be extreme music. It’s music about extremeness and complexity.” When you’re blending two very separate genres, I would imagine that you knew there would be a cost to doing those things. Like a risk in doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And you pursued it anyway because you said, “I wouldn’t know what to do otherwise. I have no other choices.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;At no point in time did I consider it as taking any risk. There is no risk in doing what you just do.&lt;/span&gt; You don’t have to take any risk. The only risk you take is if you don’t do anything else, basically. All of us, we do something else as well, like investing a lot of time–“risk” is the wrong word because it’s doing it and hoping that more and more people recognize it and dig it. But, taking a “risk” is not what I’ve ever felt. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah. I think it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; taking a risk but it doesn’t feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah. You’re being true to yourself. You only know who you are. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When you’re expressing yourself creatively, what’s the risk?&lt;/span&gt; You’re not writing music to please others. You’re writing it to please yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RM8_92lgdBE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yeah. Very selfish view, of course. Very selfish. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Extremeness is also in the selfishness of course.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s what makes it great, though. You’re never going to cater–there is no “extreme” audience. There is no sort of group that’s just waiting for extreme complex blending of heavy metal and jazz. You are blazing a trail and you’re finding an audience that probably never knew that that music could exist. That’s why we’re talking. Your music is so innovative and creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’d like to know about your creative process. Could you describe how you start with a song, whether it starts with a complex idea or if you kind of manufacture that complexity over time as you investigate where you might want to go with the idea? Or does it just start out with, “I hear &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; based on quintuplets in my head and I need to write this out?” How does an idea start for you and how does it become complex?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Well, yeah. That’s a good question. There are two basic approaches: one is doing original [music] and the other is doing cover [music]. When doing the original, it’s something that I’ve always done, even back in the times when I played in a metal band and I made up some metal riffs–it’s a similar creative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The material gets more complex and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;your ears get used to more and more complex stuff&lt;/span&gt;. Basically, you have an idea in the shower or whatever or walking on the street–I cannot force something. It depends on my mood. Sometimes there is a creative window that opens and, “Oh, there is an idea!” Usually I record it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Usually I don’t have time at that time to go on with it, so I have to record it on my phone, like a little passage. Then when there is some time to dig into it or sink my teeth into composing, then I get back to my phone and have my ideas and try to combine them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Sometimes I’m inspired, sometimes not.&lt;/span&gt; There are not many days in a year that I have this time to do this. Sometimes it takes me a day or something to collect all the ideas or to go on from one idea to finish a song. Sometimes it takes me a couple of days and it’s not even finished and I have to come back to it later. Sometimes it takes even more than a year or even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the songs on the last album &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/breaking-brain/id1043463853&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Breaking Brain&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, there is a song called &lt;em&gt;Smoochy Borg Funk&lt;/em&gt; that the basic idea was something I wanted to use for &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/tank-goodness/id948140673&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tank Goodness&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was over 3 years ago. Then one part was missing and I didn’t know what other part would finish the song. It was missing an idea. So I came back to it years later and then I finished it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Or, the the mustafari song, &lt;em&gt;Mustafari Likes Di Carnival&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Tank Goodness&lt;/em&gt; also, was quite a long process. When the song was finished, still the intro was not there. The intro I wrote one year later, or half a year later, when I had lots of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Usually every idea that comes and fits to some other idea, every idea is making the pool bigger&lt;/span&gt;–the pool that you can draw from. It may not be random stuff, it has to fit together. I try to keep all the ideas in one pool and not make it random, but just throw something into the pool and there aren’t too many elements in the pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As soon as I see something fits together, I say, “Well, that’s good for my pool.” This pool that I have when I do a cover, the cover already gives me ideas in the pool to draw from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; was already a finished structure and I just rearranged it. I tried to find a way to make the same melody inside of this quintuplet grid. This was kind of just editing something. It’s hard to start from scratch with an original song. You need this moment of inspiration that I keep on the phone because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the moment of inspiration, you never can tell when it comes&lt;/span&gt;. So, then there is this later moment of assembling the inspired moments together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-WPWbEXSzUQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This assembling is inspiring in and of itself. From there, it takes only one or two days to finish a whole composition, but the whole process, I cannot even say or generalize how long it takes to write one song. There are many factors. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You need inspiration, you need the right parts, you need luck.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;what I use for composing is the computer. This is probably the most important tool.&lt;/span&gt; I was speaking of the pool of ideas and I’m using the computer to treat those ideas or to make all these rhythmic experiments possible. The computer is extremely helpful because all the polyrhythmic stuff and all these structures of chains of riffs or whatever, I put them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Putting them together on paper would take ten times longer. I don’t hear it in my head. The computer plays it to me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I can just put them together in the computer and the computer plays it to me and I can hear it.&lt;/span&gt; I would not hear it just having the sheet because first I would have to practice it and then I would hear it and then maybe I would say, “No, that’s completely bullshit. I have to try something else.” The computer helps me to instantly hear it and to edit it. So, this is very important to me. Creating this polyrhythmic stuff…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do your ideas start with melodies or riffs or polyrhythm technical ideas? Where are you starting from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yeah, starting is basically a bass and guitar riff. Something like this is the starting point for rhythmic experiments. In &lt;em&gt;Mahna Mahna&lt;/em&gt;, we do 5 against 7. This was from a time where I was experimenting with septuplets and thinking, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“What happens if I group the septuplets in 5?”&lt;/span&gt; Then I didn’t feel it at that time, so I had to make my computer play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Also, the whole thing has to have a harmonic context.&lt;/span&gt; On top of the rhythmic structure, you have a harmonic structure. This is like a third layer. The harmonics and the changes have their own rhythms. Usually the changes go bar by bar. Sometimes–I cannot generalize it, but it’s often like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JfVyrOeQbNA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The harmonic context is a third rhythmic layer also. I wouldn’t be able to hear that in my head. I can just hear what the computer plays to me and just edit. In the same way that I pick up the guitar and find a nice voicing or something, I’m experimenting with several melodic minor and harmonic minor voicings, exploiting the fretboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This is what I do when I practice. Sometimes I come across a cool voicing. It’s the same thing like coming across a nice riff. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When I find something that appeals to my ear, I take it out and drop it into one of the pools I use for the songs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It sounds like the computer opened up new compositional possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Were you composing before you had the computer and was your music anything like what it is now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes. It couldn’t be what it is now without the computer because the computer makes the whole process so much faster. I would get so exhausted or distracted on the way to doing the math of the basic ideas. I would get distracted on the way and I would find other ideas when writing something down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;When the creative window is open, I usually get distracted by my own ideas. The computer doesn’t distract me.&lt;/span&gt; The computer is not distracted. If I have a 23:16 idea, I just put it together times 5. Writing that down would take too long. When writing it down, I’d get a different idea along the way. When the computer does it, it’s just, “Okay, 5 times 23.” When the computer plays it for me, I think, “Oh, that sounds nice, but I have to make some adjustments to make it sound more musical.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t want it to sound mathematical or constructed. It has to sound musical to me.&lt;/span&gt; I also want it to be a construction of doom and be something that really has a high level of sophistication. This high level of unusual sophistication–the thing is “unusual” comes from using the computer because sometimes you can put together ideas you wouldn’t get if you did it another way. This inspires me often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Sometimes I make a mistake and I do some copy and paste stuff and I paste it in the “wrong” place of the grid. The computer will play it to me 1/16 note later and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;this displaced riff sometimes sounds nicer than it did when it wasn’t displaced. This opens a new window for other things.&lt;/span&gt; It’s a mixture of human and computer artwork. It’s a computer-aided composition or creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I think that’s wonderful. Were you exploring with polyrhythms before the computer to a lower degree of complexity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;[Here, Jan’s camera ran out of storage, but I kept rolling with audio from my iPad.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes. Yes. No. Actually, no. I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; experimenting with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metric_modulation&quot;&gt;metric modulation &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because at that time I didn’t know have a sequencer and it was a bigger deal to make tempo changes. This was an obstacle because it was a big deal to make a tempo change on the computer. This was a kind of distraction in the creative process. It was killing creativity. So, I had to find a different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This is something where I could not use a computer (metric modulation). Metric modulation was some of the very first rhythmic sophistication tools I used before the computer. Some other stuff like interlocking of grooves, like &lt;em&gt;Zehrfunk&lt;/em&gt; was interesting because you have one riff and you disperse it on two different instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5YAlXVoc4W8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is one of the things that I do: dispersion of 16th notes.&lt;/span&gt; You have something rhythmic and you give one part to one guitar and the other part to the other guitar and you have a stereo effect. Every part sounds nice and grooving, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;they’re completely displaced and add together as something beautiful. It’s beautiful for itself also.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This is one of the things that the computer is great for. You just select some single notes and do a cut and paste as a separate part, then listen to it and say, “okay, that’s grooving, that sounds great.” Or, “No, this note I have to give to the other instrument and instead of that, I’ll use the third note from the other instrument for the first instrument.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, trying out new things and instantly listening to them and deciding whether they’re good or not. Experimenting with them and getting faster and faster, finding ways to compose. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I got better over the years in what I could do with all the options to make it sound different,&lt;/span&gt; what measures I have to take to make a riff that the computer plays me, but does not yet sound great… What can I do to make it sound great? I get more and more of these options over the years and I know what to do to make it sound better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It’s very interesting. The contrast between your talking about the freshness of improvisation, the ability to (in the moment) be musical, but on the other hand some of your music is so technical and detailed and absolutely precisely constructed… it’s very interesting how you blended those two things. They’re another set of opposites. I know jazz is kind of like that, but you’re going to a different level. You’re going to such a level of complexity that no one can just pick up a chart and go, “Oh yeah, let’s sight-read this track.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How do you feel about that contrast where it’s probably 2AM and you’re moving 23:16, moving certain notes from one instrument to another, doing a cool trade-off thing. But you still want this freshness. Can you talk a little about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the contrast has to be there because the construction is so intricate.&lt;/span&gt; The more I need this other improvisational part of the music, the more complex construction I need, the more I have to practice it, the more time I have to spend learning it–the more I crave the compositional part. And also the contrast. Inside myself, I think the grass is greener on the other side. I’m always wanting the other thing. [Jan’s timer starts beeping.] Oh, shit. Now we have another minute left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So now we need a part 4?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J: Yes. Now it’s getting very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[End of interview.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-3&quot;&gt;End of Part 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just one more part left! Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-4&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt; of this interview…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-3/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-3/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jan Zehrfeld Interview, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of our multi-part interview with Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett, the world’s best and only jazz-metal band. Make sure you read/watch &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; so you are prepared for Part 2!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done with Part 2? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-3&quot;&gt;Check out Part 3&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Panzerballett is? Check out our Discover post about them!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conducted Part 2 on Thursday, November 12 at 1AM Arizona time, which is 9AM in Munich, Germany. I was really tired at first and we talked until almost 4AM my time. Believe it or not, there are two more parts to this interview beyond this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Jan’s camera could only record ~40 minutes at a time, so Part 2 ends abruptly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-2&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-part2-20151112.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-part2-20151112.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OE4mOZ8bX0Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second attempt at a videoconference interview went much better, though I still had a couple issues. Parts 3 and 4 will be slightly better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and we are here for part 2 of our conversation with Jan Zehrfeld. Hello, Jan!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jan: Hello, Anthony!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, in the first part, we ran out of disk space while you were talking about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tribal_Tech&quot;&gt;Tribal Tech &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and who helped you discover some of this complex music. I thought you could finish your answer there and complete the cliffhanger you left us with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Ha! Yes, of course. It was about Tribal Tech and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Henderson&quot;&gt;Scott Henderson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who then became one of my heroes of guitar and as a musician. I was talking about that it was a punch to the face and also to the brain. Later on, when I checked out some of his instruction videos and I’d seen some more concerts, I thought he was one of the coolest guys on the planet and one of the coolest musicians. He does exactly those two things: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He combines these two worlds. He’s a very, very good jazz musician and also has a rock attitude&lt;/span&gt;. This is what always impressed me very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Last year I went to a Tribal Tech concert and, again, he proved it by playing a version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_Will_Never_Be_Another_You&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;There Will Never Be Another You&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with a total punk attitude. It was something that no jazz musician ever could pull off. In the interviews with Scott, he used to say that he sometimes had the urge to tell some jazz-head telling him, “You play rock music! You’re not a real musician. You don’t play jazz.” And he has the urge to say, “First, I’ll kick your ass on &lt;em&gt;Giant Steps&lt;/em&gt; and then I’ll give you a Strat with a Marshall stack and you show me what you can do with it!” So, yeah, it impressed me because he could kick many musicians’ balls. That was Scott Henderson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Li75Dg10FS0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then there was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A drummer back then showed me Meshuggah. He played me the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaosphere&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chaosphere&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album. On the first play, I totally didn’t get it. I just thought, “Well, that’s a good sound and very aggressive.” I mean, I listened to metal a lot, he was a drummer and he told me, “The rhythmic stuff is so checked out. You’re into complex rhythms, so check it out.” In the first place, I didn’t get it. I just thought, “Wow, okay that’s amazing. It sounds kinda new.” But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I didn’t get what exactly made it so different from all the other metal bands I’d heard until I sat down and transcribed something&lt;/span&gt; and got behind their rhythmic principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was good material for my thesis, which I wrote a couple years later. So, it was a drummer friend of mine who played me this. I’m very grateful for that. I would have discovered it later someday, but still, maybe it would have been a couple years later and maybe I would be somewhere else. Who knows? Maybe I would have played some other music like smooth jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then I studied in Graz in Austria and there was this saxophone teacher and I told him, “Well, I like this jazz sound. It’s great. But, I’m also a rock guitar player. Can you recommend something?” He said, “&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Yes, my son! You should listen to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Screaming_Headless_Torsos&quot;&gt;Screaming Headless Torsos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.” That was very good advice! Some of the best advice! I bought their album and fell in love with their sound as well because they have a version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1995_(Screaming_Headless_Torsos_album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blue in Green&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis&quot;&gt;Miles Davis&lt;/a&gt; [and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Evans&quot;&gt;Bill Evans&lt;/a&gt;]. It’s a reggae version of it with punk mixed into it and also jazz improvisation, which was also a starting point for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JRCNotvdEXY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Another fellow student showed me &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planet_X_(band)&quot;&gt;Planet X &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because I was also trying to rehearse fusion with heavy stuff in my very first compositions. He told me, “Well, if you’re into that stuff, you should listen to Planet X.” I checked it out and also was impressed. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_MacAlpine&quot;&gt;Tony MacAlpine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was one of the first… It was the same time as &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; also used the 7-string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I also listened to Steve Vai, but Steve Vai was a secondary influence because it was so much about virtuosity of the guitar, which is so amazing, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I was not aiming for that. I was aiming toward putting together these jazz and metal worlds.&lt;/span&gt; Planet X was doing that as well because they had these really heavy 7-string guitars with fusion harmonies going. Nobody else did it that way. I didn’t know of anything else. This was a big influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_Holdsworth&quot;&gt;Allan Holdsworth &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! My God! I went to a rock guitar clinic from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vinnie_Moore&quot;&gt;Vinnie Moore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Vinnie was talking about him. Vinnie Moore is a very versatile musician and he had a rock class and there were many rock students who didn’t know anything about jazz. Sometimes when he played some very interesting stuff, showed some legato stuff, he told us, “&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Do you guys know Allan Holdsworth is one of the best musicians on the planet&lt;/span&gt; and one of the best jazz guitarists?” This was the starting point where I thought, “Yeah, the legato stuff I like. Vinnie Moore, I think he might be right.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I checked out Allan Holdsworth. I went to the store and got the album &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/None_Too_Soon&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;None too Soon&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where Allan only plays jazz standards, which is actually something like from the point of view now, knowing his other albums, now I know this is something special for him to do jazz standards. It was probably the best starting point you could get because I was learning jazz standards. Also, I saw there was this rhythm section, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Willis&quot;&gt;Gary Willis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Kinsey&quot;&gt;Scott Kinsey &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who were Tribal Tech guys. So I thought, “Well, I have to buy this album. Allan Holdsworth, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I have to check that out. Vinnie Moore said so.&lt;/span&gt;” I checked it out. It was also like an offenbahrung… It was an epiphany, a revelation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eyJLiyUoxsg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Allan Holdsworth for me still–it was ‘98 and this is 2015, so it was 17 years ago–I still do not feel that I have come closer to him. I’ve checked him out a lot, but I don’t feel really significantly closer to Allan’s playing and to his planet because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Allan is from a totally different planet&lt;/span&gt;. I still remember this album, &lt;em&gt;None too Soon&lt;/em&gt;, had a big impact. It was so sophisticated and it was an outlook of how far it could get playing this distorted sound, which I of course like. He has a violin-like approach and these &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&quot;&gt;Coltrane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; lines. It was also very, very important and amazing. I still listen to Allan Holdsworth’s music more than any other artist, actually. You can say &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s music with a lot of content and playing improvisation with a lot of content&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You must have been happy to hear Allan and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virgil_Donati&quot;&gt;Virgil Donati &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; get together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Oh my God! Yes! Virgil Donati! I forgot about him. Virgil was part of the Planet X revelation, of course. Yes! Yes! That was great! We had one tour three years ago when the whole band had an off day and this was close to the city where we played and there was Virgil with Allan on tour. The whole band went and watched Virgil and Allan. It was amazing, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4kpPlh6c6aw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You’ve talked a lot about the rock side of your influences–more of rock than jazz. Did you listen to traditional jazz or any straight-up jazz musicians growing up? Or during these formative times? Like John Coltrane or anyone like that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I did, but not to that extent, I have to admit. I studied jazz music and we were obliged to as good students. I wanted to be a good student. We were obliged to listen to a lot of jazz and there was traditional/mainstream/bebop jazz. I was never really in love with it. Many jazz musicians will say, “I knew that! I knew you were never really in love with it!” I dug it and I appreciated it and I could use all the improvisations from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wes_Montgomery&quot;&gt;Wes Montgomery &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and many more. Not only jazz guitar players like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Martino&quot;&gt;Pat Martino &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Christian&quot;&gt;Charlie Christian &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and the saxophone guys…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the first solos I transcribed was a trumpet solo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clifford_Brown&quot;&gt;Clifford Brown &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, actually. Also, interestingly, was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulf_Wakenius&quot;&gt;Ulf Wakenius &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who later on was a guest on one of our albums. I met his son when I used to live in LA. It was about half a year and in that period I met Ulf’s son, Eric. This was kind of nice because Ulf was one of the first jazz guitarists that I got to listen to and transcribe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5OGoftbnqLM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was always more of an obligation to check jazz out and never–der Funke ist to me übergesprungen richtig–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: “The lightbulb never went off” or something like that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes yes! Something like that. Because it was missing this essential part of music that I wanted to do myself: the aggressive part. The distorted, aggressive, heavy part. It was always missing. So, it was good for the intellectual side. It was appealing, but it was still missing the raw power from metal. There was always something missing. I really practiced this stuff. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I practiced it for three years and almost never played rock or any distorted thing in that time&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It was a little bit frustrating because something was missing all the time and I didn’t even realize it until later, at one point, when there was the exam in the first half of the whole study. It wasn’t the final final, but the first final. I always wanted to be the best and they gave me some medium grade. This was depressing, but there was a good reason. I didn’t deserve anything better because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it didn’t sound very convincing, probably because I saw it as an obligation to play traditional jazz&lt;/span&gt;. They didn’t want me to play anything else. This was just a part of my studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It wasn’t in the final exam, but in one of the concerts before, when I tried out some stuff–and this was some of the first Panzerballett stuff–and I realized &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; was what I wanted to do but &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; was not what they wanted to hear&lt;/span&gt; in the exam. They wanted to hear &lt;em&gt;dip dee doodle-ee dip dee doo dee doo doe dyah doop&lt;/em&gt;. It’s nice. I dig it. But there has to be more or something different to it as well. That’s why I always have to incorporate &lt;em&gt;THIS&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sign_of_the_horns#Heavy_metal_culture&quot;&gt;sign of the horns &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;] here into the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: You’ve mentioned several times that jazz was missing the wrecking ball, but have you ever felt that heavy metal was missing the jazz element of more melodic…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Of course! Of course! If you only have the raw power, it’s nice but that’s why I think there are parallels between the virtuosic metal and classical music because you have to be able to be technically extremely good to perform both like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yngwie_Malmsteen&quot;&gt;Yngwie Malmsteen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has the same “anspruch”–all my German friends know what I want to say. It’s the same “anspruch” like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niccol%C3%B2_Paganini&quot;&gt;Paganini &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jM4W3qaNfng&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Virtuosity? Discipline?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes, maybe. Yngwie Malmsteen blended virtuosity into heavy metal. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_Van_Halen&quot;&gt;Eddie Van Halen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and all the guys &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;we can be grateful to for putting really high class virtuosity into metal&lt;/span&gt; and making it a style that is really for the technical proficient musician. It has become important to practice a lot–8 hours a day–because of Yngwie and Eddie and this is a great thing! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It has this competitiveness&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: They’ve raised the standard. They’ve raised the bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes. But, also, the same thing that I was missing in heavy metal, I’m still missing the openness and the improvisational part. I was studying at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musicians_Institute&quot;&gt;MI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; just for a few weeks and there was a live performance workshop where I played some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pantera&quot;&gt;Pantera &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff. I played the whole thing and then I improvised a solo. During the piece, everything was great. “Yeah! Yeah!” And then during the improvised solo, “What the &lt;em&gt;fuck&lt;/em&gt; are you doing?! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s not the original solo! It’s something different!&lt;/span&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This was something that I never understood. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Why does it have to be the same solo? It’s the MIDI-file attitude;&lt;/span&gt; it has to be performed the same and the same all the time, every evening when you perform this music it will be awesome, but still I need some freshness. It has to stay fresh and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;jazz makes it fresh all the time&lt;/span&gt;. Jazz improvisation makes it different every time. It’s like building something from 0 to 100. This is something that only jazz has–this improvisation and dynamic development inside of a piece. Not only jazz has it, but probably the improvisation can make it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[End of interview.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-2&quot;&gt;End of Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Jan’s camera ran out of disk space. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-3&quot;&gt;Move on to Part 3&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jan Zehrfeld Interview, Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-context&quot;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of a multi-part interview with Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett, the world’s best and only jazz-metal band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done with Part 1? &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-2&quot;&gt;Check out &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-3&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Don’t know who Panzerballett is? Check out our Discover post about them!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the time difference between Arizona and Germany, we conducted this interview early in the morning for Jan and in the middle of the night for myself. I was probably more tired than he was, but it’s hard to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Jan’s camera could only record ~40 minutes at a time, so our interview ended abruptly. I also hadn’t figured out how to record our conversation correctly, so I’m missing the audio and video from my end. And it was so hot in the Arizona summer that I had to run the air conditioner so my computer wouldn’t melt. This made the quality of my audio suck eggs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing this is just a personal hobby project or I’d feel like I really failed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-1&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-part1-20151022.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/panzerballett/jan-zehrfeld-interview-part1-20151022.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kkNfXg1RRuY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first videoconference interview I’ve done with the site. There are some issues that I’m figuring out. This was a great learning experience for me, which probably makes it a less enjoyable viewing and listening experience. Anyone who complains will be justified, but will also be called a “freeloader.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony from MakeWeirdMusic.com and I am here with Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett. Jan, could you introduce yourself? The purpose of the site is to introduce people (particularly musicians) to new music and to expand their horizons. So, go ahead and tell us what you do and how you got into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Jan: Hello! I’m Jan Zehrfeld from Munich, Germany. I started a band called Panzerballett, or “Panzer Ballet” as Americans say it, back in 2004 and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;this is kind of extreme music&lt;/span&gt;. It mixes and blends together styles which are basically far away from each other, like &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;there is a lot of heavy metal in there as well as jazz&lt;/span&gt;. So, you could call it “jazz metal” or “metal jazz” or whatever, also mixed with some other styles like funk and maybe some grooving styles, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think mainly it’s about extremeness and complexity&lt;/span&gt; and about complex rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m a big fan of extremely sophisticated music. Back in 2004, I was just finishing my studies as a jazz guitar player. My influences were, at that time, or my heroes were &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Henderson&quot;&gt;Scott Henderson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tribal_Tech&quot;&gt;Tribal Tech &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planet_X_(band)&quot;&gt;Planet X &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virgil_Donati&quot;&gt;Virgil Donati &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_MacAlpine&quot;&gt;Tony MacAlpine &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meshuggah&quot;&gt;Meshuggah &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mats/Morgan_Band&quot;&gt;Mats/Morgan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which are friends of Meshuggah, also from Sweden. They do kind of similar rhythmic stuff like Meshuggah, but not that heavy. It’s more funky or &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Zappa&lt;/a&gt;-esque, maybe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eQR2nzu3vkc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Well, I’m not a big fan of Frank Zappa, actually, but I dig his music a lot. I mean, I respect it a lot and I can see there are many people drawing parallels between the music I compose and Frank Zappa’s music, which I totally agree to because the basic statement of the music is kind of the same. Panzerballett’s music came many years after and the musical statements are related. I think there is a lot of music that were my main influences that were influenced by Frank Zappa’s music. So, there are big parallels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t actually listen a lot to Frank Zappa&lt;/span&gt; because it’s not my cup of tea. He has lots of criticism about politics happening back then in America, which I don’t know and I’m not inside the whole thing so I don’t understand it that well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And there is a lot of lyrics and I don’t do lyrics &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. I cannot write lyrics, actually. Everything that I’ve tried is nothing that I’d like people to hear. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t think it’s anything that I consider as “worth spreading.”&lt;/span&gt; I think only about the music itself, not about lyrics. I would say, now that I got kind of into a dead end, or blind alley… I was about to explain the music of Panzerballett…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So tell me about when you finished your studies in 2004, how did Panzerballett come about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: I had this vision of what I wanted to do and, having written a thesis about Meshuggah and Meshuggah’s music and development, I got deep into the stuff and transcribed and played and covered some of Meshuggah’s stuff in my final exam… I started composing my own songs during my jazz guitar studies and I thought, “Well, I want to actually form a band that’s playing only my own compositions.” That’s when I started looking for musicians because the band that I had back then for my final exam–it was fun playing with them, but they didn’t have time for a steady band. So, I had to actually look for musicians who had enough time to form a band and to really rehearse a lot and get into things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then I found three guys, Max Bucher, Flo Schmidt, and Gregor Bürger. I knew all of them from the local scene as jazz musicians and Gregor had his own funk big band, which is still happening. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.earforce-bigband.de&quot;&gt;Ear Force &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I played in his big band. The first thing was I was looking for was a keyboard player, but I couldn’t find any. There weren’t that many keyboard players who were much into jazz music or, on the other hand, the jazz pianists playing keyboards with sounds usually didn’t do that. So, there were maybe two or three guys and they were already professionals that didn’t want to or have enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was racking my brain how to solve this problem. Then there was, in a different context, a rehearsal with a band that was rehearsing just for fun and they were already good musicians who didn’t want to join Panzerballett, but they invited me to come into the rehearsal room and they said, “Well, bring your own songs. We can jam on them.” These were a drummer, bass player, and a saxophone player. I thought, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Well, I could compose something for this session without it being a band, but I want to do something cool.”&lt;/span&gt; So, I started composing something for guitar, saxophone, drums, and bass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These were actually the first songs that later I used for Panzerballett. Because it turned out that it’s actually working with heavy guitar and saxophone, these were fusion compositions and it was a lot of fun trying out things with this lineup and this instrumentation. I didn’t think that the saxophone could be something that could play a role like a keyboard, but on the other hand, I found out I could play some of the role the keyboard would, so I found a way for this lineup and instrumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was kind of the starting point for writing my own compositions and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; I found those compositions in Munich for having this steady band and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; we met once a week and rehearsed for half a year and it turned out that it worked and we played our first gig. I think it was half a year later. We formed in January and the first gig was around June or something in a small club. It turned out it was fun and it worked. We decided, “Well, let’s make a record.” I wrote some more songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At first, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it takes a lot of work until you have enough material for a concert and then a CD&lt;/span&gt;. In the concert, there were some songs that were not in 100% in the Panzerballett concept because we played some standards and some blues stuff as well. It wasn’t the thing that I actually wanted to do with Panzerballett. In the end, maybe a couple months later, we had enough material and we went into the studio in March 2005. This was the debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;During the recording of this album, we were a quartet. I found that in the studio, songs were missing a guitar or something. Sometimes the saxophone was standing there a little bit “alone” and I thought, “I could actually do overdubs.” In every song, I found some parts that I could double some guitars or some saxophones and play comping and guitar solos. After we recorded this debut, I thought, “It would be great if we could do this live as well.” So I asked a friend, a second guitar player, who played all these parts live. It was Andreas Dombert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This was the beginning of 2006 when we started to play live as a quintet. From that time on, it’s stayed as a quintet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It turned out that in this Panzerballett sound, you have two main parts: one is the wrecking ball heavy metal part which is the riff part which is bass and rhythm guitar (what I basically do) and then there’s the melody part, which is the saxophone and to support this, the lead guitar doubles the saxophone, which is a nice blend. You can arrange a second voice, which sounds very nice, and the melody part gets stronger and gets equal to the riff part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jM4W3qaNfng?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And of course the drums play a very big role. Or it’s the counterpart? We have two main parts: the drums and the rest of the band because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the drums hold it all together&lt;/span&gt;. All the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyrhythm&quot;&gt;polyrhythmic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff that happens in the composition has to be underlined in the drums. Both parts, which are rhythmically working against each other are brought together in the drums. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It has to happen in the drummer’s brain.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It took some time to realize or to implement and assemble. Sebastian came to the band since our first drummer, Max, came from more of a jazzy funky groovy world and not so much from a metal world. He was not a metal head at all. Sometimes I felt the music needed something like a metal impact from the drummer. He played great, but at some time, when I met Sebastian, I immediately knew that this is the guy that I needed for the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: A perfect fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: A perfect fit! Right! And then we had some other lineup changes, but basically from the time on that Sebastian joined the band, it was sounding already a lot like it sounds now. The first record with Sebastian was &lt;em&gt;Starke Stucke&lt;/em&gt; and then there was this record label, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.actmusic.com/en&quot;&gt;ACT &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was from–actually it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siegfried_Loch&quot;&gt;Siggi Loch &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who founded this label and he used to be the head of Warner at one time, then he founded his own label. This is a very important jazz label. He came to one of our release shows from the debut and he signed us after that after that. He told me, “If we want to work together you have to cover music as well.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;He wanted 50% cover material. It was his concept.&lt;/span&gt; At first, I thought I wanted to only write my own stuff, but then I thought about it and tried to cover and my first cover was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Pink_Panther_Theme&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it was a bit fun and it turns out that it worked. I tried to translate &lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt; into the same style that I composed the other songs. It worked out well and it was fun doing it because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s another way of working because you already have a musical pool you can draw from&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/c27XfStLp1o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This was more than just covering; it was a bigger invasion into the musical material&lt;/span&gt;. I call it “verkrassung,” or the “crassification” of it. That’s kind of my word for it. It’s really an invasion in taking out the elements and putting them together in a completely different way. This was the fun part about it. This is where I think the humor comes from. This is where people recognize some humorous stuff in the arrangements because they recognize what actually happens to the musical material when they know it and they know the original and how I treat the music. They can hear it and recognize it and that’s the fun part about Panzerballett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: After &lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt;, I thought, “Let’s take some more songs that everybody knows from both the jazz world and the metal world.” So, I took &lt;em&gt;Paranoid&lt;/em&gt; and made a jazz ballad out of it. I took &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smoke_on_the_Water&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smoke on the Water&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and translated it. It all worked well and it was kind of the starting point that’s gone until now. The latest record, we have &lt;strong&gt;again&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Pink Panther&lt;/em&gt;. This is an arrangement of an arrangement. We have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mah_Nà_Mah_Nà&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mahna Mahna&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on this record. I’m sure you know it. Everybody knows it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yes. I did an arrangement of it myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Oh really?! I want to hear it! Through all the years, it’s always been my aim and my intention to do research and exploit the old boundaries of what’s possible and to &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;go to the limit of what’s possible for the single player and for the whole band&lt;/span&gt;. If you can play your own part, it doesn’t mean the whole band can play it as well. It was really a lot of work for every single musician separately as well as for the whole band. It’s like building some complex sculpture and you first you have to build the single elements and then you have to put them together. It’s like twice the amount of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It takes a lot of time, especially when we started this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuplet&quot;&gt;quintuplet &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing, it took a lot of work. The first quntuplet arrangement was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Brecker_Bros.&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The whole song is based on quintuplets and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it took us half a year to get through the head of the song&lt;/span&gt;. And then we had to find a way of improvising on it, which took another half a year until we got through it. In the following years, we started to really play it more and more relaxed and now we actually, after writing some more quintuplet arrangements, we got used to it. In the first phases, it was really hard to “get” it. Now it’s starting from zero again because we started from septuplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BFoZoTwGfJk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: When I first heard &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;, I thought, “Are they actually doing this all in quintuplets?” And then I thought, “No, that’s really stupid. Why would anyone do that?” I thought I was totally wrong. Then after about four months of really listening to it, I thought, “No, they really are subdividing quintuplets.” It just blows me away that you did something like that. It’s so detailed and complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Yes, when thinking about it, it blows me away too. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This was the exciting thing about it: to do something that nobody else does.&lt;/span&gt; That way to divide the groove and divide the beat into 5 parts. I didn’t hear it before. Of course in Zappa’s music, you have lots of quintuplets, but not a whole song in quintuplets. Or you have some solo players playing some fast drums in quintuplets, but it’s a totally different effect to arrange something for a whole band based on this quintuplet quantization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I thought I was interpreting it incorrectly because it was so far out of the norm that I must be misinterpreting what was being done. So when I said, “That would be stupid,” I was thinking &lt;em&gt;for me&lt;/em&gt;, “Why would you think that’s what they did? That’s nonsensical.” But that’s what it was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Totally! &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It is total nonsense to do it. And that’s the fun part about it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, you mentioned you’re really into complexity and you’re using these genres that don’t typically go together–jazz and metal. Can you talk about what got you into the complexity and why that is so attractive to you that you wanted to form a whole–not just a band about it, but a completely unique band that blends these interesting genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Well, probably because &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I cannot do anything else than that because anything else would not make sense to me&lt;/span&gt;. It’s a reflection of my own inner way of thinking. From the time that I played guitar or maybe one year after I took up playing guitar, I got into jazz music and I always liked to play jazz music. I decided to study jazz music as well, so this was something that had a big part of my musicianship. It played a very important role to have freedom of improvising and also there’s sophistication and the elaborateness of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The complexity of jazz was always attractive, the harmonies, etc. On the other hand, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the reason I play music is to channel aggression&lt;/span&gt;. The reason why I took up playing guitar when I was 16, it was the time of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guns_N%27_Roses&quot;&gt;Guns n’ Roses &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica&quot;&gt;Metallica &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… The metal boom. The power that came from metal or heavy rock…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AC/DC&quot;&gt;AC/DC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was my first love of rock music. AC/DC had maybe the heaviest impact on my musical taste up to then. The first riffs I learned were AC/DC riffs. I still dig their music a lot. I was recently at a concert on their last tour. It was one of the greatest shows I’ve ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I always needed the wrecking ball in the music and this is something that was always missing in jazz&lt;/span&gt;: the loudness and the distortion. It never got aggressive enough for me. I wanted to blend this. Jazz musicians were kind of denying this or they were basically refusing to play distorted loud music. This element of wrecking ball in heavy metal… they never wanted to do this. So, that was the hard part of finding musicians who are actually willing to play this. A saxophone that wants to play in a band that is loud and playing metal riffs 50% of the time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve always wanted to bring these elements together. I wanted to be able to both do improvisation and play complex stuff and also being kind of the wrecking ball. The music has to have all these free elements. So, that’s what turned out of it. Meshuggah was a big impact because they blended metal with Indian rhythms. This polyrhythmic thing has as great a sophistication as jazz has in a harmonic context. Rhythmic maybe as well. But, Meshuggah, the rhythm is so much more important and is so much more sophisticated. This is something that I really grasped onto. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh yeah. You could say, “I latched onto it,” or, “I grasped it…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Who&amp;#39;s been listening to the new Panzerballett album, &amp;quot;Breaking Brain?&amp;quot; I love it! What do you think? &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/8vDJXoL22G&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/8vDJXoL22G&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Make Weird Music (@MakeWeirdMusic) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MakeWeirdMusic/status/664232776204464128&quot;&gt;November 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: So complexity from jazz harmony, complexity from Indian rhythms or polyrhythms… This always felt great for me to, on the one hand, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;punch the audience in the face by playing really energetic and loud music&lt;/span&gt; and, on the other hand, to make it sophisticated in a way that they actually don’t get it in the first place, or they have to first think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You have two elements: this raw–like in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quentin_Tarantino&quot;&gt;Quentin Tarantino &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; movie–you have this &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;raw power combined with those really sophisticated conversations&lt;/span&gt;. You have both elements and that’s also something for me. Humor comes from music, you have both of these elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Usually you get punched in the face at a metal concert and, of course, meanwhile there are tech metal bands that have lots of sophistication, but then there’s this really jazzy part about it with improvisation. The whole band gets down to almost zero and we start building a groove or we start playing improvisation from zero to 100. In each night you have a different solo, each night something new happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This element was always important to me, to keep it fresh for myself, to keep it fresh for the musicians, not only playing every night the same stuff like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIDI#Standard_MIDI_files&quot;&gt;MIDI file &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; playing every night. You really have something and you build something new. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You have an element of the music that’s open.&lt;/span&gt; This seems appealing to me to have both of these elements. There aren’t that many bands that have both of these elements. For instance, in Tribal Tech it was like that, especially in the era where they played not so much jamming, like the last era where they do lots of jamming. That’s not appealing that much to me. But, in the era where the compositions were extremely elaborate and they also had this amazing improvisation and this was my favorite era of Tribal Tech as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Where did you come across these technical artists? How did you first discover them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;J: Tribal Tech was through a friend of mine. It was the same guy that I played my demo to later on and inspired me to name the band Panzerballett because he said, “It sounds like tanks that are kind of dancing ballet.” It was the same guy who took me–years before that–he was very into technical music, he’s a guitar player who got into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Gilbert&quot;&gt;Paul Gilbert &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt; [NOTE: Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;our Steve Vai interview&lt;/a&gt;!] and all those guitar heroes very early, and he always showed me those guys and he was buying all these guitar magazines, which I did not do at the time, but he got me to this technical music. He also took me to a Tribal Tech concert in Munich. My first experience was not a CD or recording, but a live concert and it was a punch in the face, and to the brain as well. And it was so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-1&quot;&gt;End of Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Jan’s camera ran out of disk space. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-2&quot;&gt;Check out Part 2 for more&lt;/a&gt; and then &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld/part-3&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/jan-zehrfeld/</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lyla by Avishai Cohen</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-we-learning&quot;&gt;What are we learning?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post explores a solo guitar arrangement I did of a beautiful song called &lt;em&gt;Lyla&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/avishai-cohen&quot;&gt;Avishai Cohen&lt;/a&gt;. The original recording features &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhodes_piano&quot;&gt;Fender Rhodes keyboard &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, drums, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_bass&quot;&gt;upright bass &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, flute, and trumpet. I’m a sucker for moody songs played on the Rhodes (see also &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt;’s incredibly beautiful song, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/the-power-and-the-glory/id731975200&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aspirations&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) and this song certainly fits that description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was immediately attracted to this song when I first heard it a few years ago and it’s never quite left my short-term musical memory banks. At some point, I realized the sheet music for the song was available in Avishai’s online store, so I bought it and saw that it could probably be arranged into a nice solo guitar piece. It took over a year of sporadic effort to turn it into what we’ll cover in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/avishai-cohen&quot;&gt;Check out our Discover post about Avishai Cohen!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instructional-video&quot;&gt;Instructional Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put together an instructional video that illustrates everything in the charts below. Watch that if, like me, you don’t like reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VIDEO COMING SOON&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheet-music&quot;&gt;Sheet Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an incredible web app that offers HTML5 sheet music without the need for Adobe Flash or any other plugins. It’s super-duper awesome. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the score for performing &lt;em&gt;Lyla&lt;/em&gt; on guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/36180/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re interested, here are the &lt;a href=&quot;http://musescore.org&quot;&gt;MuseScore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and MusicXML files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/lyla/lyla.mscz&quot;&gt;MuseScore (.mscz) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.rawgit.com/MakeWeirdMusic/assets/master/learn/lyla/lyla.xml&quot;&gt;MusicXML (.xml) &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;structure&quot;&gt;Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main parts to this arrangement (the original recording has 3 or 4 parts). There’s the opening section that’s fairly straightforward consisting of chord triads. I’ll call that ‘Part A’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part, ‘Part B,’ is the part with the beautiful harmonic minor melody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;harmonic-minor&quot;&gt;Harmonic Minor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re unfamiliar with the harmonic minor scale, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minor_scale#Harmonic_minor_scale&quot;&gt;Wikipedia has a nice entry about it &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s the scale that’s most often used to play Middle Eastern-sounding music. It’s a natural minor scale with a raised 7th note. Avishai plays with the scale in the Part B melody, but if you think of it as staying within B harmonic minor, you’ll be all right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a C major scale: C D E F G A B C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a C natural minor scale: C D &lt;strong&gt;Eb&lt;/strong&gt; F G &lt;strong&gt;Ab&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Bb&lt;/strong&gt; C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a C harmonic minor scale: C D Eb F G Ab &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the 3rd, 6th, and 7th change between major and natural minor. Then notice that the 7th changes between the natural minor and the harmonic minor. Alternatively, the 3rd and 6th are the only notes that differ between a major and harmonic minor scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrelevant conceptual question: Can you guess what a C harmonic major scale looks like based on the above information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performing-and-hands&quot;&gt;Performing and Hands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that left-hand fingerings are quite a stretch at times. Maintaining consistently solid notes is a huge challenge, as is playing the piece with continuity between measures. Part B relies on a series of minor 2nd intervals since it’s based in harmonic minor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part A has its own challenges, though. That stretch in measure 17 is a doozy to play smooth. Same with measure 18 and 19. Further beware of transitioning out of those little fills around the open high E string and effortlessly landing on that Bb major triad. Tough stuff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace_note&quot;&gt;grace notes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the score. Those are the little notes with lines through them. They’re basically “notes of no rhythmic value.” In other words, play them as fast as you can before playing the following note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll also note some notes with “4:3” within brackets. This is a particular &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuplet&quot;&gt;tuplet &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; called a quadruplet. That means that 4 beats will replace 3 beats. In the case of this song, two quadruplet quarter notes are equal duration to a non-quadruplet dotted quarter note. Clear as mud, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this piece can be played with a pick, I recommend playing with fingers instead. It’s a little more sensible and this is a sensitive piece of music that can use the finesse and softness of fingers. I’m a self-avowed picking nerd and I can’t imagine wanting to play this piece with a pick. But, to each his/her own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the melody in Part B beginning on the 3rd beat of each measure, you’ll want to lead with the fingers that play the melody. I’ve indicated left hand fingerings with the little numbers near the note heads in the upper stave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-signature&quot;&gt;Time Signature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song is in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triple_metre&quot;&gt;the 3/4 time signature &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is normally pretty straightforward. What makes this song difficult from a time perspective is where the accents live in Part B. The melody begins on the 3 and the rhythm support is on 1 and 2. Traditional 3/4 songs usually have the melody begin on beat 1, but this song’s melody lives almost entirely within beat 3. Pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/lyla/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/lyla/</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
