<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>A resource for musicians to discover new artists, learn weird music techniques, listen to interviews, and share their weird music.
</description>
    <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 23:10:14 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 23:10:14 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Morgan Ågren Releases</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-releases&quot;&gt;New Releases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2016, we did &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/morgan-agren&quot;&gt;a lengthy interview with Morgan Ågren&lt;/a&gt; and he mentioned a couple new releases to be released later in the year. Well, it’s December 2016 and the releases are–well, released. I thought it’d be cool to hear Morgan himself tell us about the new CDs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/through-the-eyes-of-a-morgchestra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/35th-anniversary-collection-2cd-25-hours&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mats/Morgan 35th Anniversary Collection&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Morgan for chatting with us again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/irRvqSiasPI?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcription&quot;&gt;Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I have with me today, all the way from Sweden, Morgan Ågren. Morgan, thank you so much for joining. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Well, it’s my pleasure. I saw some other people that you have online here, so it’s my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you have two new releases out and I thought it’d be cool to hear in your own words what they are and what they mean to you. So, go ahead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah! Actually, two albums happened just very recently and neither of these albums were really planned as a regular release. One of them is this one [holds up the CD], which is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/through-the-eyes-of-a-morgchestra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it features the music that we performed with the symphony orchestra two months ago. I started to compose for this project a year ago, like in October 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;While doing that, in order to be able to do music for the symphony orchestra, I needed to have sounds to allow me to hear how it could possibly sound later. So, I installed good string plugins and bassoons and all the orchestra. Then slowly I started to try to build up the music and 6 months later, without having even thought about it, I just realized one day when I went through the material, “Hmm, this sounds like an album.” When I realized that, I started to work on the music so it would be good for release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DyfNjA7ApCs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At that moment it was almost good enough for release, but I did some more changes. I replaced some programmed clarinet, bassoon, and stuff with real bassoons, clarinets, violins, upright bass, and some other instruments replaced by real musicians who came to my studio. I wanted to give that extra push to everything. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In one way, it’s the best work I’ve done in my life, I think.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s quite different from what Mats and I do regularly or my own stuff. When I composed for this, I had to think about the fact that it’s an orchestra that will perform it. It’s a bit different because the sound from an orchestra is fantastic. Even when they tune, you have this incredible sound. Then there are some limits rhythmically speaking. You don’t want to do anything too complicated, rhythmically speaking. That’s one thing to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I added my strings in Pro Tools and then I started to fool around with clarinet. Simple sounds, like standard clarinet sounds, and then the music came out. I didn’t really know that I would be able to end up with material because this is not the typical way for me to compose. I think it’s one of the best things I’ve ever done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s great! &lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; is available now through BandCamp and through your website, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should purchase &lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/through-the-eyes-of-a-morgchestra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Through the Eyes of a Morgchestra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; via BandCamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, there are hard copies to get through my home page and I have a box ready for Steven at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cuneiformrecords.com&quot;&gt;Cuneiform Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He will sell them and make them available through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waysidemusic.com&quot;&gt;Wayside Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And sometime in late January, it’s going to be out on all the iTunes, Spotify, and stuff. I also gave up the good and bad thoughts about streaming. Finally I just–well, never mind. I’m going to put everything there, finally. I don’t know if that’s good or not. It’s probably good beacuse people are going to be able to hear it and people don’t buy that many CDs, but some still are. This is a separate discussion for, like, a 2 hour discussion on streaming or not. I decided to use it. It’s going to be there in the end of January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent. And then you have a second release, the &lt;em&gt;35th Anniversary Collection&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ljqNLREnXnM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, this is the anniversary collection [holds up the CD]. This was very natural for me to put together because I realized last year that next year is going to be 35 years that me and Mats have played together. Then we wanted to plan some cool things to do because of that fact that we’ve been playing together for 35 years. So, we had only a couple weeks ago, we had two concerts in Stockholm in this old, super-nice theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Usually, we used to play at the local jazz club called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fasching.se&quot;&gt;Fasching &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We played there for 25 years and it’s easy and it works. I would just call them and then we’d play. You know, 330 people maximum, so usually we’d set up and play and it’s super nice. But this time, having an anniversary, we wanted to have a little more like a celebration edge to it. So, I got in contact with this theater and we had two dates there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then I started to try to put together a “best of” collection. That took quite some time, actually, because it was not easy. There is quite a lot to choose from and you have to use this “kill your darlings” thing. There’s stuff you maybe want to have, but it’s only 77 minutes per disc. It’s a double CD, but it was still really hard to pick. After finding which songs to use and after putting them in a nice order, it’s like a new album. Track number 1 fits well with track 2 and there might be 10 years between them as to when we recorded them. Now I think it’s like a new album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I spent time with a really expensive guy doing remastering. He got me a really nice deal and I think that now it’s a 6-page digipak and a 60-page booklet. Super good and remastered. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I would say that this is the only Mats/Morgan album you need.&lt;/span&gt; If you want only one album, this will be pretty much everything you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;You should also purchase &lt;a href=&quot;https://morganagren.bandcamp.com/album/35th-anniversary-collection-2cd-25-hours&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mats/Morgan 35th Anniversary Collection&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; via BandCamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wLmtuhaCc2c?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s really, really cool. When does that come out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: The physical copies are all ready. They’re available on my homepage. I’m going to send Steven at Wayside some copies, too. That one is also going to be available on iTunes and Spotify and stuff in January. I should also take the opportunity to thank Steven at Cuneiform because all the releases have 5-year contracts and a bunch of the tracks that I really wanted to have on this collection–I printed both of these myself, so I needed to ask him permission to use different songs on the album. He was fine with that, so I’m happy because of that. Now it’s really good, I think, and it has some nice pictures inside. I had to go through a lot of hard disks to find photos and stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. How was the Morgchestra show? We talked last time and it was shortly before the shows, so we wanted to wait and talk again. So, how did it go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: I was very happy. It’s a mixed feeling because when I came to the rehearsal hall the first day, I heard the orchestra rehearsing my music even before I got to the stage. I was leaving my bags and stuff behind the stage and while doing that I heard &lt;em&gt;my chords&lt;/em&gt; played &lt;em&gt;by them&lt;/em&gt; and that’s a really unreal feeling. It’s huge and it’s fantastic and all that. At the same time, it’s scary because you want this to be–it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be good. I would prefer it to be perfect, but it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be good enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Somebody decided that we were going to get this request, it costs money, there are lots of people involved and it’s a big thing. Very few people get this kind of request at all, so it’s not something that you take lightly. It has to be good. Even a year before when I started to compose it, I thought, “This &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to be good.” Everything has to be good in order for it to be worth it for the people who asked us and in order for us to feel that we can do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are limits, rhythmically and there’s a rock band with an orchestra, so it can be loud and all these possible problems that can happen. But, I think I would definitely say that the orchestra in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umeå&quot;&gt;Umea &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.norrlandsoperan.se/sve&quot;&gt;Norrlandsoperan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a very good orchestra. The conductor told me that he works with tons of orchestras and this is one of the top 3 that he’s worked with. The median age is quite young. So, the typical 60-year-old Mozart-only guy won’t want to do anything other than Mozart wasn’t there. There were maybe a few, I don’t know, but it was a very positive vibe with happy faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The volume wasn’t as big an issue as a month before when we were in Germany. Mats and I went to Germany to do a separate project with the orchestra in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leipzig&quot;&gt;Leipzig &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That was different because then you can feel that as soon as they saw the little Marshall combo and the drums, it was like they put their fingers in their ears. But, this was really good here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IqvWwwUxz5U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But then there is three short rehearsals and there’s always very few hours to rehearse and there’s tons of music. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Also one thing that I noticed was that I know this music in my sleep because I spent so much time with it. But, when we started to rehearse, everything sounded different.&lt;/span&gt; My own computer versions I know, but the real thing with all those sounds that were supposed to give me cues to the next part weren’t there any longer. So, suddently I was feeling unsure where we were in certain parts of the songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The timing is different and there is always the conductor “thing.” You have a conductor and there’s always a delay with “one.” [Conducts in the air.] The delay is incredible sometimes. The orchestra is used to that. They just play. For me, I played exactly on the one, but the orchestra played with a delay. There is a balance. You might have some patterns you’re supposed to play with a tuba guy fifty feet away and you can’t hear each other really. All those kinds of things. It was better than I dared to hope for, I think. It was really good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. So, for anyone who is just getting exposed to that, the Morgchestra CD is a recording of you and musicians in your studio and your computer. But, the show was a live representation of that music and more, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, it’s the same exact compositions in form and themes and everything, but performed by a full-sized symphony orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And I imagine you recorded it and, hopefully, will release it at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Yeah, that was another thing. When I decided to release the pre-production, I thought, “It doesn’t really matter if we end up having a good recording of the live thing. We can release that later because it’s going to be different with a full orchestra.” So, yeah, I did record it. That also required some telephone calls because this was performed during the jazz festival in Umea and Swedish radio was there to record most of the stuff that happened during the festival. Then there is always this big radio bus outside the festival house that records everything and there’s no way they’d give you a hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know some people, though, you can always try to have a split cable and record your own audio files on your own hard drive. Then there is a different situation. But, yeah, so I have 64 tracks and I have everything on video. At this moment, I don’t dare to listen to it because I want to keep the memory alive. I worked so much the last couple of months I don’t have the energy to even go into it yet. But, I will open it up next year, for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. Man, congratulations Morgan. That’s really fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomtrapp.net&quot;&gt;Tom Trapp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was a super nice conductor who also was the arranger. We did another project this year with this symphony orchestra. It was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Duke&quot;&gt;George Duke &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tribute. So, same symphony orchestra and then a big band, me and some other guys. &lt;a href=&quot;http://byronmillerpsychobass.com/&quot;&gt;Byron Miller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on bass (George Duke’s old bass player), me and Mats and some other guys. Then for this George Duke project, it was also the same conductor and we liked him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;After the first coffee break at the first rehearsal, I said to Mats, “This guy is easy to follow.” He plays guitar also. He goes down to his rehearsal space and puts the Marshall amp on 10 and he plays. Not every conductor does that, you know? He has a little bit of both sides, both worlds. So it was a great decision to involve him on this, I think. He did stuff with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropole_Orkest&quot;&gt;Metropole Orkest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Holland. He did some stuff with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd_Rundgren&quot;&gt;Todd Rundgren &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomtrapp.net/for-others/by-artist-name/&quot;&gt;people like that &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And George Duke, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, that’s cool. Did you capture the 35th Anniversary shows?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Same thing. Yes, I did. So, there were a couple of cameras and 36 channels recorded. Same thing there. I’m going to open that up sometime early next year. It was great, because the 35th anniversary concerts were so nice. In the 1990s we were a quintet, so we had a different bass player, keyboard player, and guitar player than now. We haven’t played together in quite some time, but I called them up and asked them if they wanted to join for this anniversary thing. They did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, the quartet that started about 3 years ago kicked off the show and we played for an hour and a half or something, then the keyboard player and bass player left the stage and then I brought in the three other guys from the quintet. We played some old stuff, like three or four songs and then at the end, all of us played together. Then we had another guest that no one in the US knows, I think, but he’s a famous stand-up comedian, super super weird guy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Wahlbeck&quot;&gt;Peter Wahlbeck &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He did a couple of projects that Music Für Alle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AR-qgWgrB_M?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What does that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: “Music for everyone” in German, I think. He did some cool things, super underground. We performed two songs with him at the end. All seven of us plus him and again, this really nice theater. People came from a long way. I had people from France and Germany that came to see us. My first teacher from school, who is now 92 years old, she was in the audience. She came there in a wheelchair. Parents from people in the band, my parents. It was a really, really nice thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s excellent. Cool! Well, thank you so much for your time and for the update. I really appreciate it. I think there’s some really cool information here. I’ll make sure to get the links and stuff and your promo stuff out on Make Weird Music. Cool, thank you Morgan!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MA: Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/morgan-agren/morgchestra</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/morgan-agren/morgchestra</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>X-JAMM at NAMM 2017</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 05:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/link/x-jamm-2017/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/link/x-jamm-2017/</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Moulettes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Moulettes are a progressive folk/alt pop band from Brighton, England. They write great music and are even better live than they are on record. I saw them perform twice in Montreal when I &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/kerry-minnear&quot;&gt;attended GORGG 2015&lt;/a&gt;. One member of the band, Dr. Ruth Skipper, played the electric bassoon (a technique she learned from &lt;a href=&quot;/interiew/paul-hanson&quot;&gt;Paul Hanson&lt;/a&gt;) and autoharp. Their performance was so powerful, I couldn’t believe what I was hearing and seeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took several months to coordinate, but our schedules finally aligned and we got an interview set up. I hope you enjoy these authentic musicians and their attitude of wonder toward the world and music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moulettes.co.uk&quot;&gt;Check out Moulette’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our interview with Ollie Austin and Hannah Miller of Moulettes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tx0rhXKXiOg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://alanmillerguitars.co.uk&quot;&gt;Alan Miller guitars &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Alan is Hannah’s father and makes incredible instruments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/moulettes.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/moulettes.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Rod Knowlan, guitarist for the Vancouver, Canada-based indie rock band, &lt;a href=&quot;http://headmusic.ca&quot;&gt;HEAD &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Rod is also a fan of all manner of music, weird and otherwise. I met Rod at GORGG 2015 in Montreal, where I also met the Moulettes! What a day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hi, this is Anthony with makeweirdmusic.com and I have special guests here from England, the band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moulettes&quot;&gt;Moulettes&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve got Ollie Austin and Hannah Miller. Ollie and Hannah, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Thanks for having us Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No problem. So, I’ll let you guys get this started, can you tell us about Moulettes and can you tell us about the history of the band a little and about what makes you unique?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Where do we start? I suppose Moulettes has been the project that Hannah and myself have been doing since we were at college together. It’s a bit more of a band, we’ve grown up with it as well so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s a cult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It’s a cult, yeah, [laughs]. Many people have come and gone over the years, it’s been quite a ride, really, since we were sixteen or seventeen. We’re four albums down and we’re about to start making our fifth album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What makes us unique? Wow, what a question! It’s great that you would say that about us. I think that we are unique, I think that’s what we strive for so hopefully it’s our own type of uniqueness and eclecticism that people like about the band. Just by you saying that, that’s a nice achievement in itself, really. I suppose it’s what we aim to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We don’t aim to regurgitate old things, we certainly aim for the opposite, I would say&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: There’s plenty of bands out there, plenty of artists working out there that, like you said, would deliberately regurgitate stuff…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Or working within already quite familiar parameters, I guess regurgitating has a bit of a vomity vibe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bZTibl44hNg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s a lot of vomit out there…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: There is quite a lot of vomit out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the parameters that you put into play that are unique? I’m thinking around Ruth Skipper and her electric bassoon, the kind of instrumentation that you have, the vocal harmonies… What are some of the things you guys use to make your music sound like it’s not a regurgitation of something else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Well, I suppose one really fortunate thing for me is that my dad, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alanmillerguitars.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Alan Miller &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is a luthier. He’s always been really great in that he’s made me these custom instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Look at this beautiful guitar…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, wow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: This is probably the most normal, I could get some other ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: He gets pretty far out, he’s great to experiment and discuss other possibilities of instruments and he’s made some pretty strange things for us in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I subscribed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/alanpmiller&quot;&gt;him on Youtube &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; after I met you in Montreal and I had asked Hannah about her cello. It’s so beautiful, he’s got so many great instruments, and demos on his Youtube channel, it’s been cool to see his process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2JNIXJsnh9o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: He just finished a twin-neck mandolin. In fact, he’s coming to stay next week and he said, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“I want to make something new, I’m bored with making things that have already existed.”&lt;/span&gt; Maybe that’s where some of this impetus comes from. He’s always been around being really keen to help build things that haven’t been built before. I’ve got a six-string cello over there which sounds amazing. The bottom string is a low E, which is quite a long way below my normal bottom string, it’s just great, it sounds like a panther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA:  You can always get interesting sounds playing with acoustic instruments and making them do things that they’re perhaps not made to do. You can discover some quite interesting things about acoustic instruments. You mentioned Ruth’s bassoon, and Hannah’s five-string cello, we’ve kind of always been trying to experiment with both acoustic setups, whether it be strings or brass or woodwind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We like to do big rock shows and there a production no-man’s land and in terms of being able to make some acoustic instruments work on a big stage&lt;/span&gt; was to put them through amps. You get feedback problems, you can’t quite crank the pickup up enough so part of the fun of what we’ve tried to do is to look into new ways to, like with Hannah’s electric cello, for example, it’s an acoustic and an electric instrument and you can really crank it up and it’s not affected by the drums. We have a lot of fun with that, experimenting with new instruments. Riding the balance between acoustic and electric is something we’ve done a lot in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For people who don’t know about your band, if this is their first time hearing about you, can you tell us how many people are in the band and what everyone plays and what a live performance is like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We’re not really sure of how many people are in the band.&lt;/span&gt; [laughs] It always changes! For &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; we made a point of making a record that sounded like the band that was going to tour it. There’s many different approaches to doing albums and we set different parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZBDfcRm2u6U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;em&gt;Constellations&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: &lt;em&gt;Constellations&lt;/em&gt;, the one before &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;, I think has about 30 players on it. It’s got a lot of our favorite players. One of the purposes of the concept of the album was to tell the story of Moulettes up to that point. We kind of got players from all around, from bands that we liked, session players, both players that have been on the scene for years and current players. That was kind of like a big chamber orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; was very much more “let’s get a band in the room rocking out” kind of vibe. That has 5 people on it, electric cello, drums, electric guitar, bass and we all play synths and then the bassoon through distortion. It’s very much a “band in the room.” That was the concept behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, that was the instruments concept. Both of those records are conceptual in their nature as records. The most recent one, &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;, was centered around the natural world and taking each song as a particular creature. We used that as a starting point for inspiration behind the song. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;In terms of uniqueness, I haven’t found any songs that are about this specific nematode worm, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halicephalobus_mephisto&quot;&gt;halicephalobus mephisto nematode worm &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; That could be a first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Could be!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; is your latest album. It seems to be getting some pretty good press and it’s very well received. Have you been touring? What’s been the activity around the album?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: We did our first big coast-to-coast tour of Canada, we’d been there the season before but in this case we started at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stan_Rogers_Folk_Festival&quot;&gt;Fanfest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–would you technically say that it’s in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Breton_Island&quot;&gt;Cape Breton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: I don’t know, I don’t think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Then we did &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montreal_International_Jazz_Festival&quot;&gt;Montreal Jazz Festival &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was incredible. Then we went all the way across to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver&quot;&gt;Vancouver &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver_Island&quot;&gt;Vancouver Island &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We’re still touring it now, we’ve got a European leg coming up. Because we did the tour of Canada last year and around the release and we’re doing a series of UK festivals and the European ones this time out. It was nice, as well, for the &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; campaign, the welcoming in of it, we sold out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_Chapel,_Islington&quot;&gt;Union Chapel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in London, which was a big deal for us. It’s one of those amazing venues that you always want to play at. I’ve been to several gigs there as a kid, seeing bands, so to actually sell it out it was… it’s this amazing, Gothic-style building, it’s really eerie and dark…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s a beautiful church, massive stained-glass window…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: So it’s good to start off on that positive and it’s been really interesting to see who pops up their head in all the different compartments of the music industry. You often have proggers, indie rock people, folkies. It’s interesting who pops up and says “I really dig this, I really like this.” It seems to happen every time with different people with every album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Quite inter-generational as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8vYHuxYxUGE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When I saw you open for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Friends_(band)&quot;&gt;Three Friends &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Montreal I was just blown away! I had no idea there would be an opening act for the show so it was my first exposure to you and I felt like you guys blew the doors off of that show. It sounded incredible, the performances were incredible and I will never forget hearing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bZTibl44hNg&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Behemooth&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, it’s such a powerful song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;em&gt;Behemooth&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us a little bit about the new album and some of the dynamics going on and some of the concept? I have never heard a song about a massive sound heard in the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: There was a lot of speculation about that particular sound, which is known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloop&quot;&gt;“The Bloop” &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. During the initial stages of writing it, you know when you go down a little Internet rabbit-hole and you kind of get excited about something and it soon becomes more and more obvious that it’s very unclear what the facts are. That’s how this started, there was a lot of speculation about noise because of the people who were talking about it. If you listen to the noise–have you done that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Of course! I showed my kids! I told them all about your album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: The noise itself is very eerie and it does sound like a big, massive mammal. But there are people who say it was an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cryoseism&quot;&gt;ice-quake &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or the sound of a distant ice-quake. But I haven’t had any confirmation on either side as to what it is. The whole point is, we changed the meaning of that song so it isn’t just about that noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Made it about scientific enquiry…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, about the speculation itself…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OA: And the dialogue around it. It’s still a very relevant subject, about how people talk about science and what they think is true and what is not. One of the strands of all of Moulettes albums, including Preternatural, is there’s always a celebration of science or a discussion of science. There’s also an underpinning of some environmental stuff that we are very interested in.{: .interviewee }&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We’re from Brighton, one of the only places that has a Green (Party) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_parliament&quot;&gt;MP &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it’s the only Green MP in the UK. We are engaged on a kind of political level but it’s not kind of in your face, it’s trying to start a discussion, really, about certain issues like animals… it’s great fun, kids love it as well. Like Hannah was saying… it’s great inter-generational stuff. It’s great what some people come up with when you have animals involved. There are some massive animal lovers out there, serious animal lovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Everyone can agree on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Attenborough&quot;&gt;David Attenborough &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as well, that’s a really nice thing. He sent me a letter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Maybe we should show it, it’s one of our proudest moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: This young woman, I don’t know how old she was, maybe 15, who is also a cellist, came up to me after a gig and she was so excited about this nematode worm, and she correctly categorized it as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extremophile&quot;&gt;extremophile &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s one of these creatures that lives in circumstances that we previously thought were impossible (to harbor life). Anyway, we sent David Attenborough the CD and the vinyl (of &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/77WGYFIiryA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: What was amazing about it was that he was celebrating his 90th birthday that week and he apologized in the letter for being slow to reply. It only took him a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And hand-written! That’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, what is your tie to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentle_Giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? You opened up for Three Friends, you hung out with the whole GORGG crew, the Gentle Giant celebration. What is your tie there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: A love of great music, I think. Talking about your [Hannah’s] dad again, he was a Gentle Giant fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: IS a Gentle Giant fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, it was great meeting the GORGG. The obvious connection is Jim (Mortimore), who plays the bass in Moulettes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Jim joined us just at the end of the second album campaign and he’s just been brilliant, he’s a brilliant musician. He’s the son of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm_Mortimore&quot;&gt;Malcolm Mortimore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who was one of the drummers from Gentle Giant and is the drummer on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Friends&quot;&gt;Three Friends &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He’s an incredible drummer. Malcolm has managed to play with incredible players. We’ve met some of the best people in the business by hanging out with Malcolm. We managed to meet &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Flowers&quot;&gt;Herbie Flowers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Herbie Flowers even played on our last record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, wow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: He’s one of the thirty people that we managed to get to come and play. Herbie Flowers is one inspiration, how many good records has he been on? How many good records did Gentle Giant make? It all started with records, I guess… and discovery. We’ve always been into prog music–not that Gentle Giant is just prog music, it’s its own entity…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: And world… The amazing thing about having Herbie play on the last record was that you really recognized that bass, he’s always played the same electric and the same upright bass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It’s the same sound that you hear on the records…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: That sounds like stating the obvious, really, but it was so familiar as well, from things like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walk_on_the_Wild_Side_(Lou_Reed_song)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Walk on the Wild Side&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I think he played both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XBXUP5GqYJs?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Acoustic and electric when he did the harmony, yeah. As soon as he picked up and played the double bass on &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/moulettes/07-land-of-the-midnight-sun-feat-herbie-flowers&quot;&gt;Land of the Midnight Sun &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and we were listening to it I thought “that’s signature Herbie.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Like some of your favorite records… yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: A great musician. And he’s hilarious, really good company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So for people who have never heard Moulettes, where would you recommend they start and where are you guys going next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Where would they start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: I suppose start with the recent thing then go back. Each album is completely different so if you’re prepared for that and the different instrumentation and all sorts of stuff–it’s all different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: We’re going to say that because you’re always into the last thing you’ve done, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: What’s great is that the recent album, &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt;, is more reflective of what the band actually sounds like live. All the other albums we’ve done, we’ve had a flux of players in and out during the session and then see who’s around for the campaign. I would say that to see the show, &lt;em&gt;Preternatural&lt;/em&gt; is a rock show and I think we’re probably going to stay in that realm–probably, we don’t know, really. We like to mix it up but I’m enjoying playing the bigger shows, the bigger festivals and putting out a bigger sound. Crank it up, use some amps… that’s probably where we’re going to explore, I’d say. Who knows, it’s all up for grabs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Well, there’s more to it than that, as well. There’s quite a lot of different moods on the record so there’s something you could find that you enjoyed on it. Each song was built around what we thought the creature would want or what the themes of the song kind of evoked. There was quite a comprehensive thought process between how they all sound. So, obviously, &lt;em&gt;Behemooth&lt;/em&gt;, being this big gentle giant of the ocean wanted quite a grandiose prog anthem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xeYeNdUo3uA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Naturally. So we were kind of guided by that kind of idea, that kind of a theme song for the beast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: You can always depend on a concept album as well from us. We love to get stuck into a concept album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Love of parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Next record, we haven’t decided on the concept, I don’t know, do you have any ideas for a concept, a good concept?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, if you guys are into science there’s that show &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fringe_(TV_series)&quot;&gt;Fringe &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s all sorts of odd topics or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_X-Files&quot;&gt;X-Files &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you could look at extraterrestrial type things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Whoa… [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Or some of the ideas behind quantum physics, like given an infinite amount of time you have an infinite probability that certain odd things could happen… and odd things happen all the time. Media is everywhere now so strange things are reported all the time. There’s that show &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stranger_Things_(TV_series)&quot;&gt;Stranger Things &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on Netflix that’s kind of taking off. There’s a societal or cultural fascination with inexplicable things. I think that’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Do you think we’re alone out here or do you think there are extraterrestrial beings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Definitely…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think the universe is so big, it’s like that line in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contact_(1997_American_film)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Contact&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that says it’d be an awful waste of space…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: If there was only us…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! There’s so much space out there, there are so many planets that have to be supportive of life. I would bank on the likelihood, looking at the universe from a distance (not that I can do that), looking at something that big and I just can’t believe that we’re the only things out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OA: There’s an interesting theory–I mean there’s a lot of theories about the universe, as you know–but one of the ones that I really find fascinating is in, I would say maybe the evangelical Christian world, when I was talking about the size and scope of the universe, there’s a whole group of Christian believers thinking that, essentially, the universe was made to live eternally in it so it’s that big because we have to live in it for eternity, or, at least, it was initially designed to be like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hm…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Which is just nuts–I love all the different points of view of those things–but even if you live forever, you might get bored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: The universe is definitely finite, we’ve worked that one out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: I was reading recently about this topic and what the inference was that we were so low down the scale of intelligence that there are a bunch of other higher intelligent forms of life but they’re not bothering with us because they’re just watching the car crash thinking, “Oh, no.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: There are lots of interesting theories, like the one that you don’t want to encounter extraterrestrial life because if you do, they’re likely so far advanced…. I forget, there are something like two or three different perspectives from a couple of scientists that either the other races have already existed and have wiped themselves out or have been wiped out somehow or that they exist somewhere else… I don’t know. There are a bunch of interesting theories that could make for a good concept. Or you could just prime the punch and make an album about that. [NOTE: I was thinking about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi_paradox&quot;&gt;Fermi Paradox &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/553MXNe0wfc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Sounds good, taking a book is a good idea, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sum:_Forty_Tales_from_the_Afterlives&quot;&gt;Tales of the Afterlives &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Brian Eno did a series on that. That’s a good angle as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurie_Anderson&quot;&gt;Laurie Anderson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; did one on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moby-Dick&quot;&gt;Moby Dick &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I actually did one with my dad on Moby Dick and one on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilgamesh&quot;&gt;Epic of Gilgamesh&lt;/a&gt;. We made albums about those stories, it was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah! Good ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: You know that octopuses have the most complex sequence of DNA that we know of, including being more complex that ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! They just discovered that those little water bears…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tardigrade&quot;&gt;Tardigrades &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! They just did a DNA sequence on those and the least DNA in common with any other animal on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: And they can actually survive in space for like…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Three years…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Three years. Those guys are hard-core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Maybe we should just do a post hard-core album or even just a straight-up hard-core album about the tardigrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, with the 5-sting cello distorted..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, man. You got it… [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: 6-string!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, there’s a new 6-string lying around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Alright, well I think we’ve digressed quite a bit. Thank you so much for your time. I really appreciate you guys doing what you do, I think you guys are awesome, I love your music. I hope I see continued growth and success in what you’re doing. Keep it up and if there’s anything I can do to help promote more here in the US I’d be happy to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Whilst we’ve got you on the line, the world is watching, what are your thoughts on the debates and the presidential run?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: In a nutshell. Maybe we could do a whole concept about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Oh, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs] There’s a great concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s tainted with… ehh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z7xuCQGX9iU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think Hannah and I have similar sentiments. [laughs] I just watch it in kind of disgust and I think this is a problem that we’ve created over many decades. This isn’t new, this is the result of behaviors over a long period of time that have allowed these kinds of people to come into power. People say the world is worse now than it ever was. I think that’s a logical fallacy that every generation says that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But I would say people don’t think about the consequences of their behavior or decisions and that can lead to, in a macro-economic-cultural-social sense it can lead to some problematic outcomes where, if we do short-term gain we can end up with long-term pain. Wow, that’s really cheesy, I just made that up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: That’s a lyric, write that down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: (singing) Long term gain…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We feel sorry for a lot of our friends in the US at the moment because they’re going nuts. And, of course, a lot of the world is, you know. It’s been interesting.
I guess one thing to plug, we are coming back to Canada…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We’re doing a theater headline tour in October 2017 and we’re going to try and fit in some US dates but as you know, it’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: It’s a lesson. [laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It’s complicated with visas and whatnot. Most of the good ones are going to move up to Canada anyway, so maybe you are… no, just joking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Actually, we are going to spend two and a half months in Germany next year, get our toes in the water to see what it’s like living somewhere else. Maybe I’ll catch you on the road there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, in February we’re there. Are you going to be there in February?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It will be May through July. We’re going to try travelling on weekends, I’m hoping I can make it up to London, maybe we can catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Yeah, come to Brighton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Which bit of Germany?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Munich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Oh, nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Good beer there! That’s in Bavaria, in the heart of Bavaria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Kaeder(?? Couldn’t understand what she said) Which is just this outrageous cheesy noodle thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: My wife speaks German, she taught German at the local university so I’m hoping that she can help us navigate and we can order good foods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Yeah, good beer there…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Good beer and good schnitzel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Germany has a lot of great things about it. Have a great time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I will!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U0Q8k1nhDrU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: It would be good to see you in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: We love Canada. We really love coming to Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: We’d just love to get out to the US as well, once you kind of get out there. It’s huge, as you know. It’s terrifyingly huge for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Montreal especially, it’s just great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Is it getting cold there yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I live in Phoenix, AZ. It’s probably about 30-35 degrees Celsius today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Fair enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, it doesn’t get cold that much here in Arizona. Thank you so much for your time, I have to get ready for work, I really appreciate talking to you guys. It will be a few weeks before I get this thing online but I look forward to getting it posted and spreading the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OA: Thanks for your help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;HM: Thank you, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/moulettes/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>You Must Be This Tall</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;house-concert&quot;&gt;House Concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing this, I’m still reeling from the high of the house concert we hosted last night with the incredible &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt; and the also-incredible &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt;. It was an incredible amount of work and I’m totally, totally exhausted, but I was so excited I had to make a new video after Mike did this play-through of one of my favorite of his songs: &lt;a href=&quot;http://store.keneally.com/products/mike-keneally-you-must-be-this-tall&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You Must Be This Tall&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is! Mike is playing his one-of-a-kind Black Devil semi-hollow SG copy. It’s absolutely gorgeous (I even got to play it last night). There are LEDs in the fret markers above the fretboard that change color based on the pickup configuration. Cool! See if you can spot ‘em.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ld3rgnNdfoY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special thanks to Jack Rosenkrantz for helping me so much this weekend.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/you-must-be-this-tall</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/share/you-must-be-this-tall</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Julie Slick</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Julie Slick is scary talented. Like, every video I’ve seen of her kinda frightens me. She has so much energy, capability, and fun playing music, it’s intimidating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.julieslick.com&quot;&gt;Check out Julie Slick’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our interview with Julie Slick:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6tMVejtevKY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/julie-slick.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/julie-slick.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Casey Williams, mega-fan of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/the-residents&quot;&gt;The Residents&lt;/a&gt;, for transcribing this interview. Saved me a lot of time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony Garone: Hi, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and today we’re here with Julie Slick from Philedelphia. Julie, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Julie Slick: Thank you so much for having me! It’s great to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For anyone that might not know who you are, could you provide a brief introduction and talk about some of the projects with which you’ve been associated in recent years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Well, okay. So, I’m Julie Slick from Philadelphia, I’m a bass player. I’m probably most known for my work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew_Power_Trio&quot;&gt;Power Trio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been doing that for the last ten years, very fortunately. I’ve gotten to travel the world with him, and also through that have worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ProjeKcts&quot;&gt;The Crimson Projeckt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which also featured &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Levin&quot;&gt;Tony Levin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Mastelotto&quot;&gt;Pat Mastelotto &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/markus-reuter&quot;&gt;Markus Reuter&lt;/a&gt;, who I know has been on your program and of course Adrian and &lt;a href=&quot;http://tobiasralph.com/&quot;&gt;Tobias Ralph &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and that’s been for the last couple of years until the king decided to start touring again. And then, of course, I have my own project, my solo albums and also my recent creation, my band &lt;a href=&quot;https://echotest.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;EchoTest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I’ve been doing for the last two years with an Italian bass player, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marcomachera.com/&quot;&gt;Marco Machera &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EMXyuWkrWAU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. Can you tell us about EchoTest and some of the lesser known projects that you have-Philadelphia based?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Sure. This isn’t really Philadelphia-based, but this is actually an interesting international project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: So, Marco lives in Italy. We met at this music camp that Adrian, Pat and Tony put on every year near Woodstock, New York. They do these music camps all summer long at this resort, in Big Indian-Full Moon Resort, and it’s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://threeofaperfectpair.com/&quot;&gt;Three of a Perfect Pair Camp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. They’ve been doing it for five years now, since 2011. There’ve been a couple of off years when we’ve had some other conflicts but Marco and I met there in 2011 and so I knew he wasn’t a total weirdo, but just weird enough in the good way, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And when I was on tour with the Crimson Projeckt in 2014, I’d also, earlier that year, given up my apartment in Los Angeles. I had moved from Philly to LA for a year to try and pursue some other musical things, as we do as artists and so I got rid of the place because I was touring so much with Crimson Projeckt that. What a great opportunity! We’re gonna be in Europe, let’s do some shows. And so I made a status on Facebook and said: “If anybody wants to play some music with me while I’m in Europe, I’d love to hang out after the tour and maybe we can make some things happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/E3iW1RuFtiA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And of course, two bass players wrote to me right after that, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Lawson_(musician)&quot;&gt;Steve Lawson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in England and Marco Machera in Italy. So, I thought that was funny that two bass players contacted me to perform–not typical. You’d think a drummer, or a band or something or even just offer solo, clinic or something like that. But no, it’d be two bass players wanted to as a duo, specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I went to England and I played some lovely improvised music with Steve and did some recordings with him, and then I went to Italy. I really didn’t know Marco that well at all. I just met him at the camp, and that was pretty much it. We had a Myspace conversation in 2007 when I first joined Adrian’s band. That was pretty much it. But, you know, an excuse to go to Italy; why wouldn’t I take that opportunity? I just went on a whim and Marco booked the two dates and I wasn’t really expecting to keep the project going after that week that we booked, but we started writing songs somehow, right off the bat as soon as we plugged in our pedals. It was like this instant magic, and so we kept with the momentum and we finished a record 8 weeks later. We’ve just been going with that momentum ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wOXMxVpwhfw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And for people who have not heard the music, how would you characterize it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: I asked Marco this the other day because we were asked to describe our music in three words and he said “futuristic, artistic and bold.” and I kind of agree with that. It’s very cinematic and it’s unexpected. You think “oh, it’s a bass duo,” you’re gonna have a certain idea of what it’s gonna sound like but I really think it defies what you’d expect because we use a lot of effects and it’s a lot about the tone and the structure of the sound so it’s like taking the idea of these Fripp-ian soundscapes and this Eno quality but then this heavy groove coming from the fact that we’re both bass players. So, I think it marries those two in a very unique way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve heard some of your music, and I love how there’s layered electronic beats and delays and reverbs and it sounds like you’re playing guitar on the bass- I wasn’t quite sure, you might have had a six-string bass that looked like a guitar, or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: When Marco and I first started playing, it was very evident to me that I would be playing more on my six-string bass because he plays a five-string. So he’s got that low B, to get technical, and on my six-string, a lot of people think it’s a guitar because it’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fender_Bass_VI&quot;&gt;Bass VI &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so I’ve got two high strings on that beast of a beautiful instrument. I have a high B and a high E, so I have these extra high notes notes, Macro has that extra low note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We have our separation in tonality there, in spectrum, but then we also have the slew of pedals and the longer Marco and I have been working together, the more and more I’ve been influencing him and getting him some pedals that are very similar to mine. We both have these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventideaudio.com/products/stompboxes/multi-effect-processor/h9&quot;&gt;Eventide H9 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; pedals and I love the way they interlock together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Basically, because when we would start recording, that’s another part I was going to get into–when we record, sometimes we are together and sometimes I plug him through my pedal board, so it became a necessity for him to have some of the same pieces that I have so that we could work these ideas together with some of these harmonizing things that we have going on. And then, also, I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_synthesizer&quot;&gt;MIDI pickup &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on my bass so I can make it sound like I put it through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.roland.com/us/products/vb-99/&quot;&gt;Roland VB-99 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and that I can access another array of tones, I can make it sound like a Strat or a Les Paul or an organ or different synthesizers, and then of course once I take the output of that and put it through my pedal board so I can make it sound totally crazy, put it through these harmonized pedals, through these different reverbs, through my loopers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1voFbocwKnU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s another reason why I’m saying you listen to the music and you don’t necessarily think “this is just coming from two basses, that’s really something” because so far, the two albums that we have out are pretty much strictly bass and a little bit of programming, except for the one song, “The Drift”, had some guitar on it because it was a song that I wrote before Marco and I started working together. Also, there’s some violin tracks on some of the stuff and viola tracks, but other than that, everything you hear is bass and the programmed drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s another thing that I was gonna get into–sorry to answer your question in such a long-winded way–but growing up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew_Power_Trio#Eric_Slick&quot;&gt;my brother &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who was the original drummer of the Power Trio with Adrian, I’m used to having… The drumset would be right here, behind me, and I would be standing over there, where the TV is, and we’d be jamming King Crimson songs in our living room and recording them. So, I’m used to, like, “Eric, play a B,” when I have an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Whenever I come up with a new idea, I use the computer and the technology in such a way, like it’s my digital brother.&lt;/span&gt; I can’t call up Eric and be like “Hey, can you play this?” We’re getting close to that point but as far as it stands now, it’s easier for me to just open up &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logic_Pro&quot;&gt;Logic &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, make a quick program with Ultrabeat or something, and then I record my idea, and then I usually end up making four more drum tracks because I like weird polyrhythm stuff and playing against that and that helps me because playing to a click is obviously very boring and not easy to do when you’re trying to get a vibe going, especially as a bass player.  So that was my long-winded answer for that; that’s why our music sounds the way it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. Don’t worry about being long-winded, that’s what people want, it’s what they like about these interviews. Did you record anything with Steve Lawson?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Yes, we did! Steve always records everything, so I think we put that up pretty quickly after it happened, too. We’re due, though, for some more because I think we really haven’t done anything since then, so we should. But we have put up, I think it was called &lt;a href=&quot;http://music.stevelawson.net/album/marinate&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marinate&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it was a free download for those that bought–I think we were offering it when we released our first Echotest record, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/fourth-dementia&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourth Dementia&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was from before we were called Echotest, it was still Julie Slick and Marco Machera at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4gj4wtmMppg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then Steve had released… I’m bad, I’m forgetting… He releases so much music, can’t remember what specific release it was, but if you bought both of those, we offered &lt;em&gt;Marinate&lt;/em&gt; as a free, four song EP. That wasn’t recorded at the gig, though. I wonder if he has the gig. Good question. I think he put one of the Soundclouds up, like one of the songs up on Soundcloud.  I think that may have been also the gig that we did with &lt;a href=&quot;http://drummerandyedwards.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Andy Edwards &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on drums. So it’s a trio, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Very cool. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/steve-ball&quot;&gt;I just spoke with Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; the other night and he talked all about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/tinyorchestralmoments/&quot;&gt;Tiny Orchestral Moments &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and we have some sample audio that we’ll be posting in a week or two or something like that. So, how did you get involved with that whole guitar circle, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Ok, well, the King Crimson world, that was getting involved with Adrian, that’s a whole other thing. That was from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/School_of_Rock_(company)&quot;&gt;Paul Green School of Rock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was a student of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Green_(musician)&quot;&gt;Paul Green &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s, starting back in 1988, basically the year that he founded the school. I saw it grow from this guy’s apartment to an actual, brick-and-mortar school, to another school, another school, a movie, Adrian’s coming to do tours, all of a sudden I’m in Adrian’s band. That’s pretty much how it happened, it’s pretty insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JVQPiVZpxu0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I discovered him, and then was buying microphones because he was endorsing them, and playing bass, wanting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_Man_StingRay&quot;&gt;Stingray &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because of Tony Levin, and my brother was buying a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonor&quot;&gt;Sonor &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because he wanted what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny_Carey&quot;&gt;Danny Carey &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s drums were like, and then we ended up working with Danny down the line and it’s just mind boggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But the Seattle thing; that was just another Facebook connection. You have to give it to Facebook, I mean, I actually made a status that was a little negative and I normally try to avoid doing those sorts of things but I was expressing my frustration with self-management and having to wear so many hats and how exhausting it can be, and Steve took note of that. I was actually gonna delete the post and it’s a good thing I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He saw it, and he saw an opportunity because he was planning this Tiny Orchestral Moments session and gig, I guess for a year. And I didn’t know about it at all and it was the weekend before, I made this update on Facebook and he contacted me, weekend before with an emergency, that his bass player, Amy was going to have to fly out for a gig in Turkey. So he did a replacement quickly, and saw my post and just figured why the heck not reach out and see if I’m available?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7fqrSHYRDAY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I wasn’t, really, because I was really stressed, working on the–I play with this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talking_Heads&quot;&gt;Talking Heads &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tribute band, &lt;a href=&quot;http://startmakingsenseband.com/&quot;&gt;Start Making Sense &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and we did this recreation of the film, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Making_Sense&quot;&gt;Stop Making Sense &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to a T and I had to do all of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tina_Weymouth&quot;&gt;Tina &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s mannerisms and dance moves and I had to sing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genius_of_Love&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genius of Love&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which was insane. So I really saw this as a great opportunity to go to see XXX(insert name here, couldn’t figure it out, around the 15:00 mark) and procrastinate and connect with amazing musicians so I wouldn’t have to practice the crab dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, I’ve seen the Instagram posts. I can’t believe how intentionally accurate and to every detail you guys got it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Oh, it was so nerdy. It was completely so specific, making the cut–I straightened my hair. You know that means it’s serious. If someone put a hot iron on my head… Not messing around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I hear you. My wife does it everyday, I can’t believe she’s not scorched all across her head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: I was so scared, putting the blue in my hair and I keep seeing it creeping in more and more and more blue, which I think is cool, but as long as the stylists keep letting me do that, that’s fine. But you know, things like that, like I’m already burning my head. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;This is the kind of breaking news I know you want to talk about on Make Weird Music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely, yeah. Tell me more about your hair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Yeah, exactly. Like, what’s the actual combination of colors? Like, hue 64, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sT-mqkCrIiM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You know, people get really into the details of instruments. I don’t know why we can’t get it to hair colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: I know. I mean, honestly, I have no idea. That’s why I pay somebody else to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, for someone who would like to get into your music, where do you suggest they start, in terms of hearing Julie Slick, an innovator on the bass, someone who thinks outside the box?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS:  Well, definitely my Bandcamp is the best place right now because &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;I now even have a subscription service available &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So like, for 15 bucks a year, you get all of my music, which is a lot of albums, I think there’s 10 up there right now so that alone is worth it, so you get all of that, plus I update with behind-the-scenes videos and working on new demos in the studio, on tour kind of stuff. And I hope to be putting up more of those sorts of videos up soon; I hope to be on the road more soon, both with Echotest and with Adrian in the coming months. And that’s really the best place, would be the Bandcamp. And there’s of course, you can stream stuff and check it out as well. There’s a few things on Spotify, but I don’t really recommend that people go there, of course, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But maybe an album or two or a few songs to note?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Sure. The latest Echotest record, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/le-fil-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Le Fil Rouge&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I would check out a song called &lt;em&gt;The Drift&lt;/em&gt; on that. It’s one that actually does have guitar. And also the last track, &lt;em&gt;Pleasant Torture&lt;/em&gt;, is quite nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vAtT4F5I0so&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then, there’s the other album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/terroir&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terroir&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which looks like this, my second solo record, which came out a couple of years ago now and that one features a bunch of awesome guests like Adrian and Steve Ball actually, and Pat. A lot of people. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Torn&quot;&gt;David Torn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; plays amazing guitar on that as well, so… That’s something a little bit different, a little bit older but I think it’s cool to check out the sort of evolution of the way things are going with my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent! That’s great. Thank you very much and I look forward to seeing you on tour. Hope you’ll come through Phoenix at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Oh yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I missed the last Crimson Projeckt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Oh, that was with Danny too, when we were playing in Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I know. :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Aw man!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I punched myself for it. But, awesome. Thank you so much for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JS: Thank you so much. And hopefully you’ll get to work on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/julie-slick/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Free Concert Video from Bent Knee</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 05:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/link/bent-knee-concert/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/link/bent-knee-concert/</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Steve Ball</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Steve Ball and I have a lot in common. Like, way more in common than I ever would have suspected. We both have leadership positions in the technology industry, we both have crowded home studios filled with gear and music paraphernalia, we’re both dads to young kids, and we both work on the “fun” stuff from 9PM til 1 or 2 or 3AM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The differences between me and Steve become apparent when you investigate our histories and successes. Steve is quite an accomplished performer, artist, and composer. He has musical collaborators all over the world and has an incredible discography. He is one of the founders and leaders of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattlecircle.org/&quot;&gt;Seattle Guitar Circle &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s been in several bands, like Electric Gauchos, C3, Los Gauchos Alemanes, League of Crafty Guitarists, and more. Steve’s an incredible, prolific achiever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com&quot;&gt;Check out Steve Ball’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our interview with Steve Ball:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-b7MeucH4Xk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-ball/steve-ball.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-ball/steve-ball.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you&quot;&gt;Thank You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Rod Knowlan, guitarist for the Vancouver, Canada-based indie rock band, &lt;a href=&quot;http://headmusic.ca&quot;&gt;HEAD &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Rod is also a fan of all manner of music, weird and otherwise. I met Rod right after I met &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/kerry-minnear&quot;&gt;Kerry Minnear&lt;/a&gt; in Montreal. What a special day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Hey, this is Anthony with makeweirdmusic.com, and I’m here with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com/&quot;&gt;Steve Ball &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; all the way from Seattle, Washington. Steve, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Thanks for having me, Anthony, and great to talk to you again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you. So I know you’ve got 30 years of musical history and there’s so much to get into, but for the purposes of this interview I think it would be really cool if we could talk through the musical projects with which you’ve been recently associated and are currently involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Awesome! That’s a great lead-in to, as you described, 30 years of interactions and collaborations that I’ve done that really go all the way back to something that your audience may be familiar with and I’m probably going to do some radical product placement during our quick talk tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was involved in the very early days of something called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft&lt;/a&gt; and these were a couple of the very early musical recordings that came out of Guitar Craft. This one, in fact, I produced by hand at a place called Claymont in West Virginia. This was the very first indie release by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thelcg.net/&quot;&gt;League of Crafty Guitarists &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, called &lt;em&gt;Get Crafty.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ysUzpksFXS4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It has famously been unavailable on any modern formats but since my early days of plugging in and being a crafty guitarist I’ve done many other projects both with the League from the beginning through multiple eras, all the way through a whole host of spin-off projects that kicked off in the second phase of Guitar Craft in 1991, after the League’s 3-year tour fell apart because Robert [Fripp] and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E.G._Records&quot;&gt;E.G. Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; fell into a multi-year dispute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I formed a band in Los Angeles with my friend, Sanford Ponder, and we pulled in some names that might be familiar to your audience, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Mastelotto&quot;&gt;Pat Mastelotto &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigel_Gavin&quot;&gt;Nigel Gavin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and we recorded in 1991 and 1992 a fairly “proggy” album called &lt;a href=&quot;http://rateyourmusic.com/release/album/prometheus_f1/prometheus/&quot;&gt;Prometheus &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Around the same time there was a new band being born out of the first phase of Guitar Craft called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Guitar_Trio&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I was there at the birth of this as well. This is one of the other spin-off projects that is now going on, I think, its 25th anniversary as Paul (Richards), Bert (Lams) and Hideyo (Moriya) are about to release their new album as the California Guitar Trio. I played with and even on a couple of the early California Guitar Trio albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4HqFdQEK6_o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Eventually I moved to Seattle and put together an independent outfit around 1993 called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattlecircle.org/&quot;&gt;Seattle Guitar Circle &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. My primary mission with this project was to develop a completely independent entity so that if other Guitar Craft-related activities happened or business interactions with Robert and Guitar Craft over the years, I wanted to have something that would be independent and available to sustain itself through whatever next-gen changes that Robert and Guitar Craft needed to do. So the Seattle Guitar Circle was, by design, an independent project designed to continue the application and assimilation of what I learned from Guitar Craft in a local context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know if you can see, some of the characters here are, to this day, still working and playing together in Seattle. In fact, I was with many of them, almost all of these characters were in a room last night at a Seattle Guitar Circle meeting, including Bob Williams, &lt;a href=&quot;http://seattlecircle.org/guitarschool/about-scgs/who-we-are/&quot;&gt;Jaxie Binder &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://curtgolden.homestead.com/&quot;&gt;Curt Golden &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Rieflin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and Dean called in with a conflict as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The Seattle Guitar Circle is going on now 23 years of ongoing interactions in Seattle&lt;/span&gt;, essentially building on the same techniques that we learned from Robert Fripp and in Guitar Craft, involving improvisation, how to play in a group and how to invite music into the present moment in a unique but reliable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So there’s a glimpse of some history, mostly based upon artifacts that people no longer buy…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: (laughs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: However, as you know, I am still in the bad habit of organizing projects, groups and collaborations designed to bring music into the world on its own terms. So, in fact, as you mentioned, one of my more recent projects just happened about a month ago, it was exactly a month ago that this small set of people started out with 6 invitations for a core team that included &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy_Denio&quot;&gt;Amy Denio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who is a local Seattle jazz and new music master, Nigel Gavin, who is also a crafty guitarist from the early days and an amazing guitarist in his own right, from New Zealand, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.noragermain.com/&quot;&gt;Nora Germain &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who is a jazz violinist from Los Angeles who is a force of nature and she is plowing ahead in an amazing career already in Los Angeles as a phenomenal jazz violinist, [Paul Richards] from the California Guitar Trio and one of my best Guitar Craft buddies. We’ve been collaborating for 30 years now, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Petra_Haden&quot;&gt;Petra Haden &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who is one of the surprise wild cards. Petra is the daughter of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Haden&quot;&gt;Charlie Haden &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of the jazz world’s premiere and revered bass players and Petra is one of 3 daughters who are part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Haden_Triplets&quot;&gt;Haden Triplets &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Petra has a voice that can melt glass at 100 meters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vcXo3owlGpY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This core team was joined by about 20 other guitarists, instrumentalists and celebrities from around the country and we came together for a week of work. The odd and maybe funny instigation was fairly open-ended in that no one really knew what they were getting themselves into but what we did is, in 3 days we essentially assembled a repertoire and did a show, we showed up on a Sunday and we did a show on a Wednesday night at a place called &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapelspace.blogspot.ca/&quot;&gt;The Chapel &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Seattle, which is a well-known jazz and new music venue in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://historicseattle.org/project/good-shepherd/&quot;&gt;Good Shepherd Center &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Wallingford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We wrote and improvised our way through about 90 minutes of music for a show 2 days after we had essentially just met and then we went into one of Seattle’s most famous recording studios, a place called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_Bridge_Studio&quot;&gt;London Bridge &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where the early &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pearl_Jam&quot;&gt;Pearl Jam &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; records were recorded and a whole mess of albums that most of the world knows about. We locked out London Bridge and for 3 days we took this set of world-class musicians we recorded the repertoire we developed in the first 3 days and we improvised for a couple of days with guest producers, who were invited to come in and arrange or invent or discover something with this set of world class musicians in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we had &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Gunn&quot;&gt;Trey Gunn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Bob Williams, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlgermainmusic.com/&quot;&gt;Carl Germain &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Dean Jensen stand up in front of this group of world-class musicians and they orchestrated something out of nothing. Now we have about 6 hours of music that I’m beginning to sort through so that this tiny orchestral moment’s project will move from a wild hare-brained idea mostly inspired by Nigel and Paul Richards saying they wanted to come to Seattle to do a project. It will likely evolve into 3, maybe 4 CDs, as well as something that no one saw coming, we also had a set of documentary filmmakers who were there at the Wednesday night show and then they were with us for 3 days in London Bridge with cameras everywhere, interviewing everyone involved and asking questions that I mostly worked hard to not listen to the answers. There’s a documentary being made about the entire project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TFdCzkPMa8s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The documentary filmmakers last year released a film called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4421654/&quot;&gt;Bezango, Washington &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is an amazing documentary by Ron Austin and Louise Amandes who decided to document the early days of the Northwest comic and cartoon art community, which includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Groening&quot;&gt;Matt Groening &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynda_Barry&quot;&gt;Lynda Barry &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and a whole slew of amazing cartoon artists from the Northwest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So they came in and are now sorting through hours and hours of footage from the project and they’re mission is, as far as I understand it, is to tell the story of the project. All of this unfolded over the last month and I will say that, musically, there were unexpected surprises and some amazing improvised compositions that unfolded from these collaborations. Maybe I’ll just shut up and play you a little bit of something I’ve been mixing to give you a sense of maybe what this project was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Very cool! I think right before you played the show, a couple of names got added to that roster as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew_Power_Trio#Julie_Slick&quot;&gt;Julie Slick &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was added, and was there somebody else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Yeah, there were actually 3 or 4 significant late additions, the Friday before the project was going to begin on Sunday, I heard from Amy Denio that she could only make the first half of the project because she had landed a gig in Turkey and she was flying out of the country to go play with her regular band, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kultur_Shock&quot;&gt;Kultur Shock &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an amazing, internationally-known band. So Amy was going to disappear and rather than have a gap in this core of 3 men and 3 women, this balanced, chemically combination of players, I decided to call Julie, whom I had collaborated with 2 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IKFmZrRu7UQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I played on Julie’s record, &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/terroir&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terroir&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with a track called &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt;, which is also amazing music with a ton of collaborations, but I called up Julie , with 2 days notice, invited her to Seattle and she said yes. She showed up on Tuesday to join us with only a day of practice for the Wednesday night show and for 3 days in the studio. Her presence was also, both phenomenal and, looking back, not only did she gel completely with the personalities in the team, but musically she had a massive impact on the repertoire, the sound, the feel and, of course, the energy of all of the music that happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In addition, I also invited a crafty guitarist I’d met and played with in the Orchestra of Crafty Guitarists named &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickgrant.com/&quot;&gt;Patrick Grant &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Patrick is another powerhouse musician who has organized a project called &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiltedaxes.com/tiltedaxes.html&quot;&gt;Tilted Axes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is a “Music for Mobile Electric Guitars” project that goes into cities and with small, portable amplifiers, they strap on a guitar and an amp and they wander around cities with sometimes 10 to 20 to 30 electric guitarists playing both composed and improvised music in unlikely locations. When I met Patrick we hit it off so I invited Patrick out to join us. He also showed up on Tuesday afternoon, joined us literally off the plane and into dress rehearsal and played piano and electric guitar. He also radically changed the character, the flavor and the outcome of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’d say there are two other significant additions; one was Aileen Bunch, who is also a long-time Crafty Guitarist and a member of Patrick’s “Tilted Axes” group. She was here for another project that had happened a couple of weeks earlier where a small team of people decided to take a very famous piece of Guitar Craft repertoire called &lt;em&gt;Eye of the Needle&lt;/em&gt;, which has been played for 30 years in all sorts of Guitar Craft environments and there was a set of people who decided to work on a vocal-only version, an a cappella version of this piece. Aileen was here for that, she heard about (our) project and decided to stay. She contributed some amazing keyboard and piano parts and singing as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sQ78iTKSFkA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Finally, Nigel Gavin brought his girlfriend Sonia Wilson, who had just come from New York where she was doing merchandise for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suzanne_Vega&quot;&gt;Suzanna Vega &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Sonia turned out to be another wild card who contributed with her voice, her ukulele and her presence an entirely lovable and grounded set of music and collaborations to the entire event that also changed the nature of how and what we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So we had this combination that started out with six core people consisting of three men and three women and in the end it was a core team of about five men and five women, also surrounded by the very talented, very experienced and hard-working Seattle Guitar Circle. We had close to twenty additional contributors and Trey Gunn and Dan Moore who all brought their own craft and their own work with years and years of improvisation to the team and the results are all over the map, from &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Zappa&lt;/a&gt;-like experimental to cluster-filled, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Branca&quot;&gt;Glen Branca&lt;/a&gt;-like unfolding chaos to deeply moving orchestrated knot-work with vocals that appear from nowhere all the way to a piece called &lt;em&gt;Spiritual&lt;/em&gt; which unfolded in the very first day, the very first rehearsal, without conversation, without planning, without any real homework. The entire group essentially went from silence to an unfolding improvisation that turned into this beautiful song that is, coincidentally written by Petra’s brother, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josh_Haden&quot;&gt;Josh Haden &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So there is an actual thread of a real composition here but the entire arrangement arrived out of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My primary mission is to bring groups of people together who can make things together that they would otherwise not do on their own. Obviously there’s a long history of this, if you go back to the early League, to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.losgauchos.de/&quot;&gt;Los Gauchos Alemanes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Seattle Guitar Circle, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.electricgauchos.com/&quot;&gt;Electric Gauchos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and this latest project, Tiny Orchestral Moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4VbyYMcWB94&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’d be happy to unveil and share little bits and pieces of some of the corners of these collaborations with you and your audience over the next couple of months, if you’re up for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sounds great, where can they go to get more information as it unfolds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Eventually there will be a Tiny Orchestral Moments website. Today there is a Facebook group called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/tinyorchestralmoments/&quot;&gt;Tiny Orchestral Moments &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so if you’re on Facebook, the best way to learn a little bit and see some of the videos that have poured off of cell phones and out of the team members of the project so far, you’ll probably get the best updates there in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When we release the documentary and the probably 3 CDs that will include songs, complete improvisations that are all over the map in terms of structure and feel and some of the producer’s tracks. Trey, for example, had the team divided into instrumentalists on one side and vocalists on the other side of the room. He then orchestrated a collaboration and counterpoint between vocals and instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a whole set of experimental producer’s sessions that will probably end up on its own disk as well. For starters, if you’re on Facebook, find the Tiny Orchestral Moments group, there’s a huge amount of photos and some cool videos to check out there. Also, watch Make Weird Music for ongoing updates or you can go to http://www.steveball.com where there’s often more information than should rightly be in one place on all of this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent, thank you so much, Steve, I look forward to unraveling even more of your musical history over follow-up conversations. Thanks a lot for sharing your time with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SB: Awesome, my pleasure, I also look forward to ongoing conversations, thank you, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thanks, Steve!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-ball/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/steve-ball/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mental Medication</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KberQOJf3x8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMPORTANT NOTE: When I say, “F#5,” what I really mean is “F#sus4.” Same for all the other “5” chords. I recorded the video pretty late and flipped my 4ths and 5ths. Didn’t realize it until the next day. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soundslice-notation-and-tablature&quot;&gt;Soundslice Notation and Tablature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living sheet music brought to you by &lt;a href=&quot;http://soundslice.com&quot;&gt;Soundslice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Wanna know more? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/soundslice&quot;&gt;our interview with Soundslice co-creator, Adrian Holovaty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.soundslice.com/scores/39845/embed/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mental Medication&lt;/em&gt; is one of my favorite songs from the incredible progressive rock album, U.K. It’s a self-titled album and features incredible virtuosity by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_Holdsworth&quot;&gt;Allan Holdsworth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Bruford&quot;&gt;Bill Bruford&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wetton&quot;&gt;John Wetton&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie_Jobson&quot;&gt;Eddie Jobson&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a musical adventure and is so beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out this other really cool video with a transcription of one of the crazier parts of the song:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ByLT9JQTMtI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know if you try playing it yourself!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/mental-medication</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/learn/mental-medication</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ostrich Von Nipple</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ostrich Von Nipple is an avant garde musician on the very excellent European record label, &lt;a href=&quot;http://psychofonrecords.com&quot;&gt;Psychofon Records &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Not much is known about OVN except he (I’m assuming OVN is a “he”) has been releasing very weird music for a few years now. If you’re a fan of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/the-residents&quot;&gt;The Residents&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll definitely dig OVN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychofon reached out to me after the &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/homer-flynn&quot;&gt;Homer Flynn interview&lt;/a&gt; and sent a nice package of some very strange music on their label, including a single from The Residents’ own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychofonrecords.com/randy-rose/&quot;&gt;Randy Rose &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a French band called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychofonrecords.com/artist-ddaa/&quot;&gt;DDAA &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and (obviously) Ostrich Von Nipple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The packaging work is very unique and beautifully made. The music is really weird and has a lot of personality. It’s very early 1980s Residents with a twist (if you can even imagine that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ostrichvonnipple.com&quot;&gt;Check out Ostrich Von Nipple’s website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an interview with Ostrich Von Nipple, Stephen Albert, and Andreas Mathews:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jCAk_S5ojaQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/ostrich-von-nipple/ostrich-von-nipple.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/ostrich-von-nipple/ostrich-von-nipple.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hi, this is Anthony for MakeWeirdMusic.com. I’m here with Andy and Stephen from Psychofon Records and our special guest artist, Ostrich Von Nipple. Andy and Stephen, thank you so much for getting this set up. Ostrich, thank you for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Ostrich: Well thank you very much for having me, Anthony. I must say, this is a pleasure for me to appear here. &lt;strong&gt;God dammit, this interview is over!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So Ostrich, where does your name come from? What does it mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Well, it comes from perhaps about two decades ago, sir. There was a time when I was playing with my friends and we later became known as The Goons of Waxing Gibbous. We had a performance one particular day. It was a dark day. The sea–she was angry that day, but we carried on and decided: if we’re going to entertain these fine gentlemen in our carefully picked garb, perhaps we should present them with our names as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We chose our names and mine seemed to roll right off the tongue. I kept it and later realized its importance for &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the nipple is the pathway for life-giving milk. Sustenance.&lt;/span&gt; And what does an ostrich do, according to myth when it’s kinda chickened out? It buries its head in the sand and you see, sir, this is all too natural for me and those that I love. &lt;strong&gt;This interview is over!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Okay, I’m sorry about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9Ka13vwxbaE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No worries. It happens all the time. What music has been an influence for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Well [groans], well I’d say there’s a wide variety of music that influences me musically. A bit more specifically, I’ll say that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I do love soundtrack music, particularly cartoon music&lt;/span&gt;, but really any sort of films and whatnot. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I also am heavily influenced by classical Indian music and the Hindustani raga.&lt;/span&gt; That happens to be a passion of mine and I feel very uncomfortable discussing it with the three of you staring at me like I’m some kind of–I’m just kidding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This interview is over!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. [Gets up and leaves.] Sorry, I had to turn off my air conditioner. It was making a lot of noise. Didn’t mean to give you the impression this interview was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Oh, I’m very sorry. I seem to have a temperament. Huh. Not like a temperature like you would need a thermometer to read, but a temperament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Like a breathmint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: That’s ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve noticed you follow a certain grammar with all of your album titles. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ostrichvonnipple.bandcamp.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ostrich Von Nipple Contemplates the Cosmos&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychofonrecords.com/product/ostrich-von-nipple-quantifies-absurdity-cd/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quantifies Absurdity&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;… Can you tell me if there’s intention behind that? A meaning? What leads to these particular grammars?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Well, yes, that is true. Each one of these records is typically named in a present tense form. A verb. It’s fucking grammar. And it’s a very conscious effort because I do like the feeling that the idea that this is happening currently. That &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;what you’re listening to and experiencing is happening currently, never in the past, never in the future, but always now. I would hope that a listener would join me on this active journey each and every time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And I’d just like to say that I thank the Academy for presenting me with this fucking honor. It’s been a pleasure there as I sit and speak to you. I need a moment. [Pauses.] I’m sorry about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZR3-OTpjPsc?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So your music gives you a sort of omnipresence because you’re always performing it live in the moment for the listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Yes, I would say that’s a fair assessment. Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Because I’ve spent plenty of time listening to tons of music that made me feel somewhat alienated. It is my hope that this would be the exact opposite. [A head is peering, gazing over OVN’s shoulder.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is there someone with you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Yes. You, and Stephen, and Andreas are with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Can you tell me–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Do you receive me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah. I receive you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Okay, great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us about your “Absurdity” project? It seems like you’ve been releasing several titles under &lt;em&gt;Qualifies Absurdity&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Quantifies Absurdity&lt;/em&gt;, more fun grammar stuff. What’s the concept behind these “Absurdity” projects?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: I would have to say that the Absurdity project really came about towards the end of an album I was working on prior to its release, as well as an EP entitled &lt;em&gt;Ostrich Von Nipple Plays Some Shitty Tunes&lt;/em&gt;. Now, I found myself in the situation where I seemed to be creating music from all of these other areas that I typically don’t explore or explore, perhaps, for a different amount of time, therefore experiencing for a different amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I kept working all these ideas and I’m shaking my head as I answer because I look so serious. And as I continued working on this music, I realized that it was all quite absurd. Absurd in some fashion and some form. But, again, as I shake my head in earnest, I must tell you &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;these concepts all have a common thread and somehow seem to work together&lt;/span&gt;. And if I’ve made you feel that this answer is somewhat rehearsed in any way, I assure you it is only because I am such a poor actor. This interview is over!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4JACTpu9GIY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughing.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: That was embarrassing. I’m sorry guys. Can we reset back to the–what the one? Okay. Next question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The next question is for Andy. Is that cool?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Andy, how did you discover Ostrich Von Nipple?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: It was around 2012 when I first heard Ostrich on YouTube and I was amazed by his outstanding music. It caught me directly so I took my chance and asked him if he would like to work with me. Psychofon Records didn’t exist yet and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;because of Ostrich Von Nipple, I decided to create a new record label&lt;/span&gt;. Ostrich has a direct connection to Psychofon and without Ostrich, the label would not exist. That is to say….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Pregnant pause.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What’s your favorite Ostrich Von Nipple album and why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: Okay, I don’t really have a favorite release. I simply love all of his music and it’s art just for the art. That’s the most important thing for me and that’s also why I support his ideas and all his various projects. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I will produce whatever he submits and all his various work because I know it will be great.&lt;/span&gt; If I had to pick one, I would say &lt;em&gt;Ostrich Von Nipple Quantifies Absurdity&lt;/em&gt;. When it was released, it was the heaviest project done and it’s a perfect example of the raw energy of the extraordinary Ostrich Von Nipple sound. Indeed, unearthly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He didn’t pay you to say that, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: Um, yeah sure. Naturally. What can I say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What is your role in the creation of his music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: It’s a good question. I handle all the label-related work. Everything that happens after receiving the music and artwork from the artists, from creation of the records, CDs, and of course, I create all the collector’s variations, all the way down to packaging and shipping and stuff. Things like that. I always wanted to have my own label and now we are celebrating next year our 5th birthday. Man, time flies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Psychofon has a specific mission and that is to produce music from the other, from artists from other dimensions, almost like we are growing a special garden of people with a unique taste for music and art. Ostrich fits that bill perfectly. In a world of artistic conformity and a general dumbing down of the mind, I feel that it takes something like Psychofon Records as a gateway for unknown and unseen art.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GLKq3TPCJXA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As you may have noticed, not so many people support independent art. I’m deeply rooted with the indie art movement from the 70s and 80s. I see it as an obligation to support the important task that the remains of the counterculture continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you for doing that. I think it’s important. I really appreciate you putting that effort into bringing good stuff in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: Thank you very much, Anthony, for the kind words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you choose which artists you’re going to represent on your label?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: That really depends on my personal taste. I only sign artists that I really, really love. If I hear something and I really like it, we will move forward. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;What is also important is that the artist fits our concept of music from the ether.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. I have a couple of CDs here, one from DDAA, which is nice. Got a nice big digipak and then another nice big digipak for &lt;em&gt;Ostrich Von Nipple Quantifies Absurdity&lt;/em&gt;. Nice tri-fold package. And then we’ve got this plastic package for this one with the lenticular printed cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: Yeah, it’s a lenticular cards. I grew up in my youth with this shit so I have a special–I love these lenticular cards. I thought, “When I do a label one day, then I have to do something special like lenticular cards.” I’m always looking for some special stuff we can do for covers and all that shit. So I like very much to create it. That is, for me, the most important part of my role. It’s wonderful to put my life inside these little creations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s awesome. I forgot to ask you, what do you do at Psychofon? You’re the owner, you started the label, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: Yeah, I’m the owner of Psychofon Records. Right. I run Psychofon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And what does that look like? What does the owner of Psychofon do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AM: I occupy myself since my youth with collecting electronic music, underground, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plunderphonics&quot;&gt;plunderphonics &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musique_concrète&quot;&gt;musique concrete &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, brote music?, record art objects, and all this avant garde stuff. And I’m the proud collector of releases with interesting pictures. So, my collection that I gathered over the years is very unique and reflects the history of this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1xrDnUWsWDE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I really love music that is released in an abnormal way.&lt;/span&gt; I have albums that use small toy cars with needle and speakers attached that drive over the records called “vinyl killers.” For example, little fingerphones, the smallest and most simple record player in the world. I also collect the most beautiful picture discs. All these things were always fascinating for me, still to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I have collected an immense wealth of packaging ideas over the last 40 years and that helps me with new projects. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;My process usually starts with a kind of meditation focusing on the project as a world.&lt;/span&gt; The music and artwork and the whole concept. I create and build everything by myself and with my bare hands. For that, you need a lot of experience and I’m a craftsman originally by trade and I know a lot about different materials and techniques for metal working, industrial productions, etcetera. This comes in handy when trying to come up with unique ideas for packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of the strangest releases I’ve put together was for Ostrich Von Nipple’s debut on Psychofon, &lt;em&gt;Ostrich Von Nipple Plays Some Shitty Tunes&lt;/em&gt;. Our promotion package came with a handmade graffiti press information and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the album was contained inside a frisbee, so you can actually throw Ostrich to a friend and they can catch it and listen to the music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Ostrich, what are your thoughts on Andy and Psychofon Records?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Well, I think being handy today in the records business is important, Anthony. Thank you for asking. I think in this particular business you have to worry about construction of certain elements because music is sort of like building a house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You want to start with the foundation and then you start to build up around it and create a structure. Eventually, you can put the paneling on for the walls, complete the exterior, and you have something substantial, and then it’s always time to go inside and do the decorating and the final touches. So, yes, I thank you for asking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Stephen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SA: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Why are you here? What do you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SA: I’m the website administrator and designer for Psychofon Records. I also write most of the English text for the site and pretty much anything that goes on on the Internet relating to Psychofon Recrords. Most of my tasks involve updating the site, getting projects ready for release, calculating costs in the ever-changing shipping system, which is a nightmare. We handle shipping across the world and we have customers across the world, but the fun comes when I get to write press release info for one of my favorite artists in the world, Ostrich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How did you get associated with Psychofon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FZlVSiztG9s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SA: It started when I did some work for Ostrich Von Nipple in 2014 as a volunteer. I designed some graphics for him just for fun. He liked my work and this is how I got in contact with Psychofon in general, through working with and getting closer to Ostrich. At the point when I was contacting him, I was really in love with his music and just a total fanboy. And I was really also starting to realize the unique stuff that Psychofon put out and Ostrich told me that I should approach Andy and see if he would let me build his website as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I pitched some ideas to him about an automated web shop and he was reluctant at first, but then after I showed him some examples of my work and visited the Psychofon headquarters in Bremerhaven, we put together a plan to create this site. I think it was a big success. From that point forward, my range of responsibilities grew and I found myself approaching media companies for promotion, distribution, other various things. I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now I have the privilege of direct contact with the artists on the label, which is, for me, completely crazy. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That’s the best payment anyone could ever receive for doing this kind of stuff&lt;/span&gt;, at least for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Are there any difficulties in dealing with secretive artists like OVN over here, who’s enjoying a beverage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SA: Not at all. In fact, it’s really fun. I think you could see that. It keeps things interesting. It keeps you on your toes. In my line of work, there’s a lot of dry, boring editing and emailing to do and search engine optimization and social media crap. It’s great because I can have one on one time with these guys and learn more about their craft and what they do while I work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Really, their identities are not important. At what point does the face matter? What you’re looking at right now is Ostrich Von Nipple. There is no other person under that mask.&lt;/span&gt; I think if you take off the mask, it’s just a black void that goes on to infinity. If you want to know who he is, just look no further than his music. Listen to the words and get the emotional intent from the compositions. For me, I’m really really into the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;With Ostrich, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;his music is as intimate as you can get with anybody.&lt;/span&gt; His music is a great example of that. He obscures his identity, but he, at the same time, bares his soul to the world with his albums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Ostrich, what were you doing before Psychofon Records picked you up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N-3QOgjPKTE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Well, back before Psychofon Records, I did have one other CD that was released worldwide called Ostrich Von Nipple Contemplates the Cosmos. That particular record was released on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wmrecordings.com&quot;&gt;WM Recordings &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the time, which I don’t believe is even around anymore. I think they may be WM Digital. Hmph, lots of consonants there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Anyhow, I had finished that record and had it released. Quite honestly, Anthony, I was on top of the world. Here I was, a young fucking bird brain with ne’er a nipple to spare. Top-selling records on the charts. I won’t–you can look up the charts, but it’s important that I tell you that I took that chance and went with Psychofon Records because it’s not about me, Anthony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: It’s not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: This interview is over!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, Stephen. What’s your favorite OVN release? What do you recommend to people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SA: Just like Andy, I’m a big fan of his work as a whole. But, really, the concept behind his music is that every album represents just one piece of a puzzle. He’s told me this a hundred times. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The puzzle slowly comes together with every release and they all fit together somehow.&lt;/span&gt; I find that concept really genius. That’s why I’m so into his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of his most impressive works in my opinion would have to be the picture disc that came out not too long ago. It contains two 15-minute musical pieces titled &lt;em&gt;Swarm Suite&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;So Do They&lt;/em&gt;. They’re incredible collages of pretty much all of his previous work intertwined with new material and art by this Nevada artist, &lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.poxodd.com&quot;&gt;Poxodd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who’s just incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/g-ss6lAYDlk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t think a lot of people realize how hard it is to make a 15-minute piece of continuous progressive music, let alone two 15-minute pieces in the short amount of time he put it together. This has always stuck out to me as one of his most mature works or impressive accomplishments. It really showcases the various sounds and moods of Ostrich Von Nipple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: I concur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right guys. Thank you so much for your time. I really appreciate it. How can people pick up some of OVN’s records?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;SA: Well, you can easily go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://psychofonrecords.com&quot;&gt;PsychofonRecords.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and we have a fully-working web shop up there. It has everything you would possibly be interested in buying. I strongly suggest buying &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. Just grab it all indiscriminately. Don’t look at the price. Don’t look at the shipping. Don’t even look at the pictures or the words. Just click the “Add to Cart” button and go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use discount code OVNMWM10 for a 10% discount on your purchase. Good through March 1, 2017!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Andy, thank you so much. Ostrich, this interview is &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; over, so thank you for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;OVN: Thank you sir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool. Thank you, guys.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2016 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/ostrich-von-nipple/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/ostrich-von-nipple/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mad Hatter Guitar Products</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mad-hatter-guitar-products&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter Guitar Products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, I randomly received an email from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/robertscovill/following&quot;&gt;Robert Scovill &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, world-famous front of house sound engineer for huge artists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Petty&quot;&gt;Tom Petty &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, inviting me to play guitar at a mega-church in Scottsdale, AZ. I was dumbfounded. Turned out he was serious, so I went and played a few times at that church. It was there that I met and played with Ed Heisler, founder of Mad Hatter Guitar Products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed and I didn’t talk for several years until we bumped into each other at a guitar show in Tempe, AZ in 2014 or 2015. And it wasn’t until about 10 minutes into our conversation that we realized we had played together several years prior. I ended up buying one of his electronic upgrade kits for my 1997 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jemsite.com/gallery/browseimages.php?c=11&quot;&gt;Ibanez Jem7vwh &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what a difference it would make to get the upgrade kit installed in this guitar. It turns out that Ibanez used (uses?) incredibly cheap, low-end components, even in its high-end guitars. After Ed helped me install the kit in the guitar (it was a tight fit), it sounded amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since he’s basically a 1-man show and he’s passionate about doing what he does and he’s such a good guy and he cares about weird music, I thought he’d be a great fit on the site. Plus, I’d have to say, with his upgrade kit, I have more flexibility in guitar tone than ever. There are a lot of guitar players that visit the site that’d definitely get a lot out of buying his gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;Find out more about Mad Hatter at their website! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I invited Ed into my tiny bedroom studio to talk about Mad Hatter, and talk we did! I learned a lot in this interview and I hope you do, too. We talk about guitar electronics, manufacturing processes, how the electronics work, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2agooTHb3f8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s audio of the interview (NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/mad-hatter/mad-hatter.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/mad-hatter/mad-hatter.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony: Hey, this is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and I’m here with Ed Heisler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Ed: How you doing, Anthony?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I’m all right. Thanks for joining us today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Great to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Thank you. Why don’t you tell us about who you are, what you do, and why you’re here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Well, I’m Ed Heisler, AKA “Electric Ed”, with Mad Hatter Guitar Products. We sell products that are basically a whole electronics system for electric guitars. We have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com/pages/terminator&quot;&gt;relacement kit upgrade &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to enhance your tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Tell us about how it is an upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: A lot of what you find in guitars, especially those made in Asia, is very subpar. Even in Mexico, they tend to use cheaper components even though some of the guitars coming out of those countries are great guitars. Some of the best guitars are coming out of Korea, actually, and it’s just amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s some stuff coming out of China that’s really well made, actually, and in Mexico, the Mexican &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fender_Stratocaster&quot;&gt;Strats &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Mexican &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fender_Telecaster&quot;&gt;Telecasters &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A lot different than when I was a young kid. You’d start with these guitars and the action was 2-3” inches off the neck. They were garbage whereas that’s totally changed today and the quality is much better. But in order for manufacturers to save money, they cut costs wherever they can and one of the places is the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TzWZCwI6sTg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So a lot of people buy these great-playing guitars. They go to the music store and go, “Wow, these play great,” and they say, “Well, if I upgrade the pickups to maybe some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DiMarzio&quot;&gt;DiMarzios &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seymour_Duncan&quot;&gt;Seymour Duncans &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, this could be a great sounding guitar, too.” But what they don’t realize is you’re basically putting the pickups into a guitar that plays good, but you’re putting them through &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potentiometer&quot;&gt;potentiometers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, output jacks, and switches that are basically garbage because that’s where they’re cutting costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And if you don’t mind, I have a box called my “Box of Doom.” I pull this stuff out of guitars… This is from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Squier&quot;&gt;Squier &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Strat. This is about as cheezy and cheap as it gets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Now what–some people, myself included, wouldn’t be able to look at that and go, “That looks like junk,” versus, “That looks fantastic.” So tell me how to identify junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: The way I can identify it is that pretty much anything coming out of Asia is junk. Anything coming out of China is going to be junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: As far as musical electronics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah. Obviously your iPhone was probably made there, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Yeah, I was thinking, “There’s probably some variance there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, but as far as guitar electronics… What you’ll find is a lot of these–sometimes you’ll notice when you turn it on, you’ll notice the volume’s there, the volume’s there and you roll it down and boom, it’s gone. There’s no graduation of it that you normally would have in a quality pot. The switches and contacts are not that good either. When you feel it, it just feels cheap and doesn’t feel as good. What we use at Mad Hatter is a much better quality product. What we did is basically we–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Before you go there, I’m curious… What are these components made of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Oh jeez, just the cheapest stuff they can find. They’re supposed to be carbon, but it’s more or less the quality of it. The quality of how they put it together because they’re so mass-produced. The issue is to make it as quick as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What are some of the other side effects of poor quality in terms of sound or even the physical use?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Oh, tone. First of all, I think these are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capacitance&quot;&gt;250K &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [pots]. I’ll measure them and realize that instead of measuring 250K, it might measure 190 or 180K. It might not–It just won’t even be close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So they don’t meet specifications?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Not at all. No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IEGgC3MnlbA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: The quality assurance is fairly low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: There would be no quality assurance. The only thing they’re looking to see is that it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you might pick up two of the same guitar, one made right after the other, and they’ll sound very different. One might sound much worse than bad and the other might just sound bad? It’ll never sound great?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: There’s more to that–that’s pretty much any guitar out there. I’d like to talk about that later–the characterstics of the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Okay, cool. Is that what makes–over time, when your pots start crackling–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: They get dirty. Yeah, that’s pretty much all pots. Even the pots that we use were designed after the great pots used in guitars in the 1950s. I basically went to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ctscorp.com/products/controls-2/variable-resistorspotentiometers/&quot;&gt;CTS Corp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and said, “Listen. I want a pot that is basically what you guys were manufacturing in the 1950s that were put into ‘59 plain tops, in the 1960s strats, and 50s strats and stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Just so we can start with the basics, what is a potentiometer and what does it do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rUkrpqEmXb8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Okay, a potentiometer is basically–originally they would call them “rheostats.” What it does is it tapers–we’ll use an audio taper, okay?–As opposed to a linear. In audio, it basically curves off the sound and what you’re doing with an electric guitar on a volume pot is, basically, when you start rolling off the volume, what you’re doing is you’re going from one center wiper of the potentiometer into another one that’s hooked up to ground, and what you’re doing is shorting out the sound. As you slowly roll it down towards ground, basically you’re making it sound more quiet until you’re eventually hearing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So, it’s basically re-routing the signal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Into a wire that has no effect on your output, other than buzzing (if you don’t have good ground).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, that’s a whole other thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So when you turn it, is there like two contacts inside?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Basically you have a wiper in the center two contacts on each side and that resistance goes back and forth. Basically you’re sweeping from one side to the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And that’s for volume. What about tone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/t9Qwx75eg8w?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: What you’re doing there is the same concept, but you’re usually only using two contacts. You can see here, you have a capacitor and different capacitors give you a different dynamic and roll off the tone. Unless you have a resistance here going through the volume pot. The guitars in the 1980s, where they had no tone pot, they tended to be brighter. The reason why is because you didn’t have the tone pot in the circuit, which was going to create a little bit of roll-off just naturally by itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So when you roll the tone knob all the way down and it sounds mellow, what are you doing electronically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: You’re adding this capacity into it and this capacitor is going to roll off those frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, interesting. So when you change the capacitance there, it’s going to change the character of the high end or of the whole signal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: The whole signal. Yeah, that’s why with our kits, we design them so you can easily grab different capacitors and try them out and swap them and see what you like. There’s so many characteristics you can find. You can sit there all day having fun. A lot of times, I’ll take a capacitor–well, here I can show you right here. [Picks up a guitar.] See in this guitar here, I’ve added–we have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capacitor_types&quot;&gt;polymer caps &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I’ve added this one here and this one here, what it does is when you roll it off, it doesn’t go as deep as most caps. So it gives you a smaller frequency range, but yet it gives you a greater distance to dial in that frequency, if that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you have more granularity and control over those frequencies, so a little turn on another capacitor would be the same as a larger turn on this capacitor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Exactly. You can easily swap them out and that’s how we designed it. Fenders use the orange drop. I had one guitar where I bought some bumble bee-type caps that used to be used in the old &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gibson_Guitar_Corporation&quot;&gt;Gibsons &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I put those on there. Russia makes some great–new old stock Russian ones you can find online. You can find oil-filled ones and then the bumble bees. Sometimes you can spend hundreds of dollars on caps. Some of the old vintage ones, people get serious about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So the variety of tone you get out of one instrument is pretty significant just by switching out capacitors and switching out your potentiometers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Oh yeah. Sometimes you won’t even really hear it–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Are these your pots too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, this is our kit right here. This is our single volume, dual tone kit. Basically what you’d normally use on a Stratocaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What does a dual tone give you? A lot of guitars I see have one tone knob.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Fender used two. What they did was on the original ones they had one for the neck and one for the middle and then the bridge was direct. You’d basically bypass the tone so it was really bright. But what I’ve done here is I’ve used the first tone pot and I’ve tied the bridge pickup on the 250K side of the pot because we have a dual-value pot, which I can go into and discuss. And then I put the neck on the 500K to make it brighter, so you can change the different values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So the whole guitar, all the pickups, you have much more control over how they might sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Oh yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Every guitar is different. Every guitar has a characteristic of its own. We were talking earlier about picking up two different guitars that were made in the same place and sound different. I remember when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_Clapton&quot;&gt;Eric Clapton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackie_(guitar)&quot;&gt;Blackie &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came out and I remember they took his Blackie and took it to the Fender Custom Shop and every nick and every little thing–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Their relic series–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah. They measure the capacity of the amps and the pots and they try to make it exactly identical. I was at a store where they had two of them. They had gotten two of them and I played one and was like, “Wow, this one’s nice.” Then I grabbed the other one and we were looking at it and it was unbelievable how different it sounded. Just, it didn’t ring out as much as the first one did because the wood’s different. Even though the Custom Shop sat there and made sure they had the same resistance on all the pickups and the potentiometers were the same, it still was different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Different trees, different wood densities… Those affect the vibrations of the strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah. I mean, no two guitars are alike. Just like you and me. I think every guitar has its own characteristic. That’s basically how Mad Hatter started. It was based on that concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vzmKenvFwTE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: I walked into a music store one day and hanging onto a wall was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gibson_Les_Paul&quot;&gt;Les Paul Standard &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A black one with factory gold. It was just, boom, playing it and, “Oh, I gotta have that.” I picked it up and it’s got a little bit of a fatter neck and it played great. But I noticed it wasn’t ringing. Sometimes you pick up a guitar and you just feel a little vibration. I thought, “Man, this plays great, but it’s really not ringing. It plays so nice.” Plus it looked cool. I had to have it, so I saved my money and got it home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;First thing I did was upgraded the pots. I pulled the pots out of it and they were Gibson pots and stamped with the Gibson medallion. They claim they’re CTS, but I don’t know. I put it on the meter. The 500K pot was reading about 300, so it was &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; off. I took them out and put new pots in there and I started putting different caps and pickups and it was just like, “Yeah, maybe not this one.” I tried this type of pickup and it just kept going back and forth trying to find the right tone for that guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was doing it and thinking, “Wouldn’t it be nice–” Every time I did it, I had to pull out my soldering iron, plug it in, wait for it to heat up, unsolder it, solder it back in. It was like, “What a pain! Wouldn’t it be nice if I just had some switches or something?” And that was the first design. I sat down with pencil and paper and etched out what became the solderless tone shaping system. That’s what the routing board was with little switches on it where you could change whether you wanted to go with the 250K or 500K and stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: This is a hobby for you, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: It started out that way! Just like a lot of guitar players, it was just something that started as a hobby and it’s growing into a business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So it started out with pencil and paper and you’re manipulating electronics in this Gibson guitar and then, when did you decide, “I need ot have my own system that is consistent?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: About that same time. Yeah and I sat down and just manufactured a board. That was our first generation. Since then, at the end of last year, we decided, “How can we improve on this? How can we make it better?” We looked at what my customer service emails were and stuff and I thought, “Okay.” I kind of did an evaluation and I thought, “You know what? I need to eliminate the board.” That’s when we came up with the Terminator system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cyu51lHNGVw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, okay. I have the system with the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: You have the original solderless tone shaping system. And now we have the terminator system, which is more–if you understand guitar electronics, you’ll look at this system you’ll say, “Oh, I know exactly what to do here.” Now you have total and complete control. You can basically take any schematic online, just google whatever, and you say, “Oh, you know what? I can try that with this.” You can use our schematics that we send out with the product or you can use whatever you find online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And that involves changing capacitance. Do you have different kinds of pots with different values?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Let me talk a little about our pot. That was the main thing that I really wanted to make sure, because this is where it all starts. This is where the pickups go to, the switch in here. The switch–let me jump over here a little bit. We use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HEICO&quot;&gt;Switchcraft &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; toggle switches and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.electro-nc.com/guitar.shtml&quot;&gt;CLR selector switches &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: CLR is a company? A brand?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: It’s a company. I didn’t bring any Switchcraft. I’m sorry about that. But that’s the toggle switches you find on Les Pauls. The three way. We use Switchcraft. That’s what Gibson’s been using forever and it’s the best. They’re made here in the United States. This is CLR. These are made over in North Carolina. You see this spring here, that’s how you usually tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;These are the ones that Fender’s been using. Leo started using them in the 1950s. All the American made strats, you’re going to find these in there. And they’re just much better quality. You can tell just by moving it. It just feels much more solid. You’re not going to have an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So this is the new Terminator system where we mounted the terminal to the side so on a Strat, your pickup wires would go here. On every component we have dead terminals where you can land–in this case we have two dead terminals so you can land the center tap wires on the pickup. So the pickup wire, you have a signal wire and a ground wire. Typically a two wire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;On a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humbucker&quot;&gt;humbucker &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, you have your middle wires for each coil where they come together, where the south poles of each coil come together. And those you call your center tap. A lot of times when people try to turn their humbucker into a single coil, they’re basically dropping at the ground there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So anyways, we have the terminals here where you can land those as well and do mods and stuff like that. This one here is our HSH switch. What this one does is for a guitar with a humbucker, single, humbucker and you go to position 2, you’re going to split the coil of the humbucker with the middle, and then the same thing in position 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But going back to the pot, I went to CTS and I said, “Look, this is what I want. I need a pot. I want it to be smaller in diameter.” So we went with a 17mm diameter instead of the normal big, fat ones. But, I said, “Internally, I want it to be the same as what you guys were making in the 1950s. A carbon pot. I want it to be a brass bushing, brass end, with the 22 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knurling&quot;&gt;knurled &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; teeth end here, split.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then what I did was I made the shaft here, the bushing length, 12mm. The reason why I did that was because I wanted to be able to fit comfortably into guitars with pickguards like stratocasters, telecasters, whatever, Ibanezes and stuff, and then guitars with carved tops like Gibsons and stuff like that. And it does. I have yet to find a guitar where this does not fit. The 12mm length can fit in any guitar that’s manufactured today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then we went with the bushing diameter, we went with 8mm. The reason why is because our target market is upgrade those guitars made overseas and they use an 8mm hole, which is a smart hole. Most of our customers–We don’t want our customers to have to drill out the hole and make it larger if they don’t have to. With this one, you won’t have to do that. And then what we have–although with our yin yang push/pull pots, they are 3/8” so you’d have to make those a little bit bigger. We’ll talk about those in a minute. Then I also wanted dual value. 250K, 500K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Okay, I was wondering why the dual pots over there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7EldDxjU7Q8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: I wanted it to be as universal as possible so that way strats that are 250K, Gibsons that are 500K. And then with the new Terminator system we can bridge them together so they’re 750K so they can be even brighter. So we have 3 options now with the pot. We have an exclusive deal with CTS corporation for this pot. We’re the only one that they’ll make this for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Wow. So in the case of my custom 7-string, which has a tone bypass circuit where you turn the tone all the way up and then it effectively shuts off the tone knob, you don’t really need that because 750K should allow everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Well, 750K would be real bright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Probably as bright as having nothing on it, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Not quite that bright, but pretty close. Yeah, it still gives you that option to roll it down to where you get that really mellow sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s cool! Are guitar companies picking up on these?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: We have a few guys that are using our products exclusively. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/MAPguitars/&quot;&gt;MAP guitars &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in California. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/jrcustomguitarco/&quot;&gt;JR Guitars Customs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Montreal, Canada. James up there is a great guy. Some of the builds he’s done are for the Alzheimer’s Association. He loves to give back. He calls me up and says, or send me emails saying, “This is what I wanna do.” Something goofy, off the wall. He’s always thinking outside the box and I love working with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: These are so flexible that any idea he has, you can figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah. We’re doing a double-neck together right now. A telecaster, which is kinda cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What do these builders think of the electronics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: They love them. They’re putting our card on there as a hang tag and letting customers know that it’s a quality product inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22:53&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Is it substantially more expensive? Is it a “get what you pay for” kind of thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: The price point of our products is, for example–let me grab a kit here–this is our single volume, single tone 3SS kit. This is $79.99. If you were to go out and buy all brand new CTS pots, CLR selector switches–let me open this up here so you can see what you’re going to get when you open it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You get a Switchcraft output jack, CLR selector switch–so that’s what our price point is on that. Comparably, if you were to go out and buy all these components, you’re gonna be paying at least half that, if not more. If you’re a do-it-yourself kind of person, it’s a lot easier and you’ve got all the flexibility of the product itself and what it can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So it’s a complete electronics replacement system. So, what about pickups? Are they also variable in quality or are they fairly consistent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Or they’re variable too. There’s one manufacturer–I was going back to the Les Paul and trying different pickups in there and one manufacturer that’s very boutique-y, they average single pickups at $130 and I bought one and I put it in there and they had it out of phase and I actually called the shop up and they said, “Well, you used it.” Even their quality, you just don’t know. So it’s something that you just have to really stay on top of because you don’t know what you’re gonna get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, it’s not often you see that, but it does happen. This kit here, our SS kit, is basically a setup–you can see our instructions here. This one allows you to run–the person that ordered this wanted this kit, I just put it together for a customer, and what they’re doing here is they want to run their bridge pickup at a different K (500K or 250K) and then their neck at a different one, so that’s what this wiring diagram shows how you can actually do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah. Then you can mix it up if you want to put–sometimes some people put their bridge pickup volume at 500K and then they’ll do the tone pot at 250K or something on the same pickup. It’s just 100% complete flexibility. On these two, we also have a dead terminal for mods or whatever you wanna do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We color code it. Our green ones are “Goes to 11 volume pot” and then the red ones are our “Killer tone pot.” That way you can easily tell whether you’re using the right one. Then what we do is we blacked the black terminals for ground. If you ever see a black terminal, it’s ground. The red terminals are 500K and then the blue are 250K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: These are definitely nicer upgrades from the first generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah the first generation, you just plugged into the board. You can do a lot more now. Like if you wanted to add a treble blade, like some people like to do on their volume pots, now you can do that by just puttig it in parallel with the pot like you normally would. So like I was saying, you can basically grab any schematic offline and just follow it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How consistent are your parts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Our parts are within 10%. The values are all within 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So 500K will never be below 450K or higher than 550K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Exactly. And it’s usually been dropping to around 480, some to 500. Same thing with the 250K values, which is the top part. They’ve been at the same thing. You don’t see them below 225K. Usually I see them around 235, 240.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you get a “cleaner” tone with less noise? When I put mine in, I was pretty astonished at the clarity that I heard, but it could have been several factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: That’s really the quality of the pot and the switch because the contacts are so much better with CLR. This pot is designed with the carbon where it’s going to be a much better, cleaner tone. It’s better manufacturing, better components, all put together…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Are there any manufacturers putting out anything close to this quality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Oh yeah, there’s a couple. Even you could just go online and buy some CTS pots as well as CLR. You could solder it together yourself. But what you won’t have is the flexibility of &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/pots-switches-caps/products/mad-hatter-universal-cts-dual-value-potentiometer&quot;&gt;this dual value pot &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as well as the ability to quickly and easily switch combinations or capacitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: So that’s the benefit we have. There’s other solderless systems out there, too, but I’ve noticed that they’re on a board, so they basically either strictly into a Stratocaster or strictly into a Les Paul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u0YALIVGQ4g?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you’re basically more universal with customization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah. This kit here, it can go into a Telecaster, it can go into a two-pickup Ibanez, or a Schaller, or LTD ESP, dual humbucker. It’ll fit just fine in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: And you make other products like kill switches and what else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yes, we do have kill switches. Let me show you here. These here–we were going to the shows and constantly people are coming to me asking if we have kill switches. I have to admit, I’m thinking old school hit-a-button-and-it-kills-everything-and-shuts-it-off. Little did I know that they were talking about a momentary switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A momentary switch is where you push a button and you kill something for a moment and let it go and it turns back on. Then I saw that Eddie Van Halen had one in his guitar and I thought, “Oh, okay.” So my son and I sat down–basically I went out and I ordered a bunch of switches. A bunch and bunch of switches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;We sat down and we just plugged them in just trying them all and we came up with this one here and we just love this kill switch. We call it our &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/pots-switches-caps/products/mad-hatter-rapid-fire-kill-switch&quot;&gt;Rapid Fire Kill Switch &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a momentary and you hit it and it bounces right back. When it’s mounted on the guitar, you can just go crazy with it. What we liked about it is that it really bounced back really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The second thing we liked about it is that the hole is slightly bigger than a 3/8 hole, but it’s not like some of those switches where the hole is almost a one inch diameter and you’re boring out a huge hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckethead&quot;&gt;Buckethead &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has an arcade button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vOfd39wGapw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, he does and I’ve had people ask me about those. They see ‘em in his Les Paul. I have to say, “Gibson had to manufacture that with a 3/4 inch or 1 inch hole.” It’s a huge hole. So I ask, “Do you really want to do that to your guitar?” Some people do and that’s fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So these switches, you didn’t customize. You probably added your own wiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah what we did is we put them to this state where we solder them up, we check them out and then we give instructions on how to mount them in the guitar. When you buy them, they’re going to come in this packaging and you’re going to get a Mad Hatter Guitar Products sticker and one of our cards, which has our website and information so you can contact us for customer service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then we have instructions on how to install it and make sure you’re drilling the right size hole. If it’s a pickguard, you can drill a clearance hole. If it’s a carved top guitar, you wanna go a little smaller and thread it in there. These are $7.99. They’re not that much money. We also, for a couple bucks more, we’ll put an 18 inch lead on it, so if you want to put that switch up here or whatever, you can expand it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Cool! Can we get a demo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: On the kill switch?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: No, just on the electronics of the guitar. You brought two guitars?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: I did. Let me plug in. This is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverend_Musical_Instruments&quot;&gt;Reverend &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reverendguitars.com/instrument/warhawk-iii-390/&quot;&gt;Warhawk 390 model &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know if you’re familiar with Reverend, they’re out of Livonia, Michigan. This guitar is made in Korea. It’s all Korina wood. These pickups are their pickups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Looks like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-90&quot;&gt;P90 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: All three P90s. I kinda modded it a little bit. I’ve added some Tone Pros bridge and then obviously our system. Our single volume dual tone 5-way. Switchcraft output jack. What I have right now is it’s set up for 250K on the volume and then I have the bridge pickup on the tone here at 250K and the neck on the tone here at 500K. The middle is on 500K. XXX EDIT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Right now, this is the bridge pickup. Just gonna play some chords here. [Demos different pickups and configurations] For a Mexican Strat, it’s made really well. They used to be a lot of components were made in the United States and then shipped down there. I think all the pickguards are still, the last I heard. But yeah, it’s the same alders, maple necks and everything, but the only thing different is the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of people buy them and upgrade the pickups, but with our system in it in addition to the pickups, now you have a guitar you can pick up on Craigslist for $300 that now is valued at considerably more. $500, $600, $800. It’s not valued that much more, but it sounds as good as that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: But you’d probably upgrade a $2000 guitar, too. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Oh yeah, like I said, the first Les Paul. I’ve done a few guitars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: My Ibanez Jem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Exactly. Your Ibanez, that’s one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I couldn’t believe the difference. It was stunning and when I took it home, it was like a new guitar. It sounded like a new guitar. Probably because the pots being 17, 18 years old and probably paper on the inside and junky components. It sounded like a brand new guitar. I couldn’t believe it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, you start hearing the dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh yeah. You get all new sounds out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: The sensitivity, the midranges. It opens up the span of what you’re missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: It felt like that Allegra D commercial where it starts out with everything as hazy and then they take the medicine and the whole screen wipes and suddenly the color is vibrant and very clear and clean. That’s how it felt picking up the guitar after putting in those electronics. It was night and day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah and it makes you want to pick it up more. And you wanna get more out of it. Our slogan is, “Hear what your guitar is missing.” That’s what it truly is. When you put our system in there, you truly think, “Wow, I didn’t know those tones were there, but they’re there. They’re hidden in the guitar.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Let me pull up this Telecaster here. I get emails from people all the time saying they can’t believe the difference. The ones that really shine through–a friend of mine has a Squier bass made in Indonesia and he said–he plays at a church and he took it there and put my system in his guitar and plugged in and even people who don’t even play instruments were like, “Wow. Did you get a new guitar? It looks the same.” It was such a huge upgrade. The tone overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Uqy-VK9KW74?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: For about $80, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah. Actually, he had a P-bass, so that one is $69.99. So, that’s incredible. This one here is the guitar that I do a lot of–I love the guitar, but you can see it’s a bit Frankenstein. I can’t leave crap alone. I don’t have a guitar–you go through my guitar collection and try to find a guitar that’s stock, no luck. No chance. If you don’t mind, let me digress for a little bit. You look at the people that mess with their stuff: Les Paul, Eddie Van Halen…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: They make it their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Well, Blackie I was talking about with Eric Clapton. From my understanding that was a collaboration where he went to the music store and bought a half dozen guitars and started mixing and matching until they got to the one he liked the best. I was watching a video about Jimmy Page talking about his #1 guitar and some of the changes they did on that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But anyway, on this one here, you can see this plate doesn’t stay down anymore because I stripped out the screws. I’m constantly pulled out the screws. This has our 5-way single volume single tone kit in it. And then what I did was I had this mini toggle. Normally when I have a toggle, I have it in there to jumper the bridge and neck pickup together so I can still get that middle position of a Tele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, this is one of the guitars I’m constantly changing. I’ve got a switch here that is a 3-way switch. Normally I have a switch that jumpers the neck and bridge pickups together, but I took that out and put this switch in here and I have it wired to the volume pot. And what it does here is in this position, the volume pot is 250K and in the middle it’s 500 and then it’s 750.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh, cool, so we get to hear all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Now you’re probably not going to hear a huge difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: If you start at the 250 and jump to the 750, would it make a big difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Not really. You’re really going to notice it when you’re playing it and you try different pedals and stuff. It’s like, “Oh wow.” We did an install in a Telecaster and it was a comparison video that we’re going to be releasing here soon. We did a before and after and we stayed with a 250 and the dynamics all opened up with 250. Then I started messing around with 500K and 750 and I ended up landing on the 500K. The guitar sounded better there, so that’s what we did. [Demos the Telecaster.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So you can hear it. When you put the pedals to it and delays, that changes the characteristics of the tone and amplifies it more. Then that’s when you really start to notice it. For guys like me, I want as a shredder, I want that right tone. It’s gotta be that mid-range brown sound kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I’ll usually go more toward the 500, or actually I find on British pickups, I’ll like 250K, especially with humbuckers. That’s been my thing with Gibsons. They’re traditionally 500K, but I want the 250K because it’s so close to the bridge, sometimes those guitars have that harshness on them and with taking it to 250K kind of rolls that off and smooths it out a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you get skeptics saying, “This sounds silly or far-fetched or ridiculous. How much difference could it really make?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: It’s kind of all over the map. I get a lot of people that say, “This is genius.” I love those people. Anyone who refers to me as a genius, I’ll take it! Then I have those who just see it as a solderless system. They say, “Oh, learn how to solder.” Well, it’s not a solderless system. It’s a tone enhancement system. It’s an upgrade for your guitar to make it sound better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The solderless part of it is just a byproduct. Although I will admit that most of my customers are buying it because you can screw wires in instead of getting a soldering iron. That’s what they feel more comfortable with. For those people, it’s a huge bonus for them because what they’re getting is a huge upgrade. I think as far as tone purists, no they all get it. The guys that are really into tone, they’ll go out and buy new pots for guitars. They’re always constantly changing stuff. So, yeah, they get that aspect of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So it’s usually just people thinking, “I don’t need that.” And they’re probably not looking for tone upgrades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: No, I have one friend of mine at NAMM a couple years ago, they came by to my booth. We’ve been friends for about 30 years. Great guy, great guitar player. He works in the industry and he’s like, “I see what you’re trying to do, but I’m not sure if I get it.” He’s the type of guy who walks in a store and play every guitar on the wall until he finds that right one. Then he won’t touch it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QcTXBEAfXd0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Those are the guys, those are customers I’ll never have because they don’t want to touch nothing, they don’t want to change nothing, they like it the way it is. They don’t even want to touch the intonation. They’ll take it to a service guy and they’ll tweak it. The only thing they’ll do is change strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Interesting. That’s awesome. Anything else worth noting about these systems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Buy. Buy many. They’re great. I think it’s long overdue. I think it’s something we really, really need. I think a lot of people agree with me. I don’t see manufacturers improving their quality of electronics. They just want to make, especially the ones coming out of China, they want to make a quick, fast, cheap guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A: What attracts me to the whole thing is you’re just one guy in a garage with a shop designing electronic components. I think that’s super unique and it’s had such a dramatic effect on my own guitar, so in terms of making weird music, I feel like this kit gives you more possibilities and that’s one thing I loved about it when I put it in my guitar. I was like, “Oh, now I can get more of the country sound or I can more of the rock sound or I can get more of the jazz sound.” It increased the diversity of my tonal capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A lot of people say, “Tone is in the fingers,” but there is a mathematical limit in terms of frequency range and what you are able get out of an instrument. Your fingers will do certain things, but they will not give you above 1K frequencies. So, it’s awesome for me to see a kit made by a guy who’s passionate about fixing guitars and expanding their horizons. I think it’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Even as I was mentioning before, people who have great fingers are messing with their guitars, too. There’s so many–you can start with your fingers, and then your strings through the pickups through the electronics and then through that cable, which we do sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Oh yeah, &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/picks-straps-cables/products/mad-hatter-instrument-cables&quot;&gt;you make cables &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: We sell great cables, too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What’s special about your cables besides their cool color?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: I love cool colors. We have green, purple, orange, black. And what we do is we use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neutrik&quot;&gt;Neutrik &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ends with a kill switch on them and then they’re gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: They don’t snap apart like those Planet Waves ones?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: No, these…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: How does the kill switch work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: It shorts it out when it’s not plugged in. When you plug it in, then you have a signal. What I did is I went with a lighter cable because Monster and all them are getting a big, fat–Mogami and stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Like 8 gauge…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, you’re dragging around a rope like you’re at the gym. You should be exercising with it. So, anyway, with people nowadays doing more home recording–that’s the other thing. I’ve had my recording gear on a table, I’ll plug in the heavier cable, and boom all my stuff is being dragged off because the weight of the cable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I wanted a lighter weight, smaller cable. Some people think, “Oh, it’s smaller, maybe it’s not good quality.” This is an excellent quality cable. I’ve actually A/B tested it with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mogami_Cable&quot;&gt;Mogami &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and against the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monster_Cable&quot;&gt;Monster &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it’s right there, the same quality. Same frequencies and stuff. And we priced it, too. Like this cable, 18 foot $49.99. My goal is to keep it under $50. I have very little margin, but I just think it’s stupid to pay $100 for a great cable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What makes it a great cable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: The quality of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: What makes a quality cable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: This is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canare.com&quot;&gt;Canare cable &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and these are probably the best cables you can buy. With the Neutrik ends, probably the best ends you can buy, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you solder these yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: I do them myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: So you buy a spool of the cable and you’ve got the ends and you make them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, I sit there and put it together and test it out and make sure it’s all good. Everything’s quality tested. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: So, yeah. It’s a product that I think–we don’t sell a lot of them because we’re not really a cable manufacturer. It’s just something we offer. But, I would like to sell more of them. I think what it is is that I’m starting to see more people go toward a smaller cable. I think once it catches one, they’ll realize, “Oh yeah, you don’t need a honking cable for good tone, you just need a good solid-quality cable.” That’s what this is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Do you bundle the cable with the kit for any price?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: I guess I could, yeah! For a Make Weird Music special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use the code &quot;weirdmusic&quot; to get 10% off at &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com&quot;&gt;Mad Hatter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt; And thank Ed for his generosity. :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: All right, if we do anything like that, we’ll put it on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, we will. And obviously we sell &lt;a href=&quot;http://madhatterguitarproducts.com/collections/mad-hatter-guitar-products-tee-shirts&quot;&gt;t-shirts with the cool logo &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. And our product, let’s face it, is a geeky product. It’s not shiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: No, there’s nothing sexy about potentiometers. Those cables, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Cables, a little sexy. But potentiometers and switches, no. I wanted to have a cool logo. I wanted to use a name that was very familiar, one that I had to worry about–I open up the magazines and it’s KBG or KBC or KVD or whatever. Initials. Somebody’s last name. I wanted to use something interesting. What really got me was I remember when I was a kid, there was a company still around called Bad Ass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I remember as a kid, “Okay, the guitar isn’t cool unless you have a Badass bridge on it.” I want to bring that vibe back. I think it kinda got lost because everyone’s got technical names now. I wanted to grab something that people remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I hired a cartoon artist who drew this logo for me. He used to work for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd_McFarlane&quot;&gt;Todd McFarlane &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A guy by the name of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jayfotos.com&quot;&gt;Jay Fotos &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Brilliant artist. I was really pleased with the outcome of what he drew up. So we sell these shirts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Shirts, cables, kits, picks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Yeah, we got picks too. This year–we try to change them up every year. This year we have one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyoxymethylene&quot;&gt;delrin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; type materials. They’re like a jumbo jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: I actually need some of these. I’m doing a video on pointy picks. I’ve got delrin triangular picks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: That’s yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: .73mm. That’s it. Okay, cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: We got different sizes. Next year, might be something totally different. Last year, it was just a regular &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celluloid&quot;&gt;celluloid &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; type pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;A: Delrin’s great. I love it. Thank you so much, Ed. I really appreciate your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;E: Thank you! This is awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 12:14:46 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/mad-hatter</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.makeweirdmusic.com/gear/mad-hatter</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
