<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Make Weird Music</title>
    <description>Expanding the creative horizons of musicians and music enthusiasts.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 21:36:38 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 21:36:38 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Cribbage Variations</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-chris-opperman&quot;&gt;About Chris Opperman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first met Chris “Oppy” Opperman when I was a teenager using AOL to find musicians who were interested in Frank Zappa. My friend Todd told me about Oppy’s music and I was hooked. We’ve known each other for probably 20 years now and have stayed in touch thanks to social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris is finishing up his doctoral degree in music composition and has written a wonderful new piece of music called The Cribbage Variations for ex-Zappa bassist, Scott Thunes. More on that in the interview below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a wonderful new piece of music with tons of algorithmic composition insights that I find extremely interesting. In this interview, Chris walks us through most of the movements and even offers a performance of one of them. You’ll get a great sense of his compositional style and sense of humor through this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6-GwQRWXthQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-only-podcast&quot;&gt;Audio-Only (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/chris-opperman/the-cribbage-variations/chris-opperman-the-cribbage-variations.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/share/chris-opperman/the-cribbage-variations/chris-opperman-the-cribbage-variations.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Chris Opperman is a composer, pianist, music professor, and gentleman extraordinaire based in New Jersey. He has a long history of wonderful music including a couple solo albums, he’s worked with &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt;, he played trumpet on the album &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keneally.com/archive/discography/dancing.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dancing&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with [Mike’s band] Beer for Dolphins, and he’s here with us today to talk about a new piece that he’s written as a capstone dissertation music project for his Ph.D. All the way from New Jersey! So, Chris, thanks so much for joining us. I really appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Thanks for having me. I would like to quickly thank the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mason_Gross_School_of_the_Arts&quot;&gt;Mason Gross School of the Arts &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Gregory Mueller for setting up the studio today and letting us use their space. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that’s fantastic. It’s so easy when there’s professionals doing this. [Laughs] Cool, so Chris tell us a little bit about &lt;em&gt;The Cribbage Variations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Okay. So, I was doing research for the paper portion of my dissertation, which is going to be about &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt;’s piece, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boulez_Conducts_Zappa:_The_Perfect_Stranger&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dupree’s Paradise&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was trying to gain insight into how the 1988 arrangement was built. So, fortunate enough to be friends with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Thunes&quot;&gt;Scott Thunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so I emailed him and said, “Scott, how did this arrangement work out?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;He wrote back a nice email and he said that at one point he was walking around listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton_Webern&quot;&gt;Webern &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concerto_for_Nine_Instruments_(Webern)&quot;&gt;concerto for nine instruments, opus 24 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and wishing that it was a longer work. He tried to commission the piece from one of the other guys in the band, but he didn’t want to do it because he was busy playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cribbage&quot;&gt;Cribbage &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Mike Keneally on the bus. So, I read this email and I laughed a lot because it just seems like such a crazy idea and then I was like, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Well, what if I took Webern’s tone row and tried to smash it into the rules of Cribbage? What kind of results would I get?”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FkT-3Yh22PE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As things often happen in a creative effort, the piece spiraled completely out of control and became much larger in terms of scope and ambition and length than I’d initially intended and wound up being sufficient for the musical portion of my PhD in Musical Composition. That was a pretty nice surprise and kinda cool that it spun out from the other research I was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that’s super cool. And you’re premiering the piece next month, in November, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Yep, Sunday, November 19 at Shindell Hall, upstairs here from the studio, and it’s free and the performers will be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.masongross.rutgers.edu/music/ensembles/helix-new-music&quot;&gt;HELIX! &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is the new music ensemble here at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rutgers_University&quot;&gt;Rutgers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. They’re really doing a great job. The conductor, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.masongross.rutgers.edu/music/faculty/kynan-johns&quot;&gt;Kynan Johns &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he conducts a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustav_Mahler&quot;&gt;Mahler &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and a lot of operas around the world. He’s a really world-class conductor and he’s very excited about the piece, so that makes me feel very honored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And the piece itself has some very challenging aspects. I was listening to your rough mix last night and there’s a lot of passing of short motifs between groups of instruments. How have the rehearsals gone and what are some of the challenges they’ve faced?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: The rehearsals have gone pretty well. Obviously it’s one of the challenges–the syncopated rhythms and everything–and there’s the sheer number of notes in certain parts. The interesting thing is the parts they’re having trouble with are actually the parts where there’s a lot of space. They have a lot of really fast [sings quickly] passages and then they have [sings slowly with gaps], that kind of motif. So, kind of coordinating where they suddenly have space has been kind of a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The other thing that’s been kind of challenging is that when I was approaching the work, musicologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribd.com/document/352175588/Neoclassic-and-Anachronistic-Impulses-MARTHA-HYDE&quot;&gt;Martha Hyde wrote an article &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igor_Stravinsky&quot;&gt;Stravinsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s classical works and talked about how they kind of operate. One thing she talked about was what she called “eclectic imitation” where you would have these asynchronous or atemporaneous [The word I was looking for was “atemporal” -CO] musical ideas and they would just kind of get shoved together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, that kind of operates in this piece where you’ll have in one second in a kind of early 20th century paradigm and then the next second channeling more &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Wagner&quot;&gt;Wagner &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Liszt&quot;&gt;Liszt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So, those kind of sudden stylistic shifts in the variations, I think are kind of tough because it’s not just playing the notes, your performance practice has to suddenly change from one variation to the next one. But they’re doing a really great job, so that’s not a criticism of their hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, no. It’s legitimately challenging. As I was listening through last night, I just imagined trying to perform this as an ensemble. I love the piece. It is very stylistically diverse. How many movements and can you tell us about some of the methodology you went through or some of your thoughts as you were assembling the different movements and different genres?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Sure, absolutely. There are 15 movements because 15 is the “magic number” in Cribbage. I don’t know if you’ve ever played Cribbage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/j4nQl7gIqDk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I love Cribbage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Oh good, good! So, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rules_of_cribbage&quot;&gt;15 and 31 are the two most important numbers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The 15s happen all the time and 31s happen every once in a while. So first I built a matrix of all 144 possible combinations of the row and then I built a rhythm table for unique integers that equal 15 so that, if I wanted to pull different syncopated rhythms, I could pull them and they equal 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Some of my goals as I was working on the piece… The first thing is that a lot of people will dismiss &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twelve-tone_technique&quot;&gt;12-tone music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or 12-tone serialism as just “math music” or “not interesting” or that kind of stuff. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Whenever I approach something like this, I always want it to be musical, so the most important thing to me is that it be a functioning work of music.&lt;/span&gt; So, I wouldn’t go to someone working in a tonal paradigm and be like, “Well, your song is just all I IV V, that’s, like, super-lame.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I feel like the same kind of thing is operating here. A good craftsman, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;any tools in the hands of a good craftsman should provide a sufficient result.&lt;/span&gt; Hopefully it doesn’t sound too arrogant. I think I sound really arrogant right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, not at all. I think it’s super cool and our audience is probably the perfect audience for this. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Yeah. [Laughs.] For instance, there’s a couple ones that are easy to find. The first one, &lt;em&gt;Of Streets and Spillikins&lt;/em&gt;. The streets are when you have a cribbage board, the streets are where the pegs go and the spillikins are the pegs themselves. It starts with the trombone and the trombone plays the prime zero version of the row and has exactly 15 attacks while it’s accompanied with the rest of the thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A lot of 12-tone works start that way where you get a statement of the first row, kind of unabashedly so that you could see that the rest of the music spins out from that. I felt that would be really helpful to the listener, so we did that. The third movement is the first one that kind of addresses directly the Zappa connection with the 1988 band. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Some of the challenges you face working on a 12-tone piece is one of them is maybe you don’t want noise all the time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Chromatic saturation was something that Webern and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnold_Schoenberg&quot;&gt;Schoenberg &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alban_Berg&quot;&gt;Berg &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were trying to achieve, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milton_Babbitt&quot;&gt;Milton Babbitt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in their works. I don’t feel a need–I feel like that’s been done really well and excellently so I didn’t feel the need to be all chromatic saturation all the time. I tried to find ways to not be all chromatically saturated all the time. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think so. During those sections, I never felt that unpleasantness that I’ve normally felt listening to 12-tone music. So I was really interested to hear about how you approached that because it is so musical and approachable. It’s something that I feel is much more accessible than a lot of other 12-tone music I’ve heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: And that was partially by design. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I know there are some philosophies in music where the audience liking it is lame, but I kind of feel like I want the people on the journey with me to be part of the journey with me.&lt;/span&gt; That’s really important. One thing you can do with the 12-tone matrix is you can combine rows to create different effects. If I wanted a series of chords, then all I had to do was have 12 of them. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: I could pick–I’ll just pick at random. I’ll play something like this. [Plays a chord on the piano.] A D Eb and G. All right? Then I would just pick the corresponding notes on the matrix that start off the row. So I could pick P8, P3, P4, and P10. Then I could make a chord progression by going through the row that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was actually very strict about how the piece is constructed, so I had a series of rules. One of the rules was that all the row statements must be complete row statements because, as an analyst, it’s not fun when you’re analyzing a piece and then the composer decides, “Well, I just like this note better so I’m going to use this note.” I wanted it to be super-strict. You’ll find everything if you’re looking for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The other one is that I could repeat pitches in the row as long as I go back and then complete the row. So, I could have a phrase that goes [plays a phrase]. Okay? The notes are repeated there, but when I repeat it, I complete the row so you get a complete row statement. Also it made it possible to have 15 coinciding with 12 because it would be really hard to do if I wasn’t repeating any pitches whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is fascinating. So cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/z2pwTP7g7xE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Oh, thank you so much. The fourth movement, &lt;em&gt;A Mid-December Breeze&lt;/em&gt;–I might call it &lt;em&gt;Mid-December Winds&lt;/em&gt; because they’re played by woodwinds. That seems really obvious. I don’t know why I didn’t think of that earlier. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivier_Messiaen&quot;&gt;Messiaen &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was a composer in the mid-20th century who tries to bring back some kind of renaissance or medieval techniques when it came in terms of rhythm. He wrote a book called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Technique-Musical-Language-Bibliotheque-Leduc/dp/B0006AW8CW&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Technique of My Musical Language&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where he literally tells you how to write like him, which is pretty cool actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The idea of an isometric &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet&quot;&gt;motet &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the way it works is you have these two aspects: the rhythm and the pitches in the melody that are different numerical values.&lt;/span&gt; You have the talia, which is the rhythm, and then you have the color number of pitches. In this case, the number of pitches obviously is 12, and the number of rhythms is 15. In the fourth movement, what I did was I made a canon out of it. The flute starts off and it goes [plays the flute part] and then the oboe player comes in with a different one [plays the oboe part].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The notes will go through 12 and the repeat every 12 times and the rhythm will repeat every 15 pitches so that they wind up having a canon. You wind up with all the possible permutations to the rhythm. Obviously I didn’t do all of them or the piece would be super long. Then the three of them go together into kind of a canon. A lot of times in composition, you’re thinking about how to make multiple lines move at the same time. In a lot of rock and pop music, we have lines that don’t move–they’ll move together. [Plays chords together.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;They’ll have harmonies that are homorhythmic with itself. I find contrapuntal writing really interesting, so this is a way I could generate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counterpoint&quot;&gt;contrapuntal music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in a mathematical process in a way that also was satisfying. A lot of times these things were trial and error. I would try different rows and they would either be too dissonant or they would not be interesting enough or they wouldn’t fit mathematically and then I’d have to find a different combination of stuff that would work the way I wanted it to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I have a quick question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve heard the term “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleatoric_music&quot;&gt;aleatoric composition &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.” Is that what you’re doing? Is it kind of like rolling a dice and then you pick notes and chords and go from there? Or is this a different kind of systematic method? Or is this based on the rules that you’re inventing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: This piece is based on all the rules I’m inventing. The last piece I did for the Meraki chamber ensemble was a flute, clarinet, and cello piece. That piece was entirely aleatorically generated where I sat there with dice and rolled them. What I learned from that process–the reason why I do these things is &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;when I’m talking in the classroom with my students, I want to have the authority of someone who has actually done the homework of actually writing in these styles.&lt;/span&gt; Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: I felt like I could learn things intrinsically from the process of doing that I could never get from a book, so that’s why I did that. What I learned from the aleatoric piece was that the composer has an awful lot of control because the composer is determining the definition of the processes. If in one movement, I’m rolling–I got these musician’s dice that are these &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dice#Polyhedral_dice&quot;&gt;12-sided dice &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and have all the pitches on them. Because I’m a super nerd, right? And then I have D20s because I’m also a super nerd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So I would roll the pitch and then I would roll the D20 and I’d be, “Okay, the flute is going to play thirteen 16th notes in Ab.” But then there are different processes involved there, but the aleatoric stuff–actually, the composer has a lot more control than it sounds like at face value. The same thing here with the 12-tone matrix and that kind of stuff. The composer is determining the processes and therefore is defining what the work is going to sound like. So one of these processes–this is a really good segue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sf_Zfpq3gqk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One of these processes is an idea called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_point&quot;&gt;time point system &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that was invented by Milton Babbitt when he was at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princeton_University&quot;&gt;Princeton &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The way it works is you have a bar of 3/4 and you have your 12-tone row and then the position where the pitch goes is based chromatically on the 16th notes, so [plays a chromatic scale while counting the notes] 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. Right? If my row starts with a B, then on the very last 16th note, I’m going to have a B. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I thought, “Gee I wonder what would happen if I ran all twelve versions of the prime row at the same time with Milton Babbitt’s time point system.” Sometimes in science or in math or in anything you’re doing, you will discover that you are dumb. The result of this process, which should have been totally predictable, and I’m sitting there like, “Yeah, this is gonna sound so cool. This is so out there.” And then I play it back and what do I hear? [Plays a chromatic scale.] Sorry, that was terrible, let me try that again. [Plays a chromatic scale better twice.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Of course I’m hearing all 12 pitches in repeat because I’m using all 12 rows! But, it was so funny and so dumb that I kept it. I mean, the piano’s going [plays big intervals]–they’re all in different registers, but it has this effect where it sounds like a chromatic scale going up that never ends. But it was so funny and I was so dumb that I was like, “Okay, well I’m going to celebrate my stupidity by keeping this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Sometimes things should just be funny. I know new music is supposed to be really serious and classical music is supposed to be very serious, but sometimes I don’t want to be real serious.&lt;/span&gt; You know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Absolutely right. &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-pesci&quot;&gt;I’ve interviewed Frank Pesci&lt;/a&gt;, who’s a modern opera composer, and then &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/hyung-ki-joo&quot;&gt;Hyung-ki Joo&lt;/a&gt; from Igudesman &amp;amp; Joo. They both talked about the idea that we shouldn’t be so somber and serious and that music only became that way in the last 100 years or so. 120 years. So, I totally agree. I love this piece and I laughed at certain parts and it’s just such a fun thing to listen to. Very emotional. I was surprised at the emotionality, not because I don’t think you do that, but because it just was unexpected after certain parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h7fyOLe-xn4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Like the 12-tone stuff is usually hard to listen to, but I found myself really liking it and then it would go into some sort of really quiet, sensitive, beautiful section. Then you’d really build up from there and you were using space and dynamics. I just loved it. And it was all midi! So I’m like, “This is gonna be awesome when a real orchestra plays this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Oh yeah, it’s insane. At rehearsal, I’m like, “Wow, this sounds really good in real life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: And the piano. You hear the piano really well. One of the orchestration things–I’m used to working with large orchestras. So, suddenly I only have nine people, but I kept that in mind. The piano, I kept thinking was going to be quiet and then we get to rehearsal and the piano’s really loud and I’m like, “Hooray! I can hear the piano.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Ah, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: I really appreciate your kind words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, it’s a great piece, man. I’m really excited to even have this conversation and to share it with the world. Also, to say congratulations on finishing your PhD. I think that’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Well, I have to defend and still write a paper, but this part is finished. My advisor was like, “Good job!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: So, number seven. The seventh movement is a full-on Liszt-y and romantic double string work. Know what I mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: You come out of this kind of crazy thing and then all of a sudden, it’s like [plays slow, angular, dramatic melody]. You know, that kind of stuff. That’s good contrast. Sometimes the variations are actually variations on other works that are not the opus 24 because–I also thought about, “What is a variation?” I’m doing these variations on this row, but also variations on other pieces. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Also, I wanted–at first, I wasn’t going to tell anyone what the row was from and then we had a demo performance and one of the musicology professors here, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.masongross.rutgers.edu/music/faculty/douglas-johnson&quot;&gt;Douglas Johnson &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, walked right up to me and he goes, “Opus 24.” I’m like, “Wow, that’s totally insane and also correct and now that game is done because you already won the game. So, good job Dr. Johnson.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s cool. Two points for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Yeah. 100 points for him. That’s insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y6ENkJY9ObE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I guess he wins Cribbage. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Yeah, yeah. [Laughs.] One of the other challenges would be when I would have–there’s a brass trio and I wanted it to be really kind of regal and not [plays dissonant chords] “crunchy.” Know what I mean? So, you had to find rows where you could make them move at different times so that they would coordinate into things that were almost like tonal harmony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you have an example of that you can play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Sure, I can attempt to play. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: [Plays intro to Mov. 9 “Level Pegging.”] So you hear how the three parts are moving at different times? It’s so that I could continue the triadic harmony within the confines of the row construct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Thank you. That took a long time. [Laughs.] And then there’s another movement. The next one is called Lunn and that really makes good use of the rhythm table. A lot of syncopated rhythm. [Plays the intro to Mov. 10 “Lunn.”] They’re all harmonized, obviously. This was dedicated to Doug Lunn, who was my friend and a bass player. I heard about his passing in the middle of writing this movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, I’m sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: You can actually hear the moment when I found it because it happens at bar 283. There’s suddenly this big &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tutti&quot;&gt;tutti &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; emotional outpouring. It was like, “Wow, my friend died. This sucks.” I wanted to–I was already at the computer and I wanted to pay tribute to him. I know he was really good friends with Keneally and he was this wonderful guy. It was kind of sad, so I wanted to celebrate him also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: The eleventh movement is the most difficult one. That one is called Muggins. So, Anthony, why don’t you explain what muggins is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, jeez. [Long pause.] I don’t remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Okay. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’ve played a lot of Cribbage, but it’s infrequent. I don’t remember muggins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: So, when you forget to score…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s right! You lose points, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IxRuFz6ZWDU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: You lose points and your opponent gains points and they call muggins on you. It’s like if you didn’t call &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uno_(card_game)&quot;&gt;Uno &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something. So, when I first–here I tried to–I had this other piece called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi_paradox&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Fermi Paradox&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that we played at LPR a couple years ago and I had this kind of technique that I was calling “alien bebop” where you would have this kind of rhythm. It was kind of like [plays alien bebop on the piano]. It was all kind of harmonized. I like the technique that I did, but it was all harmonized the same. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: I had five instruments on it, but they were all playing the same texture. Not texture, but the same chord voicing. So [plays homorhythmic harmonies]. I was like, “What’s a leveled up version of that? How can I take that technique and bring it up?” While I was researching &lt;em&gt;Dupree’s Paradise&lt;/em&gt;, I came across information about what Frank Zappa used called a “chord bible.” He had a series of chords that he liked to hear in succession. They were just chord flavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So you had a 6-note version or 7-note versions and then in his orchestral works from the late 70s through early 80s (thanks Brett Clement for doing all this research), he could use that to generate material that was kind of logical. It sounded logical, but it wasn’t necessarily apparent where it was coming from. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Well, I wanted to hear a similar thing, so I thought of chord voicings that I liked and then I knew at any point I could change them as long as I had twelve. I could change the way that the voices were structured and then that happens with a lot of notes. So here I used 143 of the possible 144 combinations of the 12-tone row and I “forgot one.” [Air quotes.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oooooh. Cliffhanger?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Cliffhanger! I’m really, like, a big nerd right now. So I “forgot one” and that’s why there’s one missing. And I’ll let all you analysts out there in the audience figure out which one is missing. This one is way too hard for me to even hack through on the piano so you’ll have to come to the concert to hear it. But! What is good is I can play the very last note. I set it up so it would all end on the same note, which is G. [Plays 4 octaves of G.] Right? Because I was also like, “Oh my God, there’s so many notes. I just want one note. Okay, the note is G. I’m going to reverse-engineer it so it lands that way.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Very cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iZdnvfQcSW4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: And then you get the solo piano variation called The 144,000. Oh! One thing I want to mention that I actually think is really important is that in most pieces like &lt;em&gt;The Porpentine&lt;/em&gt; [from his solo album, &lt;em&gt;The Lionheart&lt;/em&gt;] or &lt;em&gt;The 22nd Overture&lt;/em&gt; [from his solo album, &lt;em&gt;Oppy Music&lt;/em&gt;] or those kind of “big” works, I don’t write them in chronological order. So, I’ll be working on one section. For instance, I had this part pretty early on. [Plays a chord sequence from &lt;em&gt;The Porpentine&lt;/em&gt;.] That was an idea I had before [plays majestic music from the beginning of &lt;em&gt;The Porpentine&lt;/em&gt;]–that kind of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;One thing I wanted to do is I wanted to write variations in chronological order based on the ideas and when I had them. So, this is the first kind of big piece of mine where you get all my ideas in order. I just felt like that would be interesting to me. I don’t know. I don’t know who cares about that shit. Oops, sorry. I don’t know who cares about that stuff. So this movement I can actually play for you because I wrote it on the piano. [Plays Mov. 12 “The 144,000.”] Winner winner, lucky dinner!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, that was great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Thank you. Don’t put that comment in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Of course I’m going to put that in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The best stuff is what the artists don’t want in the interview. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CO: So when I was recording &lt;em&gt;The Porpentine&lt;/em&gt;, there was this lick I budgeted a half hour to play this lick and I got it on the first time, I was so excited I was like, “Geeeeyaaahh,” over the microphone and the engineer was like, “You know you can’t do that, right?” And I was like, “Noooooo.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3tNW3nx2yD4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s funny. There were some parts in &lt;em&gt;The Cribbage Variations&lt;/em&gt; that very strongly reminded me of the band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Cow&quot;&gt;Henry Cow &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I didn’t know if you ever listened to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: My “weird” cred is going down by the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: [Laughs.] It’s probably a lot of similar influences. You know, modern composers and whatnot. And then secondly, I wanted to know what kind of a role did improvisation play in the assembly of these variations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: The piece that I just played for you, that one is the most improvisatory in that I sat at the piano and kind of felt it out from different rows, but this piece is almost entirely generated with pre-compositional methods. The other movement that has a kind of improvisational nature is the very last one, which–you know, I don’t want to spoil the surprise for people because I think it’s a pretty good trick. It’s got a surprise ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right! Chris, thank you so much again. For people who have never listened to your music, where can they find it and where would you prefer they buy it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Oh buying it would be awesome. I’d really prefer that a lot. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/chris-opperman/id6247213&quot;&gt;You can buy everything on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/artist/4IZRnl6o15sma5z16lDfOD&quot;&gt;you can listen to it for free on Spotify &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You know, composers in the 21st century–we’re happy if you listen to our music. It’s there to be listened to. So, really would be happy if you’re just listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/chrisopperman&quot;&gt;I have some unreleased stuff on my SoundCloud &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s a piece called &lt;em&gt;Ariadne&lt;/em&gt; that was played by the Montclair State University Orchestra. You can hear that there and there’s a piece called &lt;em&gt;Kagemusha&lt;/em&gt;, which was written for the Berklee Symphonic Winds. There are no studio recordings of those pieces, so that’s how you’ll have to hear that stuff. I’m real friendly. Say hi on Facebook. You can just add me and I’ll add you back. I really appreciate you guys watching this interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you have a website URL to share?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Yeah, it’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrisopperman.net&quot;&gt;chrisopperman.net &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but I haven’t updated it in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, and then remind us of the details of the performance of The Cribbage Variations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Okay, it’s going to be on Sunday, November 19, at 7PM in Shindell Choral Hall, which is on the first floor of the Mason Gross New Music Building. It’s going to be performed by HELIX!, conducted by Kynan Johns, and performed by 9 talented students at Mason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Chris, thank you so much for your time and another pre-emptive congratulations on the completion of your PhD. I think that there’s a lot more to dig into with some of your previous work, so we should probably do this again in the next couple months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: I would really enjoy that. And I have a little surprise for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Uh oh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: So, Make Weird Music. What I like about the name is it’s a command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Make weird music! So, I’m going to make you a jingle right now for your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh sweet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: Okay, are you ready?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: [Plays jingle, quite aggressively.] That is your new jingle. Congratulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Was that pre-composed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: No. [Laughs.] Greg is nodding, “Yes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you. We are going to open the interview with that and we may open other videos with that. Feel free to send as many of those over as you wish, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;CO: [Laughing.] No problem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/the-cribbage-variations</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/the-cribbage-variations</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mike Keneally, Gary Green, Kerry Minnear, &amp; Malcolm Mortimore Chat</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;deep-musicians-geeking-out&quot;&gt;Deep Musicians Geeking Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s fan-run global &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/gentle-giant&quot;&gt;Gentle Giant&lt;/a&gt; get-together, GORGG, was special for several reasons. First, we had a private concert with &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally&quot;&gt;Mike Keneally&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt;. Second, Mike got to meet some of his musical heroes from Gentle Giant. There’s lots more to talk about, but for the sake of this post, I’ll get right to business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This filmed conversation is really special. If you know anything about Gentle Giant, you’ll know that they broke up in 1980 and their music has had lasting impact on musicians and enthusiasts all over the world. To get a few of the members together for a conversation (on film!) with the equally-talented Mike Keneally was a real treat. What you see and read here is exactly how it went down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just in case you need the context, from left to right are Mike Keneally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Green_(musician)&quot;&gt;Gary Green &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (guitarist for GG), &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerry_Minnear&quot;&gt;Kerry Minnear &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (keyboards for GG), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm_Mortimore&quot;&gt;Malcolm Mortimore &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (drummer for GG’s &lt;em&gt;Three Friends&lt;/em&gt; album).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You may be interested in &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/kerry-minnear&quot;&gt;our 2015 interview with Kerry&lt;/a&gt; at GORGG in Montreal.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zJ6Kb6AhpwM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/keneally-green-minnear-mortimore/keneally-green-minnear-mortimore.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/keneally-green-minnear-mortimore/keneally-green-minnear-mortimore.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gary Green [GG]: I liked your hat last night, as well. Do you find it’s a musical hat?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Keneally [MK]: Well, hats have assumed a kind of strange, mythical status in my life that I named my first album &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hat._(album)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;hat.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The first hat that I thought of as a talismanic object after a &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Zappa&lt;/a&gt; concert when I was still lingering on the stage and somebody wearing this purple, green felt contraption came to the front of the stage and said, “I really enjoyed your performance tonight,” and I said, “I really enjoy your hat.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I think hats are important in a musical thing. [Points to Malcolm] You’re a hat man as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: I do enjoy a hat now and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: You feel like it changes your personality a bit and you’re able to adopt a slightly different personality. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Django_Reinhardt&quot;&gt;Django Reinhardt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had a hat he used to put on that he called his “composer’s hat.” He would put it on in order to adopt the proper demeanor to put him in the mood for writing. I thought perhaps you had one of those hats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I felt like it was a magical thing when after I complimented the guy on his hat, he threw it up to me and I just thought, “What a glorious gesture.” I put it on my head and I walked backstage and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andy_Partridge&quot;&gt;Andy Partridge &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Gregory_(musician)&quot;&gt;Dave Gregory &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were standing there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Leaping for the hat? [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Well, no they didn’t immediately jump for the hat. But I just thought, because that in itself is sort of a magical occurrence, and I came to associate that with the hat. It’s also–as I got into &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai’s&lt;/a&gt; band and stuff–I used to wear these absurdly weird, huge, elaborate hats and it became kind of a part of the character that I played on stage for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YmAUUU4lYQg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, hats and costume play a part in music production, don’t they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malcolm Mortimore [MM]: Of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerry Minnear [KM]: They do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And then I thought I needed to react against that and I stopped wearing the hats. Of course, everybody said, “Where are the hats?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: So, did you put it back on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I gradually brang a hat, this blue hat that I got which actually has a little &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlos_Santana&quot;&gt;Carlos Santana &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; logo on the side. Carlos Santana–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: It is a cool hat, isn’t it? Of course with a hat, you can sort of–&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Dylan&quot;&gt;Bob Dylan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; cover. You just do that [lifts an imaginary hat] and you’ve said so much without opening your mouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, yeah. That’s true. Generally, I’ll wear that hat I was wearing last night. I’ll start a performance with it and almost immediately take it off. I feel that it has a certain–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: To let the ideas out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, and then at the end I put it back on the sort of signal we’re done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: “Okay, we’ll have no more ideas tonight. I’ll keep them in til tomorrow.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, I might need these later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Anthony Garone [AG]: All right, so speaking of last night… Mike thankfully played a concert for all of us and I was curious–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Very enjoyed the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Bravo, bravo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Malcolm and Kerry and Gary, I don’t know how much exposure you had previously to Mike’s music. I know you two [Gary and Mike] had met before at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.progday.net/&quot;&gt;Progday&lt;/a&gt; before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah we’ve met a couple of times. I’ve seen him. I think–I don’t know if it was the debut of you playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.keneally.com/products/mike-keneally-wing-beat-fantastic&quot;&gt;Wing Beat Fantastic&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NEARfest&quot;&gt;Nearfest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Oh at Nearfest, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, with the drummer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umphrey%27s_McGee&quot;&gt;Umphrey’s McGee &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, whose name I can’t recall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kris_Myers&quot;&gt;Kris Myers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Kris. Right. Yes. Lovely. Anyway, that was a lovely album. Real beautiful, your collaboration with Andy Partridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Sug4hC3Ysb0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Smashing stuff. I love what you did last night. Your versatility playing across both instruments, the keyboards and that, and how it didn’t phase you at all when your guitar went up the spout and you grabbed a matchstick with wire on it and still played really well. It didn’t seem to phase you. How do you do that? How do you put yourself in a space where it’s like you’re just focused on the music. You can’t let this physical thing get in the way of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, it’s just an awareness of &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;no one’s best interests are served by becoming overwhelmed by it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Of course not. But if you can’t actually play the thing…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Well, there’s always that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Thank God it was playable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: True. But I picked it up with all the goodwill in the world. “I know this is going to work.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: It sort of carries you through, doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: It does. I do believe that there’s–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;in the middle of a performance environment, there seems to be a greater capacity for magic to occur.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: You’re ready for magic to happen before it happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, I sort of welcome it. And I almost–it might be presumptuous, but I almost assume it. I picked up that guitar thinking, “Clearly this is going to work.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: You have to expect it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: A positive attitude. Very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I feel in a real way, I’ve got everybody’s attention and it’s focused and they’re all hoping to have a good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;And there’s all the will in the world in the room to have that happen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, so the last thing I want to do is be up there visibly upset or struggling over something because that deflates all the magic of a performance right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Well, it was wonderful. Lovely to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Thank you. It meant the world to me to be able to play music to you gentlemen. It was a bit overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: See, I find that hard to believe because I finished–really, my writing career is way back. I’ve been all kinds of things since and I’ve been a teacher most latterly, and for me, what you were doing was taking me harmonically to places that I don’t naturally go to. So &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s a delight for m’head and m’brain to be witnessing something that it doesn’t normally witness.&lt;/span&gt; I think that’s why I actually bought one of your CDs, which–ask my missus–that’s a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Okay, well–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: He doesn’t buy CDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Well, to me it was a huge deal. The fact that you refused–I would have been happy, abjectly happy to just give you that album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Oh no, oh no. I did insist because–I can’t see why you would think it was great to play in front of me because it’s been so long and you’re still active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: You’re an active happening player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, but anybody who’s watching this doesn’t need me to instruct them, and I trust you don’t either, as to what’s so wonderful and constantly giving about the music that you all created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: That’s lovely to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And as a guitar player, certainly, I was incredibly inspired by the way you [Gary] found a way to just bring so much gut into this stuff. That was just incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dGvPSm1opgk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: But then also, the parts can be–it doesn’t come off academic at all. It’s just so much fun. But! The underpinning of the stuff that you [Kerry] wrote on the keyboard–because the keyboard is my first instrument–and I responded to it so viscerally. To the interplay between the hands and the way that what you created on a keyboard was then expanded upon to become full arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And just the architecture of it and the delight of the way your harmonic sense–it’s just endlessly fascinating and delightful to me. It gave me so much as I was growing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think what I love so much about Giant music still is the interplay between the instruments.&lt;/span&gt; It’s not–I’m not supposed to talk about Giant music, though are we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No, that’s great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Oh is that cool? All right. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Oh is it? Because I could go on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The interplay between the instruments is not focused on a particular player’s virtuoso skill. It truly is a group ensemble effort and I think we’d all agree that we’re all happiest in that environment.&lt;/span&gt; Neither of us–none of us are spotlight people to go out front and try and do something because I’m sure we all think none of us are good enough to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: It’s strength in numbers I think, for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Collectively, it’s this one colossal virtuoso statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: But that is, for me, the beauty of music. The interplay between players all the time. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s the conversation happening between people on the stage.&lt;/span&gt; Whether it’s written, formalized music or improvised stuff. There’s still the need for the ears always to be listening to the other people. The interplay for that, that’s always what I respond to. That’s what makes me happy and makes me exuberant all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: What’s great fun about listening to the live recordings is how the joy of the performance and the interaction takes hold. And, you know, you can hear the two of you throwing these things back and forth. “What about this? I’m going to come in a little bit early this time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Some of that, you know? It’s just so fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: But you do that with your band that I’ve seen twice now. It’s real evident that there’s so much joy with you playing the stuff. Of course, you’ve gotta have that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: At another interview today, we talked about the music. First things first, you’ve gotta enjoy what you do. If you don’t love it, you’re not going to produce anything and it’s not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Especially with all you need to undergo in order to just make it to a performance. The travel–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, the technical things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: The hotel, did you sleep well? Did you eat well? What’s the sound like on stage? Is the sound guy somebody that you can relate to on a human level? You know, all these things play into it. So whether you finally get to–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: “Are you with us or against us?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah! You finally get to the miracle of “the show’s about to start. Finally! What we’re here for.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You’d better find a way to enjoy it because everything you’ve done to get to that point.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I remember in the past, for us &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it seems to me that the number of great gigs we’ve had in all our career, it’s like you can count them on both hands. Perhaps.&lt;/span&gt; Great gigs. So in an attempt to reproduce those great gigs, I remember consciously trying to think, “Okay, what did we do the day before? What happened?” You know? There’s one particular gig we had in Miami and we ate at a restaurant and we all got food poisoning and Derek was off to the side of the stage every three minutes to heave in the bucket. But we played great. It was a super show. So, no there’s things–I don’t know what it is, but–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, it pulls that little bit of extra out of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yes, indeed. Indeed. I was speaking of the metaphorical bit. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Of course. I knew that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HKxGn0UwI-8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you guys talk a little about the importance of improvisation as it relates to your compositional approaches? I know you do very complex music that is highly orchestrated and then there’s the blend or there’s usually a section for improvisation. Where does that come from and how does that feed into your process? Is that something that happens as a band when you’re composing or is that something else that happens?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Well, I’ve asked Kerry about this sometimes before. I’ve asked him, and perhaps he’ll chat a bit more in this forum, but I always wondered how do you [Kerry] start the process of writing a tune? Does it start with you sitting down and sort of improvising something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: [Points to Mike.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: You can answer that if you like. I mean it does for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: For me, I’ve got to try to remember because it’s been a long time for me. But, as I recall, it is just that. Yeah, it is just that. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You’re trying to find something that you feel has energy, has emotion, has a statement that you want to go back to. That’s always helpful. You’re not dreading working on that again tomorrow.&lt;/span&gt; And you go back to it and then you–I don’t have anything in mind, really, at that point. I don’t know if you’re the same [Mike], but you have to take an idea so far before you begin to realize how it could be used and what sections could be involved. But because I’ve had a writer’s block for so long–that’s why I find answering these questions a little bit difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, no I get that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: I can’t remember what I did, otherwise I’d be doing it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: But, do you sit down and wait for things to happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: I keep going. Yeah. I try to. I have different approaches like discipline. I will start at 10 o’clock and I will finish. You know? And then other days, I think, “No, I’ll wait until I feel like it.” So, six days later I have a go. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There doesn’t seem to be any particular rules, but in the days of Giant, there was obviously a deadline.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: This pressure due to an album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, you have a unit to compose for and a deadline to meet. It’s pressure but it’s also inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: It is, yeah. And it forces you to work til 3 in the morning if you have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: So when you write now, or when you set aside time to compose, do things come to you that you think, “Well, that’s good. I’ll work on that further.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: I often get excited for a few minutes. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And then you come back to it the next day and the excitement–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: That can happen. Yeah. I just think–because what I want to do, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I like to be inspired. So I think, “I’m not inspired right now so I’ll stop,” which is probably a mistake.&lt;/span&gt; If I had a deadline, I wouldn’t stop, but I think, “I’m getting a bit tired and something’s on the telly,” or something. So, I might stop and think, “I’ll pick it up and be really impressed by this tomorrow and I’ll know exactly what to do because I’ll be coming at it fresh.” And then I come at it and I think, “Eh, that’s not very good.” All the vision that was in my mind–I could hear the potential of it–is something that was at that point just an abstract imaginative thing. I’ve still got a lot, a lot to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Do you feel pressure from deadlines to do stuff? Or are you just self-propelling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I can take an inordinately long time to finish stuff. The most recent album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.keneally.com/products/mike-keneally-scambot-2-special-limited-signed-edition-cd-plus-download&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scambot 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was years in the works. I was lucky to be in a situation where I was working at my friend’s home, who was also the guy in charge of the label, and he was saying, “Take the time you need to get this done correctly.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I just learned at a certain point to not be too judgmental about ideas that I was having.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I’d put down an idea and there were several times during the course of that album, more than any that I’ve done, and I’d be listening to rough mixes driving home and I’m thinking, “That’s entirely valueless. There’s nothing there.” But I was listening to a single keyboard part without even a bassline or any kind of a vocal thing on top. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I wasn’t trusting whatever the spark that made me think as I was putting my hands down on the keyboard.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: This is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: This is a good thing to do. This is a worthwhile human pursuit. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If I felt that at the moment that I had that inspiration, why should I doubt it the next day?&lt;/span&gt; Because anybody who hears that song will also be hearing it for the first time when they hear it. Hopefully–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Could you not be too close to it to make a good objective judgment of what was good though? It’s interesting what you said there, Kerry, because I wasn’t in Gentle Giant for very long, but I can remember you rattling away on the piano the themes and tunes of Three Friends. I could see that and an album had to be made. We were going to go and tour it so there was a deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I talked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Weathers&quot;&gt;John Weathers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; down in Wales sometime later and you’ve made so much music and I can’t remember exactly what he said, but he was hugely complimentary of all your talents, Kerry. He said something to the effect of, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“It was all good and Kerry just wanted it to be even better, so it had to be sort of taken away from him so it could be played.”&lt;/span&gt; Why should you have kept making it better and better and better and produced as much? In the group environment, the agenda is, perhaps, a positive thing for finishing work maybe. I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: No question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Groups are good for that thing. As Gary was saying, the interplay, there’s a chemistry of people working together. It was great for John. It was album time for bands and the whole thing was–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, if there was more than a year between releases, people would start to think, “What’s the matter. Have they broken up?” I was just thinking of how I remember the break–a lot of people at the time remember the time between Dark Side of the Moon and Wish You Were Here as this endless expanse of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: It’s like, “Oh, what’s happened? Is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd&quot;&gt;Pink Floyd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; done?” And that was, like, two years or something. Now it’s routine for there to be three or four years between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: It’s like Harry Potter books, isn’t it? They’ll wait for the next release. It used to be kind of–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: But then, it’s a very different era now in our recording. Obviously the whole industry’s totally different and the technology’s completely different. Back then, we had the pressure of the deadline and no means to record professionally at home. So, anything you were going to do was committed and had to be in the studio. So, studio time, you’re in that environment where time is money. There’s not that now, is there? It’s hard to talk about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Well, I sort of miss that aspect. I’m sort of willfully taking a break from making solo albums right now. I’m doing various collaborative projects. I’m sort of more interested in collaboration and performance than I am with creating an album by myself from scratch. But the last many albums that I’ve done were done in that home environment where you just put down the seed of an idea and then over time–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: It’s more self-discipline, then, to complete something. Isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, and that’s what I would like to do next time. I’d love to write and rehearse an album and then go into the studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I was going to say, how much of the material is finished before you take it into the studio realizing at the same time there is no studio that you take it into. You don’t get it all complete, which is what we did. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;We had it all ready to go and just going into the studio was this sort of almost mechanical act of recording it and putting it onto tape.&lt;/span&gt; That’s not the case. It’s much more organic now, this process. Just do it as you’re going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: It is, but I think some of that actual–It’s two things. It’s the interaction of human beings playing in a studio space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah. Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And it’s the discipline of having practiced the stuff so well beforehand so that it may seem rote by the time you get into the studio, but it also means you know how the songs go. You’ve already explored the intricacies. You’re ready to do a good performance. I’d be remiss not to mention how much I love the drumming on &lt;em&gt;Three Friends&lt;/em&gt;. It’s incredible work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Absolutely, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: There are several drum fills in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Friends&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prologue&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that are some of the best drum fills that have ever been committed to tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, I’ve described a couple of them like, “Oh, those impossible drum fills you played.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: He just used to explode every now and then. Hopefully in the right place, but he would explode. [Drum explosion noises and gestures.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Oh, I get excited for a few minutes as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: It just sounds so creative, but it’s controlled as well. That album has a very–it’s a unique feeling record in the catalog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Kerry wrote some great tunes and it’s a concept album. Phil’s writing, he’d come up with a good narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8vYHuxYxUGE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Friends&quot;&gt;School Days &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is just unbelievable. It’s just an unbelievable song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: I thought some of your pieces were almost like contemporary–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Serious music. [Air quotes.] Serious music in a sense that it was like picture music that just took you on. It didn’t seem to be–there’s absolutely not copy and paste about anything you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I think maybe I do get restless with myself at the idea of having a thing that just happens the same way several times through the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: I took notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: There’s not a repetition, there’s not an A/B structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: That’s because I’m trying to keep myself interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: [Laughs.] I get it! I get it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, I’m just trying to keep myself interested and presume that if it’s interesting to me, then it’ll be interesting to other people. I tend to forget–not forget, but overlook–is that a lot of listeners require that repetition in order to latch onto a piece of music in a way that means anything to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: That’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Which is fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, one shouldn’t underestimate that audience. They are capable of actualizing real things they’re perceiving. Complex structures. A lot of our fans give us a hard time–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, the people who are into what I’ve done and the people who are into what you do are hungry for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Sophisticated listeners. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: At this point, I’ve heard your music so many times, you wouldn’t think that you could still be surprised by it. What I enjoy now–because I still listen to your music–is that it still sounds contemporary and it still sounds completely vital. It’s instructive to listen to music that I was in love with 40 years ago and find that I’m still in love with it for all the reasons that I would love them. I think, “Oh, I actually had good judgment. It really was valid.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Me too. I have the same kind of thoughts about it. But, back to the present, the creating process. How does an idea spark in your brain? Do you sort of physically try to get yourself to a mental state where not much is going on so you can just be receptive and responsive? I know for me–and I don’t write hardly anything–but I find I have to get in a spot–of course, it’s always better to be at a guitar if you’re going to try to write something. Get in front of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to just have my brain go quiet. My brain’s thoughts of, “Oh that wheel didn’t arrive. The roof needs fixing.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Those thoughts have got to go away to just get to a place where stuff starts to happen.&lt;/span&gt; You get rid of the clichés because I don’t want to always play the same thing when I sit down. I don’t want to be there. I want to be in a new place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Yeah, it’s that the challenge is to not necessarily accept where your hands automatically muscularly want to go because your hands tend to fall into patterns. What I always try to do is write things that I want to hear and what I want to hear is something I’ve never heard before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: When you have established patterns that can be a struggle, but it’s fun to just push yourself that much more. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So when I pick up a guitar with the thought that I’m going to create something, I just try to willfully make my fingers go in positions and things where I’ve never seen them go before.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: So, Star Trek? Where no fingers have been before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And by virtue of physics, some kind of music is going to come out as a result that I’ve never heard myself do before. And then, if it has any kind of validity, then I’ll just sort of continue traveling down that path with either variations on that theme or I’ll compose something and just sit back and imagine myself as a listener rather than as a composer and say, “What do I want to hear next?” And that’s the next part of the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: That’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I had something there, but it’s gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Keeping life interesting is stimulating as a composer, you must be stimulated by a variation of life.&lt;/span&gt; Although some composers would go away to get out of their normal life, like going on a trip for three months, which is out of your comfort zone to come up with something that maybe isn’t the greatest thing, you know, because everything that you do is–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: For me, sometimes, I can reach that space I was talking about for me, which is sort of mindlessness almost. And I can play something and then sometimes I find something that seems to me original and mine and my identity and stuff like that. I have my little bit of inspiration, the idea, the initial spark, the seed of the thing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s like, “Okay, great. I’ve got that.” And that’s as far as it goes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: The inspiration part is–I don’t want to say it’s easy, but it comes relatively easy once I’m in the space. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;After that, there’s work. And it’s like I’m resistant–&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: To work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Do you still think that the original idea is valid? I do. I play them endlessly to death hoping that I’ll hear something else on the end of it that will metamorphose into something spectacular. But what happens is it just keeps repeating. And then it’s set in stone in memory and it looks like it could never change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Have you joined any of those bits [Gary’s] to any of his bits [Kerry]?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: We’ve got a couple between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: You need to join those bits and see what’s gonna happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: I see your point because for me, back to Kerry’s &lt;em&gt;Three Friends&lt;/em&gt; composition, the way that was worked with the melody on the bass and then expanded into the big theme at the end. That was skillfully arranging and development techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Compositional tricks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Yeah, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;tricks that worked and produced good music. “Tricks” just makes people think it’s a cheap shot.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: No, it’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: No, it’s a technique, isn’t it? But that’s when you’ve got the ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Ah. You do need the tune to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah. Gotta have the foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: He’s got that. He’s got the tune. He just keeps repeating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I’ve got a great foundation. I’ve got no roof is the trouble. Nor windows. A front door would be nice. A bit of landscaping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Can we book a studio right now? I think we need to work on some music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Mike, do you run into that where you’ve got an idea and it’s just an earworm? You’ve said you challenge yourself to send your fingers where they’ve never gone before, right? How do you escape the earworm and turn it into a full-fledged idea? That’s the root of the conversations I’ve had this week with both Gary and Kerry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: It’s not a new thing, is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Everybody stumbles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right. But everyone has techniques, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I just always assume that an earworm–and I never use that phrase, but–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I don’t either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: Today it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: A piece of music is something that just arrives when I’m away from the instrument and I’ll sing it into the phone. So, I’ve got many, many of these little snippets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Do you join them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I have. There have been times over the last several records where I just call out the voice memos and I’m at a part of the song where I need something to happen and I’ll almost randomly choose one and see if it fits. Almost anything can be made to fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s trusting in the process because I’ve done it so many times now that I can take a seed of an idea and bring it to some completion that will be worthwhile.&lt;/span&gt; It’s relaxing and it’s giving myself a break. And it’s also realizing that ultimately, what does it really mean? It’s not that it’s all an illusion, but it is also that it’s kind of a bit of fun, but it’s also something that can have so much emotional value after the fact. It’s a combination of saying, “Ultimately, this isn’t too significant. It’s just a piece of music that I’m working on,” but also the realization that once I get it completed and somebody else gets to hear it, there is a possibility that somebody’s going to be really moved by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Well there is that thing too about a thing that’s yours becomes so precious–it does with me–that it cannot be changed. It’s immutably “this.” And for anybody to suggest that it should then “do that.” It’s like, “Oh no! That mustn’t happen.”&lt;/span&gt; But it can’t be too precious and you’ve gotta trust in the fact that, “Okay, I’ve had that idea.” So you’ve got to trust that there will be more. There will be more ideas. They’re in the hot pot right behind you. You’ve gotta open that valve and hopefully they’ll just come out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I’ve encountered a lot of musicians that have this issue and as a producer, I’ve worked with quite a few who’ve managed to get their ideas to a certain point and then it just wouldn’t go any further after that. It’s really one of my–I love producing. It’s one of my greatest joys to work with someone prior to going to the studio to work with them on their ideas. They’ll say, “I’ve got this idea and I think it’s great, but I just have no idea what to do with it.” And I’ll hear it. Having that distance, I listen and I go instantly, “What if it just does this?” And they’ll go, “Oh yeah.” And I’ll play that for them and then that’ll give them the next idea. The little thing that I’ve done will then inspire the next part of the song for them. And then it’s just a little volleyball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: This is the function of the producer, to be able to understand it outside of the band, to look at it objectively and say, “No, not there. Go there. Do this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: So basically, what I’m doing is offering my services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Fab. Well, we’ll make that happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Because I think when I did the stuff with Andy Partridge, he himself felt that he was in the midst of a bit of a writer’s block, even though he’d been doing some collaborating. And also I think he was feeling a bit embittered and beaten down by the state of the industry because I think he was definitely at that point of “why? Look at what’s happened. Look at what’s happened with record sales.” I don’t think he ever felt at that point that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XTC&quot;&gt;XTC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was necessarily getting the kind of recognition they should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was a bit of, “Why continue?” And I’m over here as a fan and a friend going, “Well, because you’re a brilliant songwriter and the world is better when you write songs.” And I would love to help. So that’s where that all started. It wasn’t even with the idea that I would eventually make an album. I didn’t know I was making a Mike Keneally album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just thought I was writing songs with Andy Partridge and I had gone to his home for one week in 2006 and another week in 2008 and we had the seeds or more for 8 or 9 songs. I thought we were going to do one more week to finish things up and then I saw an interview where somebody said, “Well, what’s happening with your project with Mike Keneally?” And he was going, “I have no idea. You’ll have to ask him. It’s taking forever. I thought the album would be done by now.” I didn’t realize that I was supposed to make an album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: That’s the work bit, Gary was talking about. The work bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And actually at that point I kind of felt the looming of a sort of deadline, even though it wasn’t a specific deadline. It was just all of a sudden a form of pressure that you experienced making Gentle Giant albums, which helped make those albums so great, I think. So, I wrote Andy and said, “Okay. I understand now. I guess we’re done with the writing process. I’ll take it from here.” So I made that album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time I was thinking, “Will Andy be more involved with the actual making of the record?” And we had discussed even the possibility of him producing me making the album. But, at that point, I said, “Okay, Andy just wants to move past this,” so I said, “I’ll make the album here in California. I’ll send you rough mixes.” So I was sending him rough mixes and he was writing his responses in these lengthy detailed emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a way, he was very much a part of the making of the record just by saying, “You need to do at least one more vocal take there. And I love where you’re going in this section, but maybe try this.” So he was sort of transatlantic associate producer on that record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Cool. Well the results are fab on that album. I mean, really good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And again, because it’s the nature of the collaboration and the fact that I then had this sort of pressure, which was the specter of Andy looming, “When is this going to be done?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: It gave that album a different quality to all the others, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: And your fans and his fans as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Well, yeah there was expectation. What’s it gonna sound like when these two get together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: And the way that happens with Gentle Giant, hence GORGG that brought those fans who are just so loyal. They bring us here–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: It’s incredible. I’m a little bit stunned that I haven’t ever been here before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: They’re just so passionate about the band. I mean, my part in that and being part of the organization of Three Friends just playing Gentle Giant back catalog, I know has brought a lot of pleasure to them to see it performed live again. But for sure, the question I was always asked that Gary said was, “Where’s the new music? When’s the new music gonna happen?” And that’s [inaudible]. In fact, one of the GORGGers, he’s kind of a real [inaudible], we agreed. We both have tattoos that if the band lasted 7 or 8 years, or something like that, which it did, and then we kind of would sort of thought, “Oh we’ll change it to when there’s an hour of original music.” So, it if does that, you know. [Inaudible.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, while we’re at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: So there’s a lot of good feeling and people don’t buy albums in a world where you can get all your music for nothing. But, as Kerry’s just [inaudible] that’s fantastic to be cherished. There may not be as many as there were before, but it’s a great thing to nurture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: You have a different relationship with an album that you’ve bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: For sure, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: You do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: You have an expectation because you’ve invested. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: And back in the day, you didn’t invest just money. You invested the gasoline to drive to the record store, the time you took to stand there and look at other records and decide which one you were going to buy. It was a whole much more invested experience and as a result, I think–again, you’re in danger of just sounding like the “get off my lawn” kind of guy–I’m not a young person, so it’s quite possible that young people do have an incredibly emotional connection to music that I don’t understand because I don’t live that experience. But it seems to me that we had a deep connection of a different kind to music in those days. But I’m going to abandon this thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I think that’s true, but it’s as far as you can take that without sounding “get off my lawn.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: A bunch of old chaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: I know how it feels to young people. My son’s friends liked these compositions. “These compositions…” Gentle Giant records. He’s a musician, &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/moulettes&quot;&gt;plays in a band&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t want to advertise or anything, but that rekindled my interest in Gentle Giant and then this GORGG thing came along and then Three Friends and it was slightly embarrassing, the fashions back in the day with the silk pants and all that sort of stuff. But the music just didn’t get old because of the quality and the craft in it and the playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: There’s the logic and architecture of that music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Stands the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I can see that being very appealing to a gamer, someone who spends a lot of time perfecting motions in order to execute some incredibly detailed and difficult movement in a game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: There’s something game-ish about the music Gentle Giant puts together. Are you aware–do you know who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flying_Lotus&quot;&gt;Flying Lotus &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Look up Flying Lotus because he’s one of the most incredibly creative people making music nowadays. He’s gotten into film direction and the movie he came out with this year is apparently one of the most insanely disgusting films that has ever been made, so maybe you don’t want to start your Flying Lotus experience there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Sounds great, Mike!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: But he did an album called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmogramma&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cosmogramma&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then an album several years ago called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You%27re_Dead!&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You’re Dead!&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is–it just synthesizes all these elements of modern culture and jazz and just mind-blowing studio techniques to create this incredible stuff. It’s really amazing music. And when I met him, we instantly bonded over Gentle Giant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t necessarily what I would have expected to hear from this guy, but he was involved with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kendrick_Lamar&quot;&gt;Kendrick Lamar &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on this album, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_Pimp_a_Butterfly&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;To Pimp a Butterfly&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is one of the most influential albums of the last several years. Flying Lotus is a big part of this scene that is creating this music and he’s a huge Gentle Giant fan. I don’t think that’s an accident. There is something in this music that absolutely remains relevant. You should definitely hear some Flying Lotus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0ScYz9sNaQk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Well, it certainly appeals to a certain type of person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM: We need young producers who’ve got their fingers on the pulse of music, like this guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Some of the people who attend GORGG, they might be kind of like the people you’re describing. We have a mathematics professor, a guy who pioneers virtual reality in terms of treating veterans with PTSD, so there are people that into details. So, yeah, it dovetails right there with games. Absolutely. And they also can be a bit pedantic, some of these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Noooo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I take that back! [Laughs.] It’s true. I have a friend who’s not been very well with eye surgery and in typical pedantic fashion, he’s worked out his recovery period. He says he’s 57% of the way through it. [Laughs.] Hey Jerry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I do that when I’m making albums. I’ll do that. I’ll sometimes post online, “I believe I’m 87.3% done with the album.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: But it’s tongue in cheek, right? Please tell me it’s tongue in cheek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Well, there’s a part of me that believes it to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Well, that’s good, isn’t it? You’re nearly done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: I think you have to stand behind these statements and simultaneously see the absurdity in them and that’s kind of the way that I approach all aspects of the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Well, there you go. Yeah. [Looking at me.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m good! I loved it! We’re at 45 minutes or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Really? It just goes flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: But I think we have some action items here where we need to get Mike doing some production work for you guys. So, expect something later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Morgan Miller: Is there a question I could ask Kerry? There’s this lick on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentle_Giant_(album)&quot;&gt;the first Gentle Giant album &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that permeates every song at the beginning and end. Is there a story behind that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: That’s from Giant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Everyone sings the melody.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SQPp69MVAaw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: It’s that line rearranged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Just a kind of index link. Continuity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yes, you’re still listening to the same album. Yes, you’re not that stoned. Not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, that was done on Giant Moves, wasn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Yeah, that’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: But that’s a composerly thing in the same way the bass line from the beginning of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Friends&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mr. Class and Quality&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gets totally–this epic thing at the end, which I had that album for four years. Actually, I don’t know if the film is still running. I think I told you, I spent a summer when I was 16 years ago learning every guitar part from every record at that point, up to Giant for a Day. So, everything from the first album through Giant for a Day, I learned every guitar part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Well, then I’ve got some questions for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: That was a huge part of my musical grounding. I think it was during that process I realized that the theme of Three Friends was the bass line from the first part. That made me giddy. It made me happy for a week when I figured that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: And the guitar part is the vocal line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: What’s that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: The guitar part is the vocal line at the end. [Sings the line.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Now I’ll be happy for weeks again. That’s awesome. That’s so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: I think there’s an album in there somewhere. But yeah, they crop up all over the place, don’t they? I was always amazed at the recurrence of the vocal, the words “so sincere.” That happens in a few tunes. I don’t know or if it just happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: The other thing I realized was I was overwhelmed last night at performing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Power_and_the_Glory_(Gentle_Giant_album)&quot;&gt;Aspirations &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for you gentlemen–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KM: Thank you so much for doing that. It did sound simplistic, though, after your music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Yeah, it did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: To me it just sounded essential. When I played that, I thought, “There’s music. There’s something that’s just confidently perfect.” Without having to jump all over the place every two bars. But then also singing those lyrics, it’s like this song has never been sadder. The idea of people begging for leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: God, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Ouch. You know? “Make us strong.” Anyway, that’s enough on that topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: We’ve been calling that our “blue room discussions” as opposed to our “red room discussions” in there. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MK: Anyway, that was a bonus track of discussion if the cameras are still going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AG: Yeah, yeah. The encore interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GG: Cool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/keneally-green-minnear-mortimore</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/keneally-green-minnear-mortimore</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Andy West &amp; Markus Reuter Chat</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;deep-musicians-geeking-out&quot;&gt;Deep Musicians Geeking Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who’s followed MWM for a while knows that we have an affinity for cerebral musicians. After a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stick_Men_(prog_band)&quot;&gt;Stick Men &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; show in Phoenix in January 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy West&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/markus-reuter&quot;&gt;Markus Reuter&lt;/a&gt; had a chat in my living room. Most of the conversation happened while I was out picking up my kids from school, so my first encounter with their discussion was when I edited this video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m so glad this conversation happened because it’s very different to hear two professional musicians discuss their craft than it is having me ask questions and prompting open-ended responses. This is a very active conversation and one I think many musicians will enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time I’ve had Andy West sit in on a conversation. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/mike-keneally-andy-west&quot;&gt;Andy had a great conversation with Mike Keneally in 2016 as well&lt;/a&gt;, which you should check out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/skDll90ElwA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/andy-west-markus-reuter/andy-west-markus-reuter.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/interview/andy-west-markus-reuter/andy-west-markus-reuter.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Where artists interview artists and where you’re talking about the things that no journalist would ever ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Like, how do you actually do what you do? That’s what I want to know when I’m listening to someone talk about their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: And the interesting thing about it is that the explanations are never direct. I mean, they are, but they can also be abstractions because it’s like, “Well, do you want to know how to do 100 push-ups? Here, start with 10 and then eventually you’ll get to 100.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But when you talk about the energy from your finger going into the string and then coming back into your body, how does a journalist understand that? They can write it down.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Personally, I think I’m still a young rebel and I just don’t care if they understand. I would still say it if it’s important. I’m not trying to censor myself. I know there are a lot of potential misunderstandings if you’re like that–if I’m like that. But, I’d rather be authentic, you know what I mean? &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you’re not allowed to use the language that you want to use, then what’s the point of talking?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, so this actually touches back on something we were talking about earlier, which is kind of just being in the world. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;As an artist, you’re in the world, all you really want is to be able to express your art and have people listen and appreciate it.&lt;/span&gt; The people that want to hear it, right? The people that aren’t interested in it, that’s fine, but the world is big enough that if you have something to say that’s worth saying, there are people who will want to hear it and respond to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Exactly. I have the same feeling. If there’s something that I can imagine that I want to hear, for example, it does not feel like it’s just me. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It feels like I’m part of the group who wants to hear that and I have the motivation to actually do it. I’m the one who actually creates the sound, but it does not mean that others are not thinking about the same thing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Somehow, my career and the way I have more and more new friends–”fans”–friends, the more it shows that they’re looking for the same thing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m just one of the guys who actually goes a bit further, not just dreams about it, but actually does it.&lt;/span&gt; I think you need to connect with that. That’s kind of your drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I think so. Like you were saying, when you’re expressing yourself, it doesn’t matter what the receptors are doing because as you’re broadcasting, there’s always–because we have to broadcast. We don’t have this kind of in-born editorial thing where the perfect fan or the perfect appreciator of music is going to walk in the door. They’re going to discover you somehow, like we talked about. They’re going to discover music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;Even as listeners, we do the same thing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Along the path, you’re going to have people who walk in the room and go, “What the hell is this shit?” And they don’t appreciate it.&lt;/span&gt; And in fact, because the way the culture is and the internet and everything else, there’s a negative energy that can be associated with that that can be pretty strong. I don’t know if you’ve experienced that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: That’s true. If people are like that, then they don’t have manners. That’s what I seriously think. It’s manners. I can accept if you don’t like something. I can accept that. But if you have heard somebody else because he likes something that you don’t like, that’s where it ends for me. I remember once, a situation where one of my best friends at his 30th birthday a long time ago, we were listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Sylvian&quot;&gt;David Sylvian &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in his living room, and one of his female friends came in the room and she said, “Turn off that funeral music.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was shocking to me. It was actually eye-opening to me. Eye-opening to experience this that there’s a friend of my friend, and they were friends, but she had no sense what that music meant to him. And she said, “Turn off the funeral music.” That was so incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I don’t necessarily wrestle with this, but I do notice it and it bothers me about the world in general. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s less and less acceptance and openness, even at the same time that there’s a broader field for things to take place. It’s fascinating.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, the question is really: Why is that? I think it’s partially maybe even a misunderstanding on our side. There are a lot of people who actually develop an interest for something who really fall in love with a certain idea, a certain concept. It could be music, it could be art, it could be sports. Cars. Hi-fi systems. Whatever. There’s always something that people kind of enjoy as their hobby, but there also seems to be people who don’t have anything like that who just seem to be empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m not even judging that this is something bad, really, because I don’t really know. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I can’t imagine what it must be like to not having ever developed a passion.&lt;/span&gt; I’m actually doubting that it even exists, that there’s a human being without some sort of passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: A deep interest in something!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: They may be kind of burying that feeling deep inside and they don’t let it out because of social pressure. I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I don’t know either. I think you’re right. It’s impossible to imagine not having a deep interest in something so maybe they just focus it in different ways. They focus it on family or social environments or, hopefully, something positive. But it can also be something very negative, trolling on the internet. It’s very easy to be negative about anything, honestly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Generally, I’m more of an optimist than a pessimist. Does that actually exist in English?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah! Optimist, pessimist, sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Those are the German words and I don’t know if they translate that way. I’m actually an optimist. I believe that people and humanity is getting better and better somehow. If I’m looking at young kids and compared to what I was capable of as a 10-year-old, they live in a completely different world. They have a completely different understanding already. They know how to use tools much better than I did and I think that’s great. If there’s a way to channel that energy into something good, that’s really wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I’m curious about your perspective on this because I think of it as–just because of the evolution of people and societies and things there are a lot of opportunities that didn’t exist as we grew up. That’s the way it’s always been for every generation, there’s always opportunities. But I see it as a kind of a problem of scale and maybe it’s because of where I live here in Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;I’m curious about where you live, but here in Phoenix, what’s really interesting is the scale of the city. It’s not a gigantic city, it’s big–5 million plus, I think–but what I find really fascinating about it is the degree of opportunity. Phoenix has a lot of growth in the last 10-20 years and a lot of it is at the lower end of the economic spectrum where there’s lots of people that have moved here because it’s cheap to live here. There’s kind of jobs, but they’re not. If Amazon or Google comes to Phoenix, it’s because they’re going to open a call center. They’re not going to do advanced technology work here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;So, the kind of real big advances in opportunities for societies is not found at a scale in a town like this. If you go further and further out on the edges of town, because we have a large Hispanic population with immigrants and stuff where there’s more and more depressed–and this is a sort of gross generalization, but more and more depressed economic areas where there’s less and less opportunity and there’s political systems that want to keep it that way with schools and all that kind of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;So, it’s a scale thing. There’s kids in Scottsdale that have incredible opportunities or here in Mesa or Chandler, and then there’s kids in other parts of town that don’t have anything and it’s this big scale. So, I find myself waffling–this is a long way of me saying &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve waffled between the optimism and the pessimism because it depends on the eye you put on this massive scale of stuff. “Here’s some good stuff, here’s some not so good stuff.”&lt;/span&gt; Which is the pervading force?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you have the choice, then go for the optimism.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: There you go. Simple as that, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah! [Laughter.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I like it. It’s good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, seriously, there’s no need to be negative about anything. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If there’s one thing that we can contribute, it’s our good will. For me, optimism is part of that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah yeah, that’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, maybe there’s a kid from a bad neighborhood and you wouldn’t expect that kid to be–I don’t know… successful (to oversimplify things). But yeah, why not? I believe in that kid. That’s what you have to do. My brother actually works in that field. He works as a kind of a social worker and he works with kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I can see how frustrated he is and he doesn’t believe. He believes that of 200 kids that he works with, maybe 1 kid is going to change. He might actually be right with the numbers, but for me, that doesn’t count. It’s not the numbers. The fact that one kid is actually going to lead a good life, that’s what I’m focusing on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: There’s still some hope there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It doesn’t help to not be positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I think that’s really the crux of it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;What’s a useful thought and what’s a not useful thought?&lt;/span&gt; It’s not useful to think negatively unless it’s going to cause you to act differently to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: So, why bother? This kind of loops back to that whole thing of what you were saying with people’s judgment on music and the music you do. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Sometimes I’ve had the feeling where I don’t want to play this music for some people because I don’t want them to have the, “What’s this funeral music?” or “What’s that noisy shit?” It’s like you almost want to go, “Well, whatever.” Then there’s the other side of it, which is just to be authentic and present it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It’s not easy. It’s very hard. I know that I’ve been called–some people said that I’m autistic or something, which is ridiculous. It’s the other way around. I want to say, “You are autistic for saying that to me.” It’s just that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve actually made a choice to do what I do despite the fact that some people might not understand it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’ve accepted that as just a reality. Again, I’m not judging them and I’m not judging that, but it can be hard. I think in my career, which is not really that long, maybe 20 years now… &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’ve had long stretches, maybe 5 or 6 years where nothing happened and I only got bad feedback. It’s hard to go through and keep going, but I never had a choice to do anything else.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: You just kind of believed. Your pursuit was purely based on that interest and desire to do it, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah. And especially that my interest was in discovering new sound worlds. Like we said before, if I can develop this interest and this hunger for that, there must be others. Even if there wouldn’t be others, but there are. I kind of know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Actually, that is the great opportunity now, isn’t it? You know you can find those people eventually somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yes and this idea of a collective subconscious, it makes total sense but the way we need to look at it is obviously like &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it’s not necessarily a global collective consciousness, but it’s kind of localized spatially but also localized in the field of interest.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So in music you have a certain group of people who are interested in discovering a new sound world, then you have other people who are interested in creating the best tools for re-creating the sound of the blues, for example, but it’s still a discipline that’s at the same level as finding a new sound world because it’s about creating the tools to get where you want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Somehow I don’t make any real distinction where the one thing is better than the other. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s about this drive to create and in the end, the process is what counts.&lt;/span&gt; Somebody who sits down and tries to play like–I don’t want to give a name now. Play like–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Somebody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Jazz Guitarist X! He has to spend as much time and energy to become that player as if I decide I want to sound like me or like this sound vision I have. So, in a way, what really connects us all is the process and that’s where we can share, no matter which field we’re working in. If you’re in software development or in music composition or running a business, in a way in the end it always comes down to the same drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. It’s gotta be pure, authentic, and come from a place that will keep you going forward. Keep you moving. I’m curious because you said earlier you didn’t really–I’m gonna blow this, but somehow when you started, it wasn’t that you wanted to get up and play, but you wanted to create the sound and create the worlds that we’re hearing. In order to do that, you had to learn how to play. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;What I’m wondering is: What is your preferred mode? When you’re creating your own music, do you prefer to create just solo or do you like to work with other musicians? How do you approach this whole thing? What’s your preferred mode?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: That’s a good question. I actually enjoy collaboration very much because I somehow still have this belief that &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you’re working together, you’re making something bigger than the sum of its parts.&lt;/span&gt; Especially if creative minds get together and create something beautiful. It kind of contributes to if you’re looking for something new, if you’re doing something new for yourself and you want newer than new, work with somebody else because there’s always going to be more of a surprise factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Ideally. I found out that working solo, composing on my own, has become more important in recent years. I see that not having to make compromise–I’ve never felt like I actually have to make a compromise when I work with somebody else, but I figured that when I’m just taking my own decisions and I’m completely left on my own, I started creating something that really was–I don’t even have words for it. It had even more directness, but that’s a recent development in my musical life. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I find that now I have already played on the field of collaboration for long enough, now I can just be myself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Do you see the medium more as a blend of live and recorded or do you see it more as, “I just want to make these recordings and they’ll live on?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: There are so many modes I can go into. For example, there’s the mode of instant composition. I pretty much enjoy that. But, then ideally I even want to go beyond that. That means that the instant composition is not the end result, but I’m composing a process, let’s say. Then I’m letting the process create music. So, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I’m kind of inserting an additional level, like writing an algorithm which creates a piece of music, so my creativity goes into the algorithm and then the algorithm spits out the music.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Do you mean that literally?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I mean that literally. Yeah, literally. That’s when it becomes very interesting. The process basically becomes your collaborator. It’s almost as if I’m designing an artificial intelligence. Then that artificial intelligence that’s my musical partner then writes the piece of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Have you been able to do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Oh, that’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, I did that on several occasions. A handful of compositions out there have turned out that way. Also, when I’m working with audio, I’m using feedback loops so you always get a little bit of that element of recursion even in the audio processing, if you would. Like this little bit of looping I did last night, for example, those were already feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I can’t say that I’ve done that, but I believe I understand what you’re saying. There’s this guy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Wolfram&quot;&gt;Stephen Wolfram &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who was this mathematical genius, apparently, and he created this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolfram.com/&quot;&gt;Mathematica &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; program. I went to this website years and years ago and he had this music generator on there and you could tweak it and I’m like, “Okay, in and of itself, this is not interesting, but when you take it”–and what was cool about it is you could say, “Okay, here are my inputs,” and &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it would spit out a midi file and I could take that and say, “Okay, I really like these parts of it,” and throw out the rest and it felt very interactive in a weird way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: That’s exactly what I’m doing except for the fact that I’m not editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Less editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;That I don’t like because that’s where the beauty lies, in the things that I don’t like.&lt;/span&gt; It sounds surprising. If you want to edit, just get rid of all the stuff you like and only keep the stuff you don’t like. That would be my approach because I want to find the new sounds. “New” is really, if you think about it, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if we say we like something, why do we say that? Because we know it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, I’ve never actually asked and answered that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I believe a big part is that we like the things that we know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s another side of it, too. We also like novelty.&lt;/span&gt; I know for myself, I’ve heard a lot of music over many, many years. There is truth to what you’re saying. “I know this and I like it.” But there’s always, “Well, I’ve heard enough of that.” So, there’s also this desire for novelty that can drive you perhaps to interesting places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Of course. If you still remember when you played a C blues and you ended on a C# on your solo and it’d make you cringe. At that time, it felt wrong, but then at some point, you start learning to accept what sounds wrong in the first place and it becomes part of–and that’s what I mean with “less editing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The more experience you get, the more you can accept sounds that maybe some people don’t expect, some people don’t like, but you can learn to like them and you can learn to accept them.&lt;/span&gt; That’s what I mean when I have an algorithm in computer science writing a piece of music for me, with me, and it’s my algorithm so it’s me anyway. Then, I’m trying to keep the decisions that it’s making that are kind of odd, those are the ones that are of interest because that’s what I’m looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I’m not looking for those patterns that I could have played myself or those patterns that I would have written down myself. That’s kind of why I’m using software algorithms in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Okay, but just to challenge that a little bit because I do understand what you’re saying but I also think you must have some kind of editing. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You can’t just accept that randomness for the sake of randomness is going to have beauty.&lt;/span&gt; It may or may not, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I totally agree with you because randomness totally does not work for me at all. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If a structure happens that surprises me, it comes from some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deterministic_system&quot;&gt;deterministic processes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; It’s not random. That’s why I can accept the beauty of it. For example, I experimented a lot with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleatoric_music&quot;&gt;aleatoric composition &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I can use it well during a composition on process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Can you explain that again? I remember the term, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It’s just like rolling the dice, for example. So, you have rolling dice and the 1 is a C and 2 is a C# and so on, for example. You can easily roll the dice and make a melody. You could do the same with note length. It’s possible to create beautiful work like that, but only if it’s part of the human process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: There’s some intention or direction in there, but it’s not…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It’s like &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you’re making the choice to use the dice and that’s already enough to make it work. But if the dice were rolling by themselves, that doesn’t make any sense.&lt;/span&gt; For example, there are people who take the data from the height of the Alps and they put these numbers and then turn that into a score, for me that doesn’t make sense because that’s random data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But if the data has an intention or if you were assigning meaning to the heights of the mountains, you are saying, “Back then, people took this route from there to there and there to there,” in that order and then it starts making more sense. So, that’s what I mean, you always have the human factor. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You always have to build a story somehow around what you’re using in order for it to start making sense.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: That’s fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: The way that translates to how I compose algorithmically is that I don’t use single pitches as the smallest unit. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The smallest unit for my compositional technique is an interval so it’s already a relationship.&lt;/span&gt; If you’re taking the relationship of two pitches, these can be turned into a series that can be used for an algorithm. But if you just have individual notes, it’s much harder to create something truly “musical” from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, 12-tone composition, for example. If you just take a 12-tone series and write a melody with that, it’s just the 12 notes repeated over and over again in a fixed sequence, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you start composing polyphonically, then it starts getting into different types of relationships and it becomes music.&lt;/span&gt; It took me a while to figure that out. I have a long history of experimenting with generative music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah, wow that’s cool. I think it can lead somewhere very–I think it’s actually largely untapped still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I think so, too. And part of–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I do want to touch on this because this is another one of these things–I have so many of these things in my life where it’s “yes, but no.” One of them is actually this very topic. You read these stupid research papers, these guys at MIT invented this program that writes Bach or something insane. And then all of a sudden, there’s a news article on it and I’m just like, “This is just madness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It’s ridiculous. It’s fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Yeah. And it has nothing to do with what we were just talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: No, it has nothing to do with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: But it’s lumped in the same category to some people. So, it’s funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Yeah, but it’s just the same. People who go onto that quest to find a way to recreate Bach’s music by building neural networks or whatever that learn the structures and then can repeat them: it’s fine, it’s great. Their interest is in recreating an existing sound, just like the blues people I mentioned earlier. They want to learn to play the blues just like Player X. That’s fine, it’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;My process is that I want to find a new sound so that means I have to train the neural network with something that doesn’t exist yet, if you’re thinking in the same terms. Then the question is: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Is the neural network the right tool? No, it’s not because I basically have to create my own rules that make the music that maybe later on someone can analyze to understand what’s happening.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I was thinking, I have this huge orchestral piece which is a generative, algorithmic piece, which is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todmorden_513&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Todmorden 513&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a really fucking complex composition that’s based on a really elaborate process which involves a lot of computer-made decisions, but also quite a few decisions I made. I was thinking, “What would happen if someday in the future, maybe a class at some conservatory sits down and analyzes this piece of music, what will they discover? Will they have any understanding of the processes I used?” Probably not, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;they will find something that I have no idea was actually in the piece.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Is it right, is it wrong? Who knows. They’ll find something. I’m curious, what applications are you using to do this? What do you work with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Well, it’s mostly these days it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ableton_Live&quot;&gt;Ableton Live &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I use to create generative stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AW: And it allows you to do that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: It allows me to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: I have to look into that. That’s amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: But I also have a programmer friend in Boston that helped me recreate an old piece of software I’d written when I was 15. It is very simple. It’s just a recursive procedure that creates a recursive interval structure and he’s helped me to modify that with my current knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: There are all these things that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cycling_%2774&quot;&gt;Cycling ‘74 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have a lot of–that environment is something that you could bring some of that into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: Oh yes. And a lot of people are working with that, but at this point, maybe if I was to learn &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Max_(software)&quot;&gt;Max/MSP &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I’m sure I could do great things with it, but at this point I feel like it’s–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Well, if you have an avenue that you’re comfortable with or you think is interesting, go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: I mean, my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tobiasreber.com/&quot;&gt;Tobias Reber &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who is in my band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centrozoon&quot;&gt;Centrozoon &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; also, is a great Max/MSP programmer. Basically, whenever I would need anything, I only would have to ask him and he would program it. So, sometimes after the most recent tour, I sent him an email saying, “Hey, I had this idea. It would be great to have this and this.” What we want to do for example is a scale filtering tool that does not shut notes off that are not in the scale, but where you can dynamically change things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;For example, you could say this scale filter in C major (white keys) are going to be at maximum level and all the black keys at half level. So just imagine you send random notes into that and you kind of crossfade from the one scale to the other dynamically and you can create waves or moving waves of harmonies by morphing from one harmony to the other that way. Stuff like that, I’ve always had–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AW: Okay, so when you go there and do that kind of stuff, do you see that as an end in itself or is that a foundation for–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MR: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It’s never an end to itself. The end is the discovery of the new sound&lt;/span&gt; and quite often, I have this idea for a musical tool and I try it and it sounds like shit and I don’t think I ever can use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Actually, my very first experiment with generative music was I took a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewis_Carroll&quot;&gt;Lewis Carroll &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; poem and I turned it into DSP data and I turned those into midi notes and I listened to it and even though back then I had just read &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6del,_Escher,_Bach&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gödel, Escher, Bach&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I wanted to have this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isomorphism&quot;&gt;isomorphic translation &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–you have the same information, but coded into a new medium. Listening back to that poem as sounds sounded horrible. It didn’t work. It didn’t work. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There’s basically the same information to decode the sound to give you that poem, but it doesn’t have any meaning in it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That’s when I realized just to work with individual pitches doesn’t work because those individual pitches don’t suggest an actual relationship to something. Just putting a drone under that poem would probably have made it sound better because then there is a musical relationship. But just this one process that I thought would be sounding interesting was crap. That’s why I never use anything like that anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/interview/andy-west-markus-reuter</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/interview/andy-west-markus-reuter</guid>
        
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tuplets with Jan Zehrfeld</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-tuplets&quot;&gt;Why Tuplets?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/discover/panzerballett&quot;&gt;Panzerballett&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most amazing bands on earth right now. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Jan Zehrfeld&lt;/a&gt; is the bandleader and composer. He uses the band as an outlet to channel aggression and technical complexity. &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/jan-zehrfeld&quot;&gt;Check out our extensive interview&lt;/a&gt; for more on Panzerballett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several of Panzerballett’s songs are structured entirely on tuplets, which makes them completely unique and uncountable for most musicians. Jan and his band have spent years working in these song-worlds where every beat is divisible by 5, 7, or 9 instead of 2, 4, or 8 like we’re all typically taught. Jan spent some time talking and playing through some examples to illustrate how this all works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/panzerballett/id218184264&quot;&gt;Purchase Panzerballett’s music on Apple Music &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-apple&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the video of our interview of Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett talking about tuplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/91zrIPUJRtg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and we are in the rehearsal space of Jan Zehrfeld of Panzerballett. We want to talk today about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuplet&quot;&gt;tuplets &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; because Jan is a bit of a specialist in tuplets. So, Jan, for people who have no background in music theory, can you tell us some basics about tuplets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Of course. Basically, “tuplets” means that you have a different amount of notes above other notes. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you have two notes and instead of that, in the equal space you play three notes, you have triplets. If in the same space, you play five notes, you have quintuplets. Six notes, you have sextuplets. Seven notes, you have septuplets.&lt;/span&gt; So, the most common thing for every musician is learning triplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think this is already a step I remember, learning triplets. It’s not as easy for everyone, but in the end, I think most musicians really get it. On triplets, there is so much based on triplets, so many musical styles. You have shuffle, you have the blues, swing. You have the polka. There’s a lot. And then there are, how do you say? We say “Donkey bridge.” We have some syllables to help you pronounce it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I learned [triplets] with “trip-pull-it, trip-pull-it, trip-pull-it, trip-pull-it.” But then for quintuplets, it was “hippopotamus.” “Hip-po-pot-a-mus, hip-po-pot-a-mus, hip-po-pot-a-mus, hip-po-pot-a-mus.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Okay, in German, we have “fick-eh-dee-tit-teh.” I think it’s the best example. The Indians, like the “ta-ka-ti-na” &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konnakol&quot;&gt;Konnakol &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; stuff. “Ta-ka-ti-na-ta, ta-ka-ti-na-ta, ta-ka-ti-na-ta, ta-ka-ti-na-ta.” &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think the Indian way is maybe the most effective way to pronounce syllables like musical rhythm. It’s the most direct way to actually get close to rhythm.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/E9neoYEQt60?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;This Konnakol thing the Indians do. In German, you count, “Eins zwei drei vier fünf, eins zwei drei vier fünf, eins zwei drei vier fünf, [garbled noise].” You just get tired. Your jaw gets numb, I think. Yeah, so I think the same way as a kid, I learned triplets. The same thing applied one day to quintuplets. Also to septuplets. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think in the beginning, as anything that is unusual, it’s hard to do but the step is not as far as you might think. You just have to keep doing it.&lt;/span&gt; The step from eighth notes to triplets is not much smaller than the step from sixteenth notes to quintuplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Now, a lot of composers, or a lot of songs that I played in jazz band or something like that, will have a phrase with triplets or a phrase with quintuplets. But you’ve kind of explored a whole new world of possibilities. Can you talk about, for Panzerballett, where did you start and how did you get into this world of living in quintuplets and septuplets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Well, the start was in 2009, I wrote this arrangement of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/(I%27ve_Had)_The_Time_of_My_Life&quot;&gt;Time of my Life &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and there was this one part–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirty_Dancing&quot;&gt;Dirty Dancing &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; song?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JZ: The Dirty Dancing song, yeah. And I don’t remember if it even maybe was Sebastian [Lanser, drummer] who came up with the idea. I just had really something quite simple just after the saxophone solo, a break or something. It was kind of simple in comparison to what Sebastian came up with after that. It was a great idea. So, let me perform it for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Time of my Life demo]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1w2QfIi2xlQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Now we have the groups–we perform quintuplets. The groups are getting smaller. We have groups of five quintuplets, and then of four quintuplets, and then of three quintuplets, which causes a polyrhythm. You call it “five against four” and then “five against three.” Meaning, “five against four” it means that for every quintuplet, you have groupings of every fourth quintuplet. You have groupings of every fourth quintuplet. “Five against three means” every third quintuplet, like “x against y” means “every y-th division of the beat by x.” You can say, “this is the donkey bridge.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So in the “hippopotamus,” you’re doing “hip-po-puh hip-po-puh hip-po-puh” over “hip-po-pot-a-mus?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so you’re just subdividing the quintuplets into groups and then building phrases on top of those?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, and you have the hippopotamus… You have “hip-po-puh… TAH-mus?” What is it again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I don’t know. [Laughs]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: “Hip-po-po-TAH-mus, hip-PO-po-ta-MUS, hip-po-PO-tah-mus.” That’s every third one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Ah, so you’re using accents on every x-th or every y-th quintuplet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right. Exactly. Let me show you. It’s like the grouping of five would be “tak-a-ti-na-ta tak-a-ti-na-ta tak-a-ti-na-ta tak-a-ti-na-ta.” If you group those quintuplets in four, it’s like “tak-a-ti-NA-ta tak-a-TI-na-ta tak-A-ti-na-ta TAK-a-ti-na-TA.” And three would be “TAK-a-ti-NA-ta tak-A-ti-na-TA tak-a-TI-na-ta.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, every five “tak-a-ti” it ends up back on the one, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Exactly. Yeah, and then this was kind of the start. It took us very long to really nail this down as a band and to really learn these groupings because they sound so unusual. And then, after a lot of practice, I think it was Alexander [Panzerballett’s saxophonist] who mentioned, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“Well, why don’t we do a whole song of quintuplets? This would be a challenge, right?”&lt;/span&gt; I thought, “Okay, a whole song with this stuff? This must be very hard to accomplish.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uGVYiU407cU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I didn’t have any examples of it, of quintuplet-based songs, and I didn’t know where to start. So, I chose to rearrange something that is very known and already very dense and 16th note-based that I rewrote in quintuplets. It was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Some_Skunk_Funk&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brecker_Brothers&quot;&gt;Brecker Brothers &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I will show you the example, but before this, I would like to show you other examples that are maybe a little easier to get. After &lt;em&gt;Some Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;, I wrote this track &lt;em&gt;Euroblast&lt;/em&gt;, the first original track with quintuplets. It has some easier-to-grasp stuff going on. Let me show you the first riff of &lt;em&gt;Euroblast&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Euroblast&lt;/em&gt; riff example]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JZ: Okay, so here we have “da-ka-da-da da-ka-da-da da-ka-da-da ohm,” which is the main riff. Then in the end, again has this four against five. Then again, I got another idea, “What else could I do?” It was not having these constant groupings, like always four notes. What if I changed the groupings of notes so it doesn’t necessarily have a polyrhythm in it, but just a fucked up rhythm. [Laughs.] So, I wrote the following riff. I’ll show you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Euroblast&lt;/em&gt; riff example]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Okay, so now here we have six, five, four, and three following onto each other and then expanding again. This was another big challenge, but &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the more different combinations you try, the more you will get to “feel” the subdivisions.&lt;/span&gt; There are many possibilities. The polyrhythm is maybe a great start, but then you find you cannot always play polyrhythms, so it’s just a tool to get some nice ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sCqPbWeecbA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Before you go further, this is all fine and good for a guy playing in a rehearsal space. If you’re an individual, it’s one thing. But to get a whole band to play this stuff… How do you get five guys to all be playing in time in quintuplets when there are different people playing different subdivisions? What’s the practice process like? And since you all don’t live in the same city, how did you learn the pieces before coming together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: In the beginning, something like &lt;em&gt;Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; took us very long. The first thing is I do this pre-production where everyone gets a midi file. I play some guitars to it so it sounds kind of nice to practice to, but basically it’s to midi drums and everyone practices his part. The thing is, if you meet for the first time and there is not a midi file playing back, but others have practiced maybe to the same midi file, which is really nailing it down, but if not everyone is nailing it down from himself, then you have this kind of “not yet”–like it’s not glued together yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s like a loose construct. The heads are not in sync yet. So we had to–you don’t have something to really rely on because it’s still a little bit shaky. Everyone has a different perception. One is slightly before the other one, one is slightly behind it, and it sums up to something really shaky in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So we started practicing really slow and it took us a half a year of practicing several times a month until we got through the head of &lt;em&gt;Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; I remember doing rehearsals of six hours just to play one part of something. Beginning really slow and looping one bar or two bars and then looping four bars. And then the next day, we practice the next part and one day we get together and practice the transitions between the parts, which is another challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: When did it become music? It’s one thing to play it technically correct, but then you have to play it musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There was not a moment when we said, “Okay, now it’s music,” because it’s gradual.&lt;/span&gt; The rehearsals, we started to play it correctly together, but live is something different. You have to–always, a performance is only 80% of what you can actually play. It’s always like you have a bad monitor situation. It was gradual. Just playing the head. It’s not improvisation yet, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I think the biggest step was when we got through the head and then started adding the improvisational parts. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;You start listening in a different way to the music if you start improvising on it. You have to get even deeper into it to be able to accomplish it.&lt;/span&gt; So, I think then it started after maybe two or three years, you could see the horizon, like, “Okay, now it’s starting to become really musical.” Yet, not there yet after eight years, but I think it’s gotten much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/t-u2UlTnZyo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I remember you saying something about everyone practicing to different clicks so you could get a sense of different feels for those groupings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, this was later on with the septuplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, septuplets. That’s right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JZ: We’ll get to that later. But, let me show you the example of &lt;em&gt;Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;. The rearrangement of it was kind of a trial and error thing because it’s based on the original, but I had to insert notes to make it–in the original, you have 4/4 with 16th notes, so you have 16 notes in a bar. I wanted to make it similar, as close as possible, but to have it in the quintuplet feel. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;So you have to decide: do you take a 3/4 bar with quintuplets, so you have 15 instead of 16 per bar, or do you choose 4/4, but then you have 20 quintuplets?&lt;/span&gt; With 15, you have to cut off one somewhere and with 20, you have to add 4 notes somewhere. This was kind of the start of how I rearranged this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; example]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Then I have another example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Another &lt;em&gt;Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt; example]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, you decided to add notes to the melody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, in some places I added notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: To fit 20 notes in the space of 16, you’ve gotta add notes. How do you maintain the integrity of the original melody if you’re adding notes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: That’s a good question. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t maintain the integrity, but I’m close to it.&lt;/span&gt; It’s just like in &lt;em&gt;Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;, something I did was repeating some “syllables.” It’s like repeating syllables in a sentence. If you say, “Make America-ca great ag-gai-gain.” In the original &lt;em&gt;Skunk Funk&lt;/em&gt;, you have, [sings it in 4/4] and then with quintuplets, [sings it in 4/4 with quintuplets.] Make America-ca great agai-gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, you guys lived in quintuplets for quite some time and then you decided to move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Not move on as in “leave,” but to add to your capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, so six years later, it was still very hard (the quintuplet thing), but as soon as it gets somehow manageable, it already feels like it’s too easy. It has to be challenging. You have to be on the limit, you have to explore, you have to reach out to the limit to get further. Yeah, the next step was septuplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I chose to add a part to my arrangement of the &lt;em&gt;Typewriter&lt;/em&gt;. I called it &lt;em&gt;Typewriter II&lt;/em&gt;, and there was this middle part and I chose to really do this in septuplet feel, but I already lacked the tools to learn this new rhythmic feeling. I already had this with quintuplets, so I tried the same with septuplets. First groupings of three notes and four notes. What happens?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5OGoftbnqLM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I immediately started with trying to improvise on it. Then, I thought, “Well, with septuplets, you have seven notes that pass between two clicks.” I thought, “Well, that’s too many notes. I need a click somewhere in between.” But 7 divided by two is 3.5, right? There is no…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You’d be in between two septuplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Right. So I chose to practice to a click like this. [4/8 click plus a 3/8 click.] “Tak-a-ti-na tak-a-ti” and then gradually making it faster. And then trying the groupings over it. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I practiced this for a year&lt;/span&gt; and after that–about then was the time when we started to be able to rehearse the whole thing as a band. It turned out that this click–the others didn’t practice to this click. They practiced to something else, I don’t know. But the majority was against practicing to this click, so we chose a different click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4/8 + 3/8 click improvisation example]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: So, when I noticed–then I changed the click to make it easier for the band, who managed to play it better over the other click. But for myself, having practiced so long to this odd click, I totally didn’t get it the first time. I had to learn it new again, practice almost from scratch, but after that, I was even more secure with improvising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: More tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah, the more tools you use, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;the more combinations of putting the stones in your way, the better you’ll manage getting over the stones.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So you were practicing 4+3. Were they practicing 3+4 or something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: No they were practicing, it was actually an 8th note click, like 7/8 but with one–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Like 1, 3, 5, 7?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: No, [clicks on 1 and the e of 4].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The &amp;amp; of 4 in septuplets? Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Between 4 and 5, in the middle you have to find this one…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh, it’s the e, like 4-e-&amp;amp;-a of a septuplet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Yeah. You can practice this in different ways. You can focus on the eighth notes or the sixteenth notes and it’s a different feeling, of course. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you practice with the eighth notes, maybe you get more calm over it, but the tiny little ways between the sixteenth notes… To focus on the sixteenth notes is better. I think both ways should be practiced.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How about tempos? The faster you go, the harder it is to discern septuplets, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: I recently saw a video. There is a limit to how fast the time between two notes can pass, there’s a limit to it so that you perceive it as “not bullshit.” To perceive it as music. That means that if there is a limit, if you have septuplets, you have to basically choose a slower tempo than with quintuplets or with sixteenth notes. Otherwise, if you reach the limit with sixteenth notes, you cannot put in septuplets anymore. I think this sets a limitation to if you put in–which I haven’t done yet–if you put in 11 or 13, it has to be even slower for you to feel the difference between them. From a certain tempo, you don’t hear any difference. It’s just [machine gun sound].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Jan improvising on the “other” click]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool. So what’s next in this world of tuplets for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Maybe, I don’t know, septuplets are not through yet. But, we already tried some fast 9/8 grooves, which is almost like if you have a fast 9/8 groove, it’s almost like a slow 9/16 groove. But, let’s see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: The band digs it? They’re cool with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bEdh3IjJ9Gk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: Totally. You will hear more 9 from us. You can hear it on &lt;em&gt;Shunyai&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Breaking Brain&lt;/em&gt;. On the next album, we have some more 9. And the next one, 11, is still in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, cool. Thank you so much for giving us such a great rundown of tuplets and all the examples. That’s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;JZ: You’re very welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/tuplets</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/tuplets</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Frank Pesci</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Frank Pesci is a composer of “sophisticated music with surprising harmonies.” He writes contemporary opera and is based in Cologne, Germany. Frank and I met at a small, English-speaking Anglican church in Cologne. We initially connected by laughing about the impossibility of sight-reading some old hymns during church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started talking and it turns out he’s a fan of &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/frank-zappa&quot;&gt;Frank Zappa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/steve-vai&quot;&gt;Steve Vai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/igudesman-and-joo&quot;&gt;Igudesman and Joo&lt;/a&gt;, and lots of other musicians featured here on MWM. So, we hit it off pretty well. He lived walking distance from our vacation rental and we started getting our families together. He’s a great guy with a great family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s also quite an accomplished musician with dozens of compositions having been performed across two continents, including forty choral works and five operas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his wife is also an accomplished singer. She is one of the leading sopranos in the modern opera scenes and is known for her stellar performances of Mozart’s The Magic Flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KJmaYVVuRnY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/frank-pesci/frank-pesci.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/frank-pesci/frank-pesci.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and today I am here in Cologne, Germany with Frank Pesci. Frank, thanks so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Thank you for having me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, why don’t you tell us who you are, what you do, and how you ended up doing what you do here? An American in Cologne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Well, my name is Frank Pesci. I am an American composer based in and working in Germany. I am a composer primarily focused at the moment on opera, but I’ve written nearly 100 works for the concert stage, including pieces for chorus, solo works for instrumentalists and singers, works for large ensembles like orchestras, concert bands, and things like that. Plus chamber music and everything in between. But at the moment I’m focused primarily on opera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;What I’m doing here in Germany is we’ve been living here in Germany, my wife and I, for four years. My wife is an opera singer and her career brought us here, first to Karlsruhe, which is a small town in the southwest (well, it’s a medium-sized town in the southwest) and for the last two years here in Cologne, where she’s a member of the ensemble with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oper.koeln&quot;&gt;Oper Köln &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So that’s what I’m doing here and I am working as a freelance professional composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m gonna go ask the kids to be quiet…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: That’s okay… [Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SjTEDeSWPxg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[EDIT]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Through the magic of editing, we are back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: We are back. [Laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Okay, so…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Okay, who I am, what I do, why I’m here. That’s where we wound up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So tell us about the kind of opera music you perform here or anywhere else you’ve done it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Well, as a performer, I have had really fabulous experiences here in Germany for the last four years working as a singer for opera chorus gigs as well as working as a supernumerary, which is essentially a human prop or a non-speaking acting role. They put me in a place, they need me to move a box, or I just do nothing, I just take up space. So that–in terms of performing–is what I’ve been doing for the last four years or so and that’s given me a great chance to look at opera from the other side, from outside of the pit and from the stage looking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;As far as the opera that I’m writing goes, I have been working–I work both sides of the Atlantic. I’ve been slowly trying to work my way into the scene particularly in Germany where there is a lot of new opera happening (but from an American composer, it makes it a little bit trickier). And then working contacts in the US, I have five operas that I’m pushing now that are either ready to go or at various stages of development looking for collaborative partners. It involves a lot of administrative time. [Laughs.] Just keeping things going on both sides of the Atlantic with people who are looking for different things, the artistic aesthetic is very different, and two different languages… yeah, it takes up almost as much time as writing the damn pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eDWO-dDebAw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Speaking of aesthetics, I think when people hear the word “opera,” they think of a large woman…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: In a magnesium dress. Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so can you spell out some of the modern aesthetics of opera and dispel some of the myths that people believe or misconceptions of opera?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: I would love to. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Opera is another way to tell a story.&lt;/span&gt; It is the same type of storytelling that you get from reading a story, from watching a movie, from seeing a play or going to see a musical. It is just another way of getting the point across of something that is happening in somebody’s life. Where it veers into a new territory is that sometimes what these people on stage are feeling is bigger than can be expressed solely through words or acting. So, then music becomes an extra part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;While there are lots of magnesium dress-wearing women in opera and while opera in general, in particular in the US, is struggling with a conception that it is not mainstream, that it is not for everybody, that it is snobby or snooty, or however you’d like to call it, or out of touch–&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;if you first have an opportunity to take a look and understand what these people are going through on stage, it’s very similar to things people go through in their lives all the time. It is relevant, it is something that can be connected to.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The stories that you will get in opera are life and death and love and hatred and betrayal and anguish and all the things that you see just in your normal everyday experience. What’s happening now, especially in the United States, is that there is a very strong push for new works to have immediately-relevant content. Meaning: things that are affecting society, things that are affecting real people’s lives currently, whether that has to do with technology or it has to do with modern political things, or other things that are happening culturally that are relevant in people’s lives so that it can tap into what people are experiencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B6we7T0T7Fk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Now, musically we’re also seeing a shift in that the type of music that is being used to write opera–the field is wide open. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;All kinds of musical styles are being incorporated into modern operatic contexts, some to good effect, some not so much.&lt;/span&gt; But the attitude is that if we’re going to speak to people using this medium in contemporary living, then we need to make some adjustments artistically, musically, thematically in order to draw those people in, which I’m all for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;In Germany and Europe in general, it’s a completely different thing because the aesthetic is very difficult and new music can be very difficult to hear. But they’ve cultivated an audience for that kind of thing. It’s not exactly where my aesthetic lies [laughs] so we’re going to see how that works out. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Opera is an ever-changing animal and it actually is far more adaptable than I think people realize it is.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Now you and I first connected talking about Steve Vai and Frank Zappa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Yes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: You were kind of a guitar nerd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: I was totally a guitar nerd. I taught myself how to play off of Metallica albums. [Laughs.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us about the transition–I’m assuming at that point you were also not an opera composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: No I was not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: How do you go from guitar heroes to modern opera? You didn’t study opera in music school, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: No, no I didn’t. I actually have a jazz degree and I come from a musical family. Unwittingly, my father probably–obviously without knowing it–instilled in me what I realize and recognize now are my two pillars of my musical understanding: jazz is one and opera is another. He was a jazz player when he was a kid and then he was the middle-aged man sitting in his recliner sobbing along with the radio broadcast from the Met. So, I got bombarded with all that all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hi89ySWq--Y?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think my turn to guitar was to be cool because that’s everybody’s initial reason to play the guitar&lt;/span&gt;, but also it was the music. I was listening to rock, I was listening to heavy metal, and I wanted to take part in that. Very musical family–we all sang, we all played instruments and then guitar became one of my central instruments for a while. That went through years of all kinds of stuff: I was doing rock, I was doing metal, I was doing lonely singer-songwriter coffee house gigs, I was playing jazz, I was in a funk fusion band for a while that toured when I was in college in the Southeast, but I was also singing in choirs and I was also studying classical music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then when I got to school to do my jazz degree, I was studying composition as well–like, “legit” composition in the classical vein, in addition to jazz composition. So it all just kind of morphed into one big musical experience and all of that continues to come out in my writing now. So in terms of how I got from there to opera, opera was sort of drilled into my DNA and then into my ears by my dad and then that was just something I felt like, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;“If I can be the best composer that I can be, what would that turn out to be?” For me, it was writing opera.&lt;span&gt; So, that was always the long-term goal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;At some point, I wanted to be the opera composer, I wanted to be the guy writing new works and is making those things happen. How I got there was a little circuitous, but the totality of my musical experience all plays into that now, including the jazz and the funk and the metal and all the guitar nonsense that I went through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so on your website you have a selection of pieces you’ve written. What’s the website? &lt;a href=&quot;http://frankpesci.com&quot;&gt;FrankPesci.com &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: FrankPesci.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: There’s a lot of examples of what I’ve written there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah, so what struck me was your use of what sounded more like modern-day jazz. There’s kind of atonality going on in the music, but with opera singers on top of it. So, can you talk about how those influences outside of opera inform your composition and is this unique to what you’re doing or is this what you’re seeing in the opera scene today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Well, I am seeing a lot of that in the American opera scene. I am seeing a lot of people who have disparate influences and then utilizing those influences to put something on the operatic stage. For me, I have been specifically trying to blend–I still don’t know what the best word is to say it–but to synthesize my jazz conceptions and my operatic sensibility. Just saying it out loud sounds like there’s no way in hell that’s going to work, but not exactly true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s been done before in terms of jazz and classical music. There are a couple of operas about jazz subjects that are floating around at the moment. One by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.terenceblanchard.com/&quot;&gt;Terence Blanchard &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who’s a famous jazz trumpeter and there’s another one–there’s an opera going around about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Parker&quot;&gt;Charlie Parker &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So it’s not unheard of, but for me what it is is to take these two things that are a big part of my musical understanding and then to make something that is both and neither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0WTRzqCxSx0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, aspects of it, like some of the harmonic things that you’d heard on my website and are readily there, some of the freer flowing harmonic conceptions of jazz are things that I latch on to. Also the way that players in a jazz setting will converse with each other musically and the dialogue that happens there, which then turns into a counterpoint–that is something that I freely draw from when I’m writing anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Also, just from a practical standpoint, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;most of my compositions begin as improvisations, which is directly out of my jazz upbringing.&lt;/span&gt; And then doing so in a way that still remains appropriate for the type of singers that I’m singing for. So, yes, you might have a jazz thing that is happening, or something that is definitely jazz influenced, but as you said, having an opera singer floating on top of it, you still have to keep in mind that these are people that were trained to sing a particular way and then to trying find a way to utilize that to make something new, instead of “Now I’m going to jam the opera singer into the jazz box and we’ll see what comes out on the other side.” It’s a balance and it’s a dance that you have to play, I find, but it’s one that I’ve been having fun with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Are singers looking for this new kind of material and liking it? Are they pursuing that and do you find audiences doing the same? Looking for new opera?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Well, there’s been an explosion of new opera in the US and there’s a steady stream of new opera happening in Europe. I think singers who I know–and I’m also married to one–will appreciate new music and will be able to dig into new opera, especially if it’s written for singers in mind. This is one of the things that I have the hardest problem with: there is an explosion of new opera from people who have not written opera before or are just getting into it, just getting into writing opera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[NOTE: Here’s a clip of Frank’s wife, Emily Hindrichs, singing the famous “Vengeance” coloratura aria with the Seattle Opera.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0DkiekeKwvE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There’s a new one that’s coming out this season in Santa Fe &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/deceptivecadence/2017/07/22/538088296/sing-different-steve-jobs-life-becomes-an-opera&quot;&gt;written about Steve Jobs &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s going to make a big splash and it’s by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mason_Bates&quot;&gt;Mason Bates &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, who is a really well known composer and has been doing fabulous things, but this is his first opera and it is on a very large stage. So there obviously is an appetite for it, both from people who are programming it, the singers who are participating in it, and the public. So, that is encouraging to me, but also from being a singer and knowing singers and also knowing what I’m trying to do aesthetically, &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;it still has to be singable&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s still at the base level, for me, has to be opera and has to be operatic. So, I don’t know if that answers the question particularly, but it’s always something that’s in the back of my mind, for sure. I’m always thinking about from the micro level of, “Is what I’m writing idiomatic for the type of people who I want to have sing it?” And then for the bigger level of, “How is this going to play? Will it engage audiences?” There’s a lot to think about all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of those idiomatic aspects or techniques that would differentiate something that you might write for jazz versus something you would write for an opera singer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;If you’re writing for jazz–if you’re writing for anything, you need to have a great idea of what the instruments you’re writing for can do.&lt;/span&gt; This is one of these discussions that happens in dorky composer circles about how much you use your laptop to compose and do you play back the midi stuff because when the midi plays it back, the midi can play anything. It sounds like a clarinet is doing it, mostly, but can an actual clarinet player do those kinds of things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That is so important when dealing with singers. And also knowing that some singers can’t do–some sopranos can’t do things that other sopranos can do. There are different voice types, even within particular these broad ranges. And then there are things that classically trained singers and performers can’t, or won’t, or don’t want to do that, for jazz players, comes normally like improvisation or some stylistic things that they may not be comfortable with (in terms of rhythmically stylistic things).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, it’s my job then to be able to find how to write things in such a way so that people who, with the type of classical training that I am familiar with, will be able to do what’s on the page and get across exactly the feeling, and the rhythmic precision, and the style of it just by reading what’s off the page. It’s just knowing who you’re dealing with and knowing the type of people that you’re dealing with and knowing that you have to be careful sometimes what you ask for because you might get it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/paul-hanson&quot;&gt;I interviewed Paul Hanson&lt;/a&gt;, who is a bassoonist, and he talked about the dearth of improvisation education for non-jazz musicians, particularly in the classical world. He plays in chamber orchestras or whatever with the bassoon. But once he starts improvising, people are like, “What are you doing?” So, as somebody who has a jazz background and writes songs through improvisation, what are some of the ways you’ve been able to bridge the gap between being an improviser and asking ensembles to get out of the box?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: There are ways that you can do it. Now first of all &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I do proudly revel in making instrumentalists uncomfortable and this is one of the ways I do that. The other is when I try to make them sing, which they really don’t want to do.&lt;/span&gt; But sometimes I just feel like I have to. For me, it is–again, it’s going back to the way I know that these folks are trained and you’re exactly right (and he was exactly right) in the observation also in that improvising education just doesn’t exist for classical players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dsmnr6JLWzQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t want to go super wide with it, but I feel like there’s a huge lack of improvisatory cognitive skills that are simply not taught. For me, verbal improvisation has been something I’ve done my whole life because I’m one of six kids and we all talk too much, so you always have to figure out how you can get yourself into the conversation better. From a musical perspective, even if it’s something like I will tell an instrumentalist, “These are the given pitches that you can come up with any rhythm you want, any speed you want, for this length of time.” So if things are properly measured out and doled out, “This is what I need you to do over this period of time,” that’s much more palatable and digestible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;The thing with improvisation, even in jazz improvisation, is that unless you are doing free improvisation, unless you’re &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornette_Coleman&quot;&gt;Ornette Coleman &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or somebody from that school, there are rules that you are following. There are constraints that you are having to work within. And then what has to be done is that given the thing that I want to do or that I want players or singers to do, how can I write in such a way as to make sure they are aware it’s not a free-for-all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;“There are specific things I need you to do, but I am going to allow you some mobility.” Or, I just write it so that it sounds like they’re improvising. I’ve done that, too. I’ve been in situations where I was writing a blues–there’s one piece that I have, or one of the movements in this multi-movement work for a six-piece chamber ensemble that’s a blues. It is a blues in form and it is a blues the way the harmonies relate to each other. And then we’re going to take a chorus and the flute’s going to play a solo and I had to write it in such a way that it sounds like the flautist was improvising and it would sound like to the audience that the flautist was improvising, but they were simply playing exactly what’s on the page. I know it will come across that way, but that’s the whole thing. Combining the jazz and classical idioms is, “How can you make the one sound like the other, but not lose its quality, its initial amount of integrity?” So, that’s what I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: For people who visiting this site know nothing about contemporary opera, who are some of the heroes that you would say, “Go check these people out?” Whether performers like Barbara Hannigan or composers? Where would you suggest people start if they’re looking to explore the genre?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Well you mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara_Hannigan&quot;&gt;Barbara Hannigan &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. She is somebody who is working constantly and a large amount of what she does vocally is contemporary music or recent contemporary music, within the last 30-50 years. You could easily find her on YouTube and hear some crazy shit that she does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Her stuff with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gy%C3%B6rgy_Ligeti&quot;&gt;Ligeti’s &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/f-p1utKFxCg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Le_Grand_Macabre&quot;&gt;Mysteries of the Macabre &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–yeah, that’s some pretty amazing stuff. Now in terms of modern opera, depending upon where you are in the US, you can find your local opera company and you can see what they’re doing and more often than not, they will have one contemporary piece depending upon their mission. If they’re a smaller company and they really just cater to doing the classics and the rep, then they’re going to be doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But if you are anywhere in any city and look for small, plucky, shoestring non-profit opera companies that do shows in bars, you can pretty much bet that they’re going to be doing something contemporary and it’s going to be fun. Getting into the bigger thing, there are a lot of major events that are happening, like the one that we talked about in Santa Fe with the Steve Jobs opera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_IuI9z3LUIM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;There are a bunch of new works planned in the coming season. It’s more than I can count, but a good resource would be some place like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opera_America&quot;&gt;Opera America &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is like the national trade association for professionals who work in opera and they will have a listing of everything that’s going on, anywhere. Just like I say with anybody who hasn’t listened to any opera or any classical music, you could do one of two things: you could find something that’s very popular and test your ability to go with that–something very popular opera-wise like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_boh%C3%A8me&quot;&gt;La Boheme &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Magic_Flute&quot;&gt;The Magic Flute &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something like that–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[A little girl starts crying in the background.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I don’t know if that’s yours or mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: That’s my daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Oh, it’s yours! [Laughs] Or, just take a chance and go to something new. You may hate it, but at least you’ll know. Or if you don’t want to waste any money on it, there are so many full, complete operas on YouTube that you could spend days and days and days and days watching free opera and just letting it roll. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The gateway to new opera is being open to opera.&lt;/span&gt; The gateway to opera is just by being open to new things, if it’s something that you don’t know. Don’t worry about what to wear, don’t worry about the old people with money who are scowling at you. Don’t worry about any of that crap because it doesn’t actually have anything to do with what happens on stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: &lt;a href=&quot;/interview/igudesman-and-joo&quot;&gt;Just like Hyung-ki Joo said&lt;/a&gt;. Don’t be square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Don’t be square! Have some fun with it!&lt;/span&gt; And there are pieces out there that you can have fun with. And there are new pieces that are being written that are fun, that are supposed to be fun. All you have to do is take a little bit of a chance and look around at what’s going on in your neighborhood and you’re going to find something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Alright, thanks a lot Frank. I really appreciate your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Thank you so much. I appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: And people who want to check out your stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: FrankPesci.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is it on any of the streaming services?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: Yeah. I’ve got a small YouTube channel, I’m all over SoundCloud both under my name and also under my self-publishing name, which is Ichthus Music Press. Yeah, I’m out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right. Thanks a lot Frank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;FP: I appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No problem. Cool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/frank-pesci/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/frank-pesci/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Otto D'Agnolo Interviews MWM</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/link/otto-d-interview</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/link/otto-d-interview</guid>
        
        
        <category>link</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cupcake by Robbie Seahag Mangano</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robbie Seahag Mangano and I got together in early March to film a bunch of stuff. We laughed for hours making a video that has yet to see the light of day. This performance of “Cupcake” was filmed at the end of a long, fun day of recording together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bumbleweenie.com&quot;&gt;You should buy Robbie’s new album, &lt;em&gt;Bumbleweenie&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should also check out these videos we’ve made together: &lt;a href=&quot;/share/weasel-shake&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weasel Shake&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/learn/33-in-buffalo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;33 in Buffalo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;music-video&quot;&gt;Music Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vMaI93cYsh0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/cupcake</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/cupcake</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Marco Machera</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Marco Machera is an Italian musician/songwriter. He likes to say,  “I don’t play music – I make it happen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s played bass for Marillion, Paul Gilbert, Tony Levin, Markus Reuter, and many others. He’s rather prolific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His new album is due out September 1, 2017. It’s called &lt;em&gt;Small Music from Broken Windows&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;{ data.artists.marco-machera.website }&quot;&gt;Check his website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-video&quot;&gt;Interview video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UftXn22rQ08?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-audio-podcast&quot;&gt;Interview Audio (Podcast)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(NOTE: hitting the “play” button requires a hefty download of the entire audio file!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/marco-machera/marco-machera.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; preload=&quot;none&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/audio.makeweirdmusic.com/discover/marco-machera/marco-machera.mp3&quot;&gt;download an mp3 &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcription&quot;&gt;Interview Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Marco Machera is a bassist in Italy. He’s known best for his work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/slickmachera/&quot;&gt;EchoTest &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-facebook-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/julie-slick&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt;. We are very lucky to have him here today to talk about his new album. Marco, thank you so much for joining us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Thank you for your interest. It’s a pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, you’ve got a new album and I thought it’d be cool if we talked about it here. Why don’t you tell us about it, what it’s called, and some of the story behind it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: The title is very long. It’s maybe not good for promotion, but it’s called &lt;em&gt;Small Music from Broken Windows&lt;/em&gt;. It’s my first solo record since 2014. Since then, I started the EchoTest project with Julie and I’ve been very busy with that. It’s obviously a priority for us, but I’ve always been working on my own stuff, which is usually quite different from what I do with Julie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_2UZ34eNgEo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;It’s more singer-songwriter-oriented music. I thought it was a good time now to put it out because we just published the new record with EchoTest called &lt;a href=&quot;https://julieslick.bandcamp.com/album/from-two-balconies&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;From Two Balconies&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-bandcamp&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I have it right here. [Points to EchoTest CD.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: That’s awesome. And I hope you listen to it, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Oh yeah, it’s great. I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: It’s doing very well. Then Julie got busy with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wki/Adrian_Belew&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. She tours with him a lot, so I used that time to work on my record and put the final touches to it. It’s going to be out very soon. I don’t know what will happen next, but for sure there will be more touring with EchoTest, so I don’t know if I’ll ever have a real chance to promote my own record, but that’s not something I’m doing because I want to get something out of it. You know what I mean? It’s more like a need I have to put my music out and then whatever happens happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZqLkAwDnT2Q?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Can you tell us about the style of the record? I think you said it’s mostly singer-songwriter-oriented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, it starts with that. Usually my interest is in pop music and that’s also, I think, what makes EchoTest work very well because both me and Julie have strong pop sensibilities. When I work on my own music, it’s even more evident. I really like to write songs. At the same time, I want to make them interesting somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I think Adrian Belew is a master of that craft. He’s an inspiration and that’s what I try to do with my own music. I start with a pop song formula and then I try to expand that and have different influences in it. I try to make it a little more adventurous than it should be for the music business world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: What are some of the things that you do to your songs to make them “weird” or interesting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: I don’t have to really think about it that much. It’s more of an inner thing, I think, because I have a melody and maybe I have a chorus and then I have a verse, but sometimes they just don’t follow a strict rule. even structure-wise. I’m driven most of the time by the mood of a song and I try to follow that and get inspired by the mood and the song itself. I don’t really think about, “Oh I wrote a verse and a chorus and now I should make something weird and not be too standard with it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bwHAr4kaFNw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, usually, it’s just a matter of being inspired and using the imagination and something will be out there and I can just grab it and use it for my record. Most of the time, it’s just a bunch of ideas and then I’m very interested in working with editing the songs and using weird sounds and sometimes a sound will just inspire me with a whole song. It could be a loop or some really weird, strange sound and I’ll make a song out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us about some of your favorite moments from the record and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: I think there’s one particular song called The Things that features another vocalist. It’s the first time, at least on my own solo records, that I have another singer. She’s a girl, a female singer. It’s a very personal song. I think it was the first one I wrote for this record. It was a kind of departure musically from what I had done before, in a way, because it started very minimal, just on an acoustic guitar and a drum loop and no bass, which is strange for a bass player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;That was the start of the whole record. That’s the start of the whole record and it kind of suggested to me the whole concept of the record. It’s inspired by a Lovecraft story to tell my own story. So, yeah, I will choose that song as the most representative, maybe, from the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: In what other ways is this album a departure from what people might expect of you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: First thing is a concept album. So, I’m telling a story throughout the songs. As I said before, it’s inspired by a Lovecraft short story called The Outsider, which I think is relevant these days because people like me and Julie feel like outsiders sometimes. I thought it was a very cool concept to put music on. It is also connected to the ups and downs in life and how you deal with depression, stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0d4GJEON3B8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So in a way, it’s a very personal album like it has never been before for me. The other two albums I made were more a collection of ideas I had throughout time. Then I collected them on the record and somehow I made them work as an album. But this time I just had a whole plan in my head, like a whole concept, and it’s like I wrote the music for that idea I had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Tell us more about this feeling of being an outsider. Does that apply as a musician or is it because you’re a bassist and you’re doing more with the bass than a lot of people do or what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: It definitely has to do with being a musician, I think, because first of all, I feel like I’m a musician. Even before being a bass player, I feel like I’m a musician and I’m doing music. And sometimes you feel very–I speak for myself. It doesn’t have to apply to any musician, but sometimes you feel very disillusioned. You go through ups and downs and you feel like an outsider in that it’s like you’re at the periphery. Is that the right word?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Mm-hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: The periphery of things. And sometimes you make the mistake and you think that’s a bad thing. You think you’re not part of something bigger. You do your own thing on the periphery, on the side of things. But as you do more of this and as you grow to be more confident in your music and what you have to share with other people, you actually start to perceive it as a positive thing because you have more freedom, first of all. Then, you carve your own space and you have people reacting to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;You have feedback and it’s your heart, 100%. You’re an outsider because you tried to do something that’s different in a way, but that also speaks to people. But sometimes you can’t help feeling a little bit disillusioned. Last year, for example, I was in a place where–I still am in that place, where you do your music but then you have to do other music to survive. I work often as a sideman for other people and I do corporate gigs, I play at weddings and stuff like that. They are two very different worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wOXMxVpwhfw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;When I’m home and I work on my own music, it’s pure heart and I believe in every single note I make and I create. And then you have this whole other world, which is something you do to survive and I’m not saying that I don’t like it, but it’s not like your own music. You would like to be out all year doing your own tour and playing your own music in front of people around the world. Unfortunately, that’s still not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Last year, I was feeling very bad about that situation, so I wanted to do something very different and I went to England to study to become a teacher of the Italian language for foreign students. I didn’t play a single note for a couple of months, but that kind of helped me because when I got back here, I had new energy, fresh energy for music. I’m enjoying doing both now. I enjoy doing music for the sake of doing music and I enjoy being more artistic with my own projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Did this album arise from that period or has it been in the works for quite some time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: It has been in the works for quite some time. But before that period, before that time when I decided to go to England and disappear for a while, I was like, “I’m not even going to put this album out. It’s not even worth it.” But then I did that. I got back here and I felt like, “No, I should work on this and get it finished and put it out sometime next year otherwise I won’t do it anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I think you learn by–everything in life is an experience and it will teach you something. It’s not–to go back to your question about the outsider, there’s always a positive side of things. The bright side of life, as Monty Python said. It’s actually good to be an outsider sometimes. It’s good to not be like everyone else and do something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Well, that’s what this site’s all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1WmBahJM_RM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I’m very happy to have you talk about that. I think that’s a great note to wrap up on, but I’d like to find out how to get the album, when it’s coming out, all those relevant details so we can help fund you and keep you doing what you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, it will be available very soon on Bandcamp. I have my own Bandcamp page. If you go to my website, marcomachera.com, there is a link to the Bandcamp page. That’s the most direct way to help me and fund me. It will also be available in all the usual digital outlets, like iTunes, Google, Amazon, Google Play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Is there a physical copy coming out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, there’s a physical copy. I’m very happy with it. Also the artwork really represents the concept well and all of the dark imagery behind the record, but also the positive turnout it had on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Excellent. When is it coming out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: September 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/657IiLDk5TY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Just a couple of weeks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much, Marco. That was really insightful and I can’t wait to hear the new record. Hopefully other people chime in and let you know what they think, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, hopefully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: All right, man. Thanks a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;MM: Yeah, thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/discover/marco-machera/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/discover/marco-machera/</guid>
        
        
        <category>discover</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tiny Orchestral Moments Press Release</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-immediate-release-august-1-2017&quot;&gt;FOR IMMEDIATE RELEASE AUGUST 1, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seattle Circle and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.waywardmusic.org/?p=3422&quot;&gt;Wayward Music Series&lt;/a&gt; present:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TINY ORCHESTRAL MOMENTS with JULIE SLICK, NIGEL GAVIN, JANET FEDER, PAUL RICHARDS, NORA GERMAIN, ALEX A. FAIDE, AMY DENIO, STEVE BALL – IN CONCERT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evening of collaboration and Structured Improvisation featuring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.julieslick.com/&quot;&gt;Julie Slick&lt;/a&gt; – bassist with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8V-2stZe_kM&quot;&gt;Adrian Belew Power Trio&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bq7ShX_M6uY&quot;&gt;Echo Test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LFQaiiDm2Nc&quot;&gt;Nigel Gavin&lt;/a&gt; – New Zealand composer and world-renowned fretless / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5VgbvAj7Cpk&quot;&gt;Crafty Guitarist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janet_Feder&quot;&gt;Janet Feder&lt;/a&gt; – Denver-based composer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xa0P41jRrUM&quot;&gt;prepared guitarist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4HqFdQEK6_o&quot;&gt;Paul Richards&lt;/a&gt;  –  LA-based guitarist from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cgtrio.com/&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M9vLWtLR8Sw,&quot;&gt;Nora Germain&lt;/a&gt; – LA-based jazz violinist, improvising collaborator with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vcXo3owlGpY&quot;&gt;Orchestra of Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MH_AfwF2JrM&quot;&gt;Alex Anthony Faide&lt;/a&gt; – Argentinean guitarist and founding member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JW9MFQpFtsY&quot;&gt;Electric Gauchos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P1qq06ajsqM&quot;&gt;Amy Denio&lt;/a&gt; – well-known Seattle Jazz Hall of Fame member, composer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3b9PiD6d4zo&quot;&gt;Kultur Shock&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QSnc1yMw1bw&quot;&gt;Tiptons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4VbyYMcWB94&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; – founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://steveball.typepad.com/diary/2005/12/seattle_guitar_.html&quot;&gt;Seattle Guitar Circle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0zNDF_l3_k0&quot;&gt;C3&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TFdCzkPMa8s&quot;&gt;Electric Gauchos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickgrant.com/TADCofC-musicians.html&quot;&gt;Aileen Bunch&lt;/a&gt; – Philadelphia guitarist/pianist with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NyznFRBek68&quot;&gt;Symphony of Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiltedaxes.com/&quot;&gt;Tilted Axes&lt;/a&gt;, music for mobile electric guitars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YG8iIVXYXVI&quot;&gt;Martin de Aguirre&lt;/a&gt; – Madrid-based guitarist and founding member of Argentina’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/bigtimetrio/&quot;&gt;Big Time Trio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/sonia.wilson.184&quot;&gt;Sonia Wilson&lt;/a&gt; – Auckland-based Parisian singer and Uke player, and member of New Zealand’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dDRB8Sc56Q0&quot;&gt;Gitbox Rebellion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LQuLdREXxNo&quot;&gt;Dev Ray&lt;/a&gt; – Boston-based guitarist and former member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eNC4EaJpVwM&quot;&gt;Guitar Circle New England&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The performers present collaborative repertoire for layered guitars, voices, violins, percussion and drums&lt;/em&gt; – including structured improvisation that sounds composed, and composed collaboration that sounds improvised. The show unfolds in 360-degrees as musicians move in and around the audience. Immersive surround-sound is complemented by three walls of ambient video, and supported by an orchestra of precise guitarists drawn from the Seattle community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-and-where&quot;&gt;When and Where&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday August 17th from 8-10pm (doors 7:30pm)
The Good Shepherd Chapel
4649 Sunnyside Ave N
Seattle 98103
Tickets $15 at the door&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-performance-recording&quot;&gt;Post-Performance Recording&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this performance, the team will move into &lt;a href=&quot;http://bearcreekstudio.com/&quot;&gt;Bear Creek Studio&lt;/a&gt; for two days of lock-out recording with a series of invited guest-producers from the Seattle music community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-tiny-orchestral-moments&quot;&gt;About Tiny Orchestral Moments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.O.M. began in 2016 as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V0o8Fb-jThw&quot;&gt;twelve-week series of performances initiated by the Seattle Guitar Circle&lt;/a&gt; that ran weekly from January 7th – March 24th at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Seattle-Creative-Arts-Center-142947199172829/&quot;&gt;Seattle Creative Arts Center&lt;/a&gt; in Ballard. Each week, the ensemble of ~12 (former) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt; presented a dynamic show based upon an intricate and evolving repertoire spanning Bach to Fripp to Ives, punctuated with pockets of Structured Improvisation with guitarists flowing, moving, Circulating and playing in and around the entire performance space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In August 2016, a global &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/stevebal/videos/10155200416731562/?hc_ref=PAGES_TIMELINE&quot;&gt;TOM v1 team spent a full week working in Seattle&lt;/a&gt;, and presented a major show at the Chapel – then recorded &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com/TOM&quot;&gt;five CDs of music&lt;/a&gt; and a documentary film at  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.londonbridgestudio.com/&quot;&gt;London Bridge studio&lt;/a&gt; – all releasing in Fall of 2017.&lt;/em&gt; This new show continues the previous Tiny Orchestral Moments format by inviting an expanded array of world-class players from around the globe to continue collaboration within an evolving repertoire of Structured Improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-seattle-guitar-circle&quot;&gt;About Seattle Guitar Circle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seattle Guitar Circle was founded in 1993 by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.allmusic.com/artist/steve-ball-mn0000032276&quot;&gt;Steve Ball&lt;/a&gt; (in collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Rieflin&quot;&gt;Bill Rieflin&lt;/a&gt;) after the first generation of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thelcg.net/&quot;&gt;League of Crafty Guitarists&lt;/a&gt; disbanded near the end of a three-year world tour in 1992. Over 24+ years, the Seattle Guitar Circle community staffed spin-off projects like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AwJSKUkNUjI&quot;&gt;Atomic Chamber Ensemble&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K-jgqh1WKmA&quot;&gt;Steve Ball Roadshow&lt;/a&gt;, and the acclaimed seven-year weekly performance project: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OZDi1KOIQOM&quot;&gt;Tuning the Air&lt;/a&gt;. Tiny Orchestral Moments is a new, recurring performance workshop developed by Steve Ball and the evolving Seattle music community. T.O.M. is building on a multi-decade tradition of unique, large-ensemble composition techniques such as Circulation, Group Loops and Structured Improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-seattle-circle&quot;&gt;About Seattle Circle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seattlecircle.org/&quot;&gt;Seattle Circle&lt;/a&gt; is an active 501-C3 organization founded in 1999. SC mission is to develop and promote appreciation of music throughout the Puget Sound area by hosting public education, workshops and music events. Our mission is achieved by providing professional facilities, performances, presentations and instruction in an inclusive, educational atmosphere. We provide instruction on both an individual and group level, and we regularly share the results of our work with the public through recurring events, weekly rehearsals and frequent workshops complemented by concerts, presentations and performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inquiries-interviews-press-and-project-contact&quot;&gt;Inquiries, Interviews, Press and Project Contact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Ball
(206) 660-0055
steveball@steveball.com
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steveball.com/TOM&quot;&gt;http://www.steveball.com/TOM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/share/tiny-orchestral-moments-2017</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/share/tiny-orchestral-moments-2017</guid>
        
        
        <category>share</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Failure to Fracture, Ep. 5</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-5-alex-anthony-faide&quot;&gt;Episode 5: Alex Anthony Faide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Anthony Faide is the only person on the internet who can actually play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. Here’s an interview highlighting his learning history and insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vum4Z8YvR3E?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/fracture/id978457922?i=978458012&quot;&gt;Purchase King Crimson’s &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on iTunes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://store.nexternal.com/dgm/starless-and-bible-black-c228.aspx&quot;&gt;Or, purchase the album on Robert Fripp’s website &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link-square&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the video of our interview of Alex for this episode of &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C8a526gujK0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-failure-to-fracture&quot;&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Failure to Fracture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a video series I’ve put together about all the things that have stood in the way of my successfully playing the song &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; despite years and years of study, practice, writing, and making videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;episode-list&quot;&gt;Episode List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture&quot;&gt;Episode 0: Introduction&lt;/a&gt; (includes notation/tablature)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/stress&quot;&gt;Episode 1: Stress and Tension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/picks&quot;&gt;Episode 2: Picking Picks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/inefficient-picking&quot;&gt;Episode 3: Inefficient Picking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/overzealous-precision&quot;&gt;Episode 4: Overzealous Precision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide&quot;&gt;Episode 5: Alex Anthony Faide Interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-transcript&quot;&gt;Interview Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: This is Anthony with MakeWeirdMusic.com and today I am in Seattle, Washington with Alex Anthony Faide. Thank you so much for joining us today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Thank you, guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, Alex, I found out about you on YouTube looking for people who could play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; and you had the only video–and it probably is still the only video on the internet–of someone successfully playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; so I thought it’d be cool if we could talk about that because I have a series about my failures in playing &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. I’d love to hear about some of the challenges you went through in trying to learn the piece. Mental, physical, musical… Go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Great to be here, Anthony. It is my pleasure. Yeah, it’s a long story in fact. Learning the notes took me about two weeks. I got involved in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar_Craft&quot;&gt;Guitar Craft &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in ‘95 and prior to that I never heard that piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Prior to 1995?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Prior to Guitar Craft, I had never heard it. I will also add that prior to 1995, I’d never heard &lt;a href=&quot;/discover/king-crimson&quot;&gt;King Crimson&lt;/a&gt; before. It certainly rang a bell, but I wasn’t into that or prog rock. I had no idea. I liked more shoegaze stuff or heavy metal or whatever kicks ass. Also, old guitar music, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Django_Reinhardt&quot;&gt;Django Reinhardt &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or old American music like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duane_Eddy&quot;&gt;Duane Eddy &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, through my parents. They liked cowboy kind of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hank_Williams&quot;&gt;Hank Williams &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chet_Atkins&quot;&gt;Chet Atkins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Not that obscure. That came later on from my own research. But they liked &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elvis_Presley&quot;&gt;Elvis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a lot, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Haley&quot;&gt;Bill Haley &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, some blues or jazz. I came in contact with American roots music very early, as well as with tango and other stuff. Later on, I liked many bands, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin&quot;&gt;Led Zeppelin &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatles&quot;&gt;Beatles &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolling_Stones&quot;&gt;Stones &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ACDC&quot;&gt;AC/DC &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That kind of stuff. Mainstream rock and roll from the 70s. But up until 1990-something, I had no clue who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Fripp&quot;&gt;Robert Fripp &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was or Guitar Craft or King Crimson or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SZiWvjRj1AY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;A friend of mine back then invited me to a concert that happened in Buenos Aires in 1993 or 1994. It was the Robert Fripp String Quintet with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Guitar_Trio&quot;&gt;California Guitar Trio &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Gunn&quot;&gt;Trey Gunn &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Robert, of course. That blew my mind. I was like, “What is this? What kind of music is this? Wow!” It just blew me away from the first tones coming from the instruments and the boxes. The theater was packed. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It was sort of a revelation, this shimmering sound.&lt;/span&gt; At that moment, I was into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocteau_Twins&quot;&gt;Cocteau Twins &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and dream pop and ambient rock and slow dive. This must have been 1989, 1990, somewhere in there. I liked a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_Mortal_Coil&quot;&gt;This Mortal Coil &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4AD&quot;&gt;4AD &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, average bands…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I found some mesmerizing effect from the acoustic guitars these guys played. This harpsichord-like sound and then Fripp would do his soundscaping with Trey and all this dreamy ambient shimmering guitar music with arpeggios. That got me like, “Wow, this is really moving. I feel something.” At the end of that concert, there were some people with flyers about a Guitar Craft course happening the next year. I took one and read it, it seemed okay. That got me in. I applied for the course and got in but not really having an idea of the King Crimson stuff and the repertoire and the records and the different incarnations. I had no clue whatsoever about it. No idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, first was the change of tuning, which wasn’t really a problem for me because I’ve always been out of tune, so changing it a bit wasn’t that bad. Soon I thought, “Oh, this is much better. I can play things and they sound kind of okay.” The old tuning, I played it already It was fine for me to switch. For my way of playing, I always tried to not sound like a guitar back in that day. Lots of distortion, fuzz, dropped strings. The new tuning wasn’t that much of a surprise for me. I felt immediately at home with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I had no clue we were using a different tuning back in the day. Some had said it, but I didn’t pay attention. Then I took a lesson with one of the instructors there prior to the course and he said, “Oh, you should tune differently.” “Why?” “Because it’s in 5th.” “Okay, well let’s do that and see what happens.” At first it was weird, but after a few minutes, it sounded nice. I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4HqFdQEK6_o?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;First course… there were all these King Crimson-heads and everyone knew everything about–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Who was in the band–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: The genealogy of this group. I must admit, I didn’t have a clear idea of what “prog rock” was or what kind of rock came to be in the day in Britain. All these progressive rock–I knew about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yes&quot;&gt;Yes &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd&quot;&gt;Pink Floyd &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but King Crimson was really obscure for me. I didn’t have a clue about it. So, in that context, I began to become familiar with some material and I found a few things that really blew my head off. One of those was &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, of course. Another one was &lt;em&gt;Larks Tongues in Aspic, Pt. 1&lt;/em&gt; and the other one, I think must have been &lt;em&gt;Red&lt;/em&gt;. All instrumentals. The singing is fine. I like it. But I really like the instrumentals. They’re really intense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CVb2tnFN5AA?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; I came across probably during that year after my first course in Argentina. I thought, “Oh, this is cool.” I saw some people would play some similar patterns or exercises. I didn’t know what to call them. Maybe it’s a Guitar Craft piece, maybe just an exercise, who knows? I was asking and then it somehow happened that I began to learn and pick up the pieces because some older students knew some of it, but they’re in a new tuning, so it’s different. And the arpeggio part is extremely difficult to play in the 5ths because it’s super-stretchy. So, they sound similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I began to pick up the pieces and learn the notes from people orally. There was no score at that time. It happened gradually. Then, learning the piece was not that long. It wasn’t a long time to learn the notes and the form. It’s an excerpt. It’s not the whole piece, which is 13 minutes long with an improv and other parts. The only part I always enjoyed playing is the intro a little bit and then the moto perpetuo. So, being able to play that from A to Z, that part–well, being able to develop a way of playing that with a degree of relaxation took a long time. And I’m still working on it. I think it’ll never end. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I think, “Okay, I might twist my right hand just 0.0003 nanometers,” and then it sounds different. Or, “I can do that upstroke and it sounds different.” I don’t know.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Well, that being said, practicing… &lt;a href=&quot;http://historyproject.orchestraofcraftyguitarists.com/the-primary-exercises&quot;&gt;There are the 7 primaries of Guitar Craft &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-external-link&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Are you familiar with them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KOKRkyeBzN4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I know a couple of them, but I’ve never seen them written out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: One of the first seven primaries implies a motion sequence where certain notes will be held while others are not. This has a particular name and we don’t want to discuss that right now. But that is the principle of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. So, that appears in the system of Guitar Craft and the Guitar Craft lore as one of the first 7 primaries. I think it’s the 6th. I’m not sure now. Notes are being held down and kept ringing while the others are not on an adjacent string. It takes a long time to acquire the flexibility inside of your left hand that allows you to articulate like that. It’s super extremely difficult. Little tiny movements. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It should have this quality of effortless effort.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;If you look at it, it’s as if there’s no movement almost. Just a little bit more than no motion. Then you begin to learn how to play. Up until then, it’s only work and labor. Like, 10,000 hours. Maybe more. This is not music. This is just notes and how to play them on the fretboard. Then there’s the right hand. This is particularly difficult because of inside picking. And &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;you need to think inside the space between the strings instead of the strings themselves.&lt;/span&gt; This is something very refined. Very highly developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I never before in my life had a guitar teacher that was so precise about the right hand and how we may hold our picks.&lt;/span&gt; I’ve been to many guitar teachers in my life, but no one could explain as exactly as Robert did what might be an efficient way of holding a pick. No one claims they have the most efficient way. This way allows you to remain relax while dispatching incredible acrobatics. Cross-picking and alternate picking systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I did this, learned the piece, then practiced a lot, then abandoned it for quite a time. Then I got back to it and then just abandoned it and worked on some other aspects. I always revisited it over the years. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;There was a point where I was able to play from the beginning to the end of the moto perpetuo with a degree of comfort and not fainting&lt;/span&gt; and still being able to keep up with the tempo, which originally is a lively tempo. It’s quite something. I recommend a speed where the piece begins to lift up around 120-126 bpm. It seems to be a threshold for all players who begin working with this type of acrobatic picking technique, which I find to be very unique. It’s a unique approach to picking. For me, it was a complete revelation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ih3VbHo_A2Y?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;It also helped me to develop a sense of rhythm that was otherwise not available.&lt;/span&gt; It’s like an old-school made new. It’s super old school. I think in the 20s and 30s, dance band guitar players would just be rhythm players. They kind of developed a lot of these, maybe in a rougher manner, but maybe strumming effectively for about 3 hours without falling apart because people wanted to dance. There were no CDs, no mp3s, no mp8s. Bands had to play really long. So, I think it’s coming from a place and evolving and that place is live practice, in a live situation. Then I went offline with school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;I moved to Germany and began playing some other kinds of dialects in Robert-ism language. I sort of needed a grounding in terms of guitar playing and guitar tone and sound. That was my quest. I wanted the purest electric guitar sound I could find in recording history. So, I went back and back in time and began to listen again to the twangy guys like Duane Eddy, Chet Atkins, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merle_Travis&quot;&gt;Merle Travis &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;–all these people who could really play well with a clean tone. Not only jazz players, but a lot of country picking. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy_Bryant&quot;&gt;Jimmy Bryant &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Link_Wray&quot;&gt;Link Wray &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, is shockingly powerful with very little effort. Not very technical, he just gave a damn about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N8vOTKMqzw4?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;So, I began collecting all this information of playing purely in the old tuning with all the Guitar Craft background. I thought it might be interesting to revamp &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on it original tuning and positions and transitions. That gave me, again, a whole overview that was amazing. I had to “relearn” the piece from scratch on the old tuning. It was nice to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Still, I’m having the idea of having a double neck guitar with NST and OST and see what happens. As I was revamping &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; on the old tuning again, I had my NST on my lap and kept switching. From there, I thought I needed a double-neck. Not a monster like a big Gibson, but something like a small Telecaster. It doesn’t need to be fancy, just something I can switch to properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Then, I don’t know why, I came across an old Guitar Player issue from 1986 or even older where there was a transcription of &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;. It was the time when Robert was collaborating with them and presenting some Guitar Craft proto concepts. So, I learned it properly from that. That took not long to learn the notes, but to articulate inside of that, it took 15 years, maybe, to build up the muscles. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;Maybe if I just practiced &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, it might not be the right thing to do.&lt;/span&gt; You might need to practice &lt;em&gt;Hey Joe&lt;/em&gt;. It’s all about the feeling. If you don’t feel it, it’s worthless to play it. You have to play it. This happened to me, weirdly enough, with &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;, which is a piece that sounds like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stravinsky&quot;&gt;Stravinsky &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on acid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MH_AfwF2JrM?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: One thing in my efforts in learning it, I remember Robert saying, “Your relationship with the pick changes your relationship with the instrument,” or something like that. At first I thought, “This is ridiculous.” One of those deep-sounding quotes. And now that I’m into the study, post Guitar Circle technique, I feel like it’s changed my life. The way I think about using my hand, the way I hold the pick, even the way I type influences how I hold the pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Paramount. It’s paramount. The fingers and the thumb… It all has an influence on the tone it produces. If the fingers are set up to sound nice, then everything will sound nice. Why does it sound so good? Because you’re playing good. Why are you playing good? Because you’re sounding good. You’re listening, basically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: He said to me, “Until you can do &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; [moving thumb from the bottom thumb knuckle], you cannot play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt;.” I thought, “Okay, what could possibly be so important about moving a straight thumb from that knuckle?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Capital. Capital importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Yeah! I couldn’t believe it. Can you talk about whether you had to go through physical change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Yeah, when I went to the first course, I held the pick like most guitar players. [Floppy hand picking] As if I was putting whipping cream on something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Right, loose floppy fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Right. Trying to play &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; like that would be impossible. Maybe my bones would fracture or something. Then, I think in a personal meeting with him–back in the day he would kneel before you and take a few minutes of accommodation of your arm, wrist, and every joint. Once he found a middle road of relaxation, he would adjust your thumb and not allow you to loosen your thumb, then put the pick on the index finger in a perfect balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Every hand is different. Every body has a different feel, so he would very gently and generously do this and bring your hand to the guitar. He did that and he said something like, “Oh, you’ve really lost it.” That kept on popping up, like, “What was the meaning of that? What was lost? What exactly did he mean?” So I went back home and I began noticing that there are joints that we never use, I don’t know why and maybe that’s not important, but we don’t use them as requested by this technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;But once you begin noticing the points inside–this is something you also need to feel or be aware of–then &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I began noticing a change in the tone that I was producing only in the right hand.&lt;/span&gt; Not to speak of the left, which is also another body of work. So, because the angle at which the pick hits the strings and moves back, it defines the world. It makes a huge difference. A tiny huge difference. Every little correction I was able to bring inside made a big change in the sound. It was able to sound rounder and fuller at will. Or smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/deS70z5IsG0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;And then I began to understand a little bit. I noticed where I had too much pressure, too much relaxation, what made a horrible sound on the guitar. I practice this still, every day. I don’t know if I’ll be able to achieve a perfect right hand because I like to do fingerstyle and other things on the guitar. But, for this particular approach, I prefer to have a sound that is cultivated. Regardless of what I play, I have a high standard of how I play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: I found that it took me about a year and a half to figure this out. When I was practicing, the point of the pick would start moving forward. I found it was just because on my upstrokes, the pick wasn’t flat, so it was pulling the pick forward, and when you’re playing a zillion notes per minute, every fraction of a millimeter adds up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;The Guitar Craft pick is a precision tool.&lt;/span&gt; It’s as if you have a very sharp soul. It’s a precision tool, unlike the regular rounded pick, which is more like a hammer. This is rather like a scalpel, so you do exactly what you need to. A good thing is that no one will die if you do this wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: No one except the song and your reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: And your audience. [Laughter] I noticed your approach to picking has changed radically in the last few years. I must also admit that I’m not an internet nerd. I don’t look at everything. I apologize for that. I’d rather go and play guitar. I don’t like to spend too much time on the internet. It drives me crazy. But, still, I think it’s a powerful tool to connect with others and share and exchange. It’s a super powerful weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: So, any other things? One particular frustration with the pick? A story you can tell?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Well, not a frustration. It was very interesting as I became more familiar with the whole bag of information, which is inside of this piece, to practice with reversed picking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Start with an upstroke?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C2MY5UA-NLg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: To practice it with reverse picking was crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: Because it schools you again about something you thought you already had. We guitar players have a particular talent to take things for granted. Especially guitar players. Maybe some other instrumentalists, I don’t know. But we guitar players have a tendency to take things for granted all the time. This gives us an opportunity to look at how much we assumed are able to, but are not. That’s not a frustration, though. That’s something that I find exciting always. &lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;I don’t get frustrated with guitar. Guitar is always loving. She’s fine. We are not.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Beginning to practice this with the reverse picking gave me yet another boost in terms of knowing and experiencing the space between strings, rather than the strings themselves. I had a feeling that, “Well, finally, that’s where music comes from, from the space between strings.” You know? Something happens there. You play the string. You pluck the string. You hit the string. What is the space in between? The twilight zone? This gives you the opportunity to visit all these unknown regions of string spacing. So, you have all these beautiful strings and the 5 spaces, or the 7 spaces if you go beyond the strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;Practicing reversed picking sounds super different. But, when you go back to straight normal flat picking or alternate picking, something remains. I think it’s the quest for lightness. Light, not heavy. This is a piece you cannot play in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zakk_Wylde&quot;&gt;Zakk Wylde &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; manner. It won’t work. Maybe he can play it, I don’t know. Maybe he can. For sure, he’s great. I love him. But, he’s always like a bodybuilder. Fantastic. He plays amazing stuff, but I cannot play like that and keep a whole show doing that. I’m mortal. He might be a viking or something, I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;But, &lt;em&gt;Fracture&lt;/em&gt; is clean first.&lt;/span&gt; Then, you can hit a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Muff&quot;&gt;Big Muff &lt;i class=&quot;non-mwm fa fa-wikipedia-w&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or something. On the first run, it’s much better you do it clean. On an acoustic guitar, it’s extremely hard because of the action and the general construction, the strings are heavier than electric guitar. To play on the acoustic guitar and with this tuning, it’s close to a pain in the ass, but it is possible and it sounds okay. I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewer&quot;&gt;AG: Thank you so much for taking the time to talk about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;interviewee&quot;&gt;AF: You’re welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/learn/fracture/alex-anthony-faide</guid>
        
        
        <category>learn</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
